<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Sustainability represents the what, the where and the how of what is caught.</s>
 <s id="2">The who and the why are what's important to me.</s>
 <s id="3">I want to know the people behind my dinner choices.</s>
 <s id="4">I want to know how I impact them.</s>
 <s id="5">I want to know how they impact me.</s>
 <s id="6">I want to know why they fish.</s>
 <s id="7">I want to know how they rely on the water's bounty for their living.</s>
 <s id="8">Understanding all of this enables us to shift our perception of seafood away from a commodity to an opportunity to restore our ecosystem.</s>
 <s id="9">It allows for us to celebrate the seafood that we're also so fortunate to eat.</s>
 <s id="10">So what do we call this?</s>
 <s id="11">I think we call it restorative seafood.</s>
 <s id="12">Where sustainability is the capacity to endure and maintain, restorative is the ability to replenish and progress.</s>
 <s id="13">Restorative seafood allows for an evolving and dynamic system and acknowledges our relationship with the ocean as a resource, suggesting that we engage to replenish the ocean and to encourage its resiliency.</s>
 <s id="14">It is a more hopeful, it is a more human, and is a more useful way of understanding our environment.</s>
 <s id="15">Wallet guides -- standard issue by lots in the marine conservation world -- are very handy; they're a wonderful tool.</s>
 <s id="16">Green, yellow and red lists [of] seafood species.</s>
 <s id="17">The association is very easy: buy green, don't buy red, think twice about yellow.</s>
 <s id="18">But in my mind, it's really not enough to just eat green list.</s>
 <s id="19">We can't sustain this without the measure of our success really changing the fate of the species in the yellow and the red.</s>
 <s id="20">But what if we eat only in the green list?</s>
 <s id="21">You've got pole-caught yellowfin tuna here -- comes from sustainable stocks.</s>
 <s id="22">Pole caught -- no bycatch.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">Great for fishermen.</s>
  <s id="23.2">Lots of money.</s>
  <s id="23.3">Supporting local economies.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">But it's a lion of the sea.</s>
  <s id="24.2">It's a top predator.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="25">What's the context of this meal?</s>
 <s id="26">Am I sitting down in a steakhouse to a 16-ounce portion of this?</s>
 <s id="27">Do I do this three times a week?</s>
 <s id="28">I might still be in the green list, but I'm not doing myself, or you, or the oceans any favors.</s>
 <s id="29">The point is that we have to have a context, a gauge for our actions in all this.</s>
 <s id="30">Example: I've heard that red wine is great for my health -- antioxidants and minerals -- heart healthy.</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">That's great!</s>
  <s id="31.2">I love red wine!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">I'm going to drink so much of it.</s>
  <s id="32.2">I'm going to be so healthy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="33">Well, how many bottles is it before you tell me that I have a problem?</s>
 <s id="34">Well folks, we have a protein problem.</s>
 <s id="35">We have lost this sensibility when it regards our food, and we are paying a cost.</s>
 <s id="36">The problem is we are hiding that cost beneath the waves.</s>
 <s id="37">We are hiding that cost behind the social acceptance of expanding waistlines.</s>
 <s id="38">And we are hiding that cost behind monster profits.</s>
 <s id="39">So the first thing about this idea of restorative seafood is that it really takes into account our needs.</s>
 <s id="40">Restorative seafood might best be represented not by Jaws, or by Flipper, or the Gordon's fisherman, but rather, by the Jolly Green Giant.</s>
 <s id="41">Vegetables: they might yet save the oceans.</s>
 <s id="42">Sylvia likes to say that blue is the new green.</s>
 <s id="43">Well I'd like to respectfully submit that broccoli green might then be the new blue.</s>
 <s id="44">We must continue to eat the best seafood possible, if at all.</s>
 <s id="45">But we also must eat it with a ton of vegetables.</s>
 <s id="46">The best part about restorative seafood though is that it comes on the half-shell with a bottle of Tabasco and lemon wedges.</s>
 <s id="47">It comes in a five-ounce portion of tilapia breaded with Dijon mustard and crispy, broiled breadcrumbs and a steaming pile of pecan quinoa pilaf with crunchy, grilled broccoli so soft and sweet and charred and smoky on the outside with just a hint of chili flake.</s>
 <s id="48">Whooo!</s>
 <s id="49">This is an easy sell.</s>
 <s id="50">And the best part is all of those ingredients are available to every family at the neighborhood Walmart.</s>
 <s id="51">Jamie Oliver is campaigning to save America from the way we eat.</s>
 <s id="52">Sylvia is campaigning to save the oceans from the way we eat.</s>
 <s id="53">There's a pattern here.</s>
 <s id="54">Forget nuclear holocaust; it's the fork that we have to worry about.</s>
 <s id="55">We have ravaged our Earth and then used the food that we've sourced to handicap ourselves in more ways than one.</s>
 <s id="56">So I think we have this whole eating thing wrong.</s>
 <s id="57">And so I think it's time we change what we expect from our food.</s>
 <s id="58">Sustainability is complicated but dinner is a reality that we all very much understand.</s>
 <s id="59">So let's start there.</s>
 <s id="60">There's been a lot of movement recently in greening our food systems.</s>
 <s id="61">Dan Barber and Alice Waters are leading passionately the green food Delicious Revolution.</s>
 <s id="62">But green foods often represent a way for us to disregard the responsibility as eaters.</s>
 <s id="63">Just because it comes from a green source doesn't mean we can treat it with disregard on the plate.</s>
 <s id="64">We have eco-friendly shrimp.</s>
 <s id="65">We can make them; we have that technology.</s>
 <s id="66">But we can never have any eco-friendly all-you-can-eat shrimp buffet.</s>
 <s id="67">It doesn't work.</s>
 <s id="68">Heart-healthy dinner is a very important part of restorative seafood.</s>
 <s id="69">While we try to manage declining marine populations, the media's recommending increased consumption of seafood.</s>
 <s id="70">Studies say that tens of thousands of American grandmothers, grandfathers, mothers and fathers might be around for another birthday if we included more seafood.</s>
 <s id="71">That's a reward I am not willing to pass up.</s>
 <s id="72">But it's not all about the seafood.</s>
 <s id="73">It's about the way that we look at our plates.</s>
 <s id="74">As a chef, I realize the easiest thing for me to do is reduce the portion sizes on my plate.</s>
 <s id="75">A couple things happened.</s>
 <s id="76">I made more money.</s>
 <s id="77">People started buying appetizers and salads, because they knew they weren't going to fill up on the entrees alone.</s>
 <s id="78">People spent more time engaging in their meals, engaging with each other over their meals.</s>
 <s id="79">People got, in short, more of what they came there for even though they got less protein.</s>
 <s id="80">They got more calories over the course of a diversified meal.</s>
 <p id="p81">
  <s id="81.1">They got healthier.</s>
  <s id="81.2">I made more money.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="82">This is great.</s>
 <s id="83">Environmental consideration was served with every plate, but it was served with a heaping mound of consideration for human interests at the same time.</s>
 <s id="84">One of the other things we did was begin to diversify the species that we served -- small silverfish, anchovies, mackerel, sardines were uncommon.</s>
 <s id="85">Shellfish, mussels, oysters, clams, tilapia, char -- these were the common species.</s>
 <s id="86">We were directing tastes towards more resilience, more restorative options.</s>
 <s id="87">This is what we need to favor.</s>
 <s id="88">This is what the green list says.</s>
 <s id="89">But this is also how we can actually begin to restore our environment.</s>
 <s id="90">But what of those big predators, those fashionable species, that green list tuna that I was talking about earlier?</s>
 <s id="91">Well, if you must, I have a recipe for you.</s>
 <s id="92">It pretty much works with any big fish in the ocean, so here we go.</s>
 <s id="93">Start with a 16-ounce portion of big fish.</s>
 <p id="p94">
  <s id="94.1">Get a knife.</s>
  <s id="94.2">Cut it into four portions.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="95">Put it on four plates.</s>
 <s id="96">Mound up those four plates with vegetables and then open up the very best bottle of Burgundy you have, light the candles and celebrate it.</s>
 <s id="97">Celebrate the opportunity you have to eat this.</s>
 <s id="98">Invite your friends and neighbors over and repeat once a year, maybe.</s>
 <s id="99">I expect a lot from food.</s>
 <s id="100">I expect health and joy and family and community.</s>
 <s id="101">I expect that producing ingredients, preparing dishes and eating meals is all part of the communion of human interests.</s>
 <s id="102">I was lucky enough that my father was a fantastic cook.</s>
 <s id="103">And he taught me very early on about the privilege that eating represents.</s>
 <s id="104">I remember well the meals of my childhood.</s>
 <s id="105">They were reasonable portions of protein served with copious quantities of vegetables and small amounts of starch, usually rice.</s>
 <s id="106">This is still how I largely eat today.</s>
 <s id="107">I get sick when I go to steakhouses.</s>
 <s id="108">I get the meat sweats.</s>
 <s id="109">It's like a hangover from protein.</s>
 <s id="110">It's disgusting.</s>
 <s id="111">But of all the dire news that you'll hear and that you have heard about the state of our oceans, I have the unfortunate burden of delivering to you possibly the very worst of it and that is this whole time your mother was right.</s>
 <s id="112">Eat your vegetables.</s>
 <s id="113">It's pretty straightforward.</s>
 <s id="114">So what are we looking for in a meal?</s>
 <s id="115">Well for health, I'm looking for wholesome ingredients that are good for my body.</s>
 <s id="116">For joy, I'm looking for butter and salt and sexy things that make things taste less like penance.</s>
 <s id="117">For family, I'm looking for recipes that genuflect to my own personal histories.</s>
 <s id="118">For community though, we start at the very beginning.</s>
 <s id="119">There's no escaping the fact that everything we eat has a global impact.</s>
 <s id="120">So try and learn as best you can what that impact is and then take the first step to minimize it.</s>
 <s id="121">We've seen an image of our blue planet, our world bank.</s>
 <s id="122">But it is more than just a repository of our resources; it's also the global geography of the communion we call dinner.</s>
 <s id="123">So if we all take only what we need, then we can begin to share the rest, we can begin to celebrate, we can begin to restore.</s>
 <s id="124">We need to savor vegetables.</s>
 <s id="125">We need to savor smaller portions of seafood.</s>
 <s id="126">And we need to save dinner.</s>
 <s id="127">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="128">(Applause)</s>
</text>
