<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">A new virus emerges and spreads like wildfire.</s>
 <s id="2">In order to contain it, researchers must first collect data about who’s been infected.</s>
 <s id="3">Two main viral testing techniques are critical: one tells you if you have the virus and the other shows if you’ve already had it.</s>
 <s id="4">So, how exactly do these tests work?</s>
 <s id="5">PCR, or polymerase chain reaction testing, targets the virus’s genetic material in the body and is used to diagnose someone who is currently infected.</s>
 <s id="6">Yet, this genetic material may be present in such imperceptible amounts that actually detecting it is difficult.</s>
 <s id="7">This is where PCR comes in: it’s widely used to amplify genetic information to large enough quantities that it can be readily observed.</s>
 <s id="8">To develop a PCR test for a never-before-seen virus, researchers first sequence its genetic material, or genome, and identify regions that are unique to that specific virus.</s>
 <s id="9">PCR then targets these particular segments.</s>
 <s id="10">A PCR test begins by collecting a sample: this can be blood for hepatitis viruses, feces for poliovirus, and samples from the nose or throat for coronaviruses.</s>
 <s id="11">The sample is taken to a central laboratory where PCR is performed to test for the presence of the virus’ genome.</s>
 <s id="12">Genetic information can be encoded via DNA or RNA.</s>
 <s id="13">HPV, for example, uses DNA, while SARS-CoV-2, the cause of COVID-19, uses RNA.</s>
 <s id="14">Before running the PCR, the viral RNA— if present— must be reverse transcribed to make a strand of complementary DNA.</s>
 <s id="15">Researchers then run the PCR.</s>
 <s id="16">If the virus is present in the sample, its unique regions of genetic code will be identified by complementary primers and copied by enzymes.</s>
 <s id="17">One strand of DNA becomes hundreds of millions, which are detected using probes marked with fluorescent dye.</s>
 <s id="18">If the PCR machine senses fluorescence, the sample has tested positive for the virus, meaning the individual is infected.</s>
 <s id="19">Immunoassays, on the other hand, tap into the immune system’s memory of the virus, showing if someone has previously been infected.</s>
 <s id="20">They work by targeting virus-specific antibodies generated by the immune system during infection.</s>
 <s id="21">These are specialized classes of proteins that identify and fight foreign substances, like viruses.</s>
 <s id="22">Immunoassays may detect IgG antibodies, the most abundant class, and IgM antibodies, the type that’s first produced in response to a new infection.</s>
 <s id="23">The presence of IgM antibodies suggests a recent infection, but since it can take the body over a week to produce a detectable amount, they’re unreliable in diagnosing current infections.</s>
 <s id="24">Meanwhile, IgG antibodies circulate for an extended period after infection; their presence usually indicates that someone was exposed and recovered.</s>
 <s id="25">Before the immunoassay, health professionals draw blood from an individual.</s>
 <s id="26">This sample then comes into contact with a portion of the virus of interest.</s>
 <s id="27">If the body has, in fact, been exposed to the virus in the past, the body’s virus-specific antibodies will bind to it during the test.</s>
 <s id="28">This reaction produces a change in color, indicating that the sample tested positive and that the individual has been exposed to the virus.</s>
 <s id="29">Immunoassays are especially important when it comes to retroactively diagnosing people who were infected but went untested.</s>
 <s id="30">And there’s exciting potential for those who have developed immunity to a virus: in some cases, their blood plasma could be used as treatment in people who are currently fighting it.</s>
 <s id="31">PCR and immunoassays are always in the process of becoming more accurate and efficient.</s>
 <s id="32">For example, innovations in PCR have led to the use of self-contained testing devices that relay results within one hour.</s>
 <s id="33">Digital PCR, which quantifies individual pieces of target DNA, shows promise in further boosting accuracy.</s>
 <s id="34">And although immunoassays are difficult to develop quickly, researchers in Singapore were able to create one for SARS-CoV-2 even before COVID-19 was declared a pandemic.</s>
 <s id="35">These tests— along with the scientists who develop them and the health professionals who administer them— are absolutely essential.</s>
 <s id="36">And when deployed early, they can save millions of lives.</s>
</text>
