<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The creative process -- you know this -- from the first idea to the final product, is a long process.</s>
 <s id="2">It's super-iterative, lots of refinement, blood, sweat, tears and years.</s>
 <s id="3">And we're not saying you're going to go out for a walk and come back with the Sistine Chapel in your left hand.</s>
 <s id="4">So what frame of the creative process did we focus on?</s>
 <s id="5">Just this first part.</s>
 <s id="6">Just brainstorming, coming up with a new idea.</s>
 <s id="7">We actually ran four studies with a variety of people.</s>
 <s id="8">You were either walking indoors or outdoors.</s>
 <s id="9">And all of these studies found the same conclusion.</s>
 <s id="10">I'm only going to tell you about one of them today.</s>
 <s id="11">One of the tests we used for creativity was alternate uses.</s>
 <s id="12">In this test, you have four minutes.</s>
 <s id="13">Your job is to come up with as many other ways to use common everyday objects as you can think of.</s>
 <s id="14">So, for example, what else would you do with a key, other than to use it for opening up a lock?</s>
 <s id="15">Clearly, you could use it as a third eyeball for a giraffe, right?</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">Maybe.</s>
  <s id="16.2">That's sort of interesting, kind of new.</s>
  <s id="16.3">But is it creative?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="17">So people came up with as many ideas as they could, and we had to decide: Is this creative or not?</s>
 <s id="18">The definition of creativity that a lot of people go with is "appropriate novelty."</s>
 <s id="19">For something to be appropriate, it has to be realistic, so unfortunately, you can't use a key as an eyeball.</s>
 <s id="20">Boo!</s>
 <s id="21">But "novel," the second thing, is that nobody had to have said it.</s>
 <s id="22">So for us, it had to be appropriate first, and then for novelty, nobody else in the entire population that we surveyed could have said it.</s>
 <s id="23">So you might think you could use a key to scratch somebody's car, but if somebody else said that, you didn't get credit for it.</s>
 <s id="24">Neither of you did.</s>
 <s id="25">However, only one person said this: "If you were dying and it were a murder mystery, and you had to carve the name of the murderer into the ground with your dying words."</s>
 <s id="26">One person said this.</s>
 <s id="27">(Laughter) And it's a creative idea, because it's appropriate and it's novel.</s>
 <s id="28">You either did this test and came up with ideas while you were seated or while you were walking on a treadmill.</s>
 <s id="29">(Laughter) They did the test twice, with different objects.</s>
 <s id="30">Three groups: the first group sat first and then sat again for the second test.</s>
 <s id="31">The second group sat first and then did the second test while walking on a treadmill.</s>
 <s id="32">The third group -- and this is interesting -- they walked on the treadmill first, and then they sat.</s>
 <s id="33">OK, so the two groups that sat together for the first test, they looked pretty similar to each other, and they averaged about 20 creative ideas per person.</s>
 <s id="34">The group that was walking on the treadmill did almost twice as well.</s>
 <s id="35">And they were just walking on a treadmill in a windowless room.</s>
 <s id="36">Remember, they took the test twice.</s>
 <s id="37">The people who sat twice for that second test didn't get any better; practice didn't help.</s>
 <s id="38">But these same people who were sitting and then went on the treadmill got a boost from walking.</s>
 <s id="39">Here's the interesting thing.</s>
 <s id="40">The people who were walking on the treadmill still had a residue effect of the walking, and they were still creative afterwards.</s>
 <s id="41">So the implication of this is that you should go for a walk before your next big meeting and just start brainstorming right away.</s>
 <s id="42">We have five tips for you that will help make this the best effect possible.</s>
 <s id="43">First, you want to pick a problem or a topic to brainstorm.</s>
 <s id="44">So, this is not the shower effect, when you're in the shower and all of a sudden, a new idea pops out of the shampoo bottle.</s>
 <s id="45">This is something you're thinking about ahead of time.</s>
 <s id="46">They're intentionally thinking about brainstorming a different perspective on the walk.</s>
 <s id="47">Secondly -- I get asked this a lot: Is this OK while running?</s>
 <s id="48">Well, the answer for me is that if I were running, the only new idea I would have would be to stop running, so ...</s>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) But if running for you is a comfortable pace, good.</s>
 <s id="50">It turns out, whatever physical activity is not taking a lot of attention.</s>
 <s id="51">So just walking at a comfortable pace is a good choice.</s>
 <s id="52">Also, you want to come up with as many ideas as you can.</s>
 <s id="53">One key of creativity is to not lock on that first idea.</s>
 <s id="54">Keep going.</s>
 <s id="55">Keep coming up with new ones, until you pick one or two to pursue.</s>
 <s id="56">You might worry that you don't want to write them down, because what if you forget them?</s>
 <s id="57">So the idea here is to speak them.</s>
 <s id="58">Everybody was speaking their new ideas.</s>
 <s id="59">So you can put your headphones on and record through your phone and then just pretend you're having a creative conversation, right?</s>
 <s id="60">Because the act of writing your idea down is already a filter.</s>
 <s id="61">You're going to be like, "Is this good enough to write down?"</s>
 <s id="62">And then you write it down.</s>
 <s id="63">So just speak as many as you can, record them and think about them later.</s>
 <p id="p64">
  <s id="64.1">And finally: don't do this forever.</s>
  <s id="64.2">Right?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="65">If you're on the walk and that idea's not coming to you, come back to it later at another time.</s>
 <s id="66">I think we're coming up on a break right now, so I have an idea: Why don't you grab a leash and take your thoughts for a walk?</s>
 <s id="67">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="68">(Applause)</s>
</text>
