<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I am a PhD student.</s>
 <s id="2">And that means I have a question: How can we make digital content graspable?</s>
 <s id="3">Because you see, on the one hand, there is the digital world and no question, many things are happening there right now.</s>
 <s id="4">And for us humans, it's not quite material, it's not really there -- it's virtual.</s>
 <s id="5">On the other hand, we're humans, we live in a physical world.</s>
 <s id="6">It's rich, it tastes good, it feels good, it smells good.</s>
 <s id="7">So the question is: How do we get the stuff over from the digital into the physical?</s>
 <s id="8">That's my question.</s>
 <s id="9">If you look at the iPhone with its touch and the Wii with its bodily activity, you can see the tendency; it's getting physical.</s>
 <s id="10">The question is: What's next?</s>
 <s id="11">Now, I have three options that I would like to show you.</s>
 <s id="12">The first one is mass.</s>
 <s id="13">As humans, we are sensitive to where an object in our hand is heavy.</s>
 <s id="14">So could we use that in mobile phones?</s>
 <s id="15">Let me show you the weight-shifting mobile.</s>
 <s id="16">It is a mobile phone-shaped box that has an iron weight inside, which we can move around, and you can feel where it's heavy.</s>
 <s id="17">We shift the gravitational center of it.</s>
 <s id="18">For example, we can augment digital content with physical mass.</s>
 <s id="19">So you move around the content on the display, but you can also feel where it is just from the weight of the device.</s>
 <s id="20">Another thing it's good for is navigation.</s>
 <s id="21">It can guide you around in a city.</s>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">It can tell you by its weight, "OK, move right.</s>
  <s id="22.2">Walk ahead.</s>
  <s id="22.3">Make a left here."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">And the good thing about that is, you don't have to look at the device all the time; you have your eyes free to see the city.</s>
 <s id="24">Now, mass is the first thing -- the second thing, that's shape.</s>
 <s id="25">We're also sensitive to the shape of objects we have in our hands.</s>
 <s id="26">So if I download an e-book and it has 20 pages -- well, they could be thin, right?</s>
 <s id="27">But if it has 500 pages, I want to feel that "Harry Potter" -- it's thick.</s>
 <s id="28">(Laughter) So let me show you the shape-changing mobile.</s>
 <s id="29">Again, it's a mobile phone-shaped box, and this one can change its shape.</s>
 <s id="30">We can play with the shape itself.</s>
 <s id="31">For example, it can be thin in your pocket, which we of course want it to be.</s>
 <s id="32">But then if you hold it in your hand, it can lean towards you, be thick.</s>
 <s id="33">It's like tapered to the downside.</s>
 <s id="34">If you change the grasp, it can adjust to that.</s>
 <s id="35">It's also useful if you want to put it down on your nightstand to watch a movie or use as an alarm clock.</s>
 <s id="36">It stands.</s>
 <s id="37">It's fairly simple.</s>
 <s id="38">Another thing is, sometimes we watch things on a mobile phone that are bigger than the phone itself.</s>
 <s id="39">In that case -- like here, there's an app that's bigger than the phone's screen -- the shape of the phone could tell you, "OK, off the screen, right here, there is more content.</s>
 <s id="40">You can't see it, but it's there."</s>
 <s id="41">And you can feel it, because it's thicker at that edge.</s>
 <s id="42">The shape is the second thing.</s>
 <s id="43">The third thing operates on a different level.</s>
 <s id="44">As humans, we are social, we are empathic, and that's great.</s>
 <s id="45">Wouldn't that be a way to make mobile phones more intuitive?</s>
 <s id="46">Think of a hamster in the pocket.</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">Well, I can feel it, it's doing all right.</s>
  <s id="47.2">I don't have to check it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="48">(Laughter) Let me show you the living mobile phone.</s>
 <s id="49">So, once again, a mobile phone-shaped box.</s>
 <s id="50">But this one, it has a breath and a heartbeat, and it feels very organic.</s>
 <s id="51">(Laughter) And you can tell, it's relaxed right now.</s>
 <s id="52">Oh, now -- missed call, a new call, new girlfriend, maybe -- very exciting.</s>
 <s id="53">(Laughter) How do we calm it down?</s>
 <s id="54">You give it a pat behind the ears, and everything is all right again.</s>
 <s id="55">That's very intuitive, and that's what we want.</s>
 <s id="56">So what we have seen are three ways to make the digital graspable for us.</s>
 <s id="57">And I think making it physical is a good way to do that.</s>
 <s id="58">What's behind that is a postulation, namely, not that humans should get much more technical in the future; rather than that, technology, a bit more human.</s>
 <s id="59">(Applause)</s>
</text>
