<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Have you experienced déjà vu?</s>
 <s id="2">It's that shadowy feeling you get when a situation seems familiar.</s>
 <s id="3">A scene in a restaurant plays out exactly as you remember.</s>
 <s id="4">The world moves like a ballet you've choreographed, but the sequence can't be based on a past experience because you've never eaten here before.</s>
 <s id="5">This is the first time you've had clams, so what's going on?</s>
 <s id="6">Unfortunately, there isn't one single explanation for déjà vu.</s>
 <s id="7">The experience is brief and occurs without notice, making it nearly impossible for scientists to record and study it.</s>
 <s id="8">Scientists can't simply sit around and wait for it to happen to them -- this could take years.</s>
 <s id="9">It has no physical manifestations and in studies, it's described by the subject as a sensation or feeling.</s>
 <s id="10">Because of this lack of hard evidence, there's been a surplus of speculation over the years.</s>
 <s id="11">Since Emile Boirac introduced déjà vu as a French term meaning "already seen," more than 40 theories attempt to explain this phenomenon.</s>
 <s id="12">Still, recent advancements in neuroimaging and cognitive psychology narrow down the field of prospects.</s>
 <s id="13">Let's walk through three of today's more prevalent theories, using the same restaurant setting for each.</s>
 <s id="14">First up is dual processing.</s>
 <s id="15">We'll need an action.</s>
 <s id="16">Let's go with a waiter dropping a tray of dishes.</s>
 <s id="17">As the scene unfolds, your brain's hemispheres process a flurry of information: the waiter's flailing arms, his cry for help, the smell of pasta.</s>
 <s id="18">Within milliseconds, this information zips through pathways and is processed into a single moment.</s>
 <s id="19">Most of the time, everything is recorded in-sync.</s>
 <s id="20">However, this theory asserts that déjà vu occurs when there's a slight delay in information from one of these pathways.</s>
 <s id="21">The difference in arrival times causes the brain to interpret the late information as a separate event.</s>
 <s id="22">When it plays over the already-recorded moment, it feels as if it's happened before because, in a sense, it has.</s>
 <s id="23">Our next theory deals with a confusion of the past rather than a mistake in the present.</s>
 <s id="24">This is the hologram theory, and we'll use that tablecloth to examine it.</s>
 <s id="25">As you scan its squares, a distant memory swims up from deep within your brain.</s>
 <s id="26">According to the theory, this is because memories are stored in the form of holograms, and in holograms, you only need one fragment to see the whole picture.</s>
 <s id="27">Your brain has identified the tablecloth with one from the past, maybe from your grandmother's house.</s>
 <s id="28">However, instead of remembering that you've seen it at your grandmother's, your brain has summoned up the old memory without identifying it.</s>
 <s id="29">This leaves you stuck with familiarity, but no recollection.</s>
 <s id="30">Although you've never been in this restaurant, you've seen that tablecloth but are just failing to identify it.</s>
 <s id="31">Now, look at this fork.</s>
 <s id="32">Are you paying attention?</s>
 <s id="33">Our last theory is divided attention, and it states that déjà vu occurs when our brain subliminally takes in an environment while we're distracted by one particular object.</s>
 <s id="34">When our attention returns, we feel as if we've been here before.</s>
 <s id="35">For example, just now you focused on the fork and didn't observe the tablecloth or the falling waiter.</s>
 <s id="36">Although your brain has been recording everything in your peripheral vision, it's been doing so below conscious awareness.</s>
 <s id="37">When you finally pull yourself away from the fork, you think you've been here before because you have, you just weren't paying attention.</s>
 <s id="38">While all three of these theories share the common features of déjà vu, none of them propose to be the conclusive source of the phenomenon.</s>
 <s id="39">Still, while we wait for researchers and inventers to come up with new ways to capture this fleeting moment, we can study the moment ourselves.</s>
 <s id="40">After all, most studies of déjà vu are based on first-hand accounts, so why can't one be yours?</s>
 <s id="41">The next time you get déjà vu, take a moment to think about it.</s>
 <s id="42">Have you been distracted?</s>
 <s id="43">Is there a familiar object somewhere?</s>
 <s id="44">Is your brain just acting slow?</s>
 <s id="45">Or is it something else?</s>
</text>
