<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Approximately 7 million people around the world die from heart attacks every year, and cardiovascular disease, which causes heart attacks and other problems like strokes, is the world's leading killer.</s>
 <s id="2">So what causes a heart attack?</s>
 <s id="3">Like all muscles, the heart needs oxygen, and during a heart attack, it can't get enough.</s>
 <s id="4">Fatty deposits, or plaques, develop on the walls of our coronary arteries.</s>
 <s id="5">Those are the vessels that supply oxygenated blood to the heart.</s>
 <s id="6">These plaques grow as we age, sometimes getting chunky, hardened, or enflamed.</s>
 <s id="7">Eventually, the plaques can turn into blockages.</s>
 <s id="8">If one of the plaques ruptures or cracks, a blood clot will form around it in minutes, and a partially closed artery can become completely blocked.</s>
 <s id="9">Blood flow is cut off to the cardiac muscle and the oxygen-starved cells start to die within several minutes.</s>
 <s id="10">This is a myocardial infarction, or heart attack.</s>
 <s id="11">Things can rapidly deteriorate in the absence of treatment.</s>
 <s id="12">The injured muscle may not be able to pump blood as well, and its rhythm might be thrown off.</s>
 <s id="13">In the worst case scenario, a heart attack can cause sudden death.</s>
 <s id="14">And how do you know that someone is having a heart attack?</s>
 <s id="15">The most common symptom is chest pain caused by the oxygen-deprived heart muscle.</s>
 <s id="16">Patients describe it as crushing or vice-like.</s>
 <s id="17">It can radiate to the left arm, jaw, back, or abdomen.</s>
 <s id="18">But it's not always as sudden and dramatic as it is in the movies.</s>
 <s id="19">Some people experience nausea or shortness of breath.</s>
 <s id="20">Symptoms may be less prominent in women and the elderly.</s>
 <s id="21">For them, weakness and tiredness may be the main signal.</s>
 <s id="22">And surprisingly, in many people, especially those with diabetes, which affects the nerves that carry pain, a heart attack may be silent.</s>
 <s id="23">If you think that someone might be having a heart attack, the most important thing is to respond quickly.</s>
 <s id="24">If you have access to emergency medical services, call them.</s>
 <s id="25">They're the fastest way to get to a hospital.</s>
 <s id="26">Taking aspirin, which thins the blood, and nitroglycerin, which opens up the artery, can help keep the heart attack from getting worse.</s>
 <s id="27">In the emergency room, doctors can diagnose a heart attack.</s>
 <s id="28">They commonly use an electrocardiogram to measure the heart's electrical activity and a blood test to assess heart muscle damage.</s>
 <s id="29">The patient is then taken to a high-tech cardiac suite where tests are done to locate the blockages.</s>
 <s id="30">Cardiologists can reopen the blocked artery by inflating it with a balloon in a procedure called an angioplasty.</s>
 <s id="31">Frequently, they also insert a metal or polymer stent that will hold the artery open.</s>
 <s id="32">More extensive blockages might require coronary artery bypass surgery.</s>
 <s id="33">Using a piece of vein or artery from another part of the body, heart surgeons can reroute blood flow around the blockage.</s>
 <s id="34">These procedures reestablish circulation to the cardiac muscle, restoring heart function.</s>
 <s id="35">Heart attack treatment is advancing, but prevention is vital.</s>
 <s id="36">Genetics and lifestyle factors both affect your risk.</s>
 <s id="37">And the good news is that you can change your lifestyle.</s>
 <s id="38">Exercise, a healthy diet, and weight loss all lower the risk of heart attacks, whether you've had one before or not.</s>
 <s id="39">Doctors recommend exercising a few times a week, doing both aerobic activity and strength training.</s>
 <s id="40">A heart-healthy diet is low in sugar and saturated fats, which are both linked to heart disease.</s>
 <s id="41">So what should you eat?</s>
 <s id="42">Lots of fiber from vegetables, chicken and fish instead of red meat, whole grains and nuts like walnuts and almonds all seem to be beneficial.</s>
 <s id="43">A good diet and exercise plan can also keep your weight in a healthy range, which will lower your heart attack risk as well.</s>
 <s id="44">And of course, medications can also help prevent heart attacks.</s>
 <s id="45">Doctors often prescribe low-dose aspirin, for example, particularly for patients who've already had a heart attack and for those known to be at high risk.</s>
 <s id="46">And drugs that help manage risk factors, like high blood pressure, cholesterol, and diabetes, will make heart attacks less likely, too.</s>
 <s id="47">Heart attacks may be common, but they don't have to be inevitable.</s>
 <s id="48">A healthy diet, avoiding tobacco use, staying fit, and enjoying plenty of sleep and lots of laughter all go a long way in making sure your body's most important muscle keeps on beating.</s>
</text>
