<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Two years ago, in a small village in Nigeria, men with AK-47s stormed Chibok Government Secondary School.</s>
 <s id="2">Men from the extremist group, Boko Haram, kidnapped 276 young, innocent schoolgirls.</s>
 <s id="3">Today, 218 are still missing.</s>
 <s id="4">I worked in and out of Nigeria for three years starting in 2007, and I remember seeing the kids going to school along dirt roads.</s>
 <s id="5">They had smiles, they were polite, they were dressed neatly.</s>
 <s id="6">They often talked about the books they were reading.</s>
 <s id="7">That was tough on the kids, but they went to school for a safe place.</s>
 <s id="8">They went to school for dreams of a better future.</s>
 <s id="9">But turning those dreams into reality in Nigeria is difficult, because 61% of the people live at poverty level.</s>
 <s id="10">Compare that to the US at 15%.</s>
 <s id="11">The annual income is slightly below $6,000; compare that to the US, of $56,000.</s>
 <s id="12">Now you see the problem.</s>
 <s id="13">But I wasn't there in Nigeria trying to resolve an income disparity.</s>
 <s id="14">I wasn't there trying to volunteer for a charity, or to set up a nonprofit organization.</s>
 <s id="15">I was there to promote trade where it's very limited.</s>
 <s id="16">I strongly believe when communities are isolated from the global economy, they could become the breeding grounds of groups like Boko Haram.</s>
 <s id="17">Just the definition of "Boko Haram" stands for: "Western education is forbidden."</s>
 <s id="18">That isolation in itself is dangerous.</s>
 <s id="19">I ask you one question: Would those girls still be in school in Chibok if the conditions were different that gave rise to Boko Haram?</s>
 <s id="20">You know, you have to wonder, what if Nigerian people had access to gain full employment?</s>
 <s id="21">Or villages like Chibok were more integrated in the global economy?</s>
 <s id="22">Or families could break that poverty cycle through jobs and education?</s>
 <s id="23">Trade is a powerful weapon.</s>
 <s id="24">Trade can fight against poverty and injustice.</s>
 <s id="25">Trade is the gun to combat human trafficking.</s>
 <s id="26">Trade provides medicine to the sick.</s>
 <s id="27">Trade provides a roof for people in need of shelter.</s>
 <s id="28">Trade is the answer to give dignity back to millions of unprivileged people.</s>
 <s id="29">Trade is a humanitarian's strongest weapon.</s>
 <s id="30">I work for a company that facilitates trade in 220 countries, and I've personally assisted trade in 46 of them.</s>
 <s id="31">I've seen trade in action.</s>
 <s id="32">I see trade work.</s>
 <s id="33">But you don't have to take my word for it: economists have been studying it for years.</s>
 <s id="34">In his book "The World Is Flat," Tom Friedman said when countries trade with each other, they're the same supply chain, and they don't inflict military damage on each other.</s>
 <s id="35">But Secretary of State, Cordell Hull, who won the Nobel Peace Prize in 1945, said it best: "When goods do not cross borders, armies do."</s>
 <s id="36">So what is this magical weapon I call "trade"?</s>
 <s id="37">It's simple: I have something you want, you have something I need.</s>
 <s id="38">We make an exchange.</s>
 <s id="39">But the question is: How can something so simple have such a dramatic impact on poverty and security?</s>
 <s id="40">Let's start with poverty.</s>
 <s id="41">There's no better example than China.</s>
 <s id="42">Before China adopted economic reform 37 years ago, it maintained policies to keep the country poor.</s>
 <s id="43">Then in 1979, it implemented economic reform.</s>
 <s id="44">It allowed international trade and foreign investment.</s>
 <s id="45">And we all know what happened -- China's the fastest-growing economy.</s>
 <s id="46">But here's something: In that nation, in 1990, the annual income was only $980.</s>
 <s id="47">Fast-forward to 2015, it's a little over $14,000.</s>
 <s id="48">The poverty levels decreased [from] 84% from 1980 to 10% in 2013.</s>
 <s id="49">The unemployment rate is at 4.1%, slightly below 4.9% of that in the US.</s>
 <s id="50">Let's talk security.</s>
 <p id="p51">
  <s id="51.1">I started traveling in Colombia in 2010, and people were saying, "Are you scared?</s>
  <s id="51.2">Are you nervous?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="52">And that's because, 10 to 15 years earlier, the drug lords and the drug cartel would kidnap and torture people.</s>
 <s id="53">But then the government pumped in economic resources, and they stabilized their political platform.</s>
 <s id="54">That made a huge difference.</s>
 <s id="55">I feel very safe going to Colombia, seeing customers.</s>
 <s id="56">In fact, I just got back from Bogotá last week.</s>
 <s id="57">Colombia thanks trade for improved security, reduction of poverty, and a very attractive image to the world.</s>
 <s id="58">And I have a beautiful example of that.</s>
 <s id="59">Colombia exported $1.3 billion of roses and flowers in 2013, with 75% coming to the US.</s>
 <s id="60">So you see, trade clearly is a powerful weapon to fight poverty and crime.</s>
 <s id="61">But it doesn't stop there.</s>
 <s id="62">If I was to say "Haiti," what would pop into your mind?</s>
 <s id="63">Earthquake, hunger, poverty.</s>
 <s id="64">Would anyone think of fashion?</s>
 <s id="65">In 2010, the earthquake killed 230,000 Haitians, and displaced 1.5 million.</s>
 <s id="66">Julie Colombino from Orlando, Florida went there to help.</s>
 <s id="67">She saw humanitarian aid pour in, but she knew it wasn't sustainable.</s>
 <s id="68">She started a nonprofit company called "REBUILD globally," and this nonprofit taught Haitians how to make sandals out of old tires, which are very abundant there.</s>
 <s id="69">From that nonprofit company, spun Deux Mains, a profit company, and that caught the eye of Kenneth Cole.</s>
 <s id="70">Haiti has something the fashion world needs.</s>
 <s id="71">They have great designs, they have top-quality craftsmanship, they have eco-friendly products.</s>
 <s id="72">Kenneth Cole has the global brand and the distribution model to give Deux Mains shoes to the world.</s>
 <s id="73">Trade, pure and simple.</s>
 <s id="74">Deux Mains has made more than 2,400 pairs of sandals for Kenneth Cole, and now is in negotiation with Ron Jon, another global brand.</s>
 <s id="75">These sandals I have on today?</s>
 <s id="76">Yes, they've got the old tires on the bottom of them.</s>
 <s id="77">But my purchase was made to help Haiti out of poverty.</s>
 <s id="78">My $70 I paid wasn't a charitable contribution, it wasn't a handout.</s>
 <s id="79">It was basic economics.</s>
 <s id="80">It was trade at work.</s>
 <s id="81">Julie Colombino shared with me that for every 250 pairs of shoes produced, one more Haitian is employed.</s>
 <s id="82">So that got me thinking.</s>
 <s id="83">In the United States, each of us buys seven and a half pairs of shoes a year.</s>
 <s id="84">That's 2.4 billion pairs of shoes.</s>
 <s id="85">Now just think: If one-tenth of 1% was produced in Deux Mains, that would be 2.4 million pairs of shoes.</s>
 <s id="86">But more importantly, it would pump $120 million into the Haitian economy, and give almost 10,000 people a job.</s>
 <s id="87">That type of employment in Haiti would have a ripple effect.</s>
 <s id="88">And as workshop supervisor Jolina Auguste told me, the more sandals they sell, the less thieves on the street.</s>
 <s id="89">So you see, when people have a job, security, money, they don't take other people's stuff.</s>
 <s id="90">They don't resort to crime to survive.</s>
 <s id="91">They don't get caught up with the drug lords like in Colombia, or terrorism that teaches them how to use AK-47s.</s>
 <s id="92">The Global Terrorist Index report in 2015 said economic conditions play a very important part in one's decision to pursue violent extremism.</s>
 <s id="93">The report also says Boko Haram is the most deadly terrorist organization in the world.</s>
 <s id="94">And it recruits from the most economically marginalized regions in Nigeria.</s>
 <s id="95">But on the other hand, if there is industrial growth, there's less domestic and international terrorism.</s>
 <s id="96">According to a 2015 study that was published in the Oxford Economic Papers, when industrial growth increases by 1%, domestic terrorism decreases by 1%.</s>
 <s id="97">So what does that mean?</s>
 <s id="98">When communities gain access to the global economy through trade, they reap so many benefits.</s>
 <s id="99">I stand here and ask you one last question: If Chibok were more connected through trade, and those young men who joined Boko Haram had an option to get a job in the formal economy, would those girls still be in school?</s>
 <s id="100">I think so.</s>
 <s id="101">Trade would have given them a weapon to fight terrorism.</s>
 <s id="102">Trade would have given them hope.</s>
 <s id="103">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="104">(Applause)</s>
</text>
