<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Hawa Abdi: Many people -- 20 years for Somalia -- [were] fighting.</s>
 <s id="2">So there was no job, no food.</s>
 <s id="3">Children, most of them, became very malnourished, like this.</s>
 <s id="4">Deqo Mohamed: So as you know, always in a civil war, the ones affected most [are] the women and children.</s>
 <s id="5">So our patients are women and children.</s>
 <s id="6">And they are in our backyard.</s>
 <p id="p7">
  <s id="7.1">It's our home.</s>
  <s id="7.2">We welcome them.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="8">That's the camp that we have in now 90,000 people, where 75 percent of them are women and children.</s>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">Pat Mitchell: And this is your hospital.</s>
  <s id="9.2">This is the inside.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="10">HA: We are doing C-sections and different operations because people need some help.</s>
 <s id="11">There is no government to protect them.</s>
 <s id="12">DM: Every morning we have about 400 patients, maybe more or less.</s>
 <s id="13">But sometimes we are only five doctors and 16 nurses, and we are physically getting exhausted to see all of them.</s>
 <s id="14">But we take the severe ones, and we reschedule the other ones the next day.</s>
 <s id="15">It is very tough.</s>
 <s id="16">And as you can see, it's the women who are carrying the children; it's the women who come into the hospitals; it's the women [are] building the houses.</s>
 <s id="17">That's their house.</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">And we have a school.</s>
  <s id="18.2">This is our bright -- we opened [in the] last two years [an] elementary school where we have 850 children, and the majority are women and girls.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="19">(Applause) PM: And the doctors have some very big rules about who can get treated at the clinic.</s>
 <s id="20">Would you explain the rules for admission?</s>
 <s id="21">HA: The people who are coming to us, we are welcoming.</s>
 <s id="22">We are sharing with them whatever we have.</s>
 <s id="23">But there are only two rules.</s>
 <s id="24">First rule: there is no clan distinguished and political division in Somali society.</s>
 <s id="25">[Whomever] makes those things we throw out.</s>
 <s id="26">The second: no man can beat his wife.</s>
 <s id="27">If he beat, we will put [him] in jail, and we will call the eldest people.</s>
 <s id="28">Until they identify this case, we'll never release him.</s>
 <s id="29">That's our two rules.</s>
 <s id="30">(Applause) The other thing that I have realized, that the woman is the most strong person all over the world.</s>
 <s id="31">Because the last 20 years, the Somali woman has stood up.</s>
 <s id="32">They were the leaders, and we are the leaders of our community and the hope of our future generations.</s>
 <s id="33">We are not just the helpless and the victims of the civil war.</s>
 <s id="34">We can reconcile.</s>
 <s id="35">We can do everything.</s>
 <s id="36">(Applause) DM: As my mother said, we are the future hope, and the men are only killing in Somalia.</s>
 <s id="37">So we came up with these two rules.</s>
 <s id="38">In a camp with 90,000 people, you have to come up with some rules or there is going to be some fights.</s>
 <s id="39">So there is no clan division, and no man can beat his wife.</s>
 <s id="40">And we have a little storage room where we converted a jail.</s>
 <s id="41">So if you beat your wife, you're going to be there.</s>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">(Applause) So empowering the women and giving the opportunity -- we are there for them.</s>
  <s id="42.2">They are not alone for this.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="43">PM: You're running a medical clinic.</s>
 <s id="44">It brought much, much needed medical care to people who wouldn't get it.</s>
 <s id="45">You're also running a civil society.</s>
 <s id="46">You've created your own rules, in which women and children are getting a different sense of security.</s>
 <s id="47">Talk to me about your decision, Dr. Abdi, and your decision, Dr. Mohamed, to work together -- for you to become a doctor and to work with your mother in these circumstances.</s>
 <s id="48">HA: My age -- because I was born in 1947 -- we were having, at that time, government, law and order.</s>
 <s id="49">But one day, I went to the hospital -- my mother was sick -- and I saw the hospital, how they [were] treating the doctors, how they [are] committed to help the sick people.</s>
 <s id="50">I admired them, and I decided to become a doctor.</s>
 <s id="51">My mother died, unfortunately, when I was 12 years [old].</s>
 <s id="52">Then my father allowed me to proceed [with] my hope.</s>
 <s id="53">My mother died in [a] gynecology complication, so I decided to become a gynecology specialist.</s>
 <s id="54">That's why I became a doctor.</s>
 <s id="55">So Dr. Deqo has to explain.</s>
 <s id="56">DM: For me, my mother was preparing [me] when I was a child to become a doctor, but I really didn't want to.</s>
 <s id="57">Maybe I should become an historian, or maybe a reporter.</s>
 <s id="58">I loved it, but it didn't work.</s>
 <s id="59">When the war broke out -- civil war -- I saw how my mother was helping and how she really needed the help, and how the care is essential to the woman to be a woman doctor in Somalia and help the women and children.</s>
 <s id="60">And I thought, maybe I can be a reporter and doctor gynecologist.</s>
 <s id="61">(Laughter) So I went to Russia, and my mother also, [during the] time of [the] Soviet Union.</s>
 <s id="62">So some of our character, maybe we will come with a strong Soviet background of training.</s>
 <s id="63">So that's how I decided [to do] the same.</s>
 <s id="64">My sister was different.</s>
 <p id="p65">
  <s id="65.1">She's here.</s>
  <s id="65.2">She's also a doctor.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="66">She graduated in Russia also.</s>
 <s id="67">(Applause) And to go back and to work with our mother is just what we saw in the civil war -- when I was 16, and my sister was 11, when the civil war broke out.</s>
 <s id="68">So it was the need and the people we saw in the early '90s -- that's what made us go back and work for them.</s>
 <s id="69">PM: So what is the biggest challenge working, mother and daughter, in such dangerous and sometimes scary situations?</s>
 <s id="70">HA: Yes, I was working in a tough situation, very dangerous.</s>
 <s id="71">And when I saw the people who needed me, I was staying with them to help, because I [could] do something for them.</s>
 <s id="72">Most people fled abroad.</s>
 <s id="73">But I remained with those people, and I was trying to do something -- [any] little thing I [could] do.</s>
 <s id="74">I succeeded in my place.</s>
 <s id="75">Now my place is 90,000 people who are respecting each other, who are not fighting.</s>
 <s id="76">But we try to stand on our feet, to do something, little things, we can for our people.</s>
 <s id="77">And I'm thankful for my daughters.</s>
 <s id="78">When they come to me, they help me to treat the people, to help.</s>
 <s id="79">They do everything for them.</s>
 <s id="80">They have done what I desire to do for them.</s>
 <s id="81">PM: What's the best part of working with your mother, and the most challenging part for you?</s>
 <s id="82">DM: She's very tough; it's most challenging.</s>
 <s id="83">She always expects us to do more.</s>
 <s id="84">And really when you think [you] cannot do it, she will push you, and I can do it.</s>
 <s id="85">That's the best part.</s>
 <s id="86">She shows us, trains us how to do and how to be better [people] and how to do long hours in surgery -- 300 patients per day, 10, 20 surgeries, and still you have to manage the camp -- that's how she trains us.</s>
 <s id="87">It is not like beautiful offices here, 20 patients, you're tired.</s>
 <s id="88">You see 300 patients, 20 surgeries and 90,000 people to manage.</s>
 <s id="89">PM: But you do it for good reasons.</s>
 <p id="p90">
  <s id="90.1">(Applause) Wait.</s>
  <s id="90.2">Wait.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="91">HA: Thank you.</s>
 <s id="92">DM: Thank you.</s>
 <p id="p93">
  <s id="93.1">(Applause) HA: Thank you very much.</s>
  <s id="93.2">DM: Thank you very much.</s>
 </p>
</text>
