<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">A leader is steady, firm, decisive, unwavering.</s>
 <s id="2">Never let 'em see you sweat, always have an answer.</s>
 <s id="3">[The Way We Work] My name is Dan, I'm a partner at a global creative consultancy.</s>
 <s id="4">But there's another side to me: Carrie Dragshaw, the character I created on Instagram.</s>
 <s id="5">As I thought about my double life, I couldn't help but wonder ...</s>
 <s id="6">When your true self is a little nontraditional, how much of it can you really bring to the office?</s>
 <s id="7">For some of us is authenticity off-limits?</s>
 <s id="8">For the first 10 years of my career, I thought there was one way to be a leader: decisive and serious.</s>
 <s id="9">But that's not me.</s>
 <s id="10">So I'd put on basically office drag to fit the role: I'd talk in a deeper voice, try to hold in my hand motions.</s>
 <s id="11">I'm someone who gets really excited about things, so I'd temper that.</s>
 <s id="12">I had this little voice in my head, telling me, "You're too gay, too feminine, too flamboyant."</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">I had one well-intentioned adviser who said, "Everyone knows you're gay.</s>
  <s id="13.2">And that's great.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">But you don't need to beat them over the head with it."</s>
 <s id="15">Cut to: me in a tutu, for Halloween 2016.</s>
 <s id="16">I dressed up as my favorite TV show character, Carrie Bradshaw, thinking my friends would get a kick out of it.</s>
 <s id="17">And then, things got crazy.</s>
 <s id="18">The post went viral, and at first it was pure fun.</s>
 <s id="19">I started getting these incredible messages from people about how happy it made them, how it encouraged them to be their authentic selves.</s>
 <s id="20">And I started to think, maybe this is the time to tell that little voice in my head to just shut up and let myself be me.</s>
 <s id="21">But then things got a little too big.</s>
 <s id="22">Carrie Dragshaw was everywhere -- In the "New York Post", "US Weekly" -- and I got terrified: "What would my bosses think?</s>
 <s id="23">Would my coworkers still respect me as a leader?</s>
 <s id="24">What would my clients think?"</s>
 <s id="25">I thought I was going to have to get a different job.</s>
 <s id="26">But then, something happened, something small.</s>
 <s id="27">I got a text from my boss, it wasn't long, it just said, "Wow, Cosmo!"</s>
 <s id="28">With a link to an article that had just gone up about me.</s>
 <s id="29">And it let me put that little, scared voice away and just be excited about this whole new world, rather than freaked out.</s>
 <s id="30">That's the power of one person, sometimes all it takes is one ally to make you feel comfortable.</s>
 <s id="31">And my coworkers started acting differently.</s>
 <s id="32">They became more open, more playful with me, it was as if knowing this other side of me gave them permission to be more of themselves as well.</s>
 <s id="33">I thought that openness and vulnerability would actually decrease my standing with my team.</s>
 <s id="34">But it's done the opposite.</s>
 <s id="35">Two years in, I never could have imagined that this part of me would not just be embraced, but could actually help my career.</s>
 <s id="36">Now, I'm lucky.</s>
 <s id="37">I work in New York City, in an office where creativity is valued and I was already pretty established in my career when all of this started.</s>
 <s id="38">Maybe that's you, maybe it isn't.</s>
 <s id="39">But all of this has taught me so much about just the importance of bringing your whole self to work.</s>
 <s id="40">And it's really challenged my own misperceptions about what it takes to be successful.</s>
 <s id="41">There's no one kind of way to be a leader.</s>
 <s id="42">It's about finding your strengths and finding ways to amplify them.</s>
 <s id="43">Before, if a meeting was hard, I'd put on my perfect leader mask.</s>
 <s id="44">Now, I can say, "Gosh, that was frustrating."</s>
 <s id="45">We can talk about challenges and struggles in an open way, rather than everybody pretending that they're fine until it's too late.</s>
 <s id="46">Concealing an identity takes work.</s>
 <s id="47">Think of all the wasted energy spent pretending, wishing you were someone different.</s>
 <s id="48">What's most interesting to me, though, is that in this big study of covering, 93 percent of those who say they're doing it also believe their organization values inclusion.</s>
 <s id="49">So clearly, our workplaces and all of our strange inner voices have a long way to go on acceptance.</s>
 <s id="50">There's a big difference between adapting and disguising.</s>
 <s id="51">And I think I learned that a little late.</s>
 <s id="52">Personally, I'm taking all of this as a call to be the ally who, like my boss did for me, lets people know that it's OK to open up.</s>
 <s id="53">If you're gay, or proud of your ethnic background, or have a disability or are deeply religious, see what it's like being your full self at work.</s>
 <s id="54">You might be pleasantly surprised.</s>
</text>
