<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Communicating underwater is challenging.</s>
 <s id="2">Light and odors don't travel well, so it's hard for animals to see or smell.</s>
 <s id="3">But sound moves about four times faster in water than in air, so in this dark environment, marine mammals often rely on vocalization to communicate.</s>
 <s id="4">That's why a chorus of sounds fills the ocean.</s>
 <s id="5">Clicks, pulses, whistles, groans, boings, cries, and trills, to name a few.</s>
 <s id="6">But the most famous parts of this underwater symphony are the evocative melodies, or songs, composed by the world's largest mammals, whales.</s>
 <s id="7">Whale songs are one of the most sophisticated communication systems in the animal kingdom.</s>
 <s id="8">Only a few species are known to sing.</s>
 <s id="9">Blue, fin, bowhead minke whales, and of course humpback whales.</s>
 <s id="10">These are all baleen whales which use hairy baleen plates instead of teeth to trap their prey.</s>
 <s id="11">Meanwhile, toothed whales do use echolocation, and they and other species of baleen whales make social sounds, such as cries and whistles, to communicate.</s>
 <s id="12">But those vocalizations lack the complexity of songs.</s>
 <s id="13">So how do they do it?</s>
 <s id="14">Land mammals like us generate sound by moving air over our vocal cords when we exhale, causing them to vibrate.</s>
 <s id="15">Baleen whales have a U-shaped fold of tissue between their lungs and their large inflatable organs called laryngeal sacs.</s>
 <s id="16">We don't know this for sure because it's essentially impossible to observe the internal organs of a living, singing whale, but we think that when a whale sings, muscular contractions in the throat and chest move air from the lungs across the U-fold and into the laryngeal sacs, causing the U-fold to vibrate.</s>
 <s id="17">The resulting sound resonates in the sacs like a choir singing in a cathedral making songs loud enough to propagate up to thousands of kilometers away.</s>
 <s id="18">Whales don't have to exhale to sing.</s>
 <s id="19">Instead, the air is recycled back into the lungs, creating sound once more.</s>
 <s id="20">One reason whale songs are so fascinating is their pattern.</s>
 <s id="21">Units, like moans, cries, and chirps are arranged in phrases.</s>
 <s id="22">Repeated phrases are assembled into themes.</s>
 <s id="23">Multiple themes repeated in a predictable pattern create a song.</s>
 <s id="24">This hierarchical structure is a kind of grammar.</s>
 <s id="25">Whale songs are extremely variable in duration, and whales can repeat them over and over.</s>
 <s id="26">In one recorded session, a humpback whale sang for 22 hours.</s>
 <s id="27">And why do they do it?</s>
 <s id="28">We don't yet know the exact purpose, but we can speculate.</s>
 <s id="29">Given that the singers are males and they mostly sing during the mating season, songs might be used to attract females.</s>
 <s id="30">Or perhaps they're territorial, used to deter other males.</s>
 <s id="31">Whales return to the same feeding and breeding grounds annually, and each discrete population has a different song.</s>
 <s id="32">Songs evolve over time as units or phrases are added, changed, or dropped.</s>
 <s id="33">And when males from different populations are feeding within earshot, phrases are often exchanged, maybe because new songs make them more attractive to breeding females.</s>
 <s id="34">This is one of the fastest examples of cultural transmission, where learned behaviors are passed between unrelated individuals of the same species.</s>
 <s id="35">We can eavesdrop on these songs using underwater microphones called hydrophones.</s>
 <s id="36">These help us track species when sightings or genetic samples are rare.</s>
 <s id="37">For example, scientists have been able to differentiate the elusive blue whale's populations worldwide based on their songs.</s>
 <s id="38">But the oceans are getting noisier as a result of human activity.</s>
 <s id="39">Boating, military sonar, underwater construction, and seismic surveys for oil are occurring more often which may interfere with whale's communication.</s>
 <s id="40">Some whales will avoid key feeding or breeding grounds if human noise is too loud.</s>
 <s id="41">And humpback whales have been observed to reduce their singing in response to noise 200 kilometers away.</s>
 <s id="42">Limiting human activity along migratory routes and in other critical habitats, and reducing noise pollution throughout the ocean would help ensure whales continued survival.</s>
 <s id="43">If the whales can keep singing and we can keep listening, maybe one day we'll truly understand what they're saying.</s>
</text>
