<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm a savant, or more precisely, a high-functioning autistic savant.</s>
 <s id="2">It's a rare condition.</s>
 <s id="3">And rarer still when accompanied, as in my case, by self-awareness and a mastery of language.</s>
 <s id="4">Very often when I meet someone and they learn this about me, there's a certain kind of awkwardness.</s>
 <s id="5">I can see it in their eyes.</s>
 <s id="6">They want to ask me something.</s>
 <s id="7">And in the end, quite often, the urge is stronger than they are and they blurt it out: "If I give you my date of birth, can you tell me what day of the week I was born on?"</s>
 <s id="8">(Laughter) Or they mention cube roots or ask me to recite a long number or long text.</s>
 <s id="9">I hope you'll forgive me if I don't perform a kind of one-man savant show for you today.</s>
 <s id="10">I'm going to talk instead about something far more interesting than dates of birth or cube roots -- a little deeper and a lot closer, to my mind, than work.</s>
 <s id="11">I want to talk to you briefly about perception.</s>
 <s id="12">When he was writing the plays and the short stories that would make his name, Anton Chekhov kept a notebook in which he noted down his observations of the world around him -- little details that other people seem to miss.</s>
 <s id="13">Every time I read Chekhov and his unique vision of human life, I'm reminded of why I too became a writer.</s>
 <s id="14">In my books, I explore the nature of perception and how different kinds of perceiving create different kinds of knowing and understanding.</s>
 <s id="15">Here are three questions drawn from my work.</s>
 <s id="16">Rather than try to figure them out, I'm going to ask you to consider for a moment the intuitions and the gut instincts that are going through your head and your heart as you look at them.</s>
 <s id="17">For example, the calculation: can you feel where on the number line the solution is likely to fall?</s>
 <s id="18">Or look at the foreign word and the sounds: can you get a sense of the range of meanings that it's pointing you towards?</s>
 <s id="19">And in terms of the line of poetry, why does the poet use the word hare rather than rabbit?</s>
 <s id="20">I'm asking you to do this because I believe our personal perceptions, you see, are at the heart of how we acquire knowledge.</s>
 <s id="21">Aesthetic judgments, rather than abstract reasoning, guide and shape the process by which we all come to know what we know.</s>
 <s id="22">I'm an extreme example of this.</s>
 <s id="23">My worlds of words and numbers blur with color, emotion and personality.</s>
 <s id="24">As Juan said, it's the condition that scientists call synesthesia, an unusual cross-talk between the senses.</s>
 <s id="25">Here are the numbers one to 12 as I see them -- every number with its own shape and character.</s>
 <s id="26">One is a flash of white light.</s>
 <s id="27">Six is a tiny and very sad black hole.</s>
 <s id="28">The sketches are in black and white here, but in my mind they have colors.</s>
 <s id="29">Three is green.</s>
 <s id="30">Four is blue.</s>
 <s id="31">Five is yellow.</s>
 <s id="32">I paint as well.</s>
 <s id="33">And here is one of my paintings.</s>
 <s id="34">It's a multiplication of two prime numbers.</s>
 <s id="35">Three-dimensional shapes and the space they create in the middle creates a new shape, the answer to the sum.</s>
 <s id="36">What about bigger numbers?</s>
 <s id="37">Well you can't get much bigger than Pi, the mathematical constant.</s>
 <s id="38">It's an infinite number -- literally goes on forever.</s>
 <s id="39">In this painting that I made of the first 20 decimals of Pi, I take the colors and the emotions and the textures and I pull them all together into a kind of rolling numerical landscape.</s>
 <s id="40">But it's not only numbers that I see in colors.</s>
 <s id="41">Words too, for me, have colors and emotions and textures.</s>
 <s id="42">And this is an opening phrase from the novel "Lolita."</s>
 <s id="43">And Nabokov was himself synesthetic.</s>
 <s id="44">And you can see here how my perception of the sound L helps the alliteration to jump right out.</s>
 <s id="45">Another example: a little bit more mathematical.</s>
 <s id="46">And I wonder if some of you will notice the construction of the sentence from "The Great Gatsby."</s>
 <s id="47">There is a procession of syllables -- wheat, one; prairies, two; lost Swede towns, three -- one, two, three.</s>
 <s id="48">And this effect is very pleasant on the mind, and it helps the sentence to feel right.</s>
 <s id="49">Let's go back to the questions I posed you a moment ago.</s>
 <s id="50">64 multiplied by 75.</s>
 <s id="51">If some of you play chess, you'll know that 64 is a square number, and that's why chessboards, eight by eight, have 64 squares.</s>
 <s id="52">So that gives us a form that we can picture, that we can perceive.</s>
 <s id="53">What about 75?</s>
 <s id="54">Well if 100, if we think of 100 as being like a square, 75 would look like this.</s>
 <s id="55">So what we need to do now is put those two pictures together in our mind -- something like this.</s>
 <s id="56">64 becomes 6,400.</s>
 <s id="57">And in the right-hand corner, you don't have to calculate anything.</s>
 <s id="58">Four across, four up and down -- it's 16.</s>
 <s id="59">So what the sum is actually asking you to do is 16, 16, 16.</s>
 <s id="60">That's a lot easier than the way that the school taught you to do math, I'm sure.</s>
 <s id="61">It's 16, 16, 16, 48, 4,800 -- 4,800, the answer to the sum.</s>
 <s id="62">Easy when you know how.</s>
 <s id="63">(Laughter) The second question was an Icelandic word.</s>
 <s id="64">I'm assuming there are not many people here who speak Icelandic.</s>
 <s id="65">So let me narrow the choices down to two.</s>
 <s id="66">Hnugginn: is it a happy word, or a sad word?</s>
 <s id="67">What do you say?</s>
 <s id="68">Okay.</s>
 <s id="69">Some people say it's happy.</s>
 <s id="70">Most people, a majority of people, say sad.</s>
 <s id="71">And it actually means sad.</s>
 <s id="72">(Laughter) Why do, statistically, a majority of people say that a word is sad, in this case, heavy in other cases?</s>
 <s id="73">In my theory, language evolves in such a way that sounds match, correspond with, the subjective, with the personal, intuitive experience of the listener.</s>
 <s id="74">Let's have a look at the third question.</s>
 <s id="75">It's a line from a poem by John Keats.</s>
 <s id="76">Words, like numbers, express fundamental relationships between objects and events and forces that constitute our world.</s>
 <s id="77">It stands to reason that we, existing in this world, should in the course of our lives absorb intuitively those relationships.</s>
 <s id="78">And poets, like other artists, play with those intuitive understandings.</s>
 <s id="79">In the case of hare, it's an ambiguous sound in English.</s>
 <s id="80">It can also mean the fibers that grow from a head.</s>
 <s id="81">And if we think of that -- let me put the picture up -- the fibers represent vulnerability.</s>
 <s id="82">They yield to the slightest movement or motion or emotion.</s>
 <s id="83">So what you have is an atmosphere of vulnerability and tension.</s>
 <s id="84">The hare itself, the animal -- not a cat, not a dog, a hare -- why a hare?</s>
 <s id="85">Because think of the picture -- not the word, the picture.</s>
 <s id="86">The overlong ears, the overlarge feet, helps us to picture, to feel intuitively, what it means to limp and to tremble.</s>
 <s id="87">So in these few minutes, I hope I've been able to share a little bit of my vision of things and to show you that words can have colors and emotions, numbers, shapes and personalities.</s>
 <s id="88">The world is richer, vaster than it too often seems to be.</s>
 <s id="89">I hope that I've given you the desire to learn to see the world with new eyes.</s>
 <s id="90">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="91">(Applause)</s>
</text>
