<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Jamie Oliver: My wish ...</s>
 <s id="2">is for you to help a strong, sustainable movement to educate every child about food.</s>
 <s id="3">(Music) To inspire families to cook again and to empower people everywhere to fight obesity.</s>
 <s id="4">I came here to start a food revolution that I profoundly believe in.</s>
 <s id="5">(Applause) [Great Big Story in partnership with TED] Narrator: They had a big idea to change the world.</s>
 <s id="6">But they couldn't do it alone.</s>
 <p id="p7">
  <s id="7.1">(Voices overlapping) So, my wish ...</s>
  <s id="7.2">My wish ...</s>
  <s id="7.3">I wish ...</s>
 </p>
 <s id="8">And now here's my wish.</s>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">[Torchbearers] [Ideas in action] (Knife chop) (Music) JO: Food is simple.</s>
  <s id="9.2">It's just raw ingredients.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="10">But it's the most powerful killer on the planet.</s>
 <s id="11">Every child has the human right to be taught about food: where it comes from, how it affects their body.</s>
 <s id="12">And they should be shown at school, because it's at the front line of the fight against obesity.</s>
 <s id="13">[London, England] [Charlton Manor Primary School] What happens at Charlton Manor is that incredible head teacher took it to the next level.</s>
 <s id="14">[Timothy Baker Head teacher] Timothy Baker: In the past, the children weren't eating the right things.</s>
 <s id="15">I've been inspired by Jamie to educate this school about the fact that we're feeding the children the wrong food.</s>
 <s id="16">And I thought, well, the timetable is an already crowded place -- there are so many lessons in the primary curriculum.</s>
 <s id="17">How can you introduce another subject for teachers to teach?</s>
 <s id="18">So we looked at English, we looked at maths, science, history, geography and we saw how we could put that around food.</s>
 <s id="19">(Children laugh) Elizabeth: When you incorporate cooking, it's something everyone looks forward to.</s>
 <s id="20">Male teacher: Today we're doing a little bit of science in the kitchen.</s>
 <s id="21">Female teacher: We are going to combine our lessons on Diwali, but also our lessons on shape and symmetry.</s>
 <s id="22">Male teacher: Is this a physical change or a chemical change?</s>
 <s id="23">Children: Physical!</s>
 <s id="24">Male teacher: You're right.</s>
 <s id="25">TB: For history topics, we talk about the history of chocolate, and so we can do a whole topic around that.</s>
 <s id="26">Male teacher: And the Aztecs have been cooking with chocolate -- TB: And it's interesting because it's not made as they think, with all the milk in that they would have had -- and the taste is very, very different.</s>
 <s id="27">Some children like it; some children don't.</s>
 <s id="28">(Laughter) For maths, simple weighing and measuring.</s>
 <s id="29">Female teacher: We're going to be doing a lot of measuring because we have to measure out some liquids, which we did last term, we did some measuring.</s>
 <s id="30">JO: What he's done is he's put food at the heart of the school, and he's fed the stomach and the mind.</s>
 <s id="31">(Children yell excitedly) TB: Charlton Manor is a state school.</s>
 <s id="32">About 80 percent of children come from areas that are identified as in poverty.</s>
 <s id="33">The children had very little experience of being outside in the countryside, knowing about food-growing.</s>
 <s id="34">Over a period of time, we were able to build a garden.</s>
 <s id="35">(Children shout) Students: Welcome to the Secret Garden!</s>
 <s id="36">Kehinde: This is our greenhouse.</s>
 <s id="37">This is our compost bin.</s>
 <s id="38">This is our wormery.</s>
 <s id="39">(Music) This is our vegetable patch.</s>
 <s id="40">And these are our chickens.</s>
 <s id="41">Sean: The chickens come out, and they try and chase you.</s>
 <s id="42">I had to run for my life.</s>
 <s id="43">TB: Up at the community garden, we've got two polytunnels so we can grow year-round.</s>
 <s id="44">Sean: I will pick onions, broccoli and carrots because they're all healthy, they make you stronger -- obviously -- and they just make me happy.</s>
 <s id="45">So, yeah.</s>
 <s id="46">(Birds chirp) TB: 12 or 13 years ago, there was a reluctance to engage in this sort of curriculum.</s>
 <s id="47">There were many people that couldn't see what we were aiming for and what we were trying to do.</s>
 <s id="48">Obesity hadn't reached the epidemic proportions it has reached now.</s>
 <s id="49">We're getting children that look and appear more healthy.</s>
 <s id="50">Concentration is so much higher.</s>
 <s id="51">Behavior issues are incredibly lower than they have been in the past.</s>
 <s id="52">Elizabeth: One the of the great things they've done is introduce us to worlds of healthy food.</s>
 <s id="53">Kehinde: Before, I was a really picky eater.</s>
 <s id="54">Sean: I feel better when I eat healthier food.</s>
 <s id="55">TB: When you fail your maths A level, that's not going to shorten your life by 10 years.</s>
 <s id="56">JO: You don't die young because you didn't do your geography homework.</s>
 <s id="57">These kids die young if they don't know how to feed themselves.</s>
 <s id="58">I think Tim and the team would inspire head teachers across the world -- and parents.</s>
 <s id="59">Any teacher has the same capacity to be as brilliant as he is.</s>
 <s id="60">His story, we want to replicate, but the truth is we've got so much more to do.</s>
 <s id="61">TB: Jamie really revolutionized our school dinners, and it really has hugely impacted all the children, but so many in a deep way which is going to stick with them for the rest of their lives.</s>
 <s id="62">When you change a life like that, it makes it all worthwhile.</s>
 <s id="63">From all of us at the Charlton Manor, thank you, Jamie.</s>
 <s id="64">Student: Thank you, Jamie.</s>
 <s id="65">Student: Thank you, Jamie.</s>
 <s id="66">[Join the food revolution JamiesFoodRevolution.org]</s>
</text>
