<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">When my 91-year-old mother, Elia, moved in with me, I thought I was doing her a service.</s>
 <s id="2">In fact, it was the other way around.</s>
 <s id="3">You see, Mom was having issues with memory loss and accepting her age.</s>
 <s id="4">She looked defeated.</s>
 <s id="5">I tried to make her as comfortable as possible, but when I was at my easel, painting, I would peek over and see her just ... there.</s>
 <s id="6">She'd be staring at nothing in particular.</s>
 <s id="7">I'd watch her slowly climb the stairs, and she wasn't the mom I grew up with.</s>
 <s id="8">I saw, instead, a frail, tiny, old woman.</s>
 <s id="9">A few weeks went by, and I needed a break from my painting.</s>
 <s id="10">I wanted to play with the new camera I had just bought.</s>
 <s id="11">I was excited -- it had all sorts of dials, buttons and settings I wanted to learn, so I set up my tripod facing this large mirror, blocking the doorway to the only bathroom in the house.</s>
 <s id="12">(Laughter) After a while, I hear, (Imitating Italian accent) "I need to use the washroom."</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">(Laughter) "Five minutes, Mom.</s>
  <s id="13.2">I need to do this."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">15 minutes later, and I hear, again, "I need to use the washroom."</s>
 <s id="15">"Five more minutes."</s>
 <s id="16">Then this happened.</s>
 <s id="17">(Laughter) (Applause) And this.</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) And then, this.</s>
 <s id="19">(Laughter) I had my "aha!" moment.</s>
 <s id="20">We connected.</s>
 <s id="21">We had something tangible we could do together.</s>
 <s id="22">My mom was born in a small mountain village in central Italy, where her parents had land and sheep.</s>
 <s id="23">At a young age, her father died of pneumonia, leaving his wife and two daughters alone with all the heavy chores.</s>
 <s id="24">They found that they couldn't cope.</s>
 <s id="25">So a very hard decision was made.</s>
 <s id="26">Mom, the oldest, at 13, was married off to a complete stranger twice her age.</s>
 <s id="27">She went from being just a kid and was pushed into adulthood.</s>
 <s id="28">Mom had her first child when she was only 16.</s>
 <s id="29">Years later, and now living in Toronto, Mom got work in a clothing factory and soon became manager of a very large sewing department.</s>
 <s id="30">And because it was full of immigrant workers, Mom taught herself words from translation books.</s>
 <s id="31">She then practiced them in French, Greek, Spanish, Portuguese, Danish, Polish, Russian, Romanian, Hungarian, all around the house.</s>
 <s id="32">I was in awe of her focus and determination to succeed at whatever she loved to do.</s>
 <s id="33">After that bathroom "aha!" moment, I practiced my newfound camera skills with Mom as portrait model.</s>
 <s id="34">Through all of this, she talked, and I listened.</s>
 <s id="35">She'd tell me about her early childhood and how she was feeling now.</s>
 <s id="36">We had each other's attention.</s>
 <s id="37">Mom was losing her short-term memory, but was better recalling her younger years.</s>
 <s id="38">I'd ask, and she would tell me stories.</s>
 <s id="39">I listened, and I was her audience.</s>
 <s id="40">I got ideas.</s>
 <s id="41">I wrote them down, and I sketched them out.</s>
 <s id="42">I showed her what to do by acting out the scenarios myself.</s>
 <s id="43">We would then stage them.</s>
 <s id="44">So she posed, and I learned more about photography.</s>
 <s id="45">Mom loved the process, the acting.</s>
 <s id="46">She felt worthy again, she felt wanted and needed.</s>
 <s id="47">And she certainly wasn't camera-shy.</s>
 <s id="48">(Laughter) (Applause) Mom laughed hysterically at this one.</s>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) The idea for this image came from an old German film I'd seen, about a submarine, called "Das Boot."</s>
 <s id="50">As you can see, what I got instead looked more like "E.T."</s>
 <s id="51">(Laughter) So I put this image aside, thinking it was a total failure, because it didn't reach my particular vision.</s>
 <s id="52">But Mom laughed so hard, I eventually, for fun, decided to post it online anyway.</s>
 <s id="53">It got an incredible amount of attention.</s>
 <s id="54">Now, with any Alzheimer's, dementia, there's a certain amount of frustration and sadness for everyone involved.</s>
 <s id="55">This is Mom's silent scream.</s>
 <s id="56">Her words to me one day were, "Why is my head so full of things to say, but before they reach my mouth, I forget what they are?"</s>
 <s id="57">"Why is my head so full of things to say, but before they reach my mouth, I forget what they are?"</s>
 <s id="58">(Applause) Now, as full-time care partner and full-time painter, I had my frustrations too.</s>
 <s id="59">(Laughter) But to balance off all the difficulties, we played.</s>
 <s id="60">That was Mom's happy place.</s>
 <s id="61">And I needed her to be there, too.</s>
 <s id="62">(Laughter) (Laughter) (Laughter) Now, Mom was also preoccupied with aging.</s>
 <s id="63">She would say, "How did I get so old, so fast?"</s>
 <s id="64">(Audience sighs) "So old."</s>
 <s id="65">"So fast."</s>
 <s id="66">I also got Mom to model for my oil paintings.</s>
 <s id="67">This painting is called "The Dressmaker."</s>
 <s id="68">I remember, as a kid, Mom sewing clothes for the whole family on this massive, heavy sewing machine that was bolted to the floor in the basement.</s>
 <s id="69">Many nights, I would go downstairs and bring my schoolwork with me.</s>
 <s id="70">I would sit behind her in this overstuffed chair.</s>
 <s id="71">The low hum of the huge motor and the repetitive stitching sounds were comforting to me.</s>
 <s id="72">When Mom moved into my house, I saved this machine and stored it in my studio for safekeeping.</s>
 <s id="73">This painting brought me back to my childhood.</s>
 <s id="74">The interesting part was that it was now Mom, sitting behind me, watching me paint her working on that very same machine she sewed at when I sat behind her, watching her sew, 50 years earlier.</s>
 <s id="75">I also gave Mom a project to do, to keep her busy and thinking.</s>
 <s id="76">I provided her with a small camera and asked her to take at least 10 pictures a day of anything she wanted.</s>
 <s id="77">These are Mom's photographs.</s>
 <s id="78">She's never held a camera in her life before this.</s>
 <s id="79">She was 93.</s>
 <s id="80">We would sit down together and talk about our work.</s>
 <s id="81">I would try to explain (Laughter) how and why I did them, the meaning, the feeling, why they were relevant.</s>
 <s id="82">Mom, on the other hand, would just bluntly say, "sì," "no," "bella" or "bruta."</s>
 <s id="83">(Laughter) I watched her facial expressions.</s>
 <s id="84">She always had the last say, with words or without.</s>
 <s id="85">This voyage of discovery hasn't ended with Mom.</s>
 <s id="86">She is now in an assisted living residence, a 10-minute walk away from my home.</s>
 <s id="87">I visit her every other day.</s>
 <s id="88">Her dementia had gotten to the point where it was unsafe for her to be in my house.</s>
 <s id="89">It has a lot of stairs.</s>
 <s id="90">She doesn't know my name anymore.</s>
 <p id="p91">
  <s id="91.1">(Voice breaking) But you know what?</s>
  <s id="91.2">That's OK.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="92">She still recognizes my face and always has a big smile when she sees me.</s>
 <s id="93">(Applause) (Applause ends) I don't take pictures of her anymore.</s>
 <s id="94">That wouldn't be fair or ethical on my part.</s>
 <s id="95">And she wouldn't understand the reasons for doing them.</s>
 <s id="96">My father, my brother, (Voice breaking) my nephew, my partner and my best friend, all passed away suddenly.</s>
 <s id="97">And I didn't have the chance to tell them how much I appreciated and loved them.</s>
 <s id="98">With Mom, I need to be there and make it a very long goodbye.</s>
 <s id="99">(Applause) (Applause ends) For me, it's about being present and really listening.</s>
 <s id="100">Dependents want to feel a part of something, anything.</s>
 <s id="101">It doesn't need to be something exceptionally profound that's shared -- it could be as simple as walks together.</s>
 <s id="102">Give them a voice of interaction, participation, and a feeling of belonging.</s>
 <s id="103">Make the time meaningful.</s>
 <s id="104">Life, it's about wanting to live and not waiting to die.</s>
 <s id="105">(Applause) (Applause ends) Can I get a wave and a smile from everyone, please?</s>
 <s id="106">(Laughter) This is for you, Mom.</s>
 <s id="107">(Camera clicks) (Applause)</s>
</text>
