<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I am going to be talking about secrets.</s>
 <s id="2">Obviously the best way to divulge a secret is to tell someone to not say anything about it.</s>
 <p id="p3">
  <s id="3.1">(Laughter) Secrets.</s>
  <s id="3.2">I'm using PowerPoint this year just because, you know, I'm into the TED thing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) And when you use these things you don't have to go like that.</s>
 <s id="5">You just press it.</s>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">(Laughter) Oh, man.</s>
  <s id="6.2">Um, yes.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p7">
  <s id="7.1">(Laughter) Yes.</s>
  <s id="7.2">I'm sure!</s>
  <s id="7.3">Just change it!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="8">(Laughter) Is Bill Gates here?</s>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">Change it!</s>
  <s id="9.2">Come on!</s>
  <s id="9.3">What?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p10">
  <s id="10.1">(Laughter) Ah!</s>
  <s id="10.2">Okay.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="11">That's not my slides, but it's okay.</s>
 <s id="12">(Laughter) As you can see, these are all maps.</s>
 <s id="13">And maps are important devices for transferring information, especially if you have human cognitive ability.</s>
 <s id="14">We can see that all formulas are really maps.</s>
 <s id="15">Now, as humans, we make maps of places that we seldom even go, which seems a little wasteful of time.</s>
 <s id="16">This, of course, is a map of the moon.</s>
 <s id="17">There're some very delightful names.</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">Tranquilacalitis, [unclear].</s>
  <s id="18.2">My favorite is Frigoris.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">What are these people thinking?</s>
  <s id="19.2">Frigoris?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">What the Frigoris you doing?</s>
  <s id="20.2">Names are important.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">Frigoris?</s>
  <s id="21.2">This is the Moon.</s>
  <s id="21.3">People could live there one day.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">I'll meet you at Frigoris.</s>
  <s id="22.2">No.</s>
  <s id="22.3">I don't think so.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">(Laughter) There we see Mars, again with various names.</s>
 <s id="24">And this is all done, by the way, by the International Astronomical Union.</s>
 <s id="25">This is an actual group of people that sit around naming planetary objects.</s>
 <s id="26">This is from their actual book.</s>
 <s id="27">These are some of the names that they have chosen, ladies and gentlemen.</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">I'll go through a little of them.</s>
  <s id="28.2">Bolotnitsa.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">That, of course, is the Slavic swamp mermaid.</s>
 <s id="30">(Laughter) Now I think the whole concept of a mermaid doesn't really blend into the swamp feel.</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">(Laughter) "Oh look!</s>
  <s id="31.2">Mermaid come out of swamp.</s>
  <s id="31.3">Oh boy!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">It's time for Bolotnitsa!"</s>
 <s id="33">(Laughter) Djabran Fluctus.</s>
 <s id="34">If that don't flow off the tongue, what does?</s>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">(Laughter) I mean kids are studying this stuff and they've got the word "fluctus" up there.</s>
  <s id="35.2">That's wrong.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="36">(Laughter) One dyslexic kid and he could be ruining his life.</s>
 <s id="37">(Laughter) "It fluctus up, Mama."</s>
 <s id="38">Hikuleo Fluctus.</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">That's a little more flowing.</s>
  <s id="39.2">Hikuleo sounds like a kind of a Leonardo DiCaprio 17 syllable thing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">And that's the Tonga underworld.</s>
 <s id="41">And one of my favorites is the Itoki Fluctus, who is the Nicaraguan goddess of insects, stars, and planets.</s>
 <s id="42">Now, if you're a goddess of stars and planets wouldn't you relegate insects to somebody else?</s>
 <s id="43">(Laughter) "No, no, really, I'm so busy with the stars.</s>
 <p id="p44">
  <s id="44.1">Would you mind taking the insects?</s>
  <s id="44.2">Thank you darling.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">Oh take the spiders too.</s>
  <s id="45.2">I know they're not insects, but I don't care.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="46">Monkeys, chimps, just get rid of the hairy creatures."</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">(Laughter) Now, we're going to be going to Mars one day.</s>
  <s id="47.2">And when we do, it's going to be unfair for the people that are living there to have to live with these ridiculous names.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="48">So, you'll be on Mars, and you're at Hellespointica Depressio which has got to be a really "up" place.</s>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) Yeah, I'm at the Depressio, and I want to get over to Amazonis so I plug it into the Mars map, and click the button and there's my directions.</s>
 <s id="50">I go to Chrysokeras.</s>
 <s id="51">(Laughter) Left to the Thymiamata.</s>
 <s id="52">Then to Niliacus Lacus, which is not a bad name.</s>
 <s id="53">Niliacus Lacus, try to get the practice, slick-a-tick-a-bacus.</s>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">That's a cool name.</s>
  <s id="54.2">I will say that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">So, I hold back a little of my venom for these astronomical misnomers.</s>
 <s id="56">And then of course Arnon to Thoth.</s>
 <s id="57">And of course there will be advertisements.</s>
 <s id="58">This is from their rule book, the International Astronomical Union.</s>
 <s id="59">And you know they're international because they put it "en Francais" as well.</s>
 <s id="60">L'Union Astronomique Internationale, for those of you who don't speak French.</s>
 <s id="61">I thought I'd translate for you.</s>
 <s id="62">From the rulebook: Nomenclature is a tool.</s>
 <s id="63">The first consideration, make it clear, simple and unambiguous.</s>
 <s id="64">And I think that Djabran Fluctus, that fits that mode.</s>
 <s id="65">(Laughter) That's simple, the goddess of goats, very simple.</s>
 <s id="66">Djabran Fluctus.</s>
 <s id="67">"Now, Frank is this clear to you, Djabran Fluctus?"</s>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">"Yeah, that's the goat goddess right?</s>
  <s id="68.2">The Abacazanian?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="69">(Laughter) It's clear to me."</s>
 <p id="p70">
  <s id="70.1">"Listen, I'm going back to the swamp mermaid.</s>
  <s id="70.2">Can you call me in a little while?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="71">(Laughter) Also, from the actual document I highlighted a part I thought may be of interest.</s>
 <s id="72">Anyone can suggest changing a name.</s>
 <s id="73">So, I look to you, fellow member of the Earth community.</s>
 <s id="74">We've got to change this stuff up fast.</s>
 <s id="75">So, these are actual names of people that work there.</s>
 <s id="76">I did some more investigation.</s>
 <s id="77">These are more people working for this group.</s>
 <s id="78">And, as you can see, they don't use their first names.</s>
 <s id="79">(Laughter) These are people naming planets, and they won't use their first names.</s>
 <s id="80">Something is askew here.</s>
 <s id="81">(Laughter) Is it because his name is really Jupiter Blunck?</s>
 <s id="82">(Laughter) Is that Ganymede Andromeda Burba?</s>
 <s id="83">(Laughter) Is that Mars Ya Marov?</s>
 <p id="p84">
  <s id="84.1">I don't know.</s>
  <s id="84.2">But it's investigative material, no doubt.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="85">There are some mapping people who do use their names.</s>
 <s id="86">Witness please, Eugene Shoemaker, who, diligently, from a young boy decided he wanted to make maps of celestial bodies.</s>
 <s id="87">Must have been a very interesting day in the Shoemaker house.</s>
 <s id="88">"Mom, I want to make maps."</s>
 <p id="p89">
  <s id="89.1">"That's wonderful Eugene.</s>
  <s id="89.2">You could make maps of Toronto."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="90">"No, I want to make maps of planets."</s>
 <s id="91">"Yeah, go to your room."</s>
 <s id="92">(Laughter) Martians, Venusians, Jovians.</s>
 <s id="93">We have names for places where people don't exist.</s>
 <s id="94">That seems a little silly to me.</s>
 <s id="95">There are no Jovians.</s>
 <s id="96">Getting back to my premise, I used stamps, by the way, because you don't have to pay anybody for the rights.</s>
 <s id="97">(Laughter) (Applause) There is obviously Einstein, Niels Bohr, de Fermat's last theorem, and I'm not sure whether that's James Coburn or Richard Harris.</s>
 <p id="p98">
  <s id="98.1">(Laughter) It's definitely one of the two.</s>
  <s id="98.2">I'm not really clear which one.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="99">But obviously the point is that numbers are maps.</s>
 <s id="100">And within numbers, is there an underlying secret to the universe?</s>
 <s id="101">That is the premise of this particular presentation.</s>
 <p id="p102">
  <s id="102.1">By the way, that's a natural picture of Saturn, no adjustments.</s>
  <s id="102.2">I mean that's just beautiful.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="103">So beautiful that I will even give up a laugh to explain my love of this particular planet, and the day Saturday, named after it, wonderfully.</s>
 <s id="104">So, formulas relate number to form.</s>
 <s id="105">That's Euler, his formula was one of the inspirations that lead to the beginning of string theory which is kind of cool, not that funny, but it is cool.</s>
 <s id="106">(Laughter) He was also famous for having no body.</s>
 <s id="107">(Laughter) Which a lot of you are like, "How did he figure that out?"</s>
 <s id="108">He's got no body, no man, just a head floating high.</s>
 <s id="109">Here comes Euler.</s>
 <s id="110">(Laughter) And that's an icosahedron, which is one of the five sacred solids, very important shapes.</s>
 <s id="111">You see the icosahedron again.</s>
 <s id="112">The dodecahedron, it's dual.</s>
 <s id="113">There is a dodecahedron which I had to do in my room last night.</s>
 <s id="114">The five sacred solids, as you can see there.</s>
 <s id="115">Which is not to be confused with the five sacred salads.</s>
 <s id="116">(Laughter) Blue cheese, ranch, oil and vinegar, thousand islands and house.</s>
 <s id="117">I suggest the house.</s>
 <s id="118">The reality, now here is something important.</s>
 <s id="119">What's important about this is these shapes are duals of each other.</s>
 <s id="120">And you can see how the icosahedron withdraws into the dodecahedron and then they just merge into each other.</s>
 <s id="121">So, the whole concept of branes in the universe, if the universe is shaped like a dodecahedron this is a very good map of what could possibly be.</s>
 <s id="122">And that is, of course, what we are here to talk about.</s>
 <s id="123">What a coincidence!</s>
 <s id="124">October 9th, in France, Jean-Pierre Luminet said that the universe is probably shaped like a dodecahedron, based on information that they got from this probe.</s>
 <s id="125">This would be a normal wave pattern.</s>
 <s id="126">But what they're seeing, way out there in the far reaches of the microwave background, is this kind of odd undulation.</s>
 <s id="127">It doesn't plug in to what they suspected a flat universe would be.</s>
 <s id="128">So, you can kind of get an idea from this extrapolating that back under this huge picture, so we get this idea of what the primal universe looked like.</s>
 <s id="129">And judging from this, it looks a little like a cheeseburger.</s>
 <s id="130">(Laughter) So, I'm thinking the universe is either a dodecahedron or a cheeseburger.</s>
 <s id="131">And for me, that's a win-win.</s>
 <s id="132">Everybody goes, I'm happy.</s>
 <s id="133">(Laughter) Better really hurry up.</s>
 <s id="134">I just threw this in because as important as all of our intellectual abilities are, without heart and without love it's just -- it's all meaningless.</s>
 <s id="135">And that, to me, is really beautiful.</s>
 <s id="136">(Laughter) Except for that creepy guy in the background.</s>
 <p id="p137">
  <s id="137.1">(Laughter) Getting back to the point of my particular presentation, Kepler, one of my great heroes, who realized that these five solids, which I spoke of earlier, were related somehow to the planets, but he couldn't prove it.</s>
  <s id="137.2">It freaked him out.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="138">But it did lead to Newton discovering gravity.</s>
 <s id="139">So, maps of things leading to organized understandings of the universe in which we emerge.</s>
 <s id="140">Now this is Isaac from a Vietnamese stamp.</s>
 <p id="p141">
  <s id="141.1">(Laughter) I am not suggesting at all that my Vietnamese brothers and sisters could maybe use a little art class here and there.</s>
  <s id="141.2">But ...</s>
 </p>
 <s id="142">(Laughter) that's not a good picture.</s>
 <p id="p143">
  <s id="143.1">(Laughter) Not a good picture.</s>
  <s id="143.2">Now, my friends in the island of Nevis are a little better.</s>
  <s id="143.3">Look at that!</s>
  <s id="143.4">That's Isaac Newton.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="144">That guy is rockin'.</s>
 <s id="145">(Laughter) What a handsome cat.</s>
 <s id="146">Once again, Nicaragua let me down.</s>
 <s id="147">(Laughter) And Copernicus looks like Johnny Carson, which is really weird.</s>
 <s id="148">(Laughter) I don't get that at all.</s>
 <s id="149">Once again, these guys rock it out.</s>
 <p id="p150">
  <s id="150.1">Isaac is kickin' ass.</s>
  <s id="150.2">Man, he looks like a rock star.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="151">This is freaky is a major way.</s>
 <s id="152">This is Sierra Leone.</s>
 <s id="153">They got little babies in there, floating in there.</s>
 <p id="p154">
  <s id="154.1">(Laughter) Man.</s>
  <s id="154.2">I don't really need to comment on this.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p155">
  <s id="155.1">But I didn't know that Isaac Newton was in the Moody Blues.</s>
  <s id="155.2">Did you?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="156">(Laughter) When did this happen?</s>
 <p id="p157">
  <s id="157.1">(Laughter) It's a different kind of course.</s>
  <s id="157.2">And they've got five apples?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="158">I mean these guys are extrapolating in realms that are not necessarily valid.</s>
 <s id="159">Although five is a good number, of course.</s>
 <s id="160">Ecuador, my friend Kepler, as you can see, they call him Juan.</s>
 <p id="p161">
  <s id="161.1">(Laughter) Juan?</s>
  <s id="161.2">No!</s>
  <s id="161.3">Johannes, not Juan.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p162">
  <s id="162.1">It wasn't Carlos Chaplain.</s>
  <s id="162.2">It's wrong.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p163">
  <s id="163.1">(Laughter) René Descartes, of course.</s>
  <s id="163.2">Once again these Grenada people, this is like way too sick for anybody's imagination.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p164">
  <s id="164.1">He's all murky.</s>
  <s id="164.2">There is little kids leaning on his leg, little ghosts flying around.</s>
  <s id="164.3">We gotta clean this stuff up fast, ladies and gentlemen.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="165">(Laughter) This is, of course, the Cartesian coordinates.</s>
 <s id="166">Once again, that's Sierra Leone.</s>
 <s id="167">This is again, indicating how numbers relate to space relate to form, maps of the universe.</s>
 <s id="168">Because that's why we're here, really, I think to figure stuff out and to love each other.</s>
 <p id="p169">
  <s id="169.1">Descartes.</s>
  <s id="169.2">(Laughter) Before the horse.</s>
  <s id="169.3">(Laughter) Now, Monaco took Descartes, and just flipped him around.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="170">Now, Monaco is problematic for me, and I'll show you why.</s>
 <p id="p171">
  <s id="171.1">Here is a map.</s>
  <s id="171.2">All they have is a casino on it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="172">(Laughter) And why Franklin Delano Roosevelt is on their map I don't even want to hazard a guess.</s>
 <s id="173">But I'd say he'd been to Hellespointica Depressio recently.</s>
 <p id="p174">
  <s id="174.1">(Laughter) This is the flag of Monaco.</s>
  <s id="174.2">Ladies and gentlemen, the flag of Indonesia.</s>
  <s id="174.3">Please examine.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="175">(Laughter) (Applause) Not sure how this came to be, but it's not right.</s>
 <s id="176">In Monaco, "No, what are you talking about?</s>
 <s id="177">They are so different.</s>
 <s id="178">Look, ours is more red, it's longer.</s>
 <p id="p179">
  <s id="179.1">They stole our flag!</s>
  <s id="179.2">They stole our flag!"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p180">
  <s id="180.1">(Laughter) Bode's law wasn't even his law.</s>
  <s id="180.2">It was a guy named Titus.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="181">And the reason I just bring this up because it is a law that doesn't really work.</s>
 <s id="182">That's Jude Law and some of his films recently didn't work.</s>
 <s id="183">(Laughter) Just a correlation that indicates how things are misinterpreted.</s>
 <p id="p184">
  <s id="184.1">And I wonder if the photographer said, "Okay, Jude, could you touch your tooth?</s>
  <s id="184.2">That's good."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="185">Just a tip, if you're being photographed for press pictures, don't touch your teeth.</s>
 <s id="186">(Laughter) Prime numbers, Gauss, one of my favorites.</s>
 <s id="187">Golden section, I've been obsessed with this thing since before I was born.</s>
 <s id="188">I know that scares a lot of you, but that was my purpose entirely.</s>
 <s id="189">There we can see Fibonacci numbers related to the Golden Section, because Fibonacci and Golden Section relate to the unfolding of the measured meter of matter, as I refer to it.</s>
 <s id="190">If Fibonacci had been on Paxil, (Laughter) that would be the Fibonacci series.</s>
 <s id="191">"Ten milligram, 20 milligram."</s>
 <s id="192">"Leonardo, dinner's ready, put down those books and take your pills."</s>
 <s id="193">"Yes, Mama."</s>
 <p id="p194">
  <s id="194.1">(Laughter) Alright where is this going?</s>
  <s id="194.2">That's a good question.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="195">Here is the premise that I began 27 years ago.</s>
 <s id="196">If numbers can express the laws of this incredible universe that we live, I reason, through some sort of reverse engineering, we could extrapolate from them some basic structural element of this universe.</s>
 <p id="p197">
  <s id="197.1">And that's what I did.</s>
  <s id="197.2">Twenty-seven years ago I started working on this.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="198">And I tried to build a particle accelerator.</s>
 <s id="199">(Laughter) And that didn't work out well.</s>
 <s id="200">So, then I thought a calculator is a metaphor.</s>
 <s id="201">I can just divide numbers, that's like atom smashing.</s>
 <p id="p202">
  <s id="202.1">That's what I did.</s>
  <s id="202.2">That's how I found Moleeds.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="203">Moleeds are what I believe the thing that will allow string theory to be proved.</s>
 <s id="204">They are the nodes on the string, patterns and relationships, 27, 37.</s>
 <s id="205">That was the first chart I came up with.</s>
 <s id="206">You can see, even if you don't go for the numbers, the beauty of the symmetry.</s>
 <s id="207">The numbers from one to 36, divided into six groups.</s>
 <s id="208">Symmetry, pairs.</s>
 <s id="209">Every top adds up to 37.</s>
 <s id="210">Bottom, all 74.</s>
 <s id="211">There is so many intricate relationships that I'm not going to go there now, because you would say, "Hey, go back to the Fluctus part."</s>
 <s id="212">(Laughter) Circle of Fifths, acoustic harmony, geometric symmetry.</s>
 <s id="213">I knew those two were related.</s>
 <s id="214">Once again, the Cartesian kind of cross-over.</s>
 <s id="215">So, I said if I'm going to put a circle, see what kind of patterns I get, boom, the Red System.</s>
 <p id="p216">
  <s id="216.1">Look at that.</s>
  <s id="216.2">You can't just make this stuff up, ladies and gentlemen.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p217">
  <s id="217.1">(Laughter) You can't just go around going, "Oh, I'm going to put some triangles in a circle and they're going to be symmetrical.</s>
  <s id="217.2">And they're all going to add up, and it's going to be, oh yeah, I figured that out."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="218">This is beyond anything anybody could just make up.</s>
 <s id="219">There is the Orange System.</s>
 <s id="220">(Laughter) And you'll see over here, these are multiples of the number 27.</s>
 <p id="p221">
  <s id="221.1">And they recapitulate that shape, even though that's a circle of nine and that's a circle of 36.</s>
  <s id="221.2">It's nuts.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p222">
  <s id="222.1">(Laughter) That's the Green System.</s>
  <s id="222.2">It all folds in half on the Green System, right between 18 and 19.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p223">
  <s id="223.1">The Blue System.</s>
  <s id="223.2">The Violet.</s>
  <s id="223.3">It's all there.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p224">
  <s id="224.1">(Laughter) Look at that!</s>
  <s id="224.2">I mean you cannot make that stuff up.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="225">(Laughter) That just doesn't fall out of a tree, ladies and gentlemen.</s>
 <s id="226">Twenty-seven years of my life!</s>
 <p id="p227">
  <s id="227.1">(Laughter) And I'm presenting it here at TED.</s>
  <s id="227.2">Why?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="228">Because this is the place if aliens land, I hope they come here.</s>
 <p id="p229">
  <s id="229.1">(Laughter) "We are going to destroy the Earth.</s>
  <s id="229.2">Hmmm ... maybe not."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="230">(Laughter) In this last year I have found these subsequent systems which allow for the mathematic possibilities of the Calabi-Yau manifolds in a way that doesn't necessitate these little hidden dimensions.</s>
 <s id="231">Which works mathematically, but it just doesn't seem God-like to me.</s>
 <s id="232">It just seems like it's not sexy and elegant, it's hidden.</s>
 <s id="233">I don't want hidden, I want to see it.</s>
 <s id="234">(Laughter) I found other pairs all have symmetry, even though, unlike the master one, their symmetry is split.</s>
 <p id="p235">
  <s id="235.1">Unbelievable.</s>
  <s id="235.2">This is like crazy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="236">Am I the only one that sees this?</s>
 <s id="237">(Laughter) You know, I didn't just draw this in a day, by the way.</s>
 <s id="238">You know, try making some charts like this at home.</s>
 <p id="p239">
  <s id="239.1">You gotta be accurate!</s>
  <s id="239.2">There's measurement involved, increments.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="240">These are maps, by the way.</s>
 <s id="241">Not stamps, but one day.</s>
 <p id="p242">
  <s id="242.1">(Laughter) Okay, I'm getting to the punch.</s>
  <s id="242.2">Golden Ratio, it's crazy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="243">And look at this, built within it is the Golden Ratio.</s>
 <s id="244">I start looking at that, and look at them again.</s>
 <s id="245">They start looking like planets.</s>
 <s id="246">I go to JPL.</s>
 <s id="247">I look at the orbits of the planets.</s>
 <s id="248">I find 18 examples of it in our solar system.</s>
 <p id="p249">
  <s id="249.1">I never told anybody.</s>
  <s id="249.2">This is the first thing.</s>
  <s id="249.3">This could be history.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="250">(Laughter) Kepler was right.</s>
 <s id="251">(Laughter) Eighteen and 19, the middle of the Moleeds, 0.618 is the golden section.</s>
 <s id="252">Multiply them together, 18.618 x 19.618 is 365.247.</s>
 <s id="253">Which is .005 different from the number of days in a year.</s>
 <s id="254">Hey, you can't make this up.</s>
 <s id="255">(Laughter) Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="256">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="257">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="258">(Applause)</s>
</text>
