<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Many of us will experience some kind of trauma during our lifetime.</s>
 <s id="2">Sometimes, we escape with no long-term effects.</s>
 <s id="3">But for millions of us, those experiences linger, causing symptoms like flashbacks, nightmares, and negative thoughts that interfere with everyday life.</s>
 <s id="4">This phenomenon, called post-traumatic stress disorder, or PTSD, isn’t a personal failing; rather, it’s a treatable malfunction of certain biological mechanisms that allow us to cope with dangerous experiences.</s>
 <s id="5">To understand PTSD, we first need to understand how the brain processes a wide range of ordeals, including the death of a loved one, domestic violence, injury or illness, abuse, rape, war, car accidents, and natural disasters.</s>
 <s id="6">These events can bring on feelings of danger and helplessness, which activate the brain’s alarm system, known as the “fight-flight-freeze” response.</s>
 <s id="7">When this alarm sounds, the hypothalamic, pituitary, and adrenal systems, known as the HPA axis, work together to send signals to the parasympathetic nervous system.</s>
 <s id="8">That’s the network that communicates with adrenal glands and internal organs to help regulate functions like heart rate, digestion, and respiration.</s>
 <s id="9">These signals start a chemical cascade that floods the body with several different stress hormones, causing physiological changes that prepare the body to defend itself.</s>
 <s id="10">Our heart rate speeds up, breathing quickens, and muscles tense.</s>
 <s id="11">Even after a crisis is over, escalated levels of stress hormones may last for days, contributing to jittery feelings, nightmares, and other symptoms.</s>
 <s id="12">For most people, these experiences disappear within a few days to two weeks as their hormone levels stabilize.</s>
 <s id="13">But a small percentage of those who experience trauma have persistent problems —sometimes vanishing temporarily only to resurface months later.</s>
 <s id="14">We don’t completely understand what’s happening in the brain, but one theory is that the stress hormone cortisol may be continuously activating the “fight-flight-freeze” response while reducing overall brain functioning, leading to a number of negative symptoms.</s>
 <s id="15">These symptoms often fall into four categories: intrusive thoughts, like dreams and flashbacks, avoiding reminders of the trauma, negative thoughts and feelings, like fear, anger, and guilt, and “reactive” symptoms like irritability and difficulty sleeping.</s>
 <s id="16">Not everyone has all these symptoms, or experiences them to the same extent and intensity.</s>
 <s id="17">When problems last more than a month, PTSD is often diagnosed.</s>
 <s id="18">Genetics, on-going overwhelming stress, and many risk factors like preexisting mental illnesses or lack of emotional support, likely play a role in determining who will experience PTSD.</s>
 <s id="19">But the underlying cause is still a medical mystery.</s>
 <s id="20">A major challenge of coping with PTSD is sensitivity to triggers, physical and emotional stimuli that the brain associates with the original trauma.</s>
 <s id="21">These can be everyday sensations that aren’t inherently dangerous but prompt powerful physical and emotional reactions.</s>
 <s id="22">For example, the smell of a campfire could evoke the memory of being trapped in a burning house.</s>
 <s id="23">For someone with PTSD, that memory activates the same neurochemical cascade as the original event.</s>
 <s id="24">That then stirs up the same feelings of panic and helplessness as if they’re experiencing the trauma all over again.</s>
 <s id="25">Trying to avoid these triggers, which are sometimes unpredictable, can lead to isolation.</s>
 <s id="26">That can leave people feeling invalidated, ignored, or misunderstood, like a pause button has been pushed on their lives while the rest of the world continues around them.</s>
 <s id="27">But, there are options.</s>
 <s id="28">If you think you might be suffering from PTSD, the first step is an evaluation with a mental health professional who can direct you towards the many resources available.</s>
 <s id="29">Psychotherapy can be very effective for PTSD, helping patients better understand their triggers.</s>
 <s id="30">And certain medications can make symptoms more manageable, as can self- care practices, like mindfulness and regular exercise.</s>
 <s id="31">What if you notice signs of PTSD in a friend or family member?</s>
 <s id="32">Social support, acceptance, and empathy are key to helping and recovery.</s>
 <s id="33">Let them know you believe their account of what they’re experiencing, and that you don’t blame them for their reactions.</s>
 <s id="34">If they’re open to it, encourage them to seek evaluation and treatment.</s>
 <s id="35">PTSD has been called “the hidden wound” because it comes without outward physical signs.</s>
 <s id="36">But even if it’s an invisible disorder, it doesn’t have to be a silent one.</s>
</text>
