<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">This is the story of three plastic bottles, empty and discarded.</s>
 <s id="2">Their journeys are about to diverge with outcomes that impact nothing less than the fate of the planet.</s>
 <s id="3">But they weren't always this way.</s>
 <s id="4">To understand where these bottles end up, we must first explore their origins.</s>
 <s id="5">The heroes of our story were conceived in this oil refinery.</s>
 <s id="6">The plastic in their bodies was formed by chemically bonding oil and gas molecules together to make monomers.</s>
 <s id="7">In turn, these monomers were bonded into long polymer chains to make plastic in the form of millions of pellets.</s>
 <s id="8">Those were melted at manufacturing plants and reformed in molds to create the resilient material that makes up the triplets' bodies.</s>
 <s id="9">Machines filled the bottles with sweet bubbily liquid and they were then wrapped, shipped, bought, opened, consumed and unceremoniously discarded.</s>
 <s id="10">And now here they lie, poised at the edge of the unknown.</s>
 <s id="11">Bottle one, like hundreds of millions of tons of his plastic brethren, ends up in a landfill.</s>
 <s id="12">This huge dump expands each day as more trash comes in and continues to take up space.</s>
 <s id="13">As plastics sit there being compressed amongst layers of other junk, rainwater flows through the waste and absorbs the water-soluble compounds it contains, and some of those are highly toxic.</s>
 <s id="14">Together, they create a harmful stew called leachate, which can move into groundwater, soil and streams, poisoning ecosystems and harming wildlife.</s>
 <s id="15">It can take bottle one an agonizing 1,000 years to decompose.</s>
 <s id="16">Bottle two's journey is stranger but, unfortunately, no happier.</s>
 <s id="17">He floats on a trickle that reaches a stream, a stream that flows into a river, and a river that reaches the ocean.</s>
 <s id="18">After months lost at sea, he's slowly drawn into a massive vortex, where trash accumulates, a place known as the Great Pacific Garbage Patch.</s>
 <s id="19">Here the ocean's currents have trapped millions of pieces of plastic debris.</s>
 <s id="20">This is one of five plastic-filled gyres in the world's seas.</s>
 <s id="21">Places where the pollutants turn the water into a cloudy plastic soup.</s>
 <s id="22">Some animals, like seabirds, get entangled in the mess.</s>
 <s id="23">They, and others, mistake the brightly colored plastic bits for food.</s>
 <s id="24">Plastic makes them feel full when they're not, so they starve to death and pass the toxins from the plastic up the food chain.</s>
 <s id="25">For example, it's eaten by lanternfish, the lanternfish are eaten by squid, the squid are eaten by tuna, and the tuna are eaten by us.</s>
 <s id="26">And most plastics don't biodegrade, which means they're destined to break down into smaller and smaller pieces called micro plastics, which might rotate in the sea eternally.</s>
 <s id="27">But bottle three is spared the cruel purgatories of his brothers.</s>
 <s id="28">A truck brings him to a plant where he and his companions are squeezed flat and compressed into a block.</s>
 <s id="29">Okay, this sounds pretty bad, too, but hang in there.</s>
 <s id="30">It gets better.</s>
 <s id="31">The blocks are shredded into tiny pieces, which are washed and melted, so they become the raw materials that can be used again.</s>
 <s id="32">As if by magic, bottle three is now ready to be reborn as something completely new.</s>
 <s id="33">For this bit of plastic with such humble origins, suddenly the sky is the limit.</s>
</text>
