<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Recently, I flew over a crowd of thousands of people in Brazil playing music by George Frideric Handel.</s>
 <s id="2">I also drove along the streets of Amsterdam, again playing music by this same composer.</s>
 <s id="3">Let's take a look.</s>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">(Music: George Frideric Handel, "Allegro."</s>
  <s id="4.2">Performed by Daria van den Bercken.)</s>
  <s id="4.3">(Video) Daria van den Bercken: I live there on the third floor.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="5">(In Dutch) I live there on the corner.</s>
 <s id="6">I actually live there, around the corner.</s>
 <s id="7">and you'd be really welcome.</s>
 <p id="p8">
  <s id="8.1">Man: (In Dutch) Does that sound like fun?</s>
  <s id="8.2">Child: (In Dutch) Yes!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="9">[(In Dutch) "Handel house concert"] (Applause) Daria van den Bercken: All this was a real magical experience for hundreds of reasons.</s>
 <s id="10">Now you may ask, why have I done these things?</s>
 <s id="11">They're not really typical for a musician's day-to-day life.</s>
 <s id="12">Well, I did it because I fell in love with the music and I wanted to share it with as many people as possible.</s>
 <s id="13">It started a couple of years ago.</s>
 <s id="14">I was sitting at home on the couch with the flu and browsing the Internet a little, when I found out that Handel had written works for the keyboard.</s>
 <p id="p15">
  <s id="15.1">Well, I was surprised.</s>
  <s id="15.2">I did not know this.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="16">So I downloaded the sheet music and started playing.</s>
 <s id="17">And what happened next was that I entered this state of pure, unprejudiced amazement.</s>
 <s id="18">It was an experience of being totally in awe of the music, and I had not felt that in a long time.</s>
 <s id="19">It might be easier to relate to this when you hear it.</s>
 <s id="20">The first piece that I played through started like this.</s>
 <s id="21">(Music) Well this sounds very melancholic, doesn't it?</s>
 <s id="22">And I turned the page and what came next was this.</s>
 <s id="23">(Music) Well, this sounds very energetic, doesn't it?</s>
 <s id="24">So within a couple of minutes, and the piece isn't even finished yet, I experienced two very contrasting characters: beautiful melancholy and sheer energy.</s>
 <s id="25">And I consider these two elements to be vital human expressions.</s>
 <s id="26">And the purity of the music makes you hear it very effectively.</s>
 <s id="27">I've given a lot of children's concerts for children of seven and eight years old, and whatever I play, whether it's Bach, Beethoven, even Stockhausen, or some jazzy music, they are open to hear it, really willing to listen, and they are comfortable doing so.</s>
 <s id="28">And when classes come in with children who are just a few years older, 11, 12, I felt that I sometimes already had trouble in reaching them like that.</s>
 <s id="29">The complexity of the music does become an issue, and actually the opinions of others — parents, friends, media — they start to count.</s>
 <s id="30">But the young ones, they don't question their own opinion.</s>
 <s id="31">They are in this constant state of wonder, and I do firmly believe that we can keep listening like these seven-year-old children, even when growing up.</s>
 <s id="32">And that is why I have played not only in the concert hall but also on the street, online, in the air: to feel that state of wonder, to truly listen, and to listen without prejudice.</s>
 <s id="33">And I would like to invite you to do so now.</s>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">(Music: George Frideric Handel, "Chaconne in G Major."</s>
  <s id="34.2">Performed by Daria van den Bercken.)</s>
  <s id="34.3">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="35">(Applause)</s>
</text>
