<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The most important walls in western history aren't even in the West.</s>
 <s id="2">They surround the modern city of Istanbul, Constantinople as the Romans called it.</s>
 <s id="3">And for a thousand years, the fate of Europe depended on them.</s>
 <s id="4">Constantinople was designed to be the center of the world.</s>
 <s id="5">When the frontiers of the Roman Empire began to crumble in the 4th Century, the capital was moved to the cultured, wealthy, and still stable East.</s>
 <s id="6">There, at the crossroads between Europe and Asia, the hub of the major trade routes of the ancient world, the Emperor Constantine built his city.</s>
 <s id="7">This was the city of libraries and universities, 20 times the size of London or Paris at the time.</s>
 <s id="8">It contained the priceless knowledge of the classical world which was fading in the West.</s>
 <s id="9">To protect this masterpiece from its many enemies, Constantine's successors built the finest defensive fortifications ever made.</s>
 <s id="10">The first line of protection was a moat 60 feet wide and 22 feet deep, stretching all four miles from coast to coast.</s>
 <s id="11">Pipes from inside the city could fill it at the first sight of the enemy, and a short wall protected archers who could fire at the soaked soldiers trying to swim across.</s>
 <s id="12">Those who were lucky enough to clear the moat had to contend with an unceasing barrage from the 27 foot outer wall above.</s>
 <s id="13">Arrows, spears, or far worse, Greek fire -- an ancient form of napalm that would ignite on contact and couldn't be extinguished by water -- would rain down on them.</s>
 <s id="14">Squads of Roman defenders would carry portable flame throwers, spraying anyone trying to climb out of the moat.</s>
 <s id="15">The terrified victims would leap back, only to find that they still burned underwater.</s>
 <s id="16">At times, the Romans would also mount siphons onto the ramparts, and launch clay pots full of Greek fire from catapults at an invading army.</s>
 <s id="17">The front lines would turn into an inferno, making it appear as if the earth itself was on fire.</s>
 <s id="18">If, by some miracle, the outer wall was compromised, attackers would be faced with the final defense: the great inner wall.</s>
 <s id="19">These walls were wide enough to have four men ride side by side, allowing troops to be rushed wherever they were needed.</s>
 <s id="20">Attilla the Hun, destroyer of civilizations, who named himself the Scourge of God, took one look at them and turned around.</s>
 <s id="21">The Avars battled the walls uselessly til their catapults ran out of rocks.</s>
 <s id="22">The Turks tried to tunnel under them, but found the foundations too solid.</s>
 <s id="23">The Arabs tried to starve the city into submission, but ran out of food themselves and had to resort to cannibalism.</s>
 <s id="24">It took the guns of the modern world to finally bring them down.</s>
 <s id="25">In 1453, the Turks brought their super weapon: a monster cannon that could fire a 15 hundred pound stone ball over a mile.</s>
 <s id="26">Together with more than a hundred smaller guns, they kept up a steady bombardment day and night.</s>
 <s id="27">A section of the old walls collapsed, but even in their death throes they proved formidable.</s>
 <s id="28">The rubble absorbed the shock of the cannonballs better than the solid wall.</s>
 <s id="29">It took a month and a half of continuous blasting to finally open a breach.</s>
 <s id="30">The last Roman Emperor, Constantine the 11th, drew his sword and jumped into the gap to stop the onrushing horde, disappearing into legend.</s>
 <s id="31">The city was taken, and the Roman Empire finally disappeared.</s>
 <s id="32">But those broken walls had one last gift.</s>
 <s id="33">As the survivors fled the doomed city, they brought with them their precious books and their ancient traditions.</s>
 <s id="34">They traveled west to Italy, reintroduced the Greek language and learning to western Europe, and ignited the Renaissance.</s>
 <s id="35">Thanks to Constantinople's walls, that pile of brick and marble that guarded them for so long, we still have our classical past.</s>
</text>
