<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Hi, kids.</s>
 <s id="2">(Laughter) I'm 71.</s>
 <s id="3">(Applause) My husband is 76.</s>
 <s id="4">My parents are in their late 90s, and Olivia, the dog, is 16.</s>
 <s id="5">So let's talk about aging.</s>
 <s id="6">Let me tell you how I feel when I see my wrinkles in the mirror and I realize that some parts of me have dropped and I can't find them down there.</s>
 <s id="7">(Laughter) Mary Oliver says in one of her poems, "Tell me, what is it that you plan to do with your one wild and precious life?"</s>
 <s id="8">Me, I intend to live passionately.</s>
 <s id="9">When do we start aging?</s>
 <s id="10">Society decides when we are old, usually around 65, when we get Medicare, but we really start aging at birth.</s>
 <s id="11">We are aging right now, and we all experience it differently.</s>
 <s id="12">We all feel younger than our real age, because the spirit never ages.</s>
 <s id="13">I am still 17.</s>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">Sophia Loren.</s>
  <s id="14.2">Look at her.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="15">She says that everything you see she owes to spaghetti.</s>
 <s id="16">I tried it and gained 10 pounds in the wrong places.</s>
 <s id="17">But attitude, aging is also attitude and health.</s>
 <s id="18">But my real mentor in this journey of aging is Olga Murray.</s>
 <s id="19">This California girl at 60 started working in Nepal to save young girls from domestic bondage.</s>
 <s id="20">At 88, she has saved 12,000 girls, and she has changed the culture in the country.</s>
 <s id="21">(Applause) Now it is illegal for fathers to sell their daughters into servitude.</s>
 <s id="22">She has also founded orphanages and nutritional clinics.</s>
 <s id="23">She is always happy and eternally young.</s>
 <s id="24">What have I lost in the last decades?</s>
 <s id="25">People, of course, places, and the boundless energy of my youth, and I'm beginning to lose independence, and that scares me.</s>
 <s id="26">Ram Dass says that dependency hurts, but if you accept it, there is less suffering.</s>
 <s id="27">After a very bad stroke, his ageless soul watches the changes in the body with tenderness, and he is grateful to the people who help him.</s>
 <s id="28">What have I gained?</s>
 <s id="29">Freedom: I don't have to prove anything anymore.</s>
 <s id="30">I'm not stuck in the idea of who I was, who I want to be, or what other people expect me to be.</s>
 <s id="31">I don't have to please men anymore, only animals.</s>
 <s id="32">I keep telling my superego to back off and let me enjoy what I still have.</s>
 <s id="33">My body may be falling apart, but my brain is not, yet.</s>
 <s id="34">I love my brain.</s>
 <s id="35">I feel lighter.</s>
 <s id="36">I don't carry grudges, ambition, vanity, none of the deadly sins that are not even worth the trouble.</s>
 <s id="37">It's great to let go.</s>
 <s id="38">I should have started sooner.</s>
 <s id="39">And I also feel softer because I'm not scared of being vulnerable.</s>
 <s id="40">I don't see it as weakness anymore.</s>
 <s id="41">And I've gained spirituality.</s>
 <s id="42">I'm aware that before, death was in the neighborhood.</s>
 <s id="43">Now, it's next door, or in my house.</s>
 <s id="44">I try to live mindfully and be present in the moment.</s>
 <s id="45">By the way, the Dalai Lama is someone who has aged beautifully, but who wants to be vegetarian and celibate?</s>
 <s id="46">(Laughter) Meditation helps.</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">(Video) Child: Ommm.</s>
  <s id="47.2">Ommm.</s>
  <s id="47.3">Ommm.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">Isabel Allende: Ommm.</s>
  <s id="48.2">Ommm.</s>
  <s id="48.3">There it is.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="49">And it's good to start early.</s>
 <s id="50">You know, for a vain female like myself, it's very hard to age in this culture.</s>
 <s id="51">Inside, I feel good, I feel charming, seductive, sexy.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">Nobody else sees that.</s>
  <s id="52.2">(Laughter) I'm invisible.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="53">I want to be the center of attention.</s>
 <s id="54">I hate to be invisible.</s>
 <s id="55">(Laughter) (Applause) This is Grace Dammann.</s>
 <s id="56">She has been in a wheelchair for six years after a terrible car accident.</s>
 <s id="57">She says that there is nothing more sensual than a hot shower, that every drop of water is a blessing to the senses.</s>
 <s id="58">She doesn't see herself as disabled.</s>
 <s id="59">In her mind, she's still surfing in the ocean.</s>
 <s id="60">Ethel Seiderman, a feisty, beloved activist in the place where I live in California.</s>
 <s id="61">She wears red patent shoes, and her mantra is that one scarf is nice but two is better.</s>
 <s id="62">She has been a widow for nine years, but she's not looking for another mate.</s>
 <s id="63">She says that there is only a limited number of ways you can screw — well, she says it in another way — and she has tried them all.</s>
 <s id="64">(Laughter) I, on the other hand, I still have erotic fantasies with Antonio Banderas — (Laughter) — and my poor husband has to put up with it.</s>
 <s id="65">So how can I stay passionate?</s>
 <s id="66">I cannot will myself to be passionate at 71.</s>
 <s id="67">I have been training for some time, and when I feel flat and bored, I fake it.</s>
 <s id="68">Attitude, attitude.</s>
 <p id="p69">
  <s id="69.1">How do I train?</s>
  <s id="69.2">I train by saying yes to whatever comes my way: drama, comedy, tragedy, love, death, losses.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="70">Yes to life.</s>
 <s id="71">And I train by trying to stay in love.</s>
 <s id="72">It doesn't always work, but you cannot blame me for trying.</s>
 <s id="73">And, on a final note, retirement in Spanish is jubilación.</s>
 <p id="p74">
  <s id="74.1">Jubilation.</s>
  <s id="74.2">Celebration.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="75">We have paid our dues.</s>
 <s id="76">We have contributed to society.</s>
 <s id="77">Now it's our time, and it's a great time.</s>
 <s id="78">Unless you are ill or very poor, you have choices.</s>
 <s id="79">I have chosen to stay passionate, engaged with an open heart.</s>
 <s id="80">I am working on it every day.</s>
 <s id="81">Want to join me?</s>
 <s id="82">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="83">(Applause) June Cohen: So Isabel — IA: Thank you.</s>
 <p id="p84">
  <s id="84.1">JC: First of all, I never like to presume to speak for the TED community, but I would like to tell you that I have a feeling we can all agree that you are still charming, seductive and sexy.</s>
  <s id="84.2">Yes?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p85">
  <s id="85.1">IA: Aww, thank you.</s>
  <s id="85.2">(Applause) JC: Hands down.</s>
  <s id="85.3">IA: No, it's makeup.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="86">Moderator: Now, would it be awkward if I asked you a follow-up question about your erotic fantasies?</s>
 <p id="p87">
  <s id="87.1">IA: Oh, of course.</s>
  <s id="87.2">About what?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p88">
  <s id="88.1">(Laughter) Moderator: About your erotic fantasies.</s>
  <s id="88.2">IA: With Antonio Banderas.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="89">Moderator: I was just wondering if you have anything more to share.</s>
 <p id="p90">
  <s id="90.1">IA: Well, one of them is that — (Laughter) One of them is that I place a naked Antonio Banderas on a Mexican tortilla, I slather him with guacamole and salsa, I roll him up, and I eat him.</s>
  <s id="90.2">(Laughter) Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="91">(Applause)</s>
</text>
