<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Can you guess what you’re looking at?</s>
 <p id="p2">
  <s id="2.1">Is it a fuzzy sock?</s>
  <s id="2.2">An overripe banana?</s>
  <s id="2.3">A moldy tube of toothpaste?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="3">In fact, this is the humble sea cucumber, and while it might look odd, its daily toil paves the way for entire ecosystems to thrive.</s>
 <s id="4">Sea cucumbers are members of the phylum Echinodermata, along with sea urchins, starfish and other radially symmetrical, “spiny-skinned” marine invertebrates.</s>
 <s id="5">Some sea cucumbers have feathery tentacles flowing from their mouths, some are puffed like bloated balloons, and others simply look like Headless Chicken Monsters— the actual name given to a rare deep-sea species.</s>
 <s id="6">But they are generally characterized by their long, cylindrical shape.</s>
 <s id="7">A sea cucumber is essentially a brainless, fleshy form surrounding a digestive tract, bookended by a mouth and an anus.</s>
 <s id="8">Adhesive tube feet run the length of their bodies and allow them to scoot along the seafloor.</s>
 <s id="9">Specialized tube feet can be used for feeding and respiration, though many sea cucumbers actually breathe through their anuses.</s>
 <s id="10">Rhythmically contracting and relaxing their muscles, they draw water in and out over an internal lung-like structure called a respiratory tree that extracts oxygen from seawater.</s>
 <s id="11">Certain species of crabs and pearlfish take advantage of this rhythmic action and, once the sea cucumber’s anus is dilated, they shimmy in and take shelter.</s>
 <s id="12">The rear end of a single sea cucumber can harbor up to fifteen pearlfish at a time.</s>
 <s id="13">However, it seems that not all sea cucumbers put up with this intrusive behavior.</s>
 <s id="14">Some species are equipped with five teeth around their anus, suggesting that they may have taken an evolutionary stand against unwanted guests.</s>
 <s id="15">But even sea cucumbers that lack anal teeth are outfitted with tools to defend themselves.</s>
 <s id="16">They evade threats and launch counter-attacks using their mutable collagenous tissue, or MCT.</s>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">This gel-like tissue contains bundles of collagen, called “fibrils.”</s>
  <s id="17.2">Proteins can interact with these fibrils to slide them together, stiffening the tissue, or apart, softening it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="18">This versatile tissue has many advantages: it aids in efficient locomotion, enables sea cucumbers to fit into small spaces, and allows them to reproduce asexually by splitting apart.</s>
 <s id="19">But MCT’s most explosive application is employed when a predator attacks.</s>
 <s id="20">By loosening the attachments of internal tissues then quickly softening and contracting their muscles, many species are capable of shooting a wide range of organs out of their anuses.</s>
 <s id="21">This act is called “evisceration” and it’s a surprisingly effective defense mechanism.</s>
 <s id="22">In addition to startling and distracting predators, the innards of some sea cucumber species are sticky and toxic.</s>
 <s id="23">Evisceration may seem drastic, but sea cucumbers are able to regenerate what they’ve lost to their gut reaction in just a few weeks’ time.</s>
 <s id="24">Aside from the few species that have evolved to swim and those that feed without moving, many of these cumbersome creatures pass their time grazing the seabed.</s>
 <s id="25">Sea cucumbers are found everywhere from shallow shores to abyssal trenches 6,000 meters below sea level.</s>
 <s id="26">On the deep sea floor, they comprise the majority of animal biomass, reaching up to 95% in some areas.</s>
 <s id="27">As these sausage-shaped wonders trudge along, they vacuum up sand, digest the organic matter it contains, and excrete the byproduct.</s>
 <s id="28">In this process, sea cucumbers clean and oxygenate the seafloor by breaking down detritus and recycling nutrients.</s>
 <s id="29">This creates the conditions for sea grass beds and shellfish to thrive.</s>
 <s id="30">Sea cucumber excretions can also aid in coral formation and may play a role in buffering marine environments from ocean acidification.</s>
 <s id="31">As the ocean’s vacuum cleaners, they are very good at their job: about half of the sandy seafloor is thought to have passed through the digestive tract of a sea cucumber.</s>
 <s id="32">So next time you’re rejoicing in the feeling of sand crunching between your toes, consider this: those very grains of sand might have, at one point or another, been excreted by a pickle that breathes through its butt.</s>
</text>
