<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">“Sometimes fate is like a small sandstorm that keeps changing directions.</s>
 <s id="2">You change direction but the sandstorm chases you.</s>
 <s id="3">You turn again, but the storm adjusts.</s>
 <s id="4">Over and over you play this out, like some ominous dance with death just before dawn.</s>
 <s id="5">Why?</s>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">Because this storm isn't something that blew in from far away… This storm is you.</s>
  <s id="6.2">Something inside of you.”</s>
  <s id="6.3">This quote, from the first chapter of Haruki Murakami’s "Kafka on the Shore," captures the teenage protagonist's turmoil.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="7">Desperate to escape his tyrannical father and the family curse he feels doomed to repeat, he renames himself Kafka after his favorite author and runs away from home.</s>
 <s id="8">But memories of a missing mother, along with dreams that haunt his waking life, prove more difficult to outrun.</s>
 <s id="9">Published in Japanese in 2002 and translated into English three years later, "Kafka on the Shore" is an epic literary puzzle filled with time travel, hidden histories, and magical underworlds.</s>
 <s id="10">Readers delight in discovering how the mind-bending imagery, whimsical characters and eerie coincidences fit together.</s>
 <s id="11">Kafka narrates every second chapter, with the rest centering on an old man named Satoru Nakata.</s>
 <s id="12">After awakening from a coma he went into during the Second World War, Nakata loses the ability to read and write– but gains a mysterious knack for talking to cats.</s>
 <s id="13">When he’s asked to tail a missing pet, he’s thrown onto a dangerous path that runs parallel to Kafka’s.</s>
 <s id="14">Soon prophecies come true, portals to different dimensions open up– and fish and leeches begin raining from the sky.</s>
 <s id="15">But what ties these two characters together– and is it a force either one of them can control?</s>
 <s id="16">The collision of different worlds is a common thread in Haruki Murakami’s work.</s>
 <s id="17">His novels and short stories often forge fantastic connections between personal experience, supernatural possibilities, and Japanese history.</s>
 <s id="18">Born in Kyoto in 1949, Murakami grew up during the post-World War II American occupation of Japan.</s>
 <s id="19">The shadow of war hung over his life as it does his fiction; "Kafka on the Shore" features biological attacks, military ghosts and shady conspiracies.</s>
 <s id="20">Murakami’s work blurs historical periods and draws from multiple cultural traditions.</s>
 <s id="21">References to Western society and Japanese customs tumble over each other, from literature and fashion to food and ghost stories.</s>
 <s id="22">He has a penchant for musical references, too, especially in "Kafka on the Shore."</s>
 <s id="23">As the runaway Kafka wanders the streets of a strange city, Led Zeppelin and Prince keep him company.</s>
 <s id="24">Soon, he takes refuge in an exquisite private library.</s>
 <s id="25">While he spends his days poring over old books and contemplating a strange painting and the library’s mysterious owner, he also befriends the librarian– who introduces him to classical music like Schubert.</s>
 <s id="26">This musical sensibility makes Murakami’s work all the more hypnotic.</s>
 <s id="27">He frequently bends the line between reality and a world of dreams, and is considered a master of magic lurking in the mundane.</s>
 <s id="28">This is a key feature of magical realism.</s>
 <s id="29">In contrast to fantasy, magic in this sort of writing rarely offers a way out of a problem.</s>
 <s id="30">Instead, it becomes just one more thing that complicates life.</s>
 <s id="31">In "Kafka on the Shore," characters are faced with endless otherworldly distractions, from a love sick ghost to a flute made from cat souls.</s>
 <s id="32">These challenges offer no easy answers.</s>
 <s id="33">Instead, they leave us marveling at the resourcefulness of the human spirit to deal with the unexpected.</s>
 <s id="34">While Kafka often seems suspended in strangeness, there’s a tenderness and integrity at the heart of his mission that keeps him moving forward.</s>
 <s id="35">Gradually he comes to accept his inner confusion.</s>
 <s id="36">In the end, his experience echoes the reader’s: the deeper you go, the more you find.</s>
</text>
