<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">This sound, this smell, this sight all remind me of the campfires of my childhood, when anyone could become a storyteller in front of the dancing flames.</s>
 <s id="2">There was this wondrous ending when people and fire fell asleep almost in unison.</s>
 <s id="3">It was dreaming time.</s>
 <s id="4">Now my story has a lot to do with dreaming, although I'm known to make my dreams come true.</s>
 <s id="5">Last year, I created a one-man show.</s>
 <s id="6">For an hour and a half I shared with the audience a lifetime of creativity, how I pursue perfection, how I cheat the impossible.</s>
 <s id="7">And then TED challenged me: "Philippe, can you shrink this lifetime to 18 minutes?"</s>
 <s id="8">(Laughter) Eighteen minutes, clearly impossible.</s>
 <s id="9">But here I am.</s>
 <s id="10">One solution was to rehearse a machine gun delivery in which every syllable, every second will have its importance and hope to God the audience will be able to follow me.</s>
 <s id="11">No, no, no.</s>
 <s id="12">No, the best way for me to start is to pay my respects to the gods of creativity.</s>
 <s id="13">So please join me for a minute of silence.</s>
 <s id="14">Okay, I cheated, it was a mere 20 seconds.</s>
 <s id="15">But hey, we're on TED time.</s>
 <s id="16">When I was six years old, I fell in love with magic.</s>
 <s id="17">For Christmas I got a magic box and a very old book on card manipulation.</s>
 <s id="18">Somehow I was more interested in pure manipulation than in all the silly little tricks in the box.</s>
 <s id="19">So I looked in the book for the most difficult move, and it was this.</s>
 <s id="20">Now I'm not supposed to share that with you, but I have to show you the card is hidden in the back of the hand.</s>
 <s id="21">Now that manipulation was broken down into seven moves described over seven pages.</s>
 <s id="22">One, two, three, four, five, six and seven.</s>
 <s id="23">And let me show you something else.</s>
 <s id="24">The cards were bigger than my hands.</s>
 <s id="25">Two months later, six years old, I'm able to do one, two, three, four, five, six, seven.</s>
 <s id="26">And I go to see a famous magician and proudly ask him, "Well what do you think?"</s>
 <s id="27">Six years old.</s>
 <s id="28">The magician looked at me and said, "This is a disaster.</s>
 <s id="29">You cannot do that in two seconds and have a minuscule part of the card showing.</s>
 <s id="30">For the move to be professional, it has to be less than one second and it has to be perfect."</s>
 <s id="31">Two years later, one -- zoop.</s>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">And I'm not cheating.</s>
  <s id="32.2">It's in the back.</s>
  <s id="32.3">It's perfect.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="33">Passion is the motto of all my actions.</s>
 <s id="34">As I'm studying magic, juggling is mentioned repeatedly as a great way to acquire dexterity and coordination.</s>
 <s id="35">Now I had long admired how fast and fluidly jugglers make objects fly.</s>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">So that's it.</s>
  <s id="36.2">I'm 14; I'm becoming a juggler.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="37">I befriend a young juggler in a juggling troupe, and he agrees to sell me three clubs.</s>
 <p id="p38">
  <s id="38.1">But in America you have to explain.</s>
  <s id="38.2">What are clubs?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="39">Nothing to do with golf.</s>
 <s id="40">They are those beautiful oblong objects, but quite difficult to make.</s>
 <s id="41">They have to be precisely lathed.</s>
 <s id="42">Oh, when I was buying the clubs, somehow the young juggler was hiding from the others.</s>
 <s id="43">Well I didn't think much of it at the time.</s>
 <s id="44">Anyway, here I was progressing with my new clubs.</s>
 <s id="45">But I could not understand.</s>
 <s id="46">I was pretty fast, but I was not fluid at all.</s>
 <s id="47">The clubs were escaping me at each throw.</s>
 <s id="48">And I was trying constantly to bring them back to me.</s>
 <s id="49">Until one day I practiced in front of Francis Brunn, the world's greatest juggler.</s>
 <s id="50">And he was frowning.</s>
 <s id="51">And he finally asked, "Can I see those?"</s>
 <s id="52">So I proudly showed him my clubs.</s>
 <s id="53">He said, "Philippe, you have been had.</s>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">These are rejects.</s>
  <s id="54.2">They are completely out of alignment.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">They are impossible to juggle."</s>
 <s id="56">Tenacity is how I kept at it against all odds.</s>
 <s id="57">So I went to the circus to see more magicians, more jugglers, and I saw -- oh no, no, no, I didn't see.</s>
 <s id="58">It was more interesting; I heard.</s>
 <s id="59">I heard about those amazing men and women who walk on thin air -- the high-wire walkers.</s>
 <p id="p60">
  <s id="60.1">Now I have been playing with ropes and climbing all my childhood, so that's it.</s>
  <s id="60.2">I'm 16; I'm becoming a wire walker.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="61">I found two trees -- but not any kind of trees, trees with character -- and then a very long rope.</s>
 <s id="62">And I put the rope around and around and around and around and around till I had no more rope.</s>
 <s id="63">Now I have all of those ropes parallel like this.</s>
 <s id="64">I get a pair of pliers and some coat hangers, and I gather them together in some kind of ropey path.</s>
 <s id="65">So I just created the widest tightrope in the world.</s>
 <p id="p66">
  <s id="66.1">What did I need?</s>
  <s id="66.2">I needed the widest shoes in the world.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="67">So I found some enormous, ridiculous, giant ski boots and then wobbly, wobbly I get on the ropes.</s>
 <s id="68">Well within a few days I'm able to do one crossing.</s>
 <s id="69">So I cut one rope off.</s>
 <s id="70">And the next day one rope off.</s>
 <s id="71">And a few days later, I was practicing on a single tightrope.</s>
 <s id="72">Now you can imagine at that time I had to switch the ridiculous boots for some slippers.</s>
 <s id="73">So that is how -- in case there are people here in the audience who would like to try -- this is how not to learn wire walking.</s>
 <s id="74">(Laughter) Intuition is a tool essential in my life.</s>
 <s id="75">In the meantime, I am being thrown out of five different schools because instead of listening to the teachers, I am my own teacher, progressing in my new art and becoming a street juggler.</s>
 <s id="76">On the high wire, within months, I'm able to master all the tricks they do in the circus, except I am not satisfied.</s>
 <s id="77">I was starting to invent my own moves and bring them to perfection.</s>
 <s id="78">But nobody wanted to hire me.</s>
 <s id="79">So I started putting a wire up in secret and performing without permission.</s>
 <s id="80">Notre Dame, the Sydney Harbor Bridge, the World Trade Center.</s>
 <s id="81">And I developed a certitude, a faith that convinced me that I will get safely to the other side.</s>
 <s id="82">If not, I will never do that first step.</s>
 <s id="83">Well nonetheless, on the top of the World Trade Center my first step was terrifying.</s>
 <s id="84">All of a sudden the density of the air is no longer the same.</s>
 <s id="85">Manhattan no longer spreads its infinity.</s>
 <s id="86">The murmur of the city dissolves into a squall whose chilling power I no longer feel.</s>
 <p id="p87">
  <s id="87.1">I lift the balancing pole.</s>
  <s id="87.2">I approach the edge.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="88">I step over the beam.</s>
 <s id="89">I put my left foot on the cable, the weight of my body raised on my right leg anchored to the flank of the building.</s>
 <s id="90">Shall I ever so slightly shift my weight to the left?</s>
 <s id="91">My right leg will be unburdened, my right foot will freely meet the wire.</s>
 <s id="92">On one side, a mass of a mountain, a life I know.</s>
 <s id="93">On the other, the universe of the clouds, so full of unknown we think it's empty.</s>
 <s id="94">At my feet, the path to the north tower -- 60 yards of wire rope.</s>
 <s id="95">It's a straight line, which sags, which sways, which vibrates, which rolls on itself, which is ice, which is three tons tight, ready to explode, ready to swallow me.</s>
 <s id="96">An inner howl assails me, the wild longing to flee.</s>
 <s id="97">But it is too late.</s>
 <s id="98">The wire is ready.</s>
 <s id="99">Decisively my other foot sets itself onto the cable.</s>
 <s id="100">Faith is what replaces doubt in my dictionary.</s>
 <s id="101">So after the walk people ask me, "How can you top that?"</s>
 <s id="102">Well I didn't have that problem.</s>
 <s id="103">I was not interested in collecting the gigantic, in breaking records.</s>
 <s id="104">In fact, I put my World Trade Center crossing at the same artistic level as some of my smaller walks -- or some completely different type of performance.</s>
 <s id="105">Let's see, such as my street juggling, for example.</s>
 <s id="106">So each time I draw my circle of chalk on the pavement and enter as the improvising comic silent character I created 45 years ago, I am as happy as when I am in the clouds.</s>
 <s id="107">But this here, this is not the street.</s>
 <s id="108">So I cannot street juggle here, you understand.</s>
 <s id="109">So you don't want me to street juggle here, right?</s>
 <s id="110">You know that, right?</s>
 <s id="111">You don't want me to juggle, right?</s>
 <p id="p112">
  <s id="112.1">(Applause) (Music) (Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="112.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="113">Each time I street juggle I use improvisation.</s>
 <s id="114">Now improvisation is empowering because it welcomes the unknown.</s>
 <s id="115">And since what's impossible is always unknown, it allows me to believe I can cheat the impossible.</s>
 <s id="116">Now I have done the impossible not once, but many times.</s>
 <p id="p117">
  <s id="117.1">So what should I share?</s>
  <s id="117.2">Oh, I know.</s>
  <s id="117.3">Israel.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="118">Some years ago I was invited to open the Israel Festival by a high-wire walk.</s>
 <s id="119">And I chose to put my wire between the Arab quarters and the Jewish quarter of Jerusalem over the Ben Hinnom Valley.</s>
 <s id="120">And I thought it would be incredible if in the middle of the wire I stopped and, like a magician, I produce a dove and send her in the sky as a living symbol of peace.</s>
 <s id="121">Well now I must say, it was a little bit hard to find a dove in Israel, but I got one.</s>
 <s id="122">And in my hotel room, each time I practiced making it appear and throwing her in the air, she would graze the wall and end up on the bed.</s>
 <p id="p123">
  <s id="123.1">So I said, now it's okay.</s>
  <s id="123.2">The room is too small.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="124">I mean, a bird needs space to fly.</s>
 <s id="125">It will go perfectly on the day of the walk.</s>
 <s id="126">Now comes the day of the walk.</s>
 <s id="127">Eighty thousand people spread over the entire valley.</s>
 <s id="128">The mayor of Jerusalem, Teddy Kollek, comes to wish me the best.</s>
 <s id="129">But he seemed nervous.</s>
 <s id="130">There was tension in my wire, but I also could feel tension on the ground.</s>
 <s id="131">Because all those people were made up of people who, for the most part, considered each other enemies.</s>
 <p id="p132">
  <s id="132.1">So I start the walk.</s>
  <s id="132.2">Everything is fine.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="133">I stop in the middle.</s>
 <s id="134">I make the dove appear.</s>
 <s id="135">People applaud in delight.</s>
 <s id="136">And then in the most magnificent gesture, I send the bird of peace into the azure.</s>
 <s id="137">But the bird, instead of flying away, goes flop, flop, flop and lands on my head.</s>
 <s id="138">(Laughter) And people scream.</s>
 <s id="139">So I grab the dove, and for the second time I send her in the air.</s>
 <s id="140">But the dove, who obviously didn't go to flying school, goes flop, flop, flop and ends up at the end of my balancing pole.</s>
 <p id="p141">
  <s id="141.1">(Laughter) You laugh, you laugh.</s>
  <s id="141.2">But hey.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p142">
  <s id="142.1">I sit down immediately.</s>
  <s id="142.2">It's a reflex of wire walkers.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="143">Now in the meantime, the audience, they go crazy.</s>
 <s id="144">They must think this guy with this dove, he must have spent years working with him.</s>
 <s id="145">What a genius, what a professional.</s>
 <p id="p146">
  <s id="146.1">(Laughter) So I take a bow.</s>
  <s id="146.2">I salute with my hand.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="147">And at the end I bang my hand against the pole to dislodge the bird.</s>
 <s id="148">Now the dove, who, now you know, obviously cannot fly, does for the third time a little flop, flop, flop and ends up on the wire behind me.</s>
 <s id="149">And the entire valley goes crazy.</s>
 <s id="150">Now but hold on, I'm not finished.</s>
 <s id="151">So now I'm like 50 yards from my arrival and I'm exhausted, so my steps are slow.</s>
 <s id="152">And something happened.</s>
 <s id="153">Somebody somewhere, a group of people, starts clapping in rhythm with my steps.</s>
 <s id="154">And within seconds the entire valley is applauding in unison with each of my steps.</s>
 <s id="155">But not an applause of delight like before, an applause encouragement.</s>
 <s id="156">For a moment, the entire crowd had forgotten their differences.</s>
 <s id="157">They had become one, pushing me to triumph.</s>
 <s id="158">I want you just for a second to experience this amazing human symphony.</s>
 <s id="159">So let's say I am here and the chair is my arrival.</s>
 <s id="160">So I walk, you clap, everybody in unison.</s>
 <s id="161">(Clapping) (Applause) So after the walk, Teddy and I become friends.</s>
 <s id="162">And he tells me, he has on his desk a picture of me in the middle of the wire with a dove on my head.</s>
 <s id="163">He didn't know the true story.</s>
 <s id="164">And whenever he's daunted by an impossible situation to solve in this hard-to-manage city, instead of giving up, he looks at the picture and he says, "If Philippe can do that, I can do this," and he goes back to work.</s>
 <s id="165">Inspiration.</s>
 <s id="166">By inspiring ourselves we inspire others.</s>
 <s id="167">I will never forget this music, and I hope now neither will you.</s>
 <s id="168">Please take this music with you home, and start gluing feathers to your arms and take off and fly, and look at the world from a different perspective.</s>
 <s id="169">And when you see mountains, remember mountains can be moved.</s>
 <p id="p170">
  <s id="170.1">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="170.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="171">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="172">(Applause)</s>
</text>
