<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Chak Ek’ rose from the underworld to the surface of the eastern sea and on into the heavens.</s>
 <s id="2">His brother K’in Ahaw followed.</s>
 <s id="3">Though Chak Ek’ had risen first, K’in Ahaw outshone him, and the resentful Chak Ek’ descended back to the underworld to plot against his brother.</s>
 <s id="4">In Mayan mythology, Chak Ek’ represents Venus and K’in Ahaw represents the sun.</s>
 <s id="5">Known as both the morning and the evening star, Venus moves through the sky, sometimes visible before sunrise, sometimes after sunset, and occasionally not at all.</s>
 <s id="6">The ancient Maya identified this roughly 584 day cycle more than a thousand years ago and it still accurately predicts when and where Venus will appear in the sky around the world.</s>
 <s id="7">Five of these cycles make up almost exactly eight years, and the Maya also recognized this larger cycle.</s>
 <s id="8">They assigned Chak Ek’ five different forms, one for each cycle of Venus, that were repeated every eight years.</s>
 <s id="9">Within the 584 day cycle, Venus is visible in the evening sky for 250 days, then disappears for 8 days before reappearing as the Morning Star.</s>
 <s id="10">The ancient Maya ascribed particular significance to this point in this cycle: the first time Venus appears before sunrise after being invisible.</s>
 <s id="11">On this day, Chak Ek’ rose again from the underworld, wielding a spearthrower and darts.</s>
 <s id="12">To bring discord to the world, he decided to attack his brother and his brother’s allies.</s>
 <s id="13">His first target was K’awiil, god of sustenance and lightning.</s>
 <s id="14">Rising in the late rainy season, Chak Ek’ aimed his spear and struck K’awiil, causing damage to the food and a period of chaos in the social order until K’awiil was reborn.</s>
 <s id="15">584 days after attacking K’awiil, Chak Ek’ turned his attention back to his brother, the Sun.</s>
 <s id="16">Each night, the Sun took the form of jaguar and journeyed through the underworld.</s>
 <s id="17">Chak Ek’ speared the jaguar sun as it rose at dawn towards the end of the dry season.</s>
 <s id="18">The Sun was wounded, plunging the world into a period of chaos and warfare.</s>
 <s id="19">Chak Ek’s third victim was the god of maize, who provided sustenance for all humankind.</s>
 <s id="20">Chak Ek’ speared him at the time of the harvest.</s>
 <s id="21">He was buried in the underworld, and maize—the staple of life— was no longer available to Earth’s inhabitants.</s>
 <s id="22">But the maize god emerged after three months in the place of new beginnings– the eastern cave known as Seven Water Place– bringing food once again to earth.</s>
 <s id="23">When the turtle Ak Na'ak rose in the sky to mark the summer solstice, Chak Ek’ claimed his fourth victim.</s>
 <s id="24">With the death of this good omen, the Sun, the food supply, and the people were buried within the earth, and the forces of chaos reigned.</s>
 <s id="25">But out of the chaos rose a new order established by Hun Ajaw, one of the hero twins known to all for having vanquished the lords of the underworld.</s>
 <s id="26">A new race of humans was created, made from maize.</s>
 <s id="27">This state of balance was not to last, however.</s>
 <s id="28">Chak Ek’s fifth and final victim was a mysterious stranger from the west, and his death in the heart of the dry season shook the order established by Hun Ajaw.</s>
 <s id="29">The gods, the lords, and the maize were buried in the underworld.</s>
 <s id="30">But this victory for Chak Ek’ would also prove temporary.</s>
 <s id="31">The two brothers, Venus and the Sun, were caught in an endless cycle as they battled for supremacy, re-enacting the same five struggles, while the world alternated between order and chaos with the rising of the Morning Star.</s>
</text>
