<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Charles Osborne began to hiccup in 1922 after a hog fell on top of him.</s>
 <s id="2">He wasn't cured until 68 years later and is now listed by Guinness as the world record holder for hiccup longevity.</s>
 <s id="3">Meanwhile, Florida teen Jennifer Mee may hold the record for the most frequent hiccups, 50 times per minute for more than four weeks in 2007.</s>
 <s id="4">So what causes hiccups?</s>
 <s id="5">Doctors point out that a round of hiccups often follows from stimuli that stretch the stomach, like swallowing air or too rapid eating or drinking.</s>
 <s id="6">Others associate hiccups with intense emotions or a response to them: laughing, sobbing, anxiety, and excitement.</s>
 <s id="7">Let's look at what happens when we hiccup.</s>
 <s id="8">It begins with an involuntary spasm or sudden contraction of the diaphragm, the large dome-shaped muscle below our lungs that we use to inhale air.</s>
 <s id="9">This is followed almost immediately by the sudden closure of the vocal chords and the opening between them, which is called the glottis.</s>
 <s id="10">The movement of the diaphragm initiates a sudden intake of air, but the closure of the vocal chords stops it from entering the wind pipe and reaching the lungs.</s>
 <s id="11">It also creates the characteristic sound: "hic."</s>
 <s id="12">To date, there is no known function for hiccups.</s>
 <s id="13">They don't seem to provide any medical or physiological advantage.</s>
 <s id="14">Why begin to inhale air only to suddenly stop it from actually entering the lungs?</s>
 <s id="15">Anatomical structures, or physiological mechanisms, with no apparent purpose present challenges to evolutionary biologists.</s>
 <s id="16">Do such structures serve some hidden function that hasn't yet been discovered?</s>
 <s id="17">Or are they relics of our evolutionary past, having once served some important purpose only to persist into the present as vestigial remnants?</s>
 <s id="18">One idea is that hiccups began many millions of years before the appearance of humans.</s>
 <s id="19">The lung is thought to have evolved as a structure to allow early fish, many of which lived in warm, stagnant water with little oxygen, to take advantage of the abundant oxygen in the air overhead.</s>
 <s id="20">When descendants of these animals later moved onto land, they moved from gill-based ventilation to air-breathing with lungs.</s>
 <s id="21">That's similar to the much more rapid changes faced by frogs today as they transition from tadpoles with gills to adults with lungs.</s>
 <s id="22">This hypothesis suggests that the hiccup is a relic of the ancient transition from water to land.</s>
 <s id="23">An inhalation that could move water over gills followed by a rapid closure of the glottis preventing water from entering the lungs.</s>
 <s id="24">That's supported by evidence which suggests that the neural patterning involved in generating a hiccup is almost identical to that responsible for respiration in amphibians.</s>
 <s id="25">Another group of scientists believe that the reflex is retained in us today because it actually provides an important advantage.</s>
 <s id="26">They point out that true hiccups are found only in mammals and that they're not retained in birds, lizards, turtles, or any other exclusively air-breathing animals.</s>
 <s id="27">Further, hiccups appear in human babies long before birth and are far more common in infants that adults.</s>
 <s id="28">Their explanation for this involves the uniquely mammalian activity of nursing.</s>
 <s id="29">The ancient hiccup reflex may have been adapted by mammals to help remove air from the stomach as a sort of glorified burp.</s>
 <s id="30">The sudden expansion of the diaphragm would raise air from the stomach, while a closure of the glottis would prevent milk from entering the lungs.</s>
 <s id="31">Sometimes, a bout of hiccups will go on and on, and we try home remedies: sipping continuously from a glass of cold water, holding one's breath, a mouthful of honey or peanut butter, breathing into a paper bag, or being suddenly frightened.</s>
 <s id="32">Unfortunately, scientists have yet to verify that any one cure works better or more consistently than others.</s>
 <s id="33">However, we do know one thing that definitely doesn't work.</s>
</text>
