<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So I was trained to become a gymnast for two years in Hunan, China in the 1970s.</s>
 <s id="2">When I was in the first grade, the government wanted to transfer me to a school for athletes, all expenses paid.</s>
 <s id="3">But my tiger mother said, "No."</s>
 <s id="4">My parents wanted me to become an engineer like them.</s>
 <s id="5">After surviving the Cultural Revolution, they firmly believed there's only one sure way to happiness: a safe and well-paid job.</s>
 <s id="6">It is not important if I like the job or not.</s>
 <s id="7">But my dream was to become a Chinese opera singer.</s>
 <s id="8">That is me playing my imaginary piano.</s>
 <s id="9">An opera singer must start training young to learn acrobatics, so I tried everything I could to go to opera school.</s>
 <s id="10">I even wrote to the school principal and the host of a radio show.</s>
 <s id="11">But no adults liked the idea.</s>
 <s id="12">No adults believed I was serious.</s>
 <s id="13">Only my friends supported me, but they were kids, just as powerless as I was.</s>
 <s id="14">So at age 15, I knew I was too old to be trained.</s>
 <s id="15">My dream would never come true.</s>
 <s id="16">I was afraid that for the rest of my life some second-class happiness would be the best I could hope for.</s>
 <s id="17">But that's so unfair.</s>
 <s id="18">So I was determined to find another calling.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">Nobody around to teach me?</s>
  <s id="19.2">Fine.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">I turned to books.</s>
 <s id="21">I satisfied my hunger for parental advice from this book by a family of writers and musicians.["Correspondence in the Family of Fou Lei"] I found my role model of an independent woman when Confucian tradition requires obedience.["Jane Eyre"] And I learned to be efficient from this book.["Cheaper by the Dozen"] And I was inspired to study abroad after reading these.</s>
 <s id="22">["Complete Works of Sanmao" (aka Echo Chan)] ["Lessons From History" by Nan Huaijin] I came to the U.S. in 1995, so which books did I read here first?</s>
 <s id="23">Books banned in China, of course.</s>
 <s id="24">"The Good Earth" is about Chinese peasant life.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">That's just not convenient for propaganda.</s>
  <s id="25.2">Got it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">The Bible is interesting, but strange.</s>
 <s id="27">(Laughter) That's a topic for a different day.</s>
 <s id="28">But the fifth commandment gave me an epiphany: "You shall honor your father and mother."</s>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">"Honor," I said.</s>
  <s id="29.2">"That's so different, and better, than obey."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">So it becomes my tool to climb out of this Confucian guilt trap and to restart my relationship with my parents.</s>
 <s id="31">Encountering a new culture also started my habit of comparative reading.</s>
 <s id="32">It offers many insights.</s>
 <s id="33">For example, I found this map out of place at first because this is what Chinese students grew up with.</s>
 <s id="34">It had never occurred to me, China doesn't have to be at the center of the world.</s>
 <s id="35">A map actually carries somebody's view.</s>
 <s id="36">Comparative reading actually is nothing new.</s>
 <s id="37">It's a standard practice in the academic world.</s>
 <s id="38">There are even research fields such as comparative religion and comparative literature.</s>
 <s id="39">Compare and contrast gives scholars a more complete understanding of a topic.</s>
 <s id="40">So I thought, well, if comparative reading works for research, why not do it in daily life too?</s>
 <s id="41">So I started reading books in pairs.</s>
 <s id="42">So they can be about people -- ["Benjamin Franklin" by Walter Isaacson]["John Adams" by David McCullough] -- who are involved in the same event, or friends with shared experiences.</s>
 <s id="43">["Personal History" by Katharine Graham]["The Snowball: Warren Buffett and the Business of Life," by Alice Schroeder] I also compare the same stories in different genres -- (Laughter) [Holy Bible: King James Version]["Lamb" by Chrisopher Moore] -- or similar stories from different cultures, as Joseph Campbell did in his wonderful book.["The Power of Myth" by Joseph Campbell] For example, both the Christ and the Buddha went through three temptations.</s>
 <s id="44">For the Christ, the temptations are economic, political and spiritual.</s>
 <s id="45">For the Buddha, they are all psychological: lust, fear and social duty -- interesting.</s>
 <s id="46">So if you know a foreign language, it's also fun to read your favorite books in two languages.</s>
 <s id="47">["The Way of Chuang Tzu" Thomas Merton]["Tao: The Watercourse Way" Alan Watts] Instead of lost in translation, I found there is much to gain.</s>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">For example, it's through translation that I realized "happiness" in Chinese literally means "fast joy."</s>
  <s id="48.2">Huh!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">"Bride" in Chinese literally means "new mother."</s>
  <s id="49.2">Uh-oh.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">(Laughter) Books have given me a magic portal to connect with people of the past and the present.</s>
 <s id="51">I know I shall never feel lonely or powerless again.</s>
 <s id="52">Having a dream shattered really is nothing compared to what many others have suffered.</s>
 <s id="53">I have come to believe that coming true is not the only purpose of a dream.</s>
 <s id="54">Its most important purpose is to get us in touch with where dreams come from, where passion comes from, where happiness comes from.</s>
 <s id="55">Even a shattered dream can do that for you.</s>
 <s id="56">So because of books, I'm here today, happy, living again with a purpose and a clarity, most of the time.</s>
 <s id="57">So may books be always with you.</s>
 <s id="58">Thank you.</s>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="59.2">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="59.3">(Applause)</s>
 </p>
</text>
