<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">You might think there are many things that I can't do because I cannot see.</s>
 <s id="2">That's largely true.</s>
 <s id="3">Actually, I just needed to have a bit of help to come up to the stage.</s>
 <s id="4">But there is also a lot that I can do.</s>
 <s id="5">This is me rock climbing for the first time.</s>
 <s id="6">Actually, I love sports and I can play many sports, like swimming, skiing, skating, scuba diving, running and so on.</s>
 <s id="7">But there is one limitation: somebody needs to help me.</s>
 <s id="8">I want to be independent.</s>
 <s id="9">I lost my sight at the age of 14 in a swimming pool accident.</s>
 <s id="10">I was an active, independent teenager, and suddenly I became blind.</s>
 <s id="11">The hardest thing for me was losing my independence.</s>
 <s id="12">Things that until then seemed simple became almost impossible to do alone.</s>
 <s id="13">For example, one of my challenges was textbooks.</s>
 <s id="14">Back then, there were no personal computers, no Internet, no smartphones.</s>
 <s id="15">So I had to ask one of my two brothers to read me textbooks, and I had to create my own books in Braille.</s>
 <s id="16">Can you imagine?</s>
 <s id="17">Of course, my brothers were not happy about it, and later, I noticed they were not there whenever I needed them.</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) I think they tried to stay away from me.</s>
 <s id="19">I don't blame them.</s>
 <s id="20">I really wanted to be freed from relying on someone.</s>
 <s id="21">That became my strong desire to ignite innovation.</s>
 <s id="22">Jump ahead to the mid-1980s.</s>
 <s id="23">I got to know cutting-edge technologies and I thought to myself, how come there is no computer technology to create books in Braille?</s>
 <s id="24">These amazing technologies must be able to also help people with limitations like myself.</s>
 <s id="25">That's the moment my innovation journey began.</s>
 <s id="26">I started developing digital book technologies, such as a digital Braille editor, digital Braille dictionary and a digital Braille library network.</s>
 <s id="27">Today, every student who is visually impaired can read textbooks, by using personal computers and mobile devices, in Braille or in voice.</s>
 <s id="28">This may not surprise you, since everyone now has digital books in their tablets in 2015.</s>
 <s id="29">But Braille went digital many years before digital books, already in the late 1980s, almost 30 years ago.</s>
 <s id="30">Strong and specific needs of the blind people made this opportunity to create digital books way back then.</s>
 <s id="31">And this is actually not the first time this happened, because history shows us accessibility ignites innovation.</s>
 <s id="32">The telephone was invented while developing a communication tool for hearing impaired people.</s>
 <s id="33">Some keyboards were also invented to help people with disabilities.</s>
 <s id="34">Now I'm going to give you another example from my own life.</s>
 <s id="35">In the '90s, people around me started talking about the Internet and web browsing.</s>
 <s id="36">I remember the first time I went on the web.</s>
 <s id="37">I was astonished.</s>
 <s id="38">I could access newspapers at any time and every day.</s>
 <s id="39">I could even search for any information by myself.</s>
 <s id="40">I desperately wanted to help the blind people have access to the Internet, and I found ways to render the web into synthesized voice, which dramatically simplified the user interface.</s>
 <s id="41">This led me to develop the Home Page Reader in 1997, first in Japanese and later, translated into 11 languages.</s>
 <s id="42">When I developed the Home Page Reader, I got many comments from users.</s>
 <s id="43">One that I strongly remember said, "For me, the Internet is a small window to the world."</s>
 <s id="44">It was a revolutionary moment for the blind.</s>
 <s id="45">The cyber world became accessible, and this technology that we created for the blind has many uses, way beyond what I imagined.</s>
 <s id="46">It can help drivers listen to their emails or it can help you listen to a recipe while cooking.</s>
 <s id="47">Today, I am more independent, but it is still not enough.</s>
 <s id="48">For example, when I approached the stage just now, I needed assistance.</s>
 <s id="49">My goal is to come up here independently.</s>
 <s id="50">And not just here.</s>
 <s id="51">My goal is to be able to travel and do things that are simple to you.</s>
 <s id="52">OK, now let me show you the latest technologies.</s>
 <s id="53">This is a smartphone app that we are working on.</s>
 <s id="54">(Video) Electronic voice: 51 feet to the door, and keep straight.</s>
 <p id="p55">
  <s id="55.1">EV: Take the two doors to go out.</s>
  <s id="55.2">The door is on your right.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p56">
  <s id="56.1">EV: Nick is approaching.</s>
  <s id="56.2">Looks so happy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="57">Chieko Asakawa: Hi, Nick!</s>
 <p id="p58">
  <s id="58.1">(Laughter) CA: Where are you going?</s>
  <s id="58.2">You look so happy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="59">Nick: Oh -- well, my paper just got accepted.</s>
 <p id="p60">
  <s id="60.1">CA: That's great!</s>
  <s id="60.2">Congratulations.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p61">
  <s id="61.1">Nick: Thanks.</s>
  <s id="61.2">Wait -- how'd you know it was me, and that I look happy?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="62">(Chieko and Nick laugh) Man: Hi.</s>
 <s id="63">(Laughter) CA: Oh ... hi.</s>
 <s id="64">EV: He is not talking to you, but on his phone.</s>
 <s id="65">EV: Potato chips.</s>
 <s id="66">EV: Dark chocolate with almonds.</s>
 <s id="67">EV: You gained 5 pounds since yesterday; take apple instead of chocolate.</s>
 <s id="68">(Laughter) EV: Approaching.</s>
 <s id="69">EV: You arrived.</s>
 <s id="70">CA: Now ...</s>
 <s id="71">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="72">So now the app navigates me by analyzing beacon signals and smartphone sensors and permits me to move around indoor and outdoor environments all by myself.</s>
 <s id="73">But the computer vision part that showed who is approaching, in which mood -- we are still working on that part.</s>
 <s id="74">And recognizing facial expressions is very important for me to be social.</s>
 <s id="75">So now the fusions of technologies are ready to help me see the real world.</s>
 <s id="76">We call this cognitive assistance.</s>
 <s id="77">It understands our surrounding world and whispers to me in voice or sends a vibration to my fingers.</s>
 <s id="78">Cognitive assistance will augment missing or weakened abilities -- in other words, our five senses.</s>
 <s id="79">This technology is only in an early stage, but eventually, I'll be able to find a classroom on campus, enjoy window shopping or find a nice restaurant while walking along a street.</s>
 <s id="80">It will be amazing if I can find you on the street before you notice me.</s>
 <s id="81">It will become my best buddy, and yours.</s>
 <s id="82">So, this really is a great challenge.</s>
 <s id="83">It is a challenge that needs collaboration, which is why we are creating an open community to accelerate research activities.</s>
 <s id="84">Just this morning, we announced the open-source fundamental technologies you just saw in the video.</s>
 <s id="85">The frontier is the real world.</s>
 <s id="86">The blind community is exploring this technical frontier and the pathfinder.</s>
 <s id="87">I hope to work with you to explore the new era, and the next time that I'm on this stage, through technology and innovation, I will be able to walk up here all by myself.</s>
 <s id="88">Thank you so much.</s>
 <s id="89">(Applause)</s>
</text>
