<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I work with a species called "Bonobo."</s>
 <s id="2">And I'm happy most of the time, because I think this is the happiest species on the planet.</s>
 <s id="3">It's kind of a well-kept secret.</s>
 <s id="4">This species lives only in the Congo.</s>
 <s id="5">And they're not in too many zoos, because of their sexual behavior.</s>
 <s id="6">Their sexual behavior is too human-like for most of us to be comfortable with.</s>
 <s id="7">(Laughter) But -- (Laughter) actually, we have a lot to learn from them, because they're a very egalitarian society and they're a very empathetic society.</s>
 <s id="8">And sexual behavior is not confined to one aspect of their life that they sort of set aside.</s>
 <s id="9">It permeates their entire life.</s>
 <s id="10">And it's used for communication.</s>
 <s id="11">And it's used for conflict resolution.</s>
 <s id="12">And I think perhaps somewhere in our history we sort of, divided our lives up into lots of parts.</s>
 <s id="13">We divided our world up with lots of categories.</s>
 <s id="14">And so everything sort of has a place that it has to fit.</s>
 <s id="15">But I don't think that we were that way initially.</s>
 <s id="16">There are many people who think that the animal world is hard-wired and that there's something very, very special about man.</s>
 <s id="17">Maybe it's his ability to have causal thought.</s>
 <s id="18">Maybe it's something special in his brain that allows him to have language.</s>
 <s id="19">Maybe it's something special in his brain that allows him to make tools or to have mathematics.</s>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">Well, I don't know.</s>
  <s id="20.2">There were Tasmanians who were discovered around the 1600s and they had no fire.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="21">They had no stone tools.</s>
 <s id="22">To our knowledge they had no music.</s>
 <s id="23">So when you compare them to the Bonobo, the Bonobo is a little hairier.</s>
 <s id="24">He doesn't stand quite as upright.</s>
 <s id="25">But there are a lot of similarities.</s>
 <s id="26">And I think that as we look at culture, we kind of come to understand how we got to where we are.</s>
 <s id="27">And I don't really think it's in our biology; I think we've attributed it to our biology, but I don't really think it's there.</s>
 <s id="28">So what I want to do now is introduce you to a species called the Bonobo.</s>
 <s id="29">This is Kanzi.</s>
 <s id="30">He's a Bonobo.</s>
 <s id="31">Right now, he's in a forest in Georgia.</s>
 <s id="32">His mother originally came from a forest in Africa.</s>
 <s id="33">And she came to us when she was just at puberty, about six or seven years of age.</s>
 <s id="34">Now this shows a Bonobo on your right, and a chimpanzee on your left.</s>
 <s id="35">Clearly, the chimpanzee has a little bit harder time of walking.</s>
 <s id="36">The Bonobo, although shorter than us and their arms still longer, is more upright, just as we are.</s>
 <s id="37">This shows the Bonobo compared to an australopithecine like Lucy.</s>
 <s id="38">As you can see, there's not a lot of difference between the way a Bonobo walks and the way an early australopithecine would have walked.</s>
 <s id="39">As they turn toward us you'll see that the pelvic area of early australopithecines is a little flatter and doesn't have to rotate quite so much from side to side.</s>
 <s id="40">So the -- the bipedal gait is a little easier.</s>
 <s id="41">And now we see all four.</s>
 <s id="42">Video: Narrator: The wild Bonobo lives in central Africa, in the jungle encircled by the Congo River.</s>
 <s id="43">Canopied trees as tall as 40 meters, 130 feet, grow densely in the area.</s>
 <s id="44">It was a Japanese scientist who first undertook serious field studies of the Bonobo, almost three decades ago.</s>
 <s id="45">Bonobos are built slightly smaller than the chimpanzee.</s>
 <s id="46">Slim-bodied, Bonobos are by nature very gentle creatures.</s>
 <s id="47">Long and careful studies have reported many new findings on them.</s>
 <s id="48">One discovery was that wild Bonobos often walk bidpedally.</s>
 <s id="49">What's more, they are able to walk upright for long distances.</s>
 <s id="50">Susan Savage-Rumbaugh (video): Let's go say hello to Austin first and then go to the A frame.</s>
 <s id="51">SS: This is Kanzi and I, in the forest.</s>
 <s id="52">None of the things you will see in this particular video are trained.</s>
 <s id="53">None of them are tricks.</s>
 <s id="54">They all happened to be captured on film spontaneously, by NHK of Japan.</s>
 <s id="55">We have eight Bonobos.</s>
 <s id="56">Video: Look at all this stuff that's here for our campfire.</s>
 <s id="57">SS: An entire family at our research centre.</s>
 <s id="58">Video: You going to help get some sticks?</s>
 <s id="59">Good.</s>
 <s id="60">We need more sticks, too.</s>
 <s id="61">I have a lighter in my pocket if you need one.</s>
 <s id="62">That's a wasps' nest.</s>
 <s id="63">You can get it out.</s>
 <s id="64">I hope I have a lighter.</s>
 <s id="65">You can use the lighter to start the fire.</s>
 <s id="66">SS: So Kanzi is very interested in fire.</s>
 <s id="67">He doesn't do it yet without a lighter, but I think if he saw someone do it, he might be able to do -- make a fire without a lighter.</s>
 <s id="68">He's learning about how to keep a fire going.</s>
 <s id="69">He's learning the uses for a fire, just by watching what we do with fire.</s>
 <s id="70">(Laughter) This is a smile on the face of a Bonobo.</s>
 <s id="71">These are happy vocalizations.</s>
 <s id="72">Video: You're happy.</s>
 <s id="73">You're very happy about this part.</s>
 <p id="p74">
  <s id="74.1">You've got to put some water on the fire.</s>
  <s id="74.2">You see the water?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="75">Good job.</s>
 <s id="76">SS: Forgot to zip up the back half of his backpack.</s>
 <s id="77">But he likes to carry things from place to place.</s>
 <s id="78">Video: Austin, I hear you saying "Austin."</s>
 <s id="79">SS: He talks to other Bonobos at the lab, long-distance, farther than we can hear.</s>
 <s id="80">This is his sister.</s>
 <s id="81">This is her first time to try to drive a golf cart.</s>
 <s id="82">Video: Goodbye.</s>
 <s id="83">(Laughter) SS: She's got the pedals down, but not the wheel.</s>
 <s id="84">She switches from reverse to forward and she holds onto the wheel, rather than turns it.</s>
 <s id="85">(Laughter) Like us, she knows that that individual in the mirror is her.</s>
 <s id="86">(Music) Video: Narrator: By raising Bonobos in a culture that is both Bonobo and human, and documenting their development across two decades, scientists are exploring how cultural forces (Laughter) may have operated during human evolution.</s>
 <s id="87">His name is Nyota.</s>
 <s id="88">It means "star" in Swahili.</s>
 <s id="89">(Music) Panbanisha is trying to give Nyota a haircut with a pair of scissors.</s>
 <s id="90">In the wild, the parent Bonobo is known to groom its offspring.</s>
 <s id="91">Here Panbanisha uses scissors, instead of her hands, to groom Nyota.</s>
 <s id="92">Very impressive.</s>
 <s id="93">Subtle maneuvering of the hands is required to perform delicate tasks like this.</s>
 <s id="94">Nyota tries to imitate Panbanisha by using the scissors himself.</s>
 <s id="95">Realizing that Nyota might get hurt, Panbanisha, like any human mother, carefully tugs to get the scissors back.</s>
 <s id="96">He can now cut through tough animal hide.</s>
 <s id="97">SS: Kanzi's learned to make stone tools.</s>
 <s id="98">Video: Kanzi now makes his tools, just as our ancestors may have made them, two-and-a-half million years ago -- by holding the rocks in both hands, to strike one against the other.</s>
 <s id="99">He has learned that by using both hands and aiming his glancing blows, he can make much larger, sharper flakes.</s>
 <s id="100">Kanzi chooses a flake he thinks is sharp enough.</s>
 <s id="101">The tough hide is difficult to cut, even with a knife.</s>
 <s id="102">The rock that Kanzi is using is extremely hard and ideal for stone tool making, but difficult to handle, requiring great skill.</s>
 <s id="103">Kanzi's rock is from Gona, Ethiopia and is identical to that used by our African ancestors two-and-a-half million years ago.</s>
 <s id="104">These are the rocks Kanzi used and these are the flakes he made.</s>
 <s id="105">The flat sharp edges are like knife blades.</s>
 <s id="106">Compare them to the tools our ancestors used; they bear a striking resemblance to Kanzi's.</s>
 <s id="107">Panbanisha is longing to go for a walk in the woods.</s>
 <s id="108">She keeps staring out the window.</s>
 <s id="109">SS: This is -- let me show you something we didn't think they would do.</s>
 <s id="110">Video: For several days now, Panbanisha has not been outside.</s>
 <s id="111">SS: I normally talk about language.</s>
 <s id="112">Video: Then Panbanisha does something unexpected.</s>
 <s id="113">SS: But since I'm advised not to do what I normally do, I haven't told you that these apes have language.</s>
 <s id="114">It's a geometric language.</s>
 <s id="115">Video: She takes a piece of chalk and begins writing something on the floor.</s>
 <s id="116">What is she writing?</s>
 <s id="117">SS: She's also saying the name of that, with her voice.</s>
 <s id="118">Video: Now she comes up to Dr. Sue and starts writing again.</s>
 <s id="119">SS: These are her symbols on her keyboard.</s>
 <s id="120">(Music) They speak when she touches them.</s>
 <s id="121">Video: Panbanisha is communicating to Dr. Sue where she wants to go.</s>
 <s id="122">"A frame" represents a hut in the woods.</s>
 <s id="123">Compare the chalk writing with the lexigram on the keyboard.</s>
 <s id="124">Panbanisha began writing the lexigrams on the forest floor.</s>
 <p id="p125">
  <s id="125.1">SS (video): Very nice.</s>
  <s id="125.2">Beautiful, Panbanisha.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="126">SS: At first we didn't really realize what she was doing, until we stood back and looked at it and rotated it.</s>
 <s id="127">Video: This lexigram also refers to a place in the woods.</s>
 <s id="128">The curved line is very similar to the lexigram.</s>
 <s id="129">The next symbol Panbanisha writes represents "collar."</s>
 <s id="130">It indicates the collar that Panbanisha must wear when she goes out.</s>
 <s id="131">SS: That's an institutional requirement.</s>
 <s id="132">Video: This symbol is not as clear as the others, but one can see Panbanisha is trying to produce a curved line and several straight lines.</s>
 <s id="133">Researchers began to record what Panbanisha said, by writing lexigrams on the floor with chalk.</s>
 <s id="134">Panbanisha watched.</s>
 <s id="135">Soon she began to write as well.</s>
 <s id="136">The Bonobo's abilities have stunned scientists around the world.</s>
 <s id="137">How did they develop?</s>
 <s id="138">SS (video): We found that the most important thing for permitting Bonobos to acquire language is not to teach them.</s>
 <s id="139">It's simply to use language around them, because the driving force in language acquisition is to understand what others, that are important to you, are saying to you.</s>
 <s id="140">Once you have that capacity, the ability to produce language comes rather naturally and rather freely.</s>
 <s id="141">So we want to create an environment in which Bonobos, like all of the individuals with whom they are interacting -- we want to create an environment in which they have fun, and an environment in which the others are meaningful individuals for them.</s>
 <s id="142">Narrator: This environment brings out unexpected potential in Kanzi and Panbanisha.</s>
 <s id="143">Panbanisha is enjoying playing her harmonica, until Nyota, now one year old, steals it.</s>
 <s id="144">Then he peers eagerly into his mother's mouth.</s>
 <s id="145">Is he looking for where the sound came from?</s>
 <s id="146">Dr. Sue thinks it's important to allow such curiosity to flourish.</s>
 <s id="147">This time Panbanisha is playing the electric piano.</s>
 <s id="148">She wasn't forced to learn the piano; she saw a researcher play the instrument and took an interest.</s>
 <p id="p149">
  <s id="149.1">Researcher: Go ahead.</s>
  <s id="149.2">Go ahead.</s>
  <s id="149.3">I'm listening.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p150">
  <s id="150.1">Do that real fast part that you did.</s>
  <s id="150.2">Yeah, that part.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="151">Narrator: Kanzi plays the xylophone; using both hands he enthusiastically accompanies Dr. Sue's singing.</s>
 <s id="152">Kanzi and Panbanisha are stimulated by this fun-filled environment, which promotes the emergence of these cultural capabilities.</s>
 <p id="p153">
  <s id="153.1">(Laughter) Researcher: OK, now get the monsters.</s>
  <s id="153.2">Get them.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="154">Take the cherries too.</s>
 <s id="155">Now watch out, stay away from them now.</s>
 <p id="p156">
  <s id="156.1">Now you can chase them again.</s>
  <s id="156.2">Time to chase them.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p157">
  <s id="157.1">Now you have to stay away.</s>
  <s id="157.2">Get away.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p158">
  <s id="158.1">Run away.</s>
  <s id="158.2">Run.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p159">
  <s id="159.1">Now we can chase them again.</s>
  <s id="159.2">Go get them.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="160">Oh no!</s>
 <p id="p161">
  <s id="161.1">Good Kanzi.</s>
  <s id="161.2">Very good.</s>
  <s id="161.3">Thank you so much.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="162">Narrator: None of us, Bonobo or human, can possibly even imagine?</s>
 <s id="163">SS: So we have a bi-species environment, we call it a "panhomoculture."</s>
 <s id="164">We're learning how to become like them.</s>
 <s id="165">We're learning how to communicate with them, in really high-pitched tones.</s>
 <s id="166">We're learning that they probably have a language in the wild.</s>
 <s id="167">And they're learning to become like us.</s>
 <s id="168">Because we believe that it's not biology; it's culture.</s>
 <s id="169">So we're sharing tools and technology and language with another species.</s>
 <s id="170">Thank you.</s>
</text>
