<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The history of civilization, in some ways, is a history of maps: How have we come to understand the world around us?</s>
 <s id="2">One of the most famous maps works because it really isn't a map at all.</s>
 <p id="p3">
  <s id="3.1">[Small thing.</s>
  <s id="3.2">Big idea.]</s>
  <s id="3.3">[Michael Bierut on the London Tube Map] The London Underground came together in 1908, when eight different independent railways merged to create a single system.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="4">They needed a map to represent that system so people would know where to ride.</s>
 <s id="5">The map they made is complicated.</s>
 <s id="6">You can see rivers, bodies of water, trees and parks -- the stations were all crammed together at the center of the map, and out in the periphery, there were some that couldn't even fit on the map.</s>
 <s id="7">So the map was geographically accurate, but maybe not so useful.</s>
 <s id="8">Enter Harry Beck.</s>
 <s id="9">Harry Beck was a 29-year-old engineering draftsman who had been working on and off for the London Underground.</s>
 <s id="10">And he had a key insight, and that was that people riding underground in trains don't really care what's happening aboveground.</s>
 <p id="p11">
  <s id="11.1">They just want to get from station to station -- "Where do I get on?</s>
  <s id="11.2">Where do I get off?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="12">It's the system that's important, not the geography.</s>
 <s id="13">He's taken this complicated mess of spaghetti, and he's simplified it.</s>
 <s id="14">The lines only go in three directions: they're horizontal, they're vertical, or they're 45 degrees.</s>
 <s id="15">Likewise, he spaced the stations equally, he's made every station color correspond to the color of the line, and he's fixed it all so that it's not really a map anymore.</s>
 <s id="16">What it is is a diagram, just like circuitry, except the circuitry here isn't wires conducting electrons, it's tubes containing trains conducting people from place to place.</s>
 <s id="17">In 1933, the Underground decided, at last, to give Harry Beck's map a try.</s>
 <s id="18">The Underground did a test run of a thousand of these maps, pocket-size.</s>
 <s id="19">They were gone in one hour.</s>
 <s id="20">They realized they were onto something, they printed 750,000 more, and this is the map that you see today.</s>
 <s id="21">Beck's design really became the template for the way we think of metro maps today.</s>
 <s id="22">Tokyo, Paris, Berlin, São Paulo, Sydney, Washington, D.C. -- all of them convert complex geography into crisp geometry.</s>
 <s id="23">All of them use different colors to distinguish between lines, all of them use simple symbols to distinguish between types of stations.</s>
 <s id="24">They all are part of a universal language, seemingly.</s>
 <s id="25">I bet Harry Beck wouldn't have known what a user interface was, but that's really what he designed and he really took that challenge and broke it down to three principles that I think can be applied in nearly any design problem.</s>
 <s id="26">First one is focus.</s>
 <s id="27">Focus on who you're doing this for.</s>
 <s id="28">The second principle is simplicity.</s>
 <s id="29">What's the shortest way to deliver that need?</s>
 <s id="30">Finally, the last thing is: Thinking in a cross-disciplinary way.</s>
 <s id="31">Who would've thought that an electrical engineer would be the person to hold the key to unlock what was then one of the most complicated systems in the world -- all started by one guy with a pencil and an idea.</s>
</text>
