<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">A mother and her son trek across an endless desert.</s>
 <s id="2">Wearing special skin-tight suits to dissipate heat and recycle moisture, the travelers aren’t worried about dying of thirst.</s>
 <s id="3">Their fears are much greater.</s>
 <s id="4">The pair try to walk without rhythm, letting the vibrations of their footsteps blend into the shifting sands.</s>
 <s id="5">But soon, the sound of the desert is drowned out by a louder hissing.</s>
 <s id="6">As a mound of sand races towards them, the pair’s unnatural gait turns into a sprint.</s>
 <s id="7">The two clamber into a nearby rock face, as a sandworm 400 meters long bursts from the desert floor.</s>
 <s id="8">This is the world of "Dune."</s>
 <s id="9">Written by Frank Herbert and published in 1965, "Dune" takes place in a far-flung future, where humanity rules the stars in a giant feudal empire.</s>
 <s id="10">This medieval motif goes beyond just the government.</s>
 <s id="11">Unlike most interstellar sci-fi, Herbert's humans conquered the stars without any computers.</s>
 <p id="p12">
  <s id="12.1">Following an ancient war with robots, humanity has forbidden the construction of any machine “in the likeness of a human mind.”</s>
  <s id="12.2">But rather than stifling their expansion, this edict forced humans to evolve in startling ways— becoming biological computers, psychic witches, and prescient space pilots.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="13">Members of these super-powered factions are regularly employed by various noble houses, all competing for power and new planets to add to their kingdoms.</s>
 <s id="14">But almost all these superhuman skills rely on the same precious resource: the spice.</s>
 <s id="15">This mystical crop also known as “melange” is essential for all space travel, making it the cornerstone of the galactic economy.</s>
 <s id="16">And it only grows on the desert planet Arrakis, a dangerous and inhospitable world whose native inhabitants have long rebelled against the empire.</s>
 <s id="17">Arrakis, also called Dune, is the setting for Herbert’s novel, which follows Paul of the noble House Atreides.</s>
 <s id="18">The book begins with Paul’s family being assigned control of Dune as part of an elaborate plot by their sworn enemies: the sadistic slave drivers of House Harkonnen.</s>
 <s id="19">The conflict between these houses upends the delicate political balance on Arrakis.</s>
 <s id="20">Soon, Paul is catapulted into the middle of a planetary revolution, where he must prove himself capable of leading— and surviving— on this hostile desert world.</s>
 <s id="21">But Arrakis is not simply an endless sea of sand.</s>
 <s id="22">Herbert was an avid environmentalist, who spent over five years creating Dune’s complex ecosystem.</s>
 <s id="23">The planet is checkered with climate belts and wind tunnels that have shaped its rocky topography.</s>
 <s id="24">Different temperate zones produce varying desert flora.</s>
 <s id="25">And almost every element of Dune’s ecosystem works together to produce the planet’s essential export.</s>
 <s id="26">Herbert’s world building also includes a rich web of philosophy and religion.</s>
 <s id="27">Paul’s mother Jessica, is a member of the Bene Gesserit, an ancient cult of spice-assisted psychics.</s>
 <s id="28">Sometimes called “witches” for their mysterious powers, the Bene Gesserit have operated as a shadow government for millennia in an effort to guide society towards enlightenment.</s>
 <s id="29">Similarly ancient are the Mentats— human computers capable of processing incredible amounts of data.</s>
 <s id="30">While the Mentats are bastions of logic and reason, their results are not mere calculations, but rather, streams of constantly shifting possibilities.</s>
 <s id="31">However, no group is more central to "Dune" than the Fremen.</s>
 <s id="32">Natives of Arrakis, they are the keepers of the planet’s many secrets.</s>
 <s id="33">Paul’s journey takes him deep into the Fremen’s exclusive brotherhood, where he must prove himself trustworthy in a series of increasingly deadly challenges.</s>
 <s id="34">All these factions have deep histories that pervade the text, and Herbert also incorporates that sense of scale into the book’s structure.</s>
 <s id="35">Each chapter begins with a quote from a future history book, recalling elements of the events that are about to unfold.</s>
 <s id="36">The book also contains in-universe appendices that further explore the Empire’s history; alongside a glossary of words like “Gom jabbar” and “Shai-Hulud."</s>
 <s id="37">Dune’s epic story continues to unfold over a six-book saga that spans millennia.</s>
 <s id="38">But every story of Arrakis’ future begins here: as Paul pursues a path that is dangerous, demanding, and always on the verge of being consumed by the oncoming storm.</s>
</text>
