<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Do you remember your first kiss?</s>
 <s id="2">Or that time you burned the roof of your mouth on a hot slice of pizza?</s>
 <s id="3">What about playing tag or duck, duck, goose as a child?</s>
 <s id="4">These are all instances where we're using touch to understand something.</s>
 <s id="5">And it's the basis of haptic design.</s>
 <s id="6">"Haptic" means of or relating to the sense of touch.</s>
 <s id="7">And we've all been using that our entire lives.</s>
 <s id="8">I was working on my computer when my friend, seeing me hunched over typing, walked over behind me.</s>
 <s id="9">She put her left thumb into the left side of my lower back, while reaching her right index finger around to the front of my right shoulder.</s>
 <s id="10">Instinctively, I sat up straight.</s>
 <s id="11">In one quick and gentle gesture, she had communicated how to improve my posture.</s>
 <s id="12">The paper I was working on at that very moment centered around developing new ways to teach movement using technology.</s>
 <s id="13">I wanted to create a suit that could teach a person kung fu.</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) But I had no idea how to communicate movement without an instructor being in the room.</s>
 <s id="15">And in that moment, it became crystal clear: touch.</s>
 <s id="16">If I had vibrating motors where she had placed each of her fingers, paired with motion-capture data of my current and optimal posture, I could simulate the entire experience without an instructor needing to be in the room.</s>
 <s id="17">But there was still one important part of the puzzle that was missing.</s>
 <s id="18">If I want you to raise your wrist two inches off of your lap, using vibration, how do I tell you to do that?</s>
 <s id="19">Do I put a motor at the top of your wrist, so you know to lift up?</s>
 <s id="20">Or do I put one at the bottom of your wrist, so it feels like you're being pushed up?</s>
 <s id="21">There were no readily available answers because there was no commonly agreed-upon haptic language to communicate information with.</s>
 <s id="22">So my cofounders and I set out to create that language.</s>
 <s id="23">And the first device we built was not a kung fu suit.</s>
 <s id="24">(Laughter) But in a way, it was even more impressive because of its simplicity and usefulness.</s>
 <s id="25">We started with the use case of navigation, which is a simplified form of movement.</s>
 <s id="26">We then created Wayband, a wrist-wearable device that could orient a user toward a destination, using vibrating cues.</s>
 <s id="27">We would ask people to spin around and to stop in a way that they felt was the right way to go.</s>
 <s id="28">Informally, we tried this with hundreds of people, and most could figure it out within about 15 seconds.</s>
 <s id="29">It was that intuitive.</s>
 <s id="30">Initially, we were just trying to get people out of their phones and back into the real world.</s>
 <s id="31">But the more we experimented, the more we realized that those who stood to benefit most from our work were people who had little or no sight.</s>
 <s id="32">When we first approached a blind organization, they told us, "Don't build a blind device.</s>
 <s id="33">Build a device that everyone can use but that's optimized for the blind experience."</s>
 <s id="34">We created our company WearWorks with three guiding principles: make cool stuff, create the greatest impact we can in our lifetimes and reimagine an entire world designed for touch.</s>
 <s id="35">And on November 5, 2017, Wayband helped a person who was blind run the first 15 miles of the New York City Marathon without any sighted assistance.</s>
 <s id="36">(Applause) It didn't get him through the entire race due to the heavy rain, but that didn't matter.</s>
 <s id="37">(Laughter) We had proved the point: that it was possible to navigate a complex route using only touch.</s>
 <s id="38">So, why touch?</s>
 <s id="39">The skin has an innate sensitivity akin to the eyes' ability to recognize millions of colors or the ears' ability to recognize complex pitch and tone.</s>
 <s id="40">Yet, as a communications channel, it's been largely relegated to Morse code-like cell phone notifications.</s>
 <s id="41">If you were to suddenly receive a kiss or a punch, your reaction would be instinctive and immediate.</s>
 <s id="42">Meanwhile, your brain would be playing catch-up on the back end to understand the details of what just occurred.</s>
 <s id="43">And compared to instincts, conscious thought is pretty slow.</s>
 <s id="44">But it's a lightning bolt compared to the snail's pace of language acquisition.</s>
 <s id="45">I spent a considerable amount of time learning Spanish, Japanese, German and currently Swedish, with varying degrees of failure.</s>
 <s id="46">(Laughter) But within those failures were kernels of how different languages are organized.</s>
 <s id="47">That gave our team insight into how to use the linguistic order of well-established languages as inspiration for an entirely new haptic language, one based purely on touch.</s>
 <s id="48">It also showed us when using language mechanics wasn't the best way to deliver information.</s>
 <s id="49">In the same way a smile is a smile across every culture, what if there was some underlying mechanism of touch that transcended linguistic and cultural boundaries?</s>
 <s id="50">A universal language, of sorts.</s>
 <s id="51">You see, I could give you buzz-buzz-buzz, buzz-buzz, and you would eventually learn that that particular vibration means "stop."</s>
 <s id="52">But as haptic designers, we challenged ourselves.</s>
 <s id="53">What would it be like to design "stop?"</s>
 <s id="54">Well, based on context, most of us have the experience of being in a vehicle and having that vehicle stop suddenly, along with our body's reaction to it.</s>
 <s id="55">So if I wanted you to stop, I could send you a vibration pattern, sure.</s>
 <s id="56">Or, I could design a haptic experience that just made stopping feel like it was the right thing to do.</s>
 <s id="57">And that takes more than an arbitrary assignment of haptic cues to meanings.</s>
 <s id="58">It takes a deep empathy.</s>
 <s id="59">It also takes the ability to distill human experience into meaningful insights and then into haptic gestures and products.</s>
 <s id="60">Haptic design is going to expand the human ability to sense and respond to our environments, both physical and virtual.</s>
 <s id="61">There's a new frontier: touch.</s>
 <s id="62">And it has the power to change how we all see the world around us.</s>
 <s id="63">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="64">(Applause)</s>
</text>
