<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In the year 1901, a woman called Auguste was taken to a medical asylum in Frankfurt.</s>
 <s id="2">Auguste was delusional and couldn't remember even the most basic details of her life.</s>
 <s id="3">Her doctor was called Alois.</s>
 <s id="4">Alois didn't know how to help Auguste, but he watched over her until, sadly, she passed away in 1906.</s>
 <s id="5">After she died, Alois performed an autopsy and found strange plaques and tangles in Auguste's brain -- the likes of which he'd never seen before.</s>
 <s id="6">Now here's the even more striking thing.</s>
 <s id="7">If Auguste had instead been alive today, we could offer her no more help than Alois was able to 114 years ago.</s>
 <s id="8">Alois was Dr. Alois Alzheimer.</s>
 <s id="9">And Auguste Deter was the first patient to be diagnosed with what we now call Alzheimer's disease.</s>
 <s id="10">Since 1901, medicine has advanced greatly.</s>
 <s id="11">We've discovered antibiotics and vaccines to protect us from infections, many treatments for cancer, antiretrovirals for HIV, statins for heart disease and much more.</s>
 <s id="12">But we've made essentially no progress at all in treating Alzheimer's disease.</s>
 <s id="13">I'm part of a team of scientists who has been working to find a cure for Alzheimer's for over a decade.</s>
 <s id="14">So I think about this all the time.</s>
 <s id="15">Alzheimer's now affects 40 million people worldwide.</s>
 <s id="16">But by 2050, it will affect 150 million people -- which, by the way, will include many of you.</s>
 <s id="17">If you're hoping to live to be 85 or older, your chance of getting Alzheimer's will be almost one in two.</s>
 <s id="18">In other words, odds are you'll spend your golden years either suffering from Alzheimer's or helping to look after a friend or loved one with Alzheimer's.</s>
 <s id="19">Already in the United States alone, Alzheimer's care costs 200 billion dollars every year.</s>
 <s id="20">One out of every five Medicare dollars get spent on Alzheimer's.</s>
 <s id="21">It is today the most expensive disease, and costs are projected to increase fivefold by 2050, as the baby boomer generation ages.</s>
 <s id="22">It may surprise you that, put simply, Alzheimer's is one of the biggest medical and social challenges of our generation.</s>
 <s id="23">But we've done relatively little to address it.</s>
 <s id="24">Today, of the top 10 causes of death worldwide, Alzheimer's is the only one we cannot prevent, cure or even slow down.</s>
 <s id="25">We understand less about the science of Alzheimer's than other diseases because we've invested less time and money into researching it.</s>
 <s id="26">The US government spends 10 times more every year on cancer research than on Alzheimer's despite the fact that Alzheimer's costs us more and causes a similar number of deaths each year as cancer.</s>
 <s id="27">The lack of resources stems from a more fundamental cause: a lack of awareness.</s>
 <s id="28">Because here's what few people know but everyone should: Alzheimer's is a disease, and we can cure it.</s>
 <s id="29">For most of the past 114 years, everyone, including scientists, mistakenly confused Alzheimer's with aging.</s>
 <s id="30">We thought that becoming senile was a normal and inevitable part of getting old.</s>
 <s id="31">But we only have to look at a picture of a healthy aged brain compared to the brain of an Alzheimer's patient to see the real physical damage caused by this disease.</s>
 <s id="32">As well as triggering severe loss of memory and mental abilities, the damage to the brain caused by Alzheimer's significantly reduces life expectancy and is always fatal.</s>
 <s id="33">Remember Dr. Alzheimer found strange plaques and tangles in Auguste's brain a century ago.</s>
 <s id="34">For almost a century, we didn't know much about these.</s>
 <s id="35">Today we know they're made from protein molecules.</s>
 <s id="36">You can imagine a protein molecule as a piece of paper that normally folds into an elaborate piece of origami.</s>
 <s id="37">There are spots on the paper that are sticky.</s>
 <s id="38">And when it folds correctly, these sticky bits end up on the inside.</s>
 <s id="39">But sometimes things go wrong, and some sticky bits are on the outside.</s>
 <s id="40">This causes the protein molecules to stick to each other, forming clumps that eventually become large plaques and tangles.</s>
 <s id="41">That's what we see in the brains of Alzheimer's patients.</s>
 <s id="42">We've spent the past 10 years at the University of Cambridge trying to understand how this malfunction works.</s>
 <s id="43">There are many steps, and identifying which step to try to block is complex -- like defusing a bomb.</s>
 <s id="44">Cutting one wire might do nothing.</s>
 <s id="45">Cutting others might make the bomb explore.</s>
 <s id="46">We have to find the right step to block, and then create a drug that does it.</s>
 <s id="47">Until recently, we for the most part have been cutting wires and hoping for the best.</s>
 <s id="48">But now we've got together a diverse group of people -- medics, biologists, geneticists, chemists, physicists, engineers and mathematicians.</s>
 <s id="49">And together, we've managed to identify a critical step in the process and are now testing a new class of drugs which would specifically block this step and stop the disease.</s>
 <s id="50">Now let me show you some of our latest results.</s>
 <s id="51">No one outside of our lab has seen these yet.</s>
 <s id="52">Let's look at some videos of what happened when we tested these new drugs in worms.</s>
 <s id="53">So these are healthy worms, and you can see they're moving around normally.</s>
 <s id="54">These worms, on the other hand, have protein molecules sticking together inside them -- like humans with Alzheimer's.</s>
 <s id="55">And you can see they're clearly sick.</s>
 <s id="56">But if we give our new drugs to these worms at an early stage, then we see that they're healthy, and they live a normal lifespan.</s>
 <s id="57">This is just an initial positive result, but research like this shows us that Alzheimer's is a disease that we can understand and we can cure.</s>
 <s id="58">After 114 years of waiting, there's finally real hope for what can be achieved in the next 10 or 20 years.</s>
 <s id="59">But to grow that hope, to finally beat Alzheimer's, we need help.</s>
 <s id="60">This isn't about scientists like me -- it's about you.</s>
 <s id="61">We need you to raise awareness that Alzheimer's is a disease and that if we try, we can beat it.</s>
 <s id="62">In the case of other diseases, patients and their families have led the charge for more research and put pressure on governments, the pharmaceutical industry, scientists and regulators.</s>
 <s id="63">That was essential for advancing treatment for HIV in the late 1980s.</s>
 <s id="64">Today, we see that same drive to beat cancer.</s>
 <s id="65">But Alzheimer's patients are often unable to speak up for themselves.</s>
 <s id="66">And their families, the hidden victims, caring for their loved ones night and day, are often too worn out to go out and advocate for change.</s>
 <s id="67">So, it really is down to you.</s>
 <s id="68">Alzheimer's isn't, for the most part, a genetic disease.</s>
 <s id="69">Everyone with a brain is at risk.</s>
 <s id="70">Today, there are 40 million patients like Auguste, who can't create the change they need for themselves.</s>
 <s id="71">Help speak up for them, and help demand a cure.</s>
 <s id="72">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="73">(Applause)</s>
</text>
