<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm very fortunate to be here.</s>
 <s id="2">I feel so fortunate.</s>
 <s id="3">I've been so impressed by the kindness expressed to me.</s>
 <s id="4">I called my wife Leslie, and I said, "You know, there's so many good people trying to do so much good.</s>
 <s id="5">It feels like I've landed in a colony of angels."</s>
 <s id="6">It's a true feeling.</s>
 <s id="7">But let me get to the talk -- I see the clock is running.</s>
 <s id="8">I'm a public school teacher, and I just want to share a story of my superintendent.</s>
 <s id="9">Her name is Pam Moran in Albemarle County, Virginia, the foothills of the Blue Ridge Mountains.</s>
 <s id="10">And she's a very high-tech superintendent.</s>
 <s id="11">She uses smart boards, she blogs, she Tweets, she does Facebook, she does all this sort of high-tech stuff.</s>
 <s id="12">She's a technology leader and instructional leader.</s>
 <s id="13">But in her office, there's this old wooden, weather-worn table, kitchen table -- peeling green paint, it's kind of rickety.</s>
 <s id="14">And I said, "Pam, you're such a modern, cutting-edge person.</s>
 <s id="15">Why is this old table in your office?"</s>
 <s id="16">And she told me, she said, "You know, I grew up in Southwestern Virginia, in the coal mines and the farmlands of rural Virginia, and this table was in my grandfather's kitchen.</s>
 <s id="17">And we'd come in from playing, he'd come in from plowing and working, and we'd sit around that table every night.</s>
 <s id="18">And as I grew up, I heard so much knowledge and so many insights and so much wisdom come out around this table, I began to call it the wisdom table.</s>
 <s id="19">And when he passed on, I took this table with me and brought it to my office, and it reminds me of him.</s>
 <s id="20">It reminds me of what goes on around an empty space sometimes."</s>
 <s id="21">The project I'm going to tell you about is called the World Peace Game, and essentially it is also an empty space.</s>
 <s id="22">And I'd like to think of it as a 21st century wisdom table, really.</s>
 <s id="23">It all started back in 1977.</s>
 <s id="24">I was a young man, and I had been dropping in and out of college.</s>
 <s id="25">And my parents were very patient, but I had been doing intermittent sojourns to India on a mystical quest.</s>
 <s id="26">And I remember the last time I came back from India -- in my long white flowing robes and my big beard and my John Lennon glasses -- and I said to my father, "Dad, I think I've just about found spiritual enlightenment."</s>
 <s id="27">He said, "Well there's one more thing you need to find."</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">I said, "What is that, dad?"</s>
  <s id="28.2">"A job."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">(Laughter) And so they pleaded with me to get a degree in something.</s>
 <s id="30">So I got a degree and it turned out to be education.</s>
 <s id="31">It was an experimental education program.</s>
 <s id="32">It could have been dentistry, but the word "experimental" was in it, and so that's what I had to go for.</s>
 <s id="33">And I went in for a job interview in the Richmond Public Schools in Virginia, the capital city, bought a three-piece suit -- my concession to convention -- kept my long beard and my afro and my platform shoes -- at the time it was the '70s -- and I walked in, and I sat down and had an interview.</s>
 <s id="34">And I guess they were hard up for teachers because the supervisor, her name was Anna Aro, said I had the job teaching gifted children.</s>
 <s id="35">And I was so shocked, so stunned, I got up and said, "Well, thank you, but what do I do?"</s>
 <s id="36">(Laughter) Gifted education hadn't really taken hold too much.</s>
 <s id="37">There weren't really many materials or things to use.</s>
 <s id="38">And I said, "What do I do?"</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">And her answer shocked me.</s>
  <s id="39.2">It stunned me.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">Her answer set the template for the entire career I was to have after that.</s>
 <s id="41">She said, "What do you want to do?"</s>
 <s id="42">And that question cleared the space.</s>
 <s id="43">There was no program directive, no manual to follow, no standards in gifted education in that way.</s>
 <s id="44">And she cleared such a space that I endeavored from then on to clear a space for my students, an empty space, whereby they could create and make meaning out of their own understanding.</s>
 <s id="45">So this happened in 1978, and I was teaching many years later, and a friend of mine introduced me to a young filmmaker.</s>
 <s id="46">His name is Chris Farina.</s>
 <s id="47">Chris Farina is here today at his own cost.</s>
 <s id="48">Chris, could you stand up and let them see you -- a young, visionary filmmaker who's made a film.</s>
 <s id="49">(Applause) This film is called "World Peace and Other 4th Grade Achievements."</s>
 <s id="50">He proposed the film to me -- it's a great title.</s>
 <s id="51">He proposed the film to me, and I said, "Yeah, maybe it'll be on local TV, and we can say hi to our friends."</s>
 <s id="52">But the film has really gone places.</s>
 <s id="53">Now it's still in debt, but Chris has managed, through his own sacrifice, to get this film out.</s>
 <s id="54">So we made a film and it turns out to be more than a story about me, more than a story about one teacher.</s>
 <s id="55">It's a story that's a testament to teaching and teachers.</s>
 <s id="56">And it's a beautiful thing.</s>
 <s id="57">And the strange thing is, when I watch the film -- I have the eerie sensation of seeing it -- I saw myself literally disappear.</s>
 <s id="58">What I saw was my teachers coming through me.</s>
 <s id="59">I saw my geometry teacher in high school, Mr. Rucell's wry smile under his handlebar mustache.</s>
 <s id="60">That's the smile I use -- that's his smile.</s>
 <s id="61">I saw Jan Polo's flashing eyes.</s>
 <s id="62">And they weren't flashing in anger, they were flashing in love, intense love for her students.</s>
 <s id="63">And I have that kind of flash sometimes.</s>
 <s id="64">And I saw Miss Ethel J. Banks who wore pearls and high-heels to elementary school every day.</s>
 <s id="65">And you know, she had that old-school teacher stare.</s>
 <s id="66">You know the one.</s>
 <s id="67">(Laughter) "And I'm not even talking about you behind me, because I've got eyes in the back of my head."</s>
 <s id="68">(Laughter) You know that teacher?</s>
 <s id="69">I didn't use that stare very often, but I do have it in my repertoire.</s>
 <s id="70">And Miss Banks was there as a great mentor for me.</s>
 <s id="71">And then I saw my own parents, my first teachers.</s>
 <s id="72">My father, very inventive, spatial thinker.</s>
 <s id="73">That's my brother Malcolm there on the right.</s>
 <s id="74">And my mother, who taught me in fourth grade in segregated schools in Virginia, who was my inspiration.</s>
 <s id="75">And really, I feel as though, when I see the film -- I have a gesture she does, like this -- I feel like I am a continuation of her gesture.</s>
 <s id="76">I am one of her teaching gestures.</s>
 <s id="77">And the beautiful thing was, I got to teach my daughter in elementary school, Madeline.</s>
 <s id="78">And so that gesture of my mother's continues through many generations.</s>
 <s id="79">It's an amazing feeling to have that lineage.</s>
 <s id="80">And so I'm here standing on the shoulders of many people.</s>
 <s id="81">I'm not here alone.</s>
 <s id="82">There are many people on this stage right now.</s>
 <s id="83">And so this World Peace Game I'd like to tell you about.</s>
 <s id="84">It started out like this: it's just a four-foot by five-foot plywood board in an inner-city urban school, 1978.</s>
 <s id="85">I was creating a lesson for students on Africa.</s>
 <s id="86">We put all the problems of the world there, and I thought, let's let them solve it.</s>
 <s id="87">I didn't want to lecture or have just book reading.</s>
 <s id="88">I wanted to have them be immersed and learn the feeling of learning through their bodies.</s>
 <s id="89">So I thought, well they like to play games.</s>
 <s id="90">I'll make something -- I didn't say interactive; we didn't have that term in 1978 -- but something interactive.</s>
 <s id="91">And so we made the game, and it has since evolved to a four-foot by four-foot by four-foot Plexiglass structure.</s>
 <s id="92">And it has four Plexiglass layers.</s>
 <s id="93">There's an outer space layer with black holes and satellites and research satellites and asteroid mining.</s>
 <s id="94">There's an air and space level with clouds that are big puffs of cotton we push around and territorial air spaces and air forces, a ground and sea level with thousands of game pieces on it -- even an undersea level with submarines and undersea mining.</s>
 <s id="95">There are four countries around the board.</s>
 <s id="96">The kids make up the names of the countries -- some are rich; some are poor.</s>
 <s id="97">They have different assets, commercial and military.</s>
 <s id="98">And each country has a cabinet.</s>
 <s id="99">There's a Prime Minister, Secretary of State, Minister of Defense and a CFO, or Comptroller.</s>
 <s id="100">I choose the Prime Minister based on my relationship with them.</s>
 <s id="101">I offer them the job, they can turn it down, and then they choose their own cabinet.</s>
 <s id="102">There's a World Bank, arms dealers and a United Nations.</s>
 <s id="103">There's also a weather goddess who controls a random stock market and random weather.</s>
 <s id="104">(Laughter) That's not all.</s>
 <s id="105">And then there's a 13-page crisis document with 50 interlocking problems.</s>
 <s id="106">So that, if one thing changes, everything else changes.</s>
 <s id="107">I throw them into this complex matrix, and they trust me because we have a deep, rich relationship together.</s>
 <s id="108">And so with all these crises, we have -- let's see -- ethnic and minority tensions; we have chemical and nuclear spills, nuclear proliferation.</s>
 <s id="109">There's oil spills, environmental disasters, water rights disputes, breakaway republics, famine, endangered species and global warming.</s>
 <s id="110">If Al Gore is here, I'm going to send my fourth-graders from Agnor-Hurt and Venable schools to you because they solved global warming in a week.</s>
 <s id="111">(Laughter) (Applause) And they've done it several times too.</s>
 <s id="112">(Laughter) So I also have in the game a saboteur -- some child -- it's basically a troublemaker -- and I have my troublemaker put to use because they, on the surface, are trying to save the world and their position in the game.</s>
 <s id="113">But they're also trying to undermine everything in the game.</s>
 <s id="114">And they do it secretly through misinformation and ambiguities and irrelevancies, trying to cause everyone to think more deeply.</s>
 <s id="115">The saboteur is there, and we also read from Sun Tzu's "The Art of War."</s>
 <s id="116">Fourth-graders understand it -- nine years old -- and they handle that and use that to understand how to, not follow -- at first they do -- the paths to power and destruction, the path to war.</s>
 <s id="117">They learn to overlook short-sighted reactions and impulsive thinking, to think in a long-term, more consequential way.</s>
 <s id="118">Stewart Brand is here, and one of the ideas for this game came from him with a CoEvolution Quarterly article on a peace force.</s>
 <s id="119">And in the game, sometimes students actually form a peace force.</s>
 <s id="120">I'm just a clock watcher.</s>
 <p id="p121">
  <s id="121.1">I'm just a clarifier.</s>
  <s id="121.2">I'm just a facilitator.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="122">The students run the game.</s>
 <s id="123">I have no chance to make any policy whatsoever once they start playing.</s>
 <s id="124">So I'll just share with you ...</s>
 <s id="125">(Video) Boy: The World Peace Game is serious.</s>
 <s id="126">You're actually getting taught something like how to take care of the world.</s>
 <s id="127">See, Mr. Hunter is doing that because he says his time has messed up a lot, and he's trying to tell us how to fix that problem.</s>
 <s id="128">John Hunter: I offered them a -- (Applause) Actually, I can't tell them anything because I don't know the answer.</s>
 <s id="129">And I admit the truth to them right up front: I don't know.</s>
 <s id="130">And because I don't know, they've got to dig up the answer.</s>
 <s id="131">And so I apologize to them as well.</s>
 <s id="132">I say, "I'm so sorry, boys and girls, but the truth is we have left this world to you in such a sad and terrible shape, and we hope you can fix it for us, and maybe this game will help you learn how to do it."</s>
 <s id="133">It's a sincere apology, and they take it very seriously.</s>
 <s id="134">Now you may be wondering what all this complexity looks like.</s>
 <s id="135">Well when we have the game start, here's what you see.</s>
 <p id="p136">
  <s id="136.1">(Video) JH: All right, we're going into negotiations as of now.</s>
  <s id="136.2">Go.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="137">(Chatter) JH: My question to you is, who's in charge of that classroom?</s>
 <s id="138">It's a serious question: who is really in charge?</s>
 <s id="139">I've learned to cede control of the classroom over to the students over time.</s>
 <s id="140">There's a trust and an understanding and a dedication to an ideal that I simply don't have to do what I thought I had to do as a beginning teacher: control every conversation and response in the classroom.</s>
 <p id="p141">
  <s id="141.1">It's impossible.</s>
  <s id="141.2">Their collective wisdom is much greater than mine, and I admit it to them openly.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="142">So I'll just share with you some stories very quickly of some magical things that have happened.</s>
 <s id="143">In this game we had a little girl, and she was the Defense Minister of the poorest nation.</s>
 <s id="144">And the Defense Minister -- she had the tank corps and Air Force and so forth.</s>
 <s id="145">And she was next door to a very wealthy, oil-rich neighbor.</s>
 <s id="146">Without provocation, suddenly she attacked, against her Prime Minister's orders, the next-door neighbor's oil fields.</s>
 <s id="147">She marched into the oil field reserves, surrounded it, without firing a shot, and secured it and held it.</s>
 <s id="148">And that neighbor was unable to conduct any military operations because their fuel supply was locked up.</s>
 <s id="149">We were all upset with her, "Why are you doing this?</s>
 <p id="p150">
  <s id="150.1">This is the World Peace Game.</s>
  <s id="150.2">What is wrong with you?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="151">(Laughter) This was a little girl and, at nine years old, she held her pieces and said, "I know what I'm doing."</s>
 <s id="152">To her girlfriends she said that.</s>
 <s id="153">That's a breach there.</s>
 <s id="154">And we learned in this, you don't really ever want to cross a nine year-old girl with tanks.</s>
 <s id="155">(Laughter) They are the toughest opponents.</s>
 <s id="156">And we were very upset.</s>
 <p id="p157">
  <s id="157.1">I thought I was failing as a teacher.</s>
  <s id="157.2">Why would she do this?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="158">But come to find out, a few game days later -- and there are turns where we take negotiation from a team -- actually there's a negotiation period with all teams, and each team takes a turn, then we go back in negotiation, around and around, so each turn around is one game day.</s>
 <s id="159">So a few game days later it came to light that we found out this major country was planning a military offensive to dominate the entire world.</s>
 <s id="160">Had they had their fuel supplies, they would have done it.</s>
 <s id="161">She was able to see the vectors and trend lines and intentions long before any of us and understand what was going to happen and made a philosophical decision to attack in a peace game.</s>
 <s id="162">Now she used a small war to avert a larger war, so we stopped and had a very good philosophical discussion about whether that was right, conditional good, or not right.</s>
 <s id="163">That's the kind of thinking that we put them in, the situations.</s>
 <s id="164">I could not have designed that in teaching it.</s>
 <s id="165">It came about spontaneously through their collective wisdom.</s>
 <s id="166">(Applause) Another example, a beautiful thing happened.</s>
 <s id="167">We have a letter in the game.</s>
 <s id="168">If you're a military commander and you wage troops -- the little plastic toys on the board -- and you lose them, I put in a letter.</s>
 <s id="169">You have to write a letter to their parents -- the fictional parents of your fictional troops -- explaining what happened and offering your condolences.</s>
 <s id="170">So you have a little bit more thought before you commit to combat.</s>
 <s id="171">And so we had this situation come up -- last summer actually, at Agnor-Hurt School in Albemarle County -- and one of our military commanders got up to read that letter and one of the other kids said, "Mr. Hunter, let's ask -- there's a parent over there."</s>
 <s id="172">There was a parent visiting that day, just sitting in the back of the room.</s>
 <s id="173">"Let's ask that mom to read the letter.</s>
 <s id="174">It'll be more realer if she reads it."</s>
 <s id="175">So we did, we asked her, and she gamely picked up the letter.</s>
 <p id="p176">
  <s id="176.1">"Sure."</s>
  <s id="176.2">She started reading.</s>
  <s id="176.3">She read one sentence.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="177">She read two sentences.</s>
 <s id="178">By the third sentence, she was in tears.</s>
 <s id="179">I was in tears.</s>
 <s id="180">Everybody understood that when we lose somebody, the winners are not gloating.</s>
 <s id="181">We all lose.</s>
 <s id="182">And it was an amazing occurrence and an amazing understanding.</s>
 <s id="183">I'll show you what my friend David says about this.</s>
 <s id="184">He's been in many battles.</s>
 <s id="185">(Video) David: We've really had enough of people attacking.</s>
 <s id="186">I mean, we've been lucky [most of] the time.</s>
 <s id="187">But now I'm feeling really weird because I'm living what Sun Tzu said one week.</s>
 <s id="188">One week he said, "Those who go into battle and win will want to go back, and those who lose in battle will want to go back and win."</s>
 <s id="189">And so I've been winning battles, so I'm going into battles, more battles.</s>
 <s id="190">And I think it's sort of weird to be living what Sun Tzu said.</s>
 <s id="191">JH: I get chills every time I see that.</s>
 <s id="192">That's the kind of engagement you want to have happen.</s>
 <s id="193">And I can't design that, I can't plan that, and I can't even test that.</s>
 <s id="194">But it's self-evident assessment.</s>
 <s id="195">We know that's an authentic assessment of learning.</s>
 <s id="196">We have a lot of data, but I think sometimes we go beyond data with the real truth of what's going on.</s>
 <s id="197">So I'll just share a third story.</s>
 <s id="198">This is about my friend Brennan.</s>
 <s id="199">We had played the game one session after school for many weeks, about seven weeks, and we had essentially solved all 50 of the interlocking crises.</s>
 <s id="200">The way the game is won is all 50 problems have to be solved and every country's asset value has to be increased above its starting point.</s>
 <p id="p201">
  <s id="201.1">Some are poor, some are wealthy.</s>
  <s id="201.2">There are billions.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="202">The World Bank president was a third-grader one time.</s>
 <p id="p203">
  <s id="203.1">He says, "How many zeros in a trillion?</s>
  <s id="203.2">I've got to calculate that right away."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="204">But he was setting fiscal policy in that game for high school players who were playing with him.</s>
 <s id="205">So the team that was the poorest had gotten even poorer.</s>
 <s id="206">There was no way they could win.</s>
 <s id="207">And we were approaching four o'clock, our cut-off time -- there was about a minute left -- and despair just settled over the room.</s>
 <s id="208">I thought, I'm failing as a teacher.</s>
 <s id="209">I should have gotten it so they could have won.</s>
 <s id="210">They shouldn't be failing like this.</s>
 <s id="211">I've failed them.</s>
 <s id="212">And I was just feeling so sad and dejected.</s>
 <s id="213">And suddenly, Brennan walked over to my chair and he grabbed the bell, the bell I ring to signal a change or a reconvening of cabinets, and he ran back to his seat, rang the bell.</s>
 <s id="214">Everybody ran to his chair: there was screaming; there was yelling, waving of their dossiers.</s>
 <s id="215">They get these dossiers full of secret documents.</s>
 <s id="216">They were gesticulating; they were running around.</s>
 <p id="p217">
  <s id="217.1">I didn't know what they were doing.</s>
  <s id="217.2">I'd lost control of my classroom.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="218">Principal walks in, I'm out of a job.</s>
 <s id="219">The parents were looking in the window.</s>
 <p id="p220">
  <s id="220.1">And Brennan runs back to his seat.</s>
  <s id="220.2">Everybody runs back to their seat.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p221">
  <s id="221.1">He rings the bell again.</s>
  <s id="221.2">He says, "We have" -- and there's 12 seconds left on the clock -- "we have, all nations, pooled all our funds together.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="222">And we've got 600 billion dollars.</s>
 <s id="223">We're going to offer it as a donation to this poor country.</s>
 <s id="224">And if they accept it, it'll raise their asset value and we can win the game.</s>
 <s id="225">Will you accept it?"</s>
 <s id="226">And there are three seconds left on the clock.</s>
 <s id="227">Everybody looks at this prime minister of that country, and he says, "Yes."</s>
 <s id="228">And the game is won.</s>
 <s id="229">Spontaneous compassion that could not be planned for, that was unexpected and unpredictable.</s>
 <s id="230">Every game we play is different.</s>
 <s id="231">Some games are more about social issues, some are more about economic issues.</s>
 <s id="232">Some games are more about warfare.</s>
 <s id="233">But I don't try to deny them that reality of being human.</s>
 <s id="234">I allow them to go there and, through their own experience, learn, in a bloodless way, how not to do what they consider to be the wrong thing.</s>
 <s id="235">And they find out what is right their own way, their own selves.</s>
 <s id="236">And so in this game, I've learned so much from it, but I would say that if only they could pick up a critical thinking tool or creative thinking tool from this game and leverage something good for the world, they may save us all.</s>
 <s id="237">If only.</s>
 <p id="p238">
  <s id="238.1">And on behalf of all of my teachers on whose shoulders I'm standing, thank you.</s>
  <s id="238.2">Thank you.</s>
  <s id="238.3">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="239">(Applause)</s>
</text>
