<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Light, bright, and cheerful.</s>
 <s id="2">It's some of the most familiar of all early 18th century music.</s>
 <s id="3">It's been featured in uncounted films and television commercials, but what is it and why does it sound that way?</s>
 <s id="4">This is the opening of "Spring" from "The Four Seasons," by Italian composer Antonio Vivaldi.</s>
 <s id="5">"The Four Seasons" are famous in part because they are a delight to the ear.</s>
 <s id="6">However, even more notable is the fact that they have stories to tell.</s>
 <s id="7">At the time of their publication in Amsterdam in 1725, they were accompanied by poems describing exactly what feature of that season Vivaldi intended to capture in musical terms.</s>
 <s id="8">In providing specific plot content for instrumental music, Vivaldi was generations ahead of his time.</s>
 <s id="9">If one were to read the poems simultaneously to hearing the music, one would find the poetic scenes synchronizing nicely with the musical imagery.</s>
 <s id="10">We are told that the birds welcome spring with happy song, and here they are doing exactly that.</s>
 <s id="11">Soon, however, a thunderstorm breaks out.</s>
 <s id="12">Not only is there musical thunder and lightning, there are also more birds, wet, frightened, and unhappy.</s>
 <s id="13">In "Summer," the turtle dove sings her name "tortorella" in Italian, before a hail storm flattens the fields.</s>
 <s id="14">"Autumn" brings eager hunters dashing out in pursuit of their prey.</s>
 <s id="15">The "Winter" concerto begins with teeth chattering in the cold before one takes refuge by a crackling fire.</s>
 <s id="16">Then it's back out into the storm where there'll be slips and falls on the ice.</s>
 <s id="17">In these first weeks of winter, the old year is coming to a close, and so does Vivaldi's musical exploration of the seasons.</s>
 <s id="18">Not until the early 19th century would such expressive instrumental program music, as it was known, become popular.</s>
 <s id="19">By then, larger, more varied ensembles were the rule with woodwinds, brass, and percussion to help tell the tale.</s>
 <s id="20">But Vivaldi pulled it off with just one violin, strings, and a harpsichord.</s>
 <s id="21">Unlike his contemporary Bach, Vivaldi wasn't much interested in complicated fugues.</s>
 <s id="22">He preferred to offer readily accessible entertainment to his listeners with melodies that pop back up later in a piece to remind us of where we've been.</s>
 <s id="23">So the first movement of the "Spring" concerto begins with a theme for spring and ends with it, too, slightly varied from when it was last heard.</s>
 <s id="24">It was an inspired way to attract listeners, and Vivaldi, considered one of the most electrifying violinists of the early 18th century, understood the value of attracting audiences.</s>
 <s id="25">Such concerts might feature himself as the star violinist.</s>
 <s id="26">Others presented the young musicians of the Pietà, a Venetian girls' school where Vivaldi was Director of Music.</s>
 <s id="27">Most of the students were orphans.</s>
 <s id="28">Music training was intended not only as social skills suitable for young ladies but also as potential careers for those who might fail to make good marriages.</s>
 <s id="29">Even in the composer's own time, Vivaldi's music served as diversion for all, not just for the wealthy aristocrats.</s>
 <s id="30">300 years later, it's an approach that still works, and Vivaldi's music still sounds like trotting horses on the move.</s>
</text>
