<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">At some point between the 1st and 5th century CE, the Hindu sage Patañjali began to codify the ancient, meditative traditions practiced throughout India.</s>
 <s id="2">He recorded techniques nearly as old as Indian civilization itself in 196 manuals called the Yoga Sutras.</s>
 <s id="3">These texts defined yoga as the ‘yoking’ or restraining of the mind from focusing on external objects in efforts to reach a state of pure consciousness.</s>
 <s id="4">Over time, yoga came to incorporate physical elements from gymnastics and wrestling.</s>
 <s id="5">Today, there are a multitude of approaches to modern yoga— though most still maintain the three core elements of Patañjali’s practice: physical postures, breathing exercises, and spiritual contemplation.</s>
 <s id="6">This blend of physical and mental exercise is widely believed to have a unique set of health advantages.</s>
 <s id="7">Such as improving strength and flexibility, boosting heart and lung function, and enhancing psychological well-being.</s>
 <s id="8">But what have contemporary studies shown regarding the benefits of this ancient tradition?</s>
 <s id="9">Despite attempts by many researchers, it's tough to make specific claims about yoga's advantages.</s>
 <s id="10">Its unique combination of activities makes it difficult to determine which component is producing a specific health benefit.</s>
 <s id="11">Additionally, yoga studies are often made up of small sample sizes that lack diversity, and the heavy reliance on self-reporting makes results subjective.</s>
 <s id="12">However, there are some health benefits that have more robust scientific support than others.</s>
 <s id="13">Let’s start with flexibility and strength.</s>
 <s id="14">Twisting your body into yoga’s physical postures stretches multiple muscle groups.</s>
 <s id="15">In the short term, stretching can change the water content of these muscles, ligaments, and tendons to make them more elastic.</s>
 <s id="16">Over time, regular stretching stimulates stem cells which then differentiate into new muscle tissue and other cells that generate elastic collagen.</s>
 <s id="17">Frequent stretching also reduces the body’s natural reflex to constrict muscles, improving your pain tolerance for feats of flexibility.</s>
 <s id="18">Researchers haven’t found that any one form of yoga improves flexibility more than another, so the impact of specific postures is unclear.</s>
 <s id="19">But like other low-impact exercises, yoga reliably improves fitness and flexibility in healthy populations.</s>
 <s id="20">The practice has also been shown to be a potentially powerful therapeutic tool.</s>
 <s id="21">In studies involving patients with a variety of musculo-skeletal disorders, yoga was more helpful at reducing pain and improving mobility than other forms of low-impact exercise.</s>
 <s id="22">Adding yoga to an existing exercise routine can improve strength and flexibility for hard to treat conditions like chronic lower back pain, rheumatoid arthritis, and osteoporosis.</s>
 <s id="23">Yoga’s mix of physical exercise and regimented breathing has proven similarly therapeutic for lung health.</s>
 <s id="24">Lung diseases like chronic bronchitis, emphysema, and asthma shrink the passageways that carry oxygen, while weakening the membrane that brings oxygen into the blood.</s>
 <s id="25">But breathing exercises like those found in yoga relax the muscles constricting those passageways and improve oxygen diffusion.</s>
 <s id="26">Increasing the blood’s oxygen content is especially helpful for those with weak heart muscles who have difficulty pumping enough oxygen throughout the body.</s>
 <s id="27">And for those with healthy hearts, this practice can lower blood pressure and reduce risk factors for cardiovascular disease.</s>
 <s id="28">Yoga’s most widely celebrated benefit may be the most difficult to prove: its psychological effects.</s>
 <s id="29">Despite the longstanding association between yoga and psychological wellbeing, there’s little conclusive evidence on how the practice affects mental health.</s>
 <s id="30">One of the biggest claims is that yoga improves symptoms of depression and anxiety disorders.</s>
 <s id="31">Since diagnosis of these conditions varies widely as do their origin and severity, it’s difficult to quantify yoga’s impact.</s>
 <s id="32">However, there is evidence to suggest that yoga can help reduce the symptoms of stress, as well as meditation or relaxation.</s>
 <s id="33">Research on the effects of yoga is still evolving.</s>
 <s id="34">In the future, we’ll need larger studies, incorporating diverse participants, which can measure yoga’s impact on heart attacks, cancer rates, cognitive function and more.</s>
 <s id="35">But for now, yoga can continue its ancient tradition as a way to exercise, reflect, and relax.</s>
</text>
