<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Here are two reasons companies fail: they only do more of the same, or they only do what's new.</s>
 <s id="2">To me the real, real solution to quality growth is figuring out the balance between two activities: exploration and exploitation.</s>
 <s id="3">Both are necessary, but it can be too much of a good thing.</s>
 <s id="4">Consider Facit.</s>
 <s id="5">I'm actually old enough to remember them.</s>
 <s id="6">Facit was a fantastic company.</s>
 <s id="7">They were born deep in the Swedish forest, and they made the best mechanical calculators in the world.</s>
 <s id="8">Everybody used them.</s>
 <s id="9">And what did Facit do when the electronic calculator came along?</s>
 <s id="10">They continued doing exactly the same.</s>
 <s id="11">In six months, they went from maximum revenue ...</s>
 <s id="12">and they were gone.</s>
 <s id="13">Gone.</s>
 <s id="14">To me, the irony about the Facit story is hearing about the Facit engineers, who had bought cheap, small electronic calculators in Japan that they used to double-check their calculators.</s>
 <s id="15">(Laughter) Facit did too much exploitation.</s>
 <s id="16">But exploration can go wild, too.</s>
 <s id="17">A few years back, I worked closely alongside a European biotech company.</s>
 <s id="18">Let's call them OncoSearch.</s>
 <s id="19">The company was brilliant.</s>
 <s id="20">They had applications that promised to diagnose, even cure, certain forms of blood cancer.</s>
 <s id="21">Every day was about creating something new.</s>
 <s id="22">They were extremely innovative, and the mantra was, "When we only get it right," or even, "We want it perfect."</s>
 <s id="23">The sad thing is, before they became perfect -- even good enough -- they became obsolete.</s>
 <s id="24">OncoSearch did too much exploration.</s>
 <s id="25">I first heard about exploration and exploitation about 15 years ago, when I worked as a visiting scholar at Stanford University.</s>
 <s id="26">The founder of the idea is Jim March.</s>
 <s id="27">And to me the power of the idea is its practicality.</s>
 <s id="28">Exploration.</s>
 <s id="29">Exploration is about coming up with what's new.</s>
 <s id="30">It's about search, it's about discovery, it's about new products, it's about new innovations.</s>
 <s id="31">It's about changing our frontiers.</s>
 <s id="32">Our heroes are people who have done exploration: Madame Curie, Picasso, Neil Armstrong, Sir Edmund Hillary, etc.</s>
 <s id="33">I come from Norway; all our heroes are explorers, and they deserve to be.</s>
 <s id="34">We all know that exploration is risky.</s>
 <s id="35">We don't know the answers, we don't know if we're going to find them, and we know that the risks are high.</s>
 <s id="36">Exploitation is the opposite.</s>
 <s id="37">Exploitation is taking the knowledge we have and making good, better.</s>
 <s id="38">Exploitation is about making our trains run on time.</s>
 <s id="39">It's about making good products faster and cheaper.</s>
 <s id="40">Exploitation is not risky -- in the short term.</s>
 <s id="41">But if we only exploit, it's very risky in the long term.</s>
 <s id="42">And I think we all have memories of the famous pop groups who keep singing the same songs again and again, until they become obsolete or even pathetic.</s>
 <s id="43">That's the risk of exploitation.</s>
 <s id="44">So if we take a long-term perspective, we explore.</s>
 <s id="45">If we take a short-term perspective, we exploit.</s>
 <s id="46">Small children, they explore all day.</s>
 <s id="47">All day it's about exploration.</s>
 <s id="48">As we grow older, we explore less because we have more knowledge to exploit on.</s>
 <s id="49">The same goes for companies.</s>
 <s id="50">Companies become, by nature, less innovative as they become more competent.</s>
 <s id="51">And this is, of course, a big worry to CEOs.</s>
 <s id="52">And I hear very often questions phrased in different ways.</s>
 <s id="53">For example, "How can I both effectively run and reinvent my company?"</s>
 <s id="54">Or, "How can I make sure that our company changes before we become obsolete or are hit by a crisis?"</s>
 <s id="55">So, doing one well is difficult.</s>
 <s id="56">Doing both well as the same time is art -- pushing both exploration and exploitation.</s>
 <s id="57">So one thing we've found is only about two percent of companies are able to effectively explore and exploit at the same time, in parallel.</s>
 <s id="58">But when they do, the payoffs are huge.</s>
 <s id="59">So we have lots of great examples.</s>
 <s id="60">We have Nestlé creating Nespresso, we have Lego going into animated films, Toyota creating the hybrids, Unilever pushing into sustainability -- there are lots of examples, and the benefits are huge.</s>
 <s id="61">Why is balancing so difficult?</s>
 <s id="62">I think it's difficult because there are so many traps that keep us where we are.</s>
 <s id="63">So I'll talk about two, but there are many.</s>
 <s id="64">So let's talk about the perpetual search trap.</s>
 <s id="65">We discover something, but we don't have the patience or the persistence to get at it and make it work.</s>
 <s id="66">So instead of staying with it, we create something new.</s>
 <s id="67">But the same goes for that, then we're in the vicious circle of actually coming up with ideas but being frustrated.</s>
 <s id="68">OncoSearch was a good example.</s>
 <s id="69">A famous example is, of course, Xerox.</s>
 <s id="70">But we don't only see this in companies.</s>
 <s id="71">We see this in the public sector as well.</s>
 <s id="72">We all know that any kind of effective reform of education, research, health care, even defense, takes 10, 15, maybe 20 years to work.</s>
 <s id="73">But still, we change much more often.</s>
 <s id="74">We really don't give them the chance.</s>
 <s id="75">Another trap is the success trap.</s>
 <s id="76">Facit fell into the success trap.</s>
 <s id="77">They literally held the future in their hands, but they couldn't see it.</s>
 <s id="78">They were simply so good at making what they loved doing, that they wouldn't change.</s>
 <s id="79">We are like that, too.</s>
 <s id="80">When we know something well, it's difficult to change.</s>
 <s id="81">Bill Gates has said: "Success is a lousy teacher.</s>
 <s id="82">It seduces us into thinking we cannot fail."</s>
 <s id="83">That's the challenge with success.</s>
 <s id="84">So I think there are some lessons, and I think they apply to us.</s>
 <s id="85">And they apply to our companies.</s>
 <s id="86">The first lesson is: get ahead of the crisis.</s>
 <s id="87">And any company that's able to innovate is actually able to also buy an insurance in the future.</s>
 <s id="88">Netflix -- they could so easily have been content with earlier generations of distribution, but they always -- and I think they will always -- keep pushing for the next battle.</s>
 <s id="89">I see other companies that say, "I'll win the next innovation cycle, whatever it takes."</s>
 <s id="90">Second one: think in multiple time scales.</s>
 <s id="91">I'll share a chart with you, and I think it's a wonderful one.</s>
 <s id="92">Any company we look at, taking a one-year perspective and looking at the valuation of the company, innovation typically accounts for only about 30 percent.</s>
 <s id="93">So when we think one year, innovation isn't really that important.</s>
 <s id="94">Move ahead, take a 10-year perspective on the same company -- suddenly, innovation and ability to renew account for 70 percent.</s>
 <s id="95">But companies can't choose.</s>
 <s id="96">They need to fund the journey and lead the long term.</s>
 <s id="97">Third: invite talent.</s>
 <s id="98">I don't think it's possible for any of us to be able to balance exploration and exploitation by ourselves.</s>
 <s id="99">I think it's a team sport.</s>
 <s id="100">I think we need to allow challenging.</s>
 <s id="101">I think the mark of a great company is being open to be challenged, and the mark of a good corporate board is to constructively challenge.</s>
 <s id="102">I think that's also what good parenting is about.</s>
 <s id="103">Last one: be skeptical of success.</s>
 <s id="104">Maybe it's useful to think back at the old triumph marches in Rome, when the generals, after a big victory, were given their celebration.</s>
 <s id="105">Riding into Rome on the carriage, they always had a companion whispering in their ear, "Remember, you're only human."</s>
 <s id="106">So I hope I made the point: balancing exploration and exploitation has a huge payoff.</s>
 <s id="107">But it's difficult, and we need to be conscious.</s>
 <s id="108">I want to just point out two questions that I think are useful.</s>
 <s id="109">First question is, looking at your own company: In which areas do you see that the company is at the risk of falling into success traps, of just going on autopilot?</s>
 <s id="110">And what can you do to challenge?</s>
 <s id="111">Second question is: When did I explore something new last, and what kind of effect did it have on me?</s>
 <s id="112">Is that something I should do more of?</s>
 <s id="113">In my case, yes.</s>
 <s id="114">So let me leave you with this.</s>
 <s id="115">Whether you're an explorer by nature or whether you tend to exploit what you already know, don't forget: the beauty is in the balance.</s>
 <s id="116">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="117">(Applause)</s>
</text>
