<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I met 273 start-up founders last year.</s>
 <s id="2">And each one was looking for money.</s>
 <s id="3">As a tech investor, my goal was to sort through everyone that I met and make a quick determination about which ones had the potential to make something really big.</s>
 <s id="4">But what makes a great founder?</s>
 <s id="5">This is a question I ask myself daily.</s>
 <s id="6">Some venture capitalists place bets based on a founder's previous background.</s>
 <s id="7">Did they go to an Ivy League school?</s>
 <s id="8">Have they worked at a blue-chip company?</s>
 <s id="9">Have they built out a big vision before?</s>
 <s id="10">Effectively, how smart is this person?</s>
 <s id="11">Other VCs asses a founder's emotional quotient, or EQ.</s>
 <s id="12">How well will this person build teams and build rapport across customers and clients?</s>
 <s id="13">I have a different methodology to assess start-up founders, though, and it's not complicated.</s>
 <s id="14">I look for signs of one specific trait.</s>
 <s id="15">Not IQ, not EQ.</s>
 <s id="16">It's adaptability: how well a person reacts to the inevitability of change, and lots of it.</s>
 <s id="17">That's the single most important determinant for me.</s>
 <s id="18">I subscribe to the belief that adaptability itself is a form of intelligence, and our adaptability quotient, or AQ, is something that can be measured, tested and improved.</s>
 <s id="19">AQ isn't just useful for start-up founders, however.</s>
 <s id="20">I think it's increasingly important for all of us.</s>
 <s id="21">Because the world is speeding up.</s>
 <s id="22">We know that the rate of technological change is accelerating, which is forcing our brains to react.</s>
 <s id="23">Whether you're navigating changing job conditions brought on by automation, shifting geopolitics in a more globalized world, or simply changing family dynamics and personal relationships.</s>
 <s id="24">Each of us, as individuals, groups, corporations and even governments are being forced to grapple with more change than ever before in human history.</s>
 <s id="25">So, how do we assess our adaptability?</s>
 <s id="26">I use three tricks when meeting with founders.</s>
 <s id="27">Here's the first.</s>
 <s id="28">Think back to your most recent job interview.</s>
 <s id="29">What kind of questions were you asked?</s>
 <s id="30">Probably some variation of, "Tell me about a time when," right?</s>
 <s id="31">Instead, to interview for adaptability, I like to ask "what if" questions.</s>
 <s id="32">What if your main revenue stream were to dry up overnight?</s>
 <s id="33">What if a heat wave prevented every single customer from being able to visit your store?</s>
 <s id="34">Asking "what if," instead of asking about the past, forces the brain to simulate.</s>
 <s id="35">To picture multiple possible versions of the future.</s>
 <s id="36">The strength of that vision, as well as how many distinct scenarios someone can conjure, tells me a lot.</s>
 <s id="37">Practicing simulations is a sort of safe testing ground for improving adaptability.</s>
 <s id="38">Instead of testing how you take in and retain information, like an IQ test might, it tests how you manipulate information, given a constraint, in order to achieve a specific goal.</s>
 <s id="39">The second trick that I use to assess adaptability in founders is to look for signs of unlearning.</s>
 <s id="40">Active unlearners seek to challenge what they presume to already know, and instead, override that data with new information.</s>
 <s id="41">Kind of like a computer running a disk cleanup.</s>
 <s id="42">Take the example of Destin Sandlin, who programed his bicycle to turn left when he steered it right and vice versa.</s>
 <s id="43">He called this his Backwards Brain Bike, and it took him nearly eight months just to learn how to ride it kind of, sort of normally.</s>
 <s id="44">The fact that Destin was able to unlearn his regular bike in favor of a new one, though, signals something awesome about our adaptability.</s>
 <s id="45">It's not fixed.</s>
 <s id="46">Instead, each of us has the capacity to improve it, through dedication and hard work.</s>
 <s id="47">On the last page of Gandhi's autobiography, he wrote, "I must reduce myself to zero."</s>
 <s id="48">At many points in his very full life, he was still seeking to return to a beginner's mindset, to zero.</s>
 <s id="49">To unlearn.</s>
 <s id="50">In this way, I think it's pretty safe to say Gandhi had a high AQ score.</s>
 <s id="51">(Laughter) The third and final trick that I use to assess a founder's adaptability is to look for people who infuse exploration into their life and their business.</s>
 <s id="52">There's a sort of natural tension between exploration and exploitation.</s>
 <s id="53">And collectively, all of us tend to overvalue exploitation.</s>
 <s id="54">Here's what I mean.</s>
 <s id="55">In the year 2000, a man finagled his way into a meeting with John Antioco, the CEO of Blockbuster, and proposed a partnership to manage Blockbuster's fledgling online business.</s>
 <s id="56">The CEO John laughed him out of the room, saying, "I have millions of existing customers and thousands of successful retail stores.</s>
 <s id="57">I really need to focus on the money."</s>
 <s id="58">The other man in the meeting, however, turned out to be Reed Hastings, the CEO of Netflix.</s>
 <s id="59">In 2018, Netflix brought in 15.8 billion dollars, while Blockbuster filed for bankruptcy in 2010, directly 10 years after that meeting.</s>
 <s id="60">The Blockbuster CEO was too focused on exploiting his already successful business model, so much so that he couldn't see around the next corner.</s>
 <s id="61">In that way, his previous success became the enemy of his adaptability potential.</s>
 <s id="62">For the founders that I work with, I frame exploration as a state of constant seeking.</s>
 <s id="63">To never fall too far in love with your wins but rather continue to proactively seek out what might kill you next.</s>
 <s id="64">When I first started exploring adaptability, the thing I found most exciting is that we can improve it.</s>
 <s id="65">Each of us has the capacity to become more adaptable.</s>
 <s id="66">But think of it like a muscle: it's got to be exercised.</s>
 <s id="67">And don't get discouraged if it takes a while.</s>
 <s id="68">Remember Destin Sandlin?</s>
 <s id="69">It took him eight months just to learn how to ride a bike.</s>
 <s id="70">Over time, using the tricks that I use on founders -- asking "what if" questions, actively unlearning and prioritizing exploration over exploitation can put you in the driver's seat -- so that the next time something big changes, you're already prepared.</s>
 <s id="71">We're entering a future where IQ and EQ both matter way less than how fast you're able to adapt.</s>
 <s id="72">So I hope that these tools help you to raise your own AQ.</s>
 <s id="73">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="74">(Applause)</s>
</text>
