<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The largest organ in your body isn't your liver or your brain.</s>
 <s id="2">It's your skin, with a surface area of about 20 square feet in adults.</s>
 <s id="3">Though different areas of the skin have different characteristics, much of this surface performs similar functions, such as sweating, feeling heat and cold, and growing hair.</s>
 <s id="4">But after a deep cut or wound, the newly healed skin will look different from the surrounding area, and may not fully regain all its abilities for a while, or at all.</s>
 <s id="5">To understand why this happens, we need to look at the structure of the human skin.</s>
 <s id="6">The top layer, called the epidermis, consists mostly of hardened cells, called keratinocytes, and provides protection.</s>
 <s id="7">Since its outer layer is constantly being shed and renewed, it's pretty easy to repair.</s>
 <s id="8">But sometimes a wound penetrates into the dermis, which contains blood vessels and the various glands and nerve endings that enable the skin's many functions.</s>
 <s id="9">And when that happens, it triggers the four overlapping stages of the regenerative process.</s>
 <s id="10">The first stage, hemostasis, is the skin's response to two immediate threats: that you're now losing blood and that the physical barrier of the epidermis has been compromised.</s>
 <s id="11">As the blood vessels tighten to minimize the bleeding, in a process known as vasoconstriction, both threats are averted by forming a blood clot.</s>
 <s id="12">A special protein known as fibrin forms cross-links on the top of the skin, preventing blood from flowing out and bacteria or pathogens from getting in.</s>
 <s id="13">After about three hours of this, the skin begins to turn red, signaling the next stage, inflammation.</s>
 <s id="14">With bleeding under control and the barrier secured, the body sends special cells to fight any pathogens that may have gotten through.</s>
 <s id="15">Among the most important of these are white blood cells, known as macrophages, which devour bacteria and damage tissue through a process known as phagocytosis, in addition to producing growth factors to spur healing.</s>
 <s id="16">And because these tiny soldiers need to travel through the blood to get to the wound site, the previously constricted blood vessels now expand in a process called vasodilation.</s>
 <s id="17">About two to three days after the wound, the proliferative stage occurs, when fibroblast cells begin to enter the wound.</s>
 <s id="18">In the process of collagen deposition, they produce a fibrous protein called collagen in the wound site, forming connective skin tissue to replace the fibrin from before.</s>
 <s id="19">As epidermal cells divide to reform the outer layer of skin, the dermis contracts to close the wound.</s>
 <s id="20">Finally, in the fourth stage of remodeling, the wound matures as the newly deposited collagen is rearranged and converted into specific types.</s>
 <s id="21">Through this process, which can take over a year, the tensile strength of the new skin is improved, and blood vessels and other connections are strengthened.</s>
 <s id="22">With time, the new tissue can reach from 50-80% of some of its original healthy function, depending on the severity of the initial wound and on the function itself.</s>
 <s id="23">But because the skin does not fully recover, scarring continues to be a major clinical issue for doctors around the world.</s>
 <s id="24">And even though researchers have made significant strides in understanding the healing process, many fundamental mysteries remain unresolved.</s>
 <s id="25">For instance, do fibroblast cells arrive from the blood vessels or from skin tissue adjacent to the wound?</s>
 <s id="26">And why do some other mammals, such as deer, heal their wounds much more efficiently and completely than humans?</s>
 <s id="27">By finding the answers to these questions and others, we may one day be able to heal ourselves so well that scars will be just a memory.</s>
</text>
