<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I was not one of those kids that knew exactly what they wanted to do when they were growing up.</s>
 <s id="2">In the last 15 years of my career, I've been an English teacher, attorney, video game creator and now, a toilet paper salesman, selling millions of rolls of toilet paper a year.</s>
 <s id="3">[The Way We Work] Life is about finding the intersection of what you really, really love with what you're really, really good at.</s>
 <s id="4">As simple as it sounds, it's really not that easy to find.</s>
 <s id="5">After a brief stint as an English teacher, I went to law school and ended up becoming an attorney at a big law firm here in New York City.</s>
 <s id="6">Like most Americans, for the next two, three years, I was holding on to my job for dear life, working really late hours at a job that I thought maybe I was good at but certainly not one that I really loved.</s>
 <s id="7">I then came upon the epiphany that it takes years if not tens of thousands of hours to get really good at something.</s>
 <s id="8">I really didn't have a lot of time to waste.</s>
 <s id="9">This talk isn't for those looking to quit their job because they don't like their boss or they had a long day at work.</s>
 <s id="10">This is for those that are ready to make the completely scary leap into a brand-new career.</s>
 <s id="11">So as you think about making a career change, here are a few tips I hope you consider and a few things I've picked up along the way.</s>
 <s id="12">First, there's three things to think about before you're ready to move on.</s>
 <s id="13">Number one: professional life is about learning.</s>
 <s id="14">If you're not even interested in learning anymore, that's a huge red flag that there might not be a future for you in that industry.</s>
 <s id="15">Number two: career changes are often gut-driven.</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">If you constantly have sleepless nights where you're wide awake staring at the ceiling thinking, "Oh, man.</s>
  <s id="16.2">I can't live with myself if I never try to make this change or if I don't even actually investigate it," then trust your gut.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="17">It might be time for that career change.</s>
 <s id="18">On the flip side, one reason to not move on is short-term pain.</s>
 <s id="19">If you don't like your boss or people at the office are grating on you, that's actually not a good reason to absolutely change your career, because when you do change a career, you generally have to start from the bottom, and you'll probably feel a lot of short-term pain, whether it's through a lack of salary or lack of a title.</s>
 <s id="20">Pain at any job is inevitable.</s>
 <s id="21">So now you're convinced that it's time to change your career.</s>
 <s id="22">Then there's three things to do immediately.</s>
 <s id="23">First: network, network, network.</s>
 <s id="24">No one ever builds a career without a good mentor or a good support network.</s>
 <s id="25">What I mean by networking is getting all the great advice that you can possibly get.</s>
 <s id="26">Technology has made it so simple to reach out to new people to say, "Hey, I'm thinking about making a career change.</s>
 <s id="27">Do you have just five minutes to chat with me?"</s>
 <s id="28">That passion and that hunger and that ability to be a sponge really attracts awesome mentors and people willing to give you their time to give you some good advice.</s>
 <s id="29">So go out there and meet new people.</s>
 <s id="30">The second thing you need to do immediately is shore up your finances.</s>
 <s id="31">The reality is, when you change your career, you'll either start with a job with a lower title or lower pay or maybe even no pay, especially if you're starting your own business.</s>
 <s id="32">So going out there and making sure your finances are in order to make the transition less painful is really, really important.</s>
 <s id="33">For me personally, as I made the transition from being an attorney over to a video game creator, I wanted to have at least six to 12 months of personal runway in the bank.</s>
 <s id="34">Six to 12 months might not be the right number for you, but be honest with yourself on what that number should be.</s>
 <s id="35">Number three, if you're not ready to make the full jump right at this moment, then get your side hustle on.</s>
 <s id="36">Side hustles could be anything from volunteering with an organization that's in the new industry you want to go into, could be starting your business part-time on the weekends.</s>
 <s id="37">It's a free way to get a taste to see if you really love something.</s>
 <s id="38">So you're ready to make the move or maybe you already made the move.</s>
 <s id="39">Here are three things you should think about doing, right now.</s>
 <s id="40">One: do not -- I repeat -- do not burn bridges.</s>
 <s id="41">You spent years building those bridges, why burn them now?</s>
 <s id="42">The world is such a small place, especially with all these online platforms, that, believe me, you will see these people again and probably in the most inopportune times.</s>
 <s id="43">Number two: take stock of what you've learned in your previous career or careers.</s>
 <s id="44">Most likely, a lot of those things are really applicable to your new job and your new career, whether it's interacting with people, playing on a team or dealing with jerks and assholes.</s>
 <s id="45">All those things are really universally applicable.</s>
 <s id="46">You'll find jerks no matter what industry you're in; no one's immune to it, everyone's got to figure it out, and you probably know how to do it already.</s>
 <s id="47">Lastly, when you start your new job, you're going to be nervous.</s>
 <s id="48">But don't worry, take a deep breath, because this is what I want to tell you: you're part of a new team now, and everyone around you is rooting for your success, because your success is their success.</s>
 <s id="49">So welcome to your new career.</s>
</text>
