<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I was eight years old.</s>
 <s id="2">I remember that day clearly like it happened just yesterday.</s>
 <s id="3">My mother is a bidi roller.</s>
 <s id="4">She hand-rolls country cigarettes to sustain our family.</s>
 <s id="5">She is a hard worker and spent 10 to 12 hours every day rolling bidis.</s>
 <s id="6">That particular day she came home and showed me her bidi-rolling wage book.</s>
 <s id="7">She asked me how much money she has earned that week.</s>
 <s id="8">I went through that book, and what caught my eyes were her thumbprints on each page.</s>
 <s id="9">My mother has never been to school.</s>
 <s id="10">She uses her thumbprints instead of a signature to keep a record of her earnings.</s>
 <s id="11">On that day, for some reason, I wanted to teach her how to hold a pen and write her name.</s>
 <s id="12">She was reluctant at first.</s>
 <s id="13">She smiled innocently and said no.</s>
 <s id="14">But deep down, I was sure she wanted to give it a try.</s>
 <s id="15">With a little bit of perseverance and a lot of effort, we managed to write her name.</s>
 <s id="16">Her hands were trembling, and her face was beaming with pride.</s>
 <s id="17">As I watched her do this, for the first time in my life, I had a priceless feeling: that I could be of some use to this world.</s>
 <s id="18">That feeling was very special, because I am not meant to be useful.</s>
 <s id="19">In rural India, girls are generally considered worthless.</s>
 <s id="20">They're a liability or a burden.</s>
 <s id="21">If they are considered useful, it is only to cook dishes, keep the house clean or raise children.</s>
 <s id="22">As a second daughter of my conservative Indian family, I was fairly clear from a very early age that no one expected anything from me.</s>
 <s id="23">I was conditioned to believe that the three identities that defined me -- poor village girl -- meant that I was to live a life of no voice and no choice.</s>
 <s id="24">These three identities forced me to think that I should never have been born.</s>
 <s id="25">Yet, I was.</s>
 <s id="26">All throughout my childhood, as I rolled bidis alongside my mother, I would wonder: What did my future hold?</s>
 <s id="27">I often asked my mother, with a lot of anxiety, "Amma, will my life be different from yours?</s>
 <s id="28">Will I have a chance to choose my life?</s>
 <s id="29">Will I go to college?"</s>
 <s id="30">And she would reply back, "Try to finish high school first."</s>
 <s id="31">I am sure my mother did not mean to discourage me.</s>
 <s id="32">She only wanted me to understand that my dreams might be too big for a girl in my village.</s>
 <s id="33">When I was 13, I found the autobiography of Helen Keller.</s>
 <s id="34">Helen became my inspiration.</s>
 <s id="35">I admired her indomitable spirit.</s>
 <s id="36">I wanted to have a college degree like her, so I fought with my father and my relatives to be sent to college, and it worked.</s>
 <s id="37">During my final year of my undergraduate degree, I desperately wanted to escape from being forced into marriage, so I applied to a fellowship program in Delhi, which is about 1,600 miles away from my village.</s>
 <s id="38">(Laughter) In fact, I recall that the only way I could fill out the application was during my commute to college.</s>
 <s id="39">I did not have access to computers, so I had to borrow a college junior's cell phone.</s>
 <s id="40">As a woman, I could not be seen with a cell phone, so I used to huddle his phone under my shawl and type as slowly as possible to ensure that I would not be heard.</s>
 <s id="41">After many rounds of interviews, I got into the fellowship program with a full scholarship.</s>
 <s id="42">My father was confused, my mother was worried -- (Applause) My father was confused, my mother was worried, but I felt butterflies in my stomach because I was going to step out of my village for the first time to study in the national capital.</s>
 <s id="43">Of the 97 fellows selected that year, I was the only rural college graduate.</s>
 <s id="44">There was no one there who looked like me or spoke like me.</s>
 <s id="45">I felt alienated, intimidated and judged by many.</s>
 <s id="46">One fellow called me "Coconut Girl."</s>
 <s id="47">Can you guess why?</s>
 <s id="48">Anyone?</s>
 <s id="49">That's because I applied a lot of coconut oil to my hair.</s>
 <s id="50">(Laughter) Another asked me where I had learned to speak English, and some of my peers did not prefer to have me on their assignment teams because they thought I would not be able to contribute to their discussion.</s>
 <s id="51">I felt that many of my peers believed that a person from rural India could not supply anything of value, yet the majority of Indian population today is rural.</s>
 <s id="52">I realized that stories like mine were considered to be an exception and never the expectation.</s>
 <s id="53">I believe that all of us are born into a reality that we blindly accept until something awakens us and a new world opens up.</s>
 <s id="54">When I saw my mother's first signature on her bidi-rolling wage book, when I felt the hot Delhi air against my face after a 50-hour train journey, when I finally felt free and let myself be, I saw a glimpse of that new world I longed for, a world where a girl like me is no longer a liability or a burden but a person of use, a person of value and a person of worthiness.</s>
 <s id="55">By the time my fellowship ended, my life had changed.</s>
 <s id="56">Not only had I traced my lost voice, but also had a choice to make myself useful.</s>
 <s id="57">I was 22.</s>
 <s id="58">I came back to my village to set up the Bodhi Tree Foundation, an institution that supports rural youth by providing them with education, life skills and opportunities.</s>
 <s id="59">We work closely with our rural youth to change their life and to benefit our communities.</s>
 <s id="60">How do I know my institution is working?</s>
 <s id="61">Well, six months ago, we had a new joinee.</s>
 <s id="62">Her name is Kaviarasi.</s>
 <s id="63">I first spotted her in a local college in Tirunelveli during one of my training sessions.</s>
 <s id="64">As you can see, she has a smile which you can never forget.</s>
 <s id="65">We guided her to get an opportunity to study at Ashoka University, Delhi.</s>
 <s id="66">The best part of her story is that she is now back at Bodhi Tree as a trainer working with dedication to make a change in the lives of others like her.</s>
 <s id="67">Kaviarasi doesn't want to feel like an exception.</s>
 <s id="68">She wants to be of use to others in this world.</s>
 <s id="69">Recently, Kaviarasi mentored Anitha, who also comes from a remote, rural village, lives in a 10-foot-by-10-foot home, her parents are also farm laborers.</s>
 <s id="70">Kaviarasi helped Anitha secure admission in a prestigious undergraduate program in a top university in India with a full scholarship.</s>
 <s id="71">When Anitha's parents were reluctant to send her that far, we asked the district administration officials to speak to Anitha's parents, and it worked.</s>
 <s id="72">And then there is Padma.</s>
 <s id="73">Padma and I went to college together.</s>
 <s id="74">She's the first in her entire village to attend graduation.</s>
 <s id="75">She had been working with me at Bodhi Tree until one day she decides to go to graduate school.</s>
 <s id="76">I asked her why.</s>
 <s id="77">She told me that she wanted to make sure that she would never be a liability or a burden to anyone at any point in her life.</s>
 <s id="78">Padma, Anitha and Kaviarasi grew up in the most tough families and communities one could only imagine.</s>
 <s id="79">Yet the journey of finding my usefulness in this world served them in finding their usefulness to this world.</s>
 <s id="80">Of course there are challenges.</s>
 <s id="81">I'm aware change does not happen overnight.</s>
 <s id="82">A lot of my work involves working with families and communities to help them understand why getting an education is useful for everyone.</s>
 <s id="83">The quickest way to convince them is by doing.</s>
 <s id="84">When they see their kids getting a real education, getting a real job, they begin to change.</s>
 <s id="85">The best example is what happened at my home.</s>
 <s id="86">I was recently given an award in recognition of my social work by the chief minister of my state.</s>
 <s id="87">That meant I was going to be on television.</s>
 <s id="88">(Laughter) Everyone was hooked on to the television that morning, including my parents.</s>
 <s id="89">I would like to believe that seeing her daughter on television made my mother feel useful too.</s>
 <s id="90">Hopefully, she will stop pressuring me to get married now.</s>
 <s id="91">(Laughter) Finding my use has helped me to break free from the identities society thrusts on me -- poor village girl.</s>
 <s id="92">Finding my use has helped me to break free from being boxed, caged and bottled.</s>
 <s id="93">Finding my use has helped me to find my voice, my self-worth and my freedom.</s>
 <s id="94">I leave you with this thought: Where do you feel useful to this world?</s>
 <s id="95">Because the answer to that question is where you will find your voice and your freedom.</s>
 <s id="96">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="97">(Applause)</s>
</text>
