<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So, I have a background in technology and magic.</s>
 <s id="2">And magicians are interesting.</s>
 <s id="3">Their illusions accomplish what technology cannot.</s>
 <s id="4">But what happens when the technology of the day seems almost magical?</s>
 <s id="5">What happens when you can do this?</s>
 <s id="6">(Music) Now, 100 years ago, that would have been the magic of levitation.</s>
 <s id="7">Is it possible to create illusions in a world where technology makes anything possible?</s>
 <s id="8">Jump!</s>
 <s id="9">Now, if you know how the trick is done, where is the illusion?</s>
 <s id="10">But still, our imagination is more powerful than our reasoning, and it's easy to attribute personality to machines.</s>
 <s id="11">These are quadcopters.</s>
 <s id="12">But they are more than mechanical flying machines.</s>
 <s id="13">They analyze the environment around them and react to everything I do.</s>
 <s id="14">At once, algorithms allow these autonomous machines to fly in close formation, aware of each other and aware of me -- mathematics that can be mistaken for intelligence, and intelligence for personality.</s>
 <s id="15">Anthropomorphism: that's the illusion, an illusion created by technology and embroidered by our imagination to become an intelligent flying robot, a machine that appears to be alive.</s>
 <s id="16">(Music plays "Close Encounters of the Third Kind") (Quadcopters make tones) I think they say, "Hello."</s>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">Hey guys!</s>
  <s id="17.2">Come on.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="18">And time to land.</s>
 <s id="19">And that's it.</s>
 <s id="20">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="21">(Applause) OK, guys, time to go home.</s>
 <s id="22">Everybody in here.</s>
 <s id="23">Come on, everybody, quickly, quickly.</s>
 <s id="24">No pushing, everybody can fit.</s>
 <s id="25">There you go, a little bit to the left, a little bit to the right.</s>
 <s id="26">Come on, everybody, everybody, and ... good job!</s>
 <s id="27">(Cheers) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="28">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="29">(Applause)</s>
</text>
