<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Wouldn't it be great if we could be invisible?</s>
 <s id="2">Ha, right?</s>
 <s id="3">I mean, we could spy on people without being noticed and do whatever we want without being held responsible.</s>
 <s id="4">Now, magicians have figured out how to utilize full-sized mirrors to bend light in order to create disappearing illusions.</s>
 <s id="5">Scientists have created metamaterials to guide rays of light around tiny, two-dimensional objects.</s>
 <s id="6">Cameras can also film what is behind you and project the image so you appear invisible from the front.</s>
 <s id="7">However, none of these options can make an object as large as a person appear invisible for all angles and distances while its moving.</s>
 <s id="8">But if you are truly invisible, as in from within, here are a few problems you may not have thought about before.</s>
 <s id="9">To move around undetected by other people, you would have to be totally naked.</s>
 <s id="10">Even if it's freezing outside!</s>
 <s id="11">You can't carry anything, including your wallet and keys, otherwise people would just see your wallet and keys floating around.</s>
 <s id="12">Drivers and people on the street can't see you either, therefore they can and will run into you at some point.</s>
 <s id="13">Oh, and you better not wear any perfume or make any noise breathing, otherwise they'll know you're there.</s>
 <s id="14">And, just because you start off invisible, doesn't mean you'll stay that way.</s>
 <s id="15">What if someone accidentally spills scolding hot coffee on you?</s>
 <s id="16">And what if it rains?</s>
 <s id="17">But if you think only liquid can make you visible, you're wrong.</s>
 <s id="18">Dust consists of dead skin cells from humans, soil particles, and fibers from clothes made from cotton and other materials.</s>
 <s id="19">Dust sticks to the moisture on our skin when we sweat and the tiny hairs on our skin when we are dry.</s>
 <s id="20">So, even if you are invisible, dust would still land on every part of you.</s>
 <s id="21">We usually don't notice the dust on our skin because we can't see a thin layer of dust on top of our skin color.</s>
 <s id="22">But, if you're invisible, people would see a human-shaped blob of dust walking around with extremely dirty soles.</s>
 <s id="23">Gross!</s>
 <s id="24">What do you think the world looks like if you are invisible?</s>
 <s id="25">Well, the answer is nothing.</s>
 <s id="26">The reason you can't see in the dark is because there is no light.</s>
 <s id="27">To see an apple, light has to hit the apple and return it to your eyes.</s>
 <s id="28">Then, the retinas in your eyes catch the light reflection for your brain to interpret into the image of an apple.</s>
 <s id="29">If you're invisible, then, by definition, light would travel through you or around you instead of bouncing off you for people to see.</s>
 <s id="30">But that means that retinas in your eyes are not catching the light, either.</s>
 <s id="31">Therefore, your brain has nothing to interpret into an image.</s>
 <s id="32">Can you see your reflection without a mirror to stop the light?</s>
 <s id="33">No.</s>
 <s id="34">So, when you can't be seen by others, you also cannot see.</s>
 <s id="35">Ouch!</s>
 <s id="36">Now, have you given any thought as of whether the invisibility is permanent?</s>
 <s id="37">If it is, how can you receive medical treatment from a doctor if you're injured?</s>
 <s id="38">The doctor wouldn't know where to apply ointments or bandages because they cannot access your injury.</s>
 <s id="39">For that matter, you can't see it either.</s>
 <s id="40">I mean, what if you have an illness or an infection?</s>
 <s id="41">How can the doctor diagnose you without being able to see the color change or inflammation?</s>
 <s id="42">And what if everyone is permanently invisible?</s>
 <s id="43">Well, think about how boring the world would be without seeing people on the streets, on TV, or at home on your computer like right now.</s>
 <s id="44">It's lonely being invisible.</s>
 <s id="45">Now, which superpower physics lesson will you explore next?</s>
 <s id="46">Shifting body size and content, super speed, flight, super strength, immortality, and invisibility.</s>
</text>
