<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Words matter.</s>
 <s id="2">They can heal and they can kill ...</s>
 <s id="3">yet, they have a limit.</s>
 <s id="4">When I was in eighth grade, my teacher gave me a vocabulary sheet with the word "genocide."</s>
 <s id="5">I hated it.</s>
 <s id="6">The word genocide is clinical ...</s>
 <s id="7">overgeneral ...</s>
 <s id="8">bloodless ...</s>
 <s id="9">dehumanizing.</s>
 <s id="10">No word can describe what this does to a nation.</s>
 <s id="11">You need to know, in this kind of war, husbands kills wives, wives kill husbands, neighbors and friends kill each other.</s>
 <s id="12">Someone in power says, "Those over there ...</s>
 <s id="13">they don't belong.</s>
 <s id="14">They're not human."</s>
 <s id="15">And people believe it.</s>
 <s id="16">I don't want words to describe this kind of behavior.</s>
 <s id="17">I want words to stop it.</s>
 <s id="18">But where are the words to stop this?</s>
 <s id="19">And how do we find the words?</s>
 <s id="20">But I believe, truly, we have to keep trying.</s>
 <s id="21">I was born in Kigali, Rwanda.</s>
 <s id="22">I felt loved by my entire family and my neighbors.</s>
 <s id="23">I was constantly being teased by everybody, especially my two older siblings.</s>
 <s id="24">When I lost my front tooth, my brother looked at me and said, "Oh, it has happened to you, too?</s>
 <s id="25">It will never grow back."</s>
 <s id="26">(Laughter) I enjoyed playing everywhere, especially my mother's garden and my neighbor's.</s>
 <s id="27">I loved my kindergarten.</s>
 <s id="28">We sang songs, we played everywhere and ate lunch.</s>
 <s id="29">I had a childhood that I would wish for anyone.</s>
 <s id="30">But when I was six, the adults in my family began to speak in whispers and shushed me any time that I asked a question.</s>
 <s id="31">One night, my mom and dad came.</s>
 <s id="32">They had this strange look when they woke us.</s>
 <s id="33">They sent my older sister Claire and I to our grandparent's, hoping whatever was happening would blow away.</s>
 <s id="34">Soon we had to escape from there, too.</s>
 <s id="35">We hid, we crawled, we sometimes ran.</s>
 <s id="36">Sometimes I heard laughter and then screaming and crying and then noise that I had never heard.</s>
 <s id="37">You see, I did not know what those noises were.</s>
 <s id="38">They were neither human -- and also at the same time, they were human.</s>
 <s id="39">I saw people who were not breathing.</s>
 <s id="40">I thought they were asleep.</s>
 <s id="41">I still didn't understand what death was, or killing in itself.</s>
 <s id="42">When we would stop to rest for a little bit or search for food, I would close my eyes, hoping when I opened them, I would be awake.</s>
 <s id="43">I had no idea which direction was home.</s>
 <s id="44">Days were for hiding and night for walking.</s>
 <s id="45">You go from a person who's away from home to a person with no home.</s>
 <s id="46">The place that is supposed to want you has pushed you out, and no one takes you in.</s>
 <s id="47">You are unwanted by anyone.</s>
 <s id="48">You are a refugee.</s>
 <s id="49">From age six to 12, I lived in seven different countries, moving from one refugee camp to another, hoping we would be wanted.</s>
 <s id="50">My older sister Claire, she became a young mother ...</s>
 <s id="51">and a master at getting things done.</s>
 <s id="52">When I was 12, I came to America with Claire and her family on refugee status.</s>
 <s id="53">And that's only the beginning, because even though I was 12 years old, sometimes I felt like three years old and sometimes 50 years old.</s>
 <s id="54">My past receded, grew jumbled, distorted.</s>
 <s id="55">Everything was too much and nothing.</s>
 <s id="56">Time seemed like pages torn out of a book and scattered everywhere.</s>
 <s id="57">This still happens to me standing right here.</s>
 <s id="58">After I got to America, Claire and I did not talk about our past.</s>
 <s id="59">In 2006, after 12 years being separated away from my family, and then seven years knowing that they were dead and them thinking that we were dead, we reunited ...</s>
 <s id="60">in the most dramatic, American way possible.</s>
 <s id="61">Live, on television -- (Laughter) on "The Oprah Show."</s>
 <s id="62">(Laughter) (Applause) I told you, I told you.</s>
 <s id="63">(Laughter) But after the show, as I spent time with my mom and dad and my little sister and my two new siblings that I never met, I felt anger.</s>
 <s id="64">I felt every deep pain in me.</s>
 <s id="65">And I know that there is absolutely nothing, nothing, that could restore the time we lost with each other and the relationship we could've had.</s>
 <s id="66">Soon, my parents moved to the United States, but like Claire, they don't talk about our past.</s>
 <s id="67">They live in never-ending present.</s>
 <s id="68">Not asking too many questions, not allowing themselves to feel -- moving in small steps.</s>
 <s id="69">None of us, of course, can make sense of what happened to us.</s>
 <s id="70">Though my family is alive -- yes, we were broken, and yes, we are numb and we were silenced by our own experience.</s>
 <s id="71">It's not just my family.</s>
 <s id="72">Rwanda is not the only country where people have turned on each other and murdered each other.</s>
 <s id="73">The entire human race, in many ways, is like my family.</s>
 <s id="74">Not dead; yes, broken, numb and silenced by the violence of the world that has taken over.</s>
 <s id="75">You see, the chaos of the violence continues inside in the words we use and the stories we create every single day.</s>
 <s id="76">But also on the labels that we impose on ourselves and each other.</s>
 <s id="77">Once we call someone "other," "less than," "one of them" or "better than," believe me ...</s>
 <s id="78">under the right condition, it's a short path to more destruction.</s>
 <s id="79">More chaos and more noise that we will not understand.</s>
 <s id="80">Words will never be enough to quantify and qualify the many magnitudes of human-caused destruction.</s>
 <s id="81">In order for us to stop the violence that goes on in the world, I hope -- at least I beg you -- to pause.</s>
 <s id="82">Let's ask ourselves: Who are we without words?</s>
 <s id="83">Who are we without labels?</s>
 <s id="84">Who are we in our breath?</s>
 <s id="85">Who are we in our heartbeat?</s>
 <s id="86">(Applause)</s>
</text>
