<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">How do we explain the unexplainable?</s>
 <s id="2">This question has inspired numerous myths, religious practices, and scientific inquiries.</s>
 <s id="3">But Zen Buddhists practicing throughout China from the 9th to 13th century asked a different question – why do we need an explanation?</s>
 <s id="4">For these monks, blindly seeking answers was a vice to overcome, and learning to accept the mysteries of existence was the true path to enlightenment.</s>
 <s id="5">But fighting the urge to explain the unexplainable can be difficult.</s>
 <s id="6">So to help practice living with these mysteries, the meditating monks used a collection of roughly 1,700 bewildering and ambiguous philosophical thought experiments called kōans.</s>
 <s id="7">The name, originally gong-an in Chinese, translates to “public record or case."</s>
 <s id="8">But unlike real-world court cases, kōans were intentionally incomprehensible.</s>
 <s id="9">They were surprising, surreal, and frequently contradicted themselves.</s>
 <s id="10">On the surface, they contained a proverb about the Zen Buddhist monastic code - such as living without physical or mental attachments, avoiding binary thinking, and realizing one’s true “Buddha-nature."</s>
 <s id="11">But by framing those lessons as illogical anecdotes, they became tests to help practicing monks learn to live with ambiguity and paradox.</s>
 <s id="12">By puzzling through these confusing “cases," meditating monks could both internalize and practice Buddhist teachings.</s>
 <s id="13">Hopefully, they would let go of the search for one true answer and trigger a spiritual breakthrough.</s>
 <s id="14">Since these are intentionally unexplainable, it would be misguided to try and decipher these stories ourselves.</s>
 <s id="15">But like the monks before us, we can puzzle over them together, and investigate just how resistant they are to simple explanations.</s>
 <s id="16">Consider this kōan illustrating the practice of no-attachment.</s>
 <s id="17">Two monks, Tanzan and Ekido, are traveling together down a muddy road.</s>
 <s id="18">Ahead they see an attractive traveler, unable to cross the muddy path.</s>
 <s id="19">Tanzan politely offers his help, carrying the traveler on his back across the street, and placing her down without a word.</s>
 <s id="20">Ekido was shocked.</s>
 <s id="21">According to monastic law, monks were not supposed to go near women, let alone touch a beautiful stranger.</s>
 <s id="22">After miles of walking, Ekido could no longer restrain himself.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">“How could you carry that woman?”</s>
  <s id="23.2">Tanzan smiled, “I left the traveler there.</s>
  <s id="23.3">Are you still carrying her?”</s>
  <s id="23.4">Like all kōans, this story has numerous interpretations.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="24">But one popular reading suggests that despite never having physically carried the traveler, Ekido broke monastic law by mentally "clinging to" the woman.</s>
 <s id="25">This type of conflict – examining the grey area between the letter of the law and the spirit of the law – was common in kōans.</s>
 <s id="26">In addition to exploring ambiguity, kōans often ridiculed characters claiming total understanding of the world around them.</s>
 <s id="27">One such example finds three monks debating a temple flag rippling in the wind.</s>
 <s id="28">The first monk refers to the flag as a moving banner, while the second monk insists that they are not seeing the flag move, but rather the wind blowing.</s>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">They argue back and forth, until finally, a third monk intervenes, “It is not the flag moving, nor the wind blowing, but rather the movement of your minds!”</s>
  <s id="29.2">One interpretation of this kōan plays on the supposed wisdom of the arguing monks – the first asserting the importance of the observable world, the second favoring deeper knowledge we can infer from that world.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">But each monk’s commitment to his own “answer” blinds him to the other’s insight, and in doing so, defies an essential Buddhist ideal: abolishing binary thinking.</s>
 <s id="31">The third monk identifies their conflict as a perceptual one – both arguing monks fail to see the larger picture.</s>
 <s id="32">Of course, all these interpretations only hint at how to wrestle with these kōans.</s>
 <s id="33">Neither the wisdom from practicing monks before us, nor the supposedly wise characters in these stories can resolve them for you.</s>
 <s id="34">That’s because the purpose of these kōans isn’t reaching a simple solution.</s>
 <s id="35">It’s the very act of struggling with these paradoxical puzzles which challenge our desire for resolution, and our understanding of understanding itself.</s>
</text>
