<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">A rabbit attempts to play a church organ, while a knight fights a giant snail and a naked man blows a trumpet with his rear end.</s>
 <s id="2">Painted with squirrel-hair brushes on vellum or parchment by monks, nuns, and urban craftspeople, these bizarre images populate the margins of the most prized books from the Middle Ages.</s>
 <s id="3">Their illustrations often tell a second story as rich as the text itself.</s>
 <s id="4">Some images appear in many different illuminated manuscripts, and often reinforce the religious content of the books they decorated.</s>
 <s id="5">For example, a porcupine picking up fruit on its spines could represent the devil stealing the fruits of faith-- or Christ taking up the sins of mankind.</s>
 <s id="6">Medieval lore stated that a hunter could only capture a unicorn when it lay its horn in the lap of a virgin, so a unicorn could symbolize either sexual temptation or Christ being captured by his enemies.</s>
 <s id="7">Rabbits, meanwhile, could represent human’s lustful natures— and could redeem themselves through attempts to make sacred music despite their failings.</s>
 <s id="8">All of these references would have been familiar to medieval Europeans from other art forms and oral tradition, though some have grown more mysterious over the centuries.</s>
 <s id="9">Today, no one can say for sure what the common motif of a knight fighting a snail means— or why the knight so often appears to be losing.</s>
 <s id="10">The snail might be a symbol of the inevitability of death, which defeats even the strongest knights.</s>
 <s id="11">Or it could represent humility, and a knight’s need to vanquish his own pride.</s>
 <s id="12">Many illuminated manuscripts were copies of religious or classical texts, and the bookmakers incorporated their own ideas and opinions in illustrations.</s>
 <s id="13">The butt tuba, for example, was likely shorthand to express disapproval with-- or add an ironic spin to-- the action in the text.</s>
 <s id="14">Illuminations could also be used to make subversive political commentary.</s>
 <s id="15">The text of the "Smithfield Decretals" details the Church’s laws and punishments for lawbreakers.</s>
 <s id="16">But the margins show a fox being hanged by geese, a possible allusion to the common people turning on their powerful oppressors.</s>
 <s id="17">In the "Chronica Majora," Matthew Paris summarized a scandal of his day, in which the Welsh prince Griffin plummeted to his death from the tower of London.</s>
 <s id="18">Some believed the prince fell, Paris wrote, while others thought he was pushed.</s>
 <s id="19">He added his own take in the margins, which show the prince falling to his death while trying to escape on a rope made of bed-sheets.</s>
 <s id="20">Some margins told stories of a more personal nature.</s>
 <s id="21">"The Luttrell Psalter," a book of psalms and prayers commissioned by Sir Geoffrey Luttrell, shows a young woman having her hair done, while a young man catches a bird in a net.</s>
 <s id="22">The shaved patch on his head is growing out, indicating that he is a clergyman neglecting his duties.</s>
 <s id="23">This alludes to a family scandal where a young cleric ran away with Sir Geoffrey’s daughter Elizabeth.</s>
 <s id="24">The family’s personal spiritual advisor likely painted it into the book to remind his clients of their failings and encourage their spiritual development.</s>
 <s id="25">Some artists even painted themselves into the manuscripts.</s>
 <s id="26">The opening image of Christine de Pisan’s collected works shows de Pisan presenting the book to the Queen of France.</s>
 <s id="27">The queen was so impressed by de Pisan's previous work that she commissioned her own copy.</s>
 <s id="28">Such royal patronage enabled her to establish her own publishing house in Paris.</s>
 <s id="29">The tradition of illuminated manuscripts lasted for over a thousand years.</s>
 <s id="30">The books were created by individuals or teams for uses as wide-ranging as private prayer aids, service books in churches, textbooks, and protective talismans to take into battle.</s>
 <s id="31">Across all this variation, those tricky little drawings in the margins are a unique window into the minds of medieval artists.</s>
</text>
