<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">After cutting her arm with a broken glass, she fell into a fitful, exhausted sleep on the railway station platform.</s>
 <s id="2">Early in the morning, when the station toilets were opened, she got painfully to her feet, and made her way over to them.</s>
 <s id="3">When she saw her reflection in the mirror, she started to cry.</s>
 <s id="4">Her face was dirty and tearstained; her shirt was ripped and covered in blood.</s>
 <s id="5">She looked as if she'd been on the streets for three months, not three days.</s>
 <s id="6">She washed herself as best she could.</s>
 <s id="7">Her arms and stomach were hurting badly.</s>
 <s id="8">She tried to clean the wounds, but any pressure she applied just started the bleeding again.</s>
 <s id="9">She needed stitches, but there was no way she would go to a hospital.</s>
 <s id="10">They'd have sent her back home again.</s>
 <s id="11">Back to him.</s>
 <s id="12">She tightened her jacket -- well, fastened her jacket tightly to cover the blood.</s>
 <s id="13">She looked back at herself in the mirror.</s>
 <s id="14">She looked a little better than before but was past caring.</s>
 <s id="15">There was only one thing she could think of doing.</s>
 <s id="16">She came out of the station and into a phone box nearby.</s>
 <s id="17">(Telephone rings) (Telephone rings) Woman: Samaritans, can I help you?</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">Hello, Samaritans.</s>
  <s id="18.2">Can I help you?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="19">Girl: (Crying) I -- I don't know.</s>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">Woman: What's happened?</s>
  <s id="20.2">You sound very upset.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="21">(Girl cries) Woman: Why not start with your name?</s>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">I'm Pam.</s>
  <s id="22.2">What can I call you?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">Where are you speaking from?</s>
 <s id="24">Are you safe?</s>
 <s id="25">Girl: It's a phone box in London.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">Pam: You sound very young.</s>
  <s id="26.2">How old are you?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">Girl: Fourteen.</s>
 <s id="28">Pam: And what's happened to make you so upset?</s>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">Girl: I just want to die.</s>
  <s id="29.2">Every day I wake up and wish I was dead.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">If he doesn't kill me, then, I think, I want to do it myself.</s>
 <s id="31">Pam: I'm glad you called.</s>
 <s id="32">Let's start at the beginning.</s>
 <s id="33">Sophie Andrews: Pam continued to gently ask the girl about herself.</s>
 <s id="34">She didn't say much; there were lots of silences.</s>
 <s id="35">But she knew she was there, and having Pam on the end of the phone felt so comforting.</s>
 <s id="36">The 14-year-old that made that call was me.</s>
 <s id="37">That was me in the phone box.</s>
 <s id="38">I was running away from home, sleeping rough on the streets in London.</s>
 <s id="39">I was being sexually abused by my father and his friends.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">I was self-harming every day.</s>
  <s id="40.2">I was suicidal.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="41">The first time I called Samaritans, I was 12 and absolutely desperate.</s>
 <s id="42">It was a few months after my mother had deserted me, walked out and left me in the family home.</s>
 <s id="43">And the abuse I was suffering at the hands of my father and his friends had left me a total wreck.</s>
 <s id="44">I was running away, I was missing school, I was arriving drunk.</s>
 <s id="45">I was without hope and wanted to die.</s>
 <s id="46">And that's where Samaritans came in.</s>
 <s id="47">Samaritans has been around since 1953.</s>
 <s id="48">It's a 24/7 confidential helpline in the UK for anyone who might be feeling desperate or suicidal.</s>
 <s id="49">Which I certainly was.</s>
 <s id="50">Volunteers answer the phone around the clock every day of the year, and calls are confidential.</s>
 <s id="51">During my teenage years, when I was most desperate, Samaritans became my lifeline.</s>
 <s id="52">They promised me total confidentiality.</s>
 <s id="53">And that allowed me to trust them.</s>
 <s id="54">Disturbing as they no doubt found my story, they never showed it.</s>
 <s id="55">They were always there for me and listened without judgment.</s>
 <s id="56">Mostly, they gently encouraged me to get help; I never felt out of control with them -- an interesting parallel, as I felt so out of control in every other aspect of my life.</s>
 <s id="57">It felt my self-harm was probably the only area where I felt I had any control.</s>
 <s id="58">A few years later, I managed to get some control in my life.</s>
 <s id="59">And I had appropriate support around me to allow me to live with what had happened.</s>
 <s id="60">I had become a survivor of abuse rather than a victim.</s>
 <s id="61">And at 21, I contacted Samaritans again.</s>
 <s id="62">This time because I wanted to become a volunteer.</s>
 <s id="63">Wanted to pay something back to the organization that had really saved my life.</s>
 <s id="64">I knew that the simple act of listening in an empathetic way could have a profound effect.</s>
 <s id="65">I knew that somebody listening to me without judgment would make the biggest difference.</s>
 <s id="66">So I caught up with my education, found someone I could persuade to give me a job, and I enjoyed my volunteering at Samaritans.</s>
 <s id="67">And when I say "enjoyed," it's an odd word to use, because no one would want to think of anyone being in absolute distress or pain.</s>
 <s id="68">But I knew that that profound impact of that listening ear and someone being alongside me at that desperate time had the biggest impact, and I felt a great sense of fulfillment that I was able to help people as a Samaritan.</s>
 <s id="69">In my years volunteering at Samaritans, I was asked to perform many roles.</s>
 <s id="70">But I guess the peak came in 2008, when I was asked to chair the organization for three years.</s>
 <s id="71">So I had actually gone from that vulnerable caller in the phone box, desperate for help, to being the national lead for the organization and responsible for 22,000 volunteers.</s>
 <s id="72">I actually used to joke at the time and say if you really screwed up as a caller, you might end up running the place.</s>
 <s id="73">(Laughter) Which I did.</s>
 <s id="74">But I guess in a world which is dominated by professionalizing everything we do, I really understood that that simple act of listening could have such a life-changing effect.</s>
 <s id="75">I guess it's a simple concept that can be applied across all areas of life.</s>
 <s id="76">So in the 1980s, when I called Samaritans, child abuse was a subject no one wanted to talk about.</s>
 <s id="77">Victims were often blamed, victims were often judged.</s>
 <s id="78">And it was a topic of shame, and no one really wanted to talk about it.</s>
 <s id="79">Today, judgment and shame surround a different issue.</s>
 <s id="80">There's a different stigma that's out there.</s>
 <s id="81">And the stigma that's there today is to talk about loneliness.</s>
 <s id="82">Loneliness and isolation have profound health impacts.</s>
 <s id="83">Being lonely can have a significant impact on your own well-being.</s>
 <s id="84">Recent systematic review of research actually said that it increased the mortality rates, or premature death rates, by up to 30 percent.</s>
 <s id="85">It can lead to higher blood pressure, higher levels of depression, and actually aligned to mortality rates that might be more associated with alcohol abuse or smoking cigarettes.</s>
 <s id="86">Loneliness is actually more harmful that smoking 15 cigarettes.</s>
 <s id="87">A day.</s>
 <s id="88">Not in your life, in your day.</s>
 <s id="89">It's also associated with higher levels of dementia.</s>
 <s id="90">So a recent study also found that lonely people are twice at risk of Alzheimer's disease.</s>
 <s id="91">Of course, there's many people that live alone who are not lonely.</s>
 <s id="92">But being a caregiver for a partner that maybe has dementia can be a very lonely place.</s>
 <s id="93">And a recent landmark study gave us a very good, clear definition of what loneliness is.</s>
 <s id="94">And it said it's a subjective, unwelcome feeling of a lack or loss of companionship.</s>
 <s id="95">And it happens when there's a mismatch between the quality and the quantity of relationships that we have and those that we want.</s>
 <s id="96">Now in my life, the best help I've ever received has been from those personal connections and being listened to in an empathetic way.</s>
 <s id="97">Professionals, and I'm conscious I'm speaking to a room of professionals, have a very important place.</s>
 <s id="98">But for me, a volunteer giving up their time and listening to me without judgment in a confidential way, had such a huge, life-changing effect for me.</s>
 <s id="99">And that was something that really stayed with me.</s>
 <s id="100">So as you will have gathered, in my teenage years, I was off the rails, I was going every day wondering if I'd even live the next day.</s>
 <s id="101">But that profound impact of the volunteer listening to me stayed with me.</s>
 <s id="102">When I finally got to a point in my life where I felt I could live with what had happened, I wanted to pay something back.</s>
 <s id="103">And in my experience, people who have been helped in a transforming way always want to pay something back.</s>
 <s id="104">So I started paying back by my 25 years volunteering with Samaritans.</s>
 <s id="105">And then, in 2013, picking up on that whole issue and the new stigma of loneliness, I launched a new national helpline in the UK for older people, called The Silver Line, which is there to support lonely and isolated older people.</s>
 <s id="106">In our short history, we've taken 1.5 million calls.</s>
 <s id="107">And I know we're having a big impact, based on the feedback we get every day.</s>
 <s id="108">Some people might be calling up for a friendly chat, maybe some information about local services.</s>
 <s id="109">Some might be calling because they're suicidal.</s>
 <s id="110">Some might be calling up because they're reporting abuse.</s>
 <s id="111">And some quite simply, as I was, may have simply just given up on life.</s>
 <s id="112">I guess it's a really simple idea, setting up a helpline.</s>
 <s id="113">And I look back to those early days when I had the lofty title, I still have, of chief exec, but in the early days, I was chief exec of myself.</s>
 <s id="114">Which, I have to say, I had the best meetings ever in my career -- (Laughter) as chief exec of myself.</s>
 <s id="115">But things have moved on, and now in 2017, we have over 200 staff listening to older people every day of the year, 24/7.</s>
 <s id="116">We also have over 3,000 volunteers making weekly friendship calls from their own home.</s>
 <s id="117">We also, for people that like the written word, offer Silver Letters, and we write pen-pal letters to older people who still enjoy receiving a letter.</s>
 <s id="118">And we also have introduced something called Silver Circles -- you notice I'm owning the word "silver" here -- put "silver" in front of it and it's ours.</s>
 <s id="119">Silver Circles are group conference calls where people actually talk about shared interests.</s>
 <s id="120">My favorite group is the music group, where people, every week, play musical instruments down the phone to each other.</s>
 <s id="121">Not always the same tune at the same time.</s>
 <s id="122">(Laughter) But they do have fun.</s>
 <s id="123">And "fun" is an interesting word, because I've talked very much about desperation, loneliness and isolation.</s>
 <s id="124">But if you came to our helpline in the UK, you would also hear laughter.</s>
 <s id="125">Because at the Silver Line, we do want to cherish the wonderful lives of older people and all the experiences that they bring.</s>
 <s id="126">So here's an example, just a snippet of one of our calls.</s>
 <s id="127">(Audio) Good morning, you're through to the Silver Line.</s>
 <s id="128">My name's Alan, how can I help?</s>
 <p id="p129">
  <s id="129.1">Woman: Hello, Alan.</s>
  <s id="129.2">Good morning.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="130">Alan: Hello.</s>
 <s id="131">Woman: (Chipper) Hello!</s>
 <s id="132">Alan: Oh, how are you this morning?</s>
 <s id="133">Woman: I'm alright, thank you.</s>
 <s id="134">Alan: I'm pleased to hear it.</s>
 <s id="135">Woman: What a wonderful thing the telephone is, you know?</s>
 <s id="136">Alan: It's a remarkable invention, isn't it?</s>
 <s id="137">Woman: I remember when I was a little girl, donkey's years ago, if you wanted to make a phone call to somebody, you had to go to a shop and use the telephone of the shop and pay the shop for using the telephone and have your phone call.</s>
 <s id="138">So you didn't make phone calls just whenever you fancied.</s>
 <s id="139">Alan: Oh, no.</s>
 <s id="140">Woman: (Coughs) Oh, sorry.</s>
 <s id="141">(Coughs) Excuse me about that.</s>
 <s id="142">You had to, you know, confine your phone calls to the absolute essentials.</s>
 <s id="143">And now, here I am, sitting in my own home in my dressing gown still, and using the telephone, isn't it wonderful?</s>
 <p id="p144">
  <s id="144.1">Alan: It is.</s>
  <s id="144.2">(Laughter) SA: And that's not untypical of a call we might receive at our helpline.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="145">That's someone who really sees us as part of the family.</s>
 <s id="146">So Silver Line, I guess, are now helping older people in the same way that Samaritans has helped me.</s>
 <s id="147">They're there 24/7, they're listening confidentially and quite often not giving any advice.</s>
 <s id="148">How often do we really ever listen without giving advice?</s>
 <s id="149">It's actually quite hard.</s>
 <s id="150">Quite often on the phone calls, an older person would say, "Could you give me some advice, please?"</s>
 <s id="151">And 20 minutes later, they say, "Thank you for your advice," and we realize we haven't given any.</s>
 <s id="152">(Laughter) We've listened and listened, and we haven't interrupted.</s>
 <s id="153">But to that person, maybe we have given advice.</s>
 <s id="154">We recently conducted a survey at The Silver Line to 3,000 older people, to ask them what they thought of the service.</s>
 <s id="155">And one person quite simply came back and said, for the first time in her life, she had what we would call in the sport cricket a wicketkeeper, and what you would call in baseball, a catcher.</s>
 <s id="156">I've been here 48 hours, and I'm talking American.</s>
 <s id="157">They will not recognize me when I get home.</s>
 <s id="158">(Laughter) But for the first time in her life, she had that catcher, which is really, really important.</s>
 <s id="159">And now it's come full circle, because actually, people that are calling Silver Line and needing a catcher are now becoming catchers themselves by putting something back and becoming volunteers and becoming part of our family.</s>
 <s id="160">So I end my talk, really, where I started, talking about my own personal experience.</s>
 <s id="161">Because when I talk about my life, I often say that I've been lucky.</s>
 <s id="162">And people generally ask me why.</s>
 <s id="163">And it's because, at every stage of my life, I have been lucky enough to have someone alongside me at the right time who maybe has believed in me, which in turn has helped me just to believe a little bit more in myself, which has been so important.</s>
 <s id="164">And everyone needs a catcher at some point in their lives.</s>
 <s id="165">This is my catcher.</s>
 <s id="166">So that's Pam.</s>
 <s id="167">And she answered the call to me when I was that 14-year-old in the phone box, over 30 years ago.</s>
 <s id="168">So never, ever underestimate the power of a simple human connection.</s>
 <s id="169">Because it can be and so often is the power to save a life.</s>
 <s id="170">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="171">(Applause)</s>
</text>
