<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">When faced with a big challenge where potential failure seems to lurk at every corner, maybe you've heard this advice before: "Be more confident."</s>
 <s id="2">And most likely, this is what you think when you hear it: "If only it were that simple."</s>
 <s id="3">But what is confidence?</s>
 <s id="4">Take the belief that you are valuable, worthwhile, and capable, also known as self-esteem, add in the optimism that comes when you are certain of your abilities, and then empowered by these, act courageously to face a challenge head-on.</s>
 <s id="5">This is confidence.</s>
 <s id="6">It turns thoughts into action.</s>
 <s id="7">So where does confidence even come from?</s>
 <s id="8">There are several factors that impact confidence.</s>
 <s id="9">One: what you're born with, such as your genes, which will impact things like the balance of neurochemicals in your brain.</s>
 <s id="10">Two: how you're treated.</s>
 <s id="11">This includes the social pressures of your environment.</s>
 <s id="12">And three: the part you have control over, the choices you make, the risks you take, and how you think about and respond to challenges and setbacks.</s>
 <s id="13">It isn't possible to completely untangle these three factors, but the personal choices we make certainly play a major role in confidence development.</s>
 <s id="14">So, by keeping in mind a few practical tips, we do actually have the power to cultivate our own confidence.</s>
 <s id="15">Tip 1: a quick fix.</s>
 <s id="16">There are a few tricks that can give you an immediate confidence boost in the short term.</s>
 <s id="17">Picture your success when you're beginning a difficult task, something as simple as listening to music with deep bass; it can promote feelings of power.</s>
 <s id="18">You can even strike a powerful pose or give yourself a pep talk.</s>
 <s id="19">Tip two: believe in your ability to improve.</s>
 <s id="20">If you're looking for a long-term change, consider the way you think about your abilities and talents.</s>
 <s id="21">Do you think they are fixed at birth, or that they can be developed, like a muscle?</s>
 <s id="22">These beliefs matter because they can influence how you act when you're faced with setbacks.</s>
 <s id="23">If you have a fixed mindset, meaning that you think your talents are locked in place, you might give up, assuming you've discovered something you're not very good at.</s>
 <s id="24">But if you have a growth mindset and think your abilities can improve, a challenge is an opportunity to learn and grow.</s>
 <s id="25">Neuroscience supports the growth mindset.</s>
 <s id="26">The connections in your brain do get stronger and grow with study and practice.</s>
 <s id="27">It also turns out, on average, people who have a growth mindset are more successful, getting better grades, and doing better in the face of challenges.</s>
 <s id="28">Tip three: practice failure.</s>
 <s id="29">Face it, you're going to fail sometimes.</s>
 <s id="30">Everyone does.</s>
 <s id="31">J.K. Rowling was rejected by twelve different publishers before one picked up "Harry Potter."</s>
 <s id="32">The Wright Brothers built on history's failed attempts at flight, including some of their own, before designing a successful airplane.</s>
 <s id="33">Studies show that those who fail regularly and keep trying anyway are better equipped to respond to challenges and setbacks in a constructive way.</s>
 <s id="34">They learn how to try different strategies, ask others for advice, and perservere.</s>
 <s id="35">So, think of a challenge you want to take on, realize it's not going to be easy, accept that you'll make mistakes, and be kind to yourself when you do.</s>
 <s id="36">Give yourself a pep talk, stand up, and go for it.</s>
 <s id="37">The excitement you'll feel knowing that whatever the result, you'll have gained greater knowledge and understanding.</s>
 <s id="38">This is confidence.</s>
</text>
