<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">They wanted her piecemealed, papier-mâchéd, practically broken, limp-like and loveless, a litany of exaggeration.</s>
 <s id="2">They wanted her low.</s>
 <s id="3">And high.</s>
 <s id="4">Flat and wide.</s>
 <s id="5">Filled with all of their empty.</s>
 <s id="6">They wanted her to be more like them.</s>
 <s id="7">Not knowing her conception was immaculate.</s>
 <s id="8">That she was birthed in sandalwood-scented river water, sweet sapphire honey-touched tongue, she was too much of a mouthful for the greedy.</s>
 <s id="9">Just a small amount of her was more than they could stand.</s>
 <s id="10">Oh, they wanted her bland.</s>
 <s id="11">And barren.</s>
 <s id="12">Unspirited, un-African, uncultured, under siege in the streets.</s>
 <s id="13">They wanted her face down, ass up, hands cuffed and ankles strapped.</s>
 <s id="14">They wanted her knowing she could never want them back.</s>
 <s id="15">Oh, they wanted her holy, baptized in her divine, they wanted her secrets, pearls to swine.</s>
 <s id="16">They wanted to unravel the mystery of her design.</s>
 <s id="17">Fascinated by glory, hypnotized by her kind.</s>
 <s id="18">Oh, they wanted her complete.</s>
 <s id="19">They wanted her whole, though they came fractioned, half-hearted, half-soul, with no regards and no knowledge as to who she really was.</s>
 <s id="20">Oh, but if they knew.</s>
 <s id="21">If they knew her, praise songs would rain from the clouds of their eyes, clearing the vision, bathing the heart.</s>
 <s id="22">They would bow every time they saw her.</s>
 <s id="23">Be their best selves when she was around.</s>
 <s id="24">If they knew her, knew she was the glue to their revolution, the life flow of blood through their veins.</s>
 <s id="25">If they knew her, she would know, she would feel that her body is more than battlefield.</s>
 <s id="26">More than bone break and bleeding bigotry.</s>
 <s id="27">More than bridge over your troubled conscience.</s>
 <s id="28">More than used up, walked on, driven through, shot up.</s>
 <s id="29">More than your "Selma, Lord, Selma" Edmund Pettus.</s>
 <s id="30">More than your killer Katrina Danziger.</s>
 <s id="31">More than your bust them out of Baltimore "Highway to Nowhere."</s>
 <s id="32">If they knew her, she would know.</s>
 <s id="33">(Singing) Wild women, wild women, they walk with buffalo.</s>
 <s id="34">Have lightning on their tongues, fly whisks as weapons.</s>
 <s id="35">Wild women, they walk with machetes.</s>
 <s id="36">With wisdom, with grace, with ease.</s>
 <s id="37">Wild women have hurricanes in their bellies, releasing a flood of a lesson.</s>
 <s id="38">Oh, wild women, they fly free.</s>
 <s id="39">Just watch their ways, how they rip and shred.</s>
 <s id="40">Oh, who can understand her, this winding Niger river of a woman one who is unafraid to tear away only to roam and then become the wind.</s>
 <s id="41">She who speaks in gusts and cyclones blasting us back to high ground, high consciousness, she turns and so does the world.</s>
 <s id="42">Feel her spinning, spanning several lifetimes.</s>
 <s id="43">Hear her speaking, sparking alarm.</s>
 <s id="44">See her dancing, summoning the dead, resurrecting new life.</s>
 <s id="45">Heaven hears her knocking on the door, safely transporting the ones who call for her assistance.</s>
 <s id="46">Wild women, they open portals to new worlds, new speech, new dreams.</s>
 <s id="47">Oh, dearly beloveds, so dearly departed from the ways of the guardian, beware.</s>
 <s id="48">For wild women are not to be tamed.</s>
 <s id="49">Only admired.</s>
 <s id="50">Just let her in and witness her set your days ablaze.</s>
 <s id="51">(Cheers) (Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="52">(Applause)</s>
</text>
