<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Sunning themselves on rocks or waddling awkwardly across the beach, it’s easy to think of these immobile mammals less as sea lions, and more as sea house cats.</s>
 <s id="2">But don’t be fooled by their beachside behavior.</s>
 <s id="3">Under the waves, sea lions are incredible endurance hunters.</s>
 <s id="4">Hurtling around at speeds from 4 to 18 miles an hour and hunting for up to 30 hours at a time, these majestic mammals live up to their name.</s>
 <s id="5">And thanks to a suite of physical adaptations, finely tuned over millions of years, they make for resourceful foragers.</s>
 <s id="6">To find their favorite food, sea lions hunt much deeper than many of their semi-aquatic peers.</s>
 <s id="7">With some species diving to depths of nearly 400 meters, they’re able to cope with the mounting pressure by collapsing their pliable rib cage, and compressing a pair of springy lungs.</s>
 <s id="8">This pushes air up through the smaller airways, collapsing rings of cartilage as oxygen travels out from the lungs, to be held in the larger, upper airways.</s>
 <s id="9">Upon surfacing, this air will be used to re-inflate the lungs, but for now their heart slows down to preserve oxygen.</s>
 <s id="10">Blood flow is redirected towards only the most essential organs like the heart, lungs, and brain, which rely on reserve oxygen stored in blood and muscle.</s>
 <s id="11">Once they arrive at their hunting ground, sea lions depend on their superior vision to find their prey.</s>
 <s id="12">Most mammal eyes have a structure called a lens– a transparent, convex structure whose shape refracts light to enable sight.</s>
 <s id="13">In humans, this lens is curved to process light waves traveling through air.</s>
 <s id="14">But sea lions need to see their best at hundreds of meters deep.</s>
 <s id="15">To accommodate, their eyes have a much rounder lens to refract light underwater, as well as teardrop-shaped pupils which can expand to 25 times their original size.</s>
 <s id="16">This lets in as much light as possible, helping them pinpoint their prey in even the dimmest conditions.</s>
 <s id="17">But once they’ve closed in, they rely on something akin to a sixth sense to actually catch their meal.</s>
 <s id="18">Their whiskers, or vibrissae, are composed of keratin and full of nerve fibers that run deep into the connective tissue of their face.</s>
 <s id="19">Sea lions have full directional control over these whiskers, which can lie flat against their face, or stick out at a 90-degree angle.</s>
 <s id="20">When properly tuned, these whiskers can sense the slim trails of moving water fish leave in their wake.</s>
 <s id="21">And they’re precise enough to let blindfolded sea lions tell the difference between objects less than two centimeters different in size.</s>
 <s id="22">With these tools a healthy sea lion can catch generous helpings of fish such as anchovy, mackerel, and squid on every outing.</s>
 <s id="23">And with their exceptional memories, they can remember multiple hunting grounds, including those they haven’t visited in decades.</s>
 <s id="24">This memory also extends to breeding territories and birthing areas, as well as which neighbors are friend and foe.</s>
 <s id="25">There’s even evidence that sea lions can remember how to perform tasks after 10 years with no practice in between, letting them navigate old stomping grounds with ease.</s>
 <s id="26">Yet despite these incredible adaptations, there are changes unfolding in their habitats too rapidly for sea lions to handle.</s>
 <s id="27">As climate change warms the oceans, certain toxic algae species thrive.</s>
 <s id="28">This algae is harmless to the fish who eat it, but for the sea lions which ingest those fish, the algae’s domoic acid can trigger seizures and brain damage.</s>
 <s id="29">Changing ocean conditions keep this algae blooming year round, causing more and more sea lions to wash up on beaches.</s>
 <s id="30">This tragic discovery is just one of the many ways the health of aquatic animal communities can help us better understand Earth’s oceans.</s>
 <s id="31">These red flags help us take action to protect ourselves and other maritime mammals.</s>
 <s id="32">And the more we can learn about the changing ocean that sea lions inhabit, the better equipped we’ll be to help these clever creatures thrive.</s>
</text>
