<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <p id="p1">
  <s id="1.1">Alright.</s>
  <s id="1.2">I have a close, tight-knit circle of friends.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="2">We're all in different cities and we're all in different areas, from local news to city government to law, financial services ...</s>
 <s id="3">And despite those different areas, we seem to share similar stories of workplace drama.</s>
 <s id="4">Now, I define workplace drama as an annoyance that adds additional stress to the job.</s>
 <s id="5">So again, it's when people get on your nerves, not the job itself.</s>
 <s id="6">So as we're going through these stories, I'm realizing there has to be a better way for us to coexist with our coworkers without this much drama.</s>
 <s id="7">So I created a few steps that have been working for me, and I'm happy to share them with you guys today.</s>
 <s id="8">Step 1: rewind and reflect, also known as, "What did I do?"</s>
 <s id="9">I want you guys to all replay your most recent workplace drama situation in your head like a movie.</s>
 <s id="10">Ignore all of the emotion and just focus on you.</s>
 <s id="11">But for now, let's just think about this hypothetical: say you're on a group project, you each have your own individual assignments and then you all divide up the work.</s>
 <s id="12">But then someone becomes unresponsive -- not answering calls, they go ghost.</s>
 <s id="13">Then you or someone else has to now pick up that additional slack.</s>
 <s id="14">So in a brief, small, very tiny lapse in judgment, you vent to the nearby coworker.</s>
 <s id="15">Then all of a sudden, your ghost comes back, and they surprisingly know everything you just said.</s>
 <s id="16">(Laughter) Now, what did I do in this situation?</s>
 <s id="17">I vented to someone who was not my confidant.</s>
 <s id="18">Why would I do that?</s>
 <s id="19">Sometimes we create this unspoken bond with people that only exists in our heads.</s>
 <s id="20">They don't owe me their discretion.</s>
 <s id="21">I just assumed it was there.</s>
 <s id="22">So we're not going to go down a rabbit hole, trying to figure out why they did that.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">It doesn't matter.</s>
  <s id="23.2">They did it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="24">But the goal in this step is self-reflection.</s>
 <s id="25">We need to focus on what did we do so we can avoid it in the future.</s>
 <s id="26">Step 2: come back to reality, also known as, "It needs to stop."</s>
 <s id="27">(Laughter) So you guys ever think about problems before you get to work?</s>
 <s id="28">Oh -- it's just me?</s>
 <s id="29">(Laughter) Well, I'm guilty of it.</s>
 <s id="30">I think about all of these situations in my head, and then I get mad just thinking about it.</s>
 <s id="31">So I'm telling myself, "No, you're just being prepared, Stacy."</s>
 <s id="32">(Laughter) "You are just making sure that you can handle whatever they're about to throw at you."</s>
 <s id="33">But you're not.</s>
 <s id="34">What you're really doing is setting yourself up and creating this anxiety in your head that doesn't exist.</s>
 <s id="35">Then we also have to be careful about listening to other people's made-up scenarios.</s>
 <s id="36">Here's what I mean.</s>
 <s id="37">Let's say you're in the break room, and you're talking to some coworkers.</s>
 <s id="38">Then, all of a sudden, another coworker comes in.</s>
 <s id="39">Now, they seem to just be in deep thought -- not overly cheerful, but they're not rude.</s>
 <s id="40">They come in, they walk out.</s>
 <s id="41">Then the coworkers over here begin to diagnose what they feel is wrong with that person.</s>
 <s id="42">They're saying things like, "Oh, they're just mad they didn't get the job."</s>
 <s id="43">Or they're saying, "Oh, no, no, no -- during this season, they're just always upset."</s>
 <s id="44">And you're sitting here like, yep, that must be it.</s>
 <s id="45">You're listening to this as if this is facts.</s>
 <s id="46">Meanwhile, this coworker can be in deep thought about literally anything.</s>
 <s id="47">They could have just opened a pack of Starburst, got four yellows back-to-back, and they're just trying to figure out what happened.</s>
 <s id="48">(Laughter) (Applause) But you're over here listening.</s>
 <s id="49">And you're listening to their made-up scenario that now can impact how you choose to interact with that person throughout the day.</s>
 <s id="50">Whether we're creating fake stories in our head or listening to other people's made-up stories, it needs to stop.</s>
 <s id="51">The goal in this step: stop stressing over things that haven't happened.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">Alright.</s>
  <s id="52.2">Step 3: vent and release.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="53">It's good to have a vent buddy.</s>
 <s id="54">This is your coach, your cheerleader, your therapist, whatever you need them to be in the moment.</s>
 <s id="55">This is not like that person in Step 1 that just happened to be in earshot.</s>
 <s id="56">You have an established relationship with your vent buddy.</s>
 <s id="57">Now, here's another scenario.</s>
 <s id="58">You're getting ready to tell a customer or a client something that they just don't want to hear.</s>
 <s id="59">So, as you're in the middle of this spiel, up comes another coworker, and they interrupt you and then says the exact same thing you were saying.</s>
 <s id="60">You can't make a scene in front of a customer.</s>
 <s id="61">So you just have to sit back, "Mm-hmm," and just listen as they do this.</s>
 <s id="62">And you're burning up inside.</s>
 <s id="63">So what do we do?</s>
 <s id="64">We go to our vent buddy.</s>
 <p id="p65">
  <s id="65.1">We talk about it.</s>
  <s id="65.2">We get mad.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p66">
  <s id="66.1">And that's the time for that.</s>
  <s id="66.2">Get mad.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="67">Get angry.</s>
 <s id="68">Curse, scream, do whatever you need to do to get it out.</s>
 <s id="69">Now here's the hard part: you then have to switch that tone to positivity.</s>
 <s id="70">I truly believe in positive and negative energy, and it has a way of controlling our moods throughout the day.</s>
 <s id="71">You've got to think of things like, "OK, where do I go from here?</s>
 <s id="72">What can I do differently?"</s>
 <s id="73">And then, if you're the vent buddy, it's your responsibility to lead your friend back to the positive.</s>
 <s id="74">Now, the other hard part: you have to then apply those learnings to the situation.</s>
 <s id="75">You can't carry that resentment around.</s>
 <s id="76">If you do, that one-off situation now becomes a pattern.</s>
 <s id="77">Pattern behavior is harder to ignore than a one-off situation.</s>
 <s id="78">The goal in this step is, "Let's turn our vent session into a productive conversation."</s>
 <s id="79">Step 4: learn a new language, also known as, "We need to talk."</s>
 <s id="80">Guys, I personally don't like to pick up the phone at work.</s>
 <s id="81">I just don't.</s>
 <s id="82">I feel like whatever you need to say to me can be an instant message or an email.</s>
 <s id="83">That is my work language.</s>
 <s id="84">(Laughter) The only problem with that, you can't hear tone through an email.</s>
 <s id="85">I read emails the same way I speak, so I'm pretty sure I've misinterpreted some tones before, unless I know you.</s>
 <s id="86">So here's an example.</s>
 <s id="87">I'm going to show you guys an email, and I want you to read it, and then I'm going to read it out loud.</s>
 <s id="88">Alright, that was fast enough, you should have read it.</s>
 <s id="89">(Laughter) "Stacy, Thank you for reaching out about my group.</s>
 <s id="90">At this time, we will not need any additional support.</s>
 <s id="91">Going forward, if I feel we need help, I'll ask, you won't have to reach out.</s>
 <s id="92">Per my last email (attached below), I've outlined what I do, and what you do, so we can avoid this in the future.</s>
 <s id="93">As always, thank you for your partnership!!"</s>
 <s id="94">Guys ...</s>
 <s id="95">(Laughter) That's how you read it?</s>
 <s id="96">(Laughter) Guys, there are certain words in there that if you hear or if you see in an email, it is safe to assume they typed it with their middle fingers.</s>
 <p id="p97">
  <s id="97.1">(Laughter) I didn't know it then.</s>
  <s id="97.2">I know it now.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p98">
  <s id="98.1">(Laughter) I think I messed up some people's emails.</s>
  <s id="98.2">They're correcting them.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="99">(Laughter) With all of that said, you have to know when it is time to pick up the phone.</s>
 <s id="100">You have to know when it is time to have a face-to-face.</s>
 <s id="101">And these face-to-face conversations are not easy.</s>
 <s id="102">They are difficult, but they are necessary.</s>
 <s id="103">The goal is to try to understand the other person's perspective.</s>
 <s id="104">So you'll start the conversation with things like, "OK, you got upset when I ..."</s>
 <s id="105">Or you'll say things like, "OK, you already had the situation handled, and then I ..."</s>
 <s id="106">So that way, you can see exactly where they're coming from.</s>
 <s id="107">Also, don't try to make people like you.</s>
 <p id="p108">
  <s id="108.1">We all have our own upbringings.</s>
  <s id="108.2">We all have our experiences.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="109">And we all have our own communication styles.</s>
 <s id="110">As the new generations are entering the workforce, we're also adapting to it.</s>
 <s id="111">Meetings are now emails.</s>
 <s id="112">Emails are now texts.</s>
 <s id="113">Off-sites are now Skype.</s>
 <s id="114">So as we're adjusting to that, we need to at least try to understand what type of style of communication they use.</s>
 <s id="115">The goal in that step is to really understand their work language and accept the fact that it may be different than yours.</s>
 <s id="116">Step 5: recognize and protect, also known as, "We need to take a walk."</s>
 <s id="117">So here's my last scenario from one of my teacher friends.</s>
 <s id="118">You're about to have a meeting with a parent, and prior to it, you and a coworker, you kind of discuss it, and the coworker tells you, "It's alright, I got your back.</s>
 <s id="119">I'm going to agree with your recommendations."</s>
 <s id="120">So you're kind of side-eyeing them because they've burned you before, but you've had the "we need to talk," so you're like, "We're in sync now, I'm going to trust them."</s>
 <s id="121">You go through the meeting, the parent disagrees with you, and like clockwork, the coworker agrees with the parent in front of you, making you look ridiculous.</s>
 <s id="122">Again, we can't make a scene in front of people, right?</s>
 <s id="123">So you've got to hold it in.</s>
 <s id="124">And then, after the meeting, that same coworker has all the audacity, comes up to you and says, "Crazy meeting, right?"</s>
 <s id="125">(Laughter) Yeah.</s>
 <p id="p126">
  <s id="126.1">They're testing you now.</s>
  <s id="126.2">It's a test.</s>
  <s id="126.3">(Laughs) So that's the perfect time to just go off, right?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="127">This is a repeat offender.</s>
 <s id="128">(Laughter) You walked away, and they came back with it.</s>
 <s id="129">But we're trying to avoid workplace drama, not take a cannonball leap into it, so we have to walk away.</s>
 <s id="130">You lead that conversation by taking the first available exit.</s>
 <s id="131">You're not doing this for them.</s>
 <s id="132">You're doing this for you.</s>
 <s id="133">You have to protect your energy.</s>
 <s id="134">Don't try to figure out why they would do this, and no more coming-to-Jesus conversations.</s>
 <s id="135">It is what it is, they did what they did, and given the opportunity, they'd probably do it again.</s>
 <s id="136">But you now know that.</s>
 <s id="137">You now recognize that.</s>
 <s id="138">So that way, you can act accordingly.</s>
 <s id="139">We typically try to set expectations -- our expectations -- on other people, and then get disappointed when they don't follow through.</s>
 <s id="140">We have to learn to accept people where they are and adjust ourselves to handle those situations.</s>
 <s id="141">The goal in this step is to recognize when it is time to professionally walk away from someone.</s>
 <s id="142">Guys, I realize these steps may come off as saying, "Take the high road."</s>
 <p id="p143">
  <s id="143.1">And people always say it.</s>
  <s id="143.2">"Just take the high road."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="144">And they describe it as some elegant path of righteousness filled with rainbows and unicorns.</s>
 <s id="145">It's not that.</s>
 <s id="146">It's embarrassing.</s>
 <s id="147">It's humiliating.</s>
 <s id="148">It leaves this knot of resentment in the pit of your stomach.</s>
 <s id="149">And as you're traveling down this amazing high road, you see billboards of things you shoulda said and things you shoulda did.</s>
 <s id="150">You go over there and you look at the easy road, and they're chillin', not worried about a thing.</s>
 <s id="151">But I have to admit, the more I travel down this road, it does get a little easier.</s>
 <s id="152">Petty situations, they don't bother me as much.</s>
 <s id="153">I learn little nuggets here and there.</s>
 <s id="154">And as I continue down this path, there seem to be more opportunities waiting for me.</s>
 <s id="155">I have like-minded people who want to connect with me, projects that people want me on, leaders reaching out because they heard about me through someone else.</s>
 <s id="156">And the best part?</s>
 <s id="157">The need to even look at the easy road is no longer there.</s>
 <s id="158">Guys, we're not going to change the way adults act in the workplace.</s>
 <s id="159">We are not.</s>
 <s id="160">And for that reason, there will always be workplace drama.</s>
 <s id="161">But if we stick to these steps and put in the work that comes with it, we can learn to avoid it.</s>
 <s id="162">Guys, thank you for being my vent buddies.</s>
 <s id="163">(Laughter) And thank you so much for your time.</s>
 <s id="164">(Applause)</s>
</text>
