<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm the weekly tech critic for the New York Times.</s>
 <s id="2">I review gadgets and stuff.</s>
 <s id="3">And mostly what good dads should be doing this time of year is nestling with their kids and decorating the Christmas tree.</s>
 <s id="4">What I'm mostly doing this year is going on cable TV and answering the same question: "What are the tech trends for next year?"</s>
 <s id="5">And I'm like, "Didn't we just go through this last year?"</s>
 <s id="6">But I'm going to pick the one that interests me most, and that is the completed marriage of the cell phone and the Internet.</s>
 <s id="7">You know, I found that volcano on Google Images, not realizing how much it makes me look like the cover of Dianetics.</s>
 <s id="8">(Laughter) Anyway, this all started a few years ago, when they started carrying your voice over the Internet rather than over a phone line, and we've come a long way since that.</s>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">But that was interesting in itself.</s>
  <s id="9.2">This is companies like Vonage.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="10">Basically you take an ordinary telephone, you plug it into this little box that they give you and the box plugs into your cable modem.</s>
 <s id="11">Now, it works just like a regular phone.</s>
 <p id="p12">
  <s id="12.1">So you can pick up the phone, you hear a dial tone, but its just a fake-out.</s>
  <s id="12.2">It's a WAV file of a dial tone, just to reassure you that the world hasn't ended.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">It could be anything.</s>
  <s id="13.2">It could be salsa music or a comedy routine -- it doesn't matter.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">The little box has your phone number.</s>
 <s id="15">So that's really cool -- you can take it to London or Siberia, and your next door neighbor can dial your home number and your phone will ring, because it's got everything in the box.</s>
 <s id="16">They've got every feature known to man in there, because adding a new feature is just software.</s>
 <s id="17">And as a result of Voice Over IP -- I hate that term -- Voice Over Internet -- land-line home-phone service has gone down 30 percent in the last three years.</s>
 <s id="18">I mean, no self-respecting college kid has home phone service anymore.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">This is what college kids are more likely to have.</s>
  <s id="19.2">It's the most popular VOIP service in the world: It's Skype.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">It's a free program you download for your Mac or PC, and you make free phone calls anywhere in the world The downside is that you have to wear a headset like a nerd.</s>
 <s id="21">It's not your phone -- it's your computer.</s>
 <s id="22">But nonetheless, if you're a college kid and you have no money, believe me, this is better than trying to use your cell phone.</s>
 <s id="23">It's really cute seeing middle-aged people like me, try out Skype for the first time, which is usually when their kid goes away for a semester abroad.</s>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">They don't want to pay the international fees, so they're like, "Timmy!</s>
  <s id="24.2">Is that you?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="25">(Laughter) It's really cute.</s>
 <s id="26">But I -- at least it was when I did it -- (Laughter) I think where VOIP is really going to get interesting is when they start putting it on cell phones.</s>
 <s id="27">Imagine if you had an ordinary cell phone, and any time you were in a wireless hotspot -- free calls anywhere in the world, never pay the cellular company a nickel.</s>
 <s id="28">It'd be really, really cool -- and yet, even though the technology for this has been available for five years, incredibly, the number of standard cell phones offered by US carriers with free VOIP is zero!</s>
 <s id="29">I can't figure out why!</s>
 <p id="p30">
  <s id="30.1">(Laughter) Actually, I need to update that.</s>
  <s id="30.2">There's one now.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="31">And it's so interesting that I thought I would tell you about it.</s>
 <s id="32">It comes from T-Mobile.</s>
 <s id="33">And I am not paid by T-Mobile.</s>
 <s id="34">I'm not plugging T-Mobile.</s>
 <s id="35">The New York Times has very rigid policies about that.</s>
 <s id="36">Ever since that Jayson Blair jerk ruined it for all of us.</s>
 <s id="37">(Laughter) Basically, the reason you haven't heard about this program is because it was introduced last year on June 29.</s>
 <s id="38">Does anyone remember what else happened on June 29 last year?</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">It was the iPhone.</s>
  <s id="39.2">The iPhone came out that day.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">I'm like, can you imagine being the T-Mobile PR lady?</s>
  <s id="40.2">You know?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="41">"Hi, we have an announcement to -- WAH!!!"</s>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">(Laughter) But it's actually really, really cool.</s>
  <s id="42.2">You have a choice of phones, and we're not talking smartphones -- ordinary phones, including a Blackberry, that have Wi-Fi.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="43">The deal is, any time you're in a Wi-Fi hotspot, all your calls are free.</s>
 <s id="44">And when you're out of the hotspot, you're on the regular cellular network.</s>
 <s id="45">You're thinking, "Well, how often am I in a hotspot?"</s>
 <s id="46">The answer is, "All the time!"</s>
 <s id="47">Because they give you a regular wireless router that works with the phone, for your house.</s>
 <s id="48">Which is really ingenious, because we all know that T-Mobile is the most pathetic carrier.</s>
 <s id="49">They have coverage like the size of my thumbnail.</s>
 <p id="p50">
  <s id="50.1">(Laughter) But it's a hundred million dollars to put up one of those towers.</s>
  <s id="50.2">Right?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p51">
  <s id="51.1">They don't have that kind of money.</s>
  <s id="51.2">Instead they give each of us a seven-dollar-and-95-cent box.</s>
  <s id="51.3">They're like a stealth tower installation program.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="52">We're putting it in our homes for them!</s>
 <s id="53">Anyway, they have Wi-Fi phones in Europe.</s>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">But the thing that T-Mobile did that nobody's done before is, when you're on a call an you move from Wi-Fi into cellular range, the call is handed off in mid-syllable, seamlessly.</s>
  <s id="54.2">I'll show you the advanced technologies we use at the New York Times to test this gear.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">This is me with a camcorder on a phone going like this.</s>
 <p id="p56">
  <s id="56.1">(Laughter) As I walk out of the house from my Wi-Fi hotspot into the cellular network on a call with my wife -- look at the upper left.</s>
  <s id="56.2">That's the Wi-Fi signal.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="57">(Video): Jennifer Pogue: Hello?</s>
 <s id="58">David Pogue: Hi babes, it's me.</s>
 <s id="59">JP: Oh, hi darling, how are you?</s>
 <p id="p60">
  <s id="60.1">DP: You're on Wi-Fi.</s>
  <s id="60.2">How does it sound?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="61">JP: Oh, it sounds pretty good.</s>
 <p id="p62">
  <s id="62.1">Now, I'm leaving the house.</s>
  <s id="62.2">DP: I'm going for a walk -- do you mind?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p63">
  <s id="63.1">JP: No not at all.</s>
  <s id="63.2">I'm having a great day with the kids.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="64">DP: What are you guys doing?</s>
 <s id="65">Right there!</s>
 <s id="66">It just changed to the cellular tower in mid-call.</s>
 <p id="p67">
  <s id="67.1">I don't know why my wife says I never listen to her.</s>
  <s id="67.2">I don't get that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="68">(Laughter) The bottom line is that the boundaries, because of the Internet plus cell phone, are melting.</s>
 <s id="69">The cool thing about the T-Mobile phones is that although switching technologies is very advanced, the billing technology has not caught up.</s>
 <s id="70">So what I mean is that you can start a call in your house in the Wi-Fi hotspot, you can get in your car and talk until the battery's dead -- which would be like 10 minutes -- (Laughter) And the call will continue to be free.</s>
 <p id="p71">
  <s id="71.1">Because they don't, they haven't -- well, no, wait!</s>
  <s id="71.2">Not so fast.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="72">It also works the other way.</s>
 <s id="73">So if you start a call on your cellular network and you come home, you keep being billed.</s>
 <p id="p74">
  <s id="74.1">Which is why most people with this service get into the habit of saying, "Hey, I just got home.</s>
  <s id="74.2">Can I call you right back?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="75">Now you get it.</s>
 <s id="76">It's also true that if you use one of these phones overseas, it doesn't know what Internet hotspot you're in.</s>
 <p id="p77">
  <s id="77.1">On the Internet nobody knows you're a dog, right?</s>
  <s id="77.2">Nobody knows you're in Pakistan.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p78">
  <s id="78.1">You can make free unlimited calls home to the US with these phones.</s>
  <s id="78.2">So, very, very interesting.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="79">This is another favorite of mine.</s>
 <s id="80">Does anyone here have a working cell phone that's on, with coverage, who can make a call right now without a lot of fussing?</s>
 <p id="p81">
  <s id="81.1">OK.</s>
  <s id="81.2">Would you call me please right now?</s>
  <s id="81.3">[Phone number given.]</s>
  <s id="81.4">And don't you all call me at three a.m. asking me to fix your printer.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="82">(Laughter) I have two cell phones, so this going to be very odd, if it works.</s>
 <p id="p83">
  <s id="83.1">I should know not to do technology demos in front of an audience.</s>
  <s id="83.2">It's just, like, absurd.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p84">
  <s id="84.1">This one is going off.</s>
  <s id="84.2">And -- oh, I have the ringer off.</s>
  <s id="84.3">Tsh!</s>
  <s id="84.4">Great.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p85">
  <s id="85.1">Anyway, this one is also going off.</s>
  <s id="85.2">So they're both ringing at the same time.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="86">Excuse me one second.</s>
 <s id="87">Hello?</s>
 <p id="p88">
  <s id="88.1">Oh.</s>
  <s id="88.2">Where are you calling from?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p89">
  <s id="89.1">No, no just kidding.</s>
  <s id="89.2">There he is.</s>
  <s id="89.3">Thank you very much for doing that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="90">I didn't even know it was you -- I was looking at this guy.</s>
 <p id="p91">
  <s id="91.1">Oh great!</s>
  <s id="91.2">Yeah.</s>
  <s id="91.3">Yeah you can all stop calling now!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p92">
  <s id="92.1">(Laughter) All right!</s>
  <s id="92.2">We've made the point.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p93">
  <s id="93.1">All right.</s>
  <s id="93.2">Ringer off.</s>
  <s id="93.3">Everyone wants in on the action.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="94">(Laughter) So this is Grand Central at work -- it's a -- oh, for gods sake!</s>
 <s id="95">(Laughter) I have your numbers now!</s>
 <s id="96">(Laughter) You will pay.</s>
 <s id="97">Grand Central is this really brilliant idea where they give you a new phone number, and then at that point one phone number rings all your phones at once.</s>
 <s id="98">Your home phone, your work phone, your cell phone, your yacht phone (this is the EG crowd).</s>
 <s id="99">(Laughter) The beauty of that is you never miss a call.</s>
 <s id="100">I know a lot of you are like, "Ooh, I don't want to be reached at any hour."</s>
 <s id="101">But the beauty is it's all going through the internet, so you get all of these really cool features -- like you can say, I want these people to be able to call me only during these hours.</s>
 <p id="p102">
  <s id="102.1">And I want these people to hear this greeting, "Hi boss, I'm out making us both some money.</s>
  <s id="102.2">Leave a message."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="103">And then your wife calls, and, "Hi honey, leave me a message."</s>
 <s id="104">Very, very customizable.</s>
 <s id="105">Google bought it, and they've been working on it for a year.</s>
 <s id="106">They're supposed to come out with it very shortly in a public method.</s>
 <s id="107">By the way, this is something that really bothers me.</s>
 <p id="p108">
  <s id="108.1">I don't know if you realize this.</s>
  <s id="108.2">When you call 411 on your cell phone, they charge you two bucks.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p109">
  <s id="109.1">Did you know that?</s>
  <s id="109.2">It's an outrage.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="110">I actually got a photograph of the Verizon employee right there.</s>
 <s id="111">I'm going to tell you how to avoid that now.</s>
 <s id="112">What you're going to use is Google Cellular.</s>
 <s id="113">It's totally free -- there's not even ads.</s>
 <s id="114">If you know how to send a text message, you can get the same information for free.</s>
 <p id="p115">
  <s id="115.1">I'm about to change your life.</s>
  <s id="115.2">So here's me doing it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="116">You send a text message to the word "Google," which turns out to be 46645.</s>
 <s id="117">Leave off the last "e" for savings.</s>
 <s id="118">Anyway, so lets say you need a drugstore near Chicago.</s>
 <s id="119">You type "pharmacy Chicago," or the zip code.</s>
 <s id="120">You hit send, and in five seconds, they will send you back the two closest drugstores, complete with name address and phone number.</s>
 <s id="121">Here it comes.</s>
 <s id="122">And it's already written down -- so, like, if you're driving, you don't have to do one of these things, "Uh huh, uh huh, uh huh."</s>
 <s id="123">It works with weather, too.</s>
 <s id="124">You can say "Weather," and the name of the city you're going to travel to.</s>
 <s id="125">And then in five seconds, they send you back the complete weather forecast for that town.</s>
 <s id="126">Shortly I'll tell you why I was in Milan.</s>
 <p id="p127">
  <s id="127.1">Here we go.</s>
  <s id="127.2">And those are just the beginning.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p128">
  <s id="128.1">These are all the different things that you can text to Google and they will -- yeah!</s>
  <s id="128.2">You're all trying to write this down.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p129">
  <s id="129.1">That's cute.</s>
  <s id="129.2">I do have an email address.</s>
  <s id="129.3">You can just ask me.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p130">
  <s id="130.1">It's absolutely phenomenal.</s>
  <s id="130.2">The only downside is that it requires you to know how to text -- send a text message.</s>
  <s id="130.3">Nobody over 40 knows how to do that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="131">So I'm going to teach you something even better.</s>
 <s id="132">This is called Google Info.</s>
 <s id="133">They've just launched this voice-activated version of the same thing.</s>
 <s id="134">It's speech recognition like you've never heard before.</s>
 <s id="135">So lets say I'm in Monterey, and I want what?</s>
 <p id="p136">
  <s id="136.1">I want to find what?</s>
  <s id="136.2">Bagels.</s>
  <s id="136.3">OK.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="137">Google: Say the business and the city and state.</s>
 <s id="138">DP: Bagels, Monterey, California.</s>
 <s id="139">I got the Chinese line.</s>
 <s id="140">(Laughter) Google: Bagels, Monterey, California.</s>
 <s id="141">Top eight results: Number one, Bagel Bakery on El Dorado Street.</s>
 <s id="142">To select number one, you can press one or say "number one."</s>
 <s id="143">Number two: Bagel Bakery, commissary department.</s>
 <p id="p144">
  <s id="144.1">Number Two.</s>
  <s id="144.2">Number Two.</s>
  <s id="144.3">Two.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="145">(Laughter) Why do I listen to people in the audience?</s>
 <p id="p146">
  <s id="146.1">Well anyway -- oh!</s>
  <s id="146.2">Here we go!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="147">Google: ... commissary department on McClellan Avenue, Monterey.</s>
 <s id="148">I'll connect you, or say "details," or "go back."</s>
 <p id="p149">
  <s id="149.1">DP: He's connecting me!</s>
  <s id="149.2">He doesn't even tell me the phone number.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p150">
  <s id="150.1">He's just connecting me directly.</s>
  <s id="150.2">It's like having a personal valet.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="151">Google: Hold on.</s>
 <s id="152">(Laughter) DP: Hi, could I have 400 with a schmear?</s>
 <s id="153">No, no, no -- just kidding, no no.</s>
 <s id="154">So anyway, you never even find out the number.</s>
 <s id="155">It's just so amazing.</s>
 <s id="156">And it has incredible, incredible accuracy.</s>
 <p id="p157">
  <s id="157.1">This is even more amazing.</s>
  <s id="157.2">Put this in your speed dial.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="158">This you can ask by voice any question.</s>
 <s id="159">Who won the 1958 World Series?</s>
 <s id="160">What's the recipe for a certain cocktail?</s>
 <s id="161">It's absolutely amazing -- and they text you back the answer.</s>
 <s id="162">I tried this this morning just to make sure it's still alive.</s>
 <s id="163">"Which actors have played James Bond?"</s>
 <s id="164">They text me back this: "Sean Connery, George Lazenby, Roger Moore, Timothy Dalton, Pierce Brosnan, Daniel Craig."</s>
 <p id="p165">
  <s id="165.1">Right!</s>
  <s id="165.2">And then I was trying to pretend I was like a Valley girl.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="166">I'm like, "What's the word that means you know, like, when the sun, the moon and the earth are, like, all in a line?"</s>
 <s id="167">Just to see how the recognition was.</s>
 <s id="168">They texted me back, "It's called a syzygy."</s>
 <s id="169">Which I knew, because it's the word that won me the Ohio spelling bee in 1976.</s>
 <p id="p170">
  <s id="170.1">You know, there's a lot of people wondering, "How on earth are they going to make money doing this?"</s>
  <s id="170.2">And the answer is: look at the last line.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="171">They put this teeny-weeny little ad, about 10 characters long.</s>
 <s id="172">And a lot of people also want to know, "How does it work?</s>
 <p id="p173">
  <s id="173.1">How can it be so good?</s>
  <s id="173.2">It's as though there is a human being on the other end of the line."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="174">Because there is one!</s>
 <s id="175">They have 10,000 people who are being paid 20 cents per answer.</s>
 <s id="176">As you can imagine, it's college kids and old people.</s>
 <s id="177">That's who can afford to do that.</s>
 <p id="p178">
  <s id="178.1">But it's a human being on the line.</s>
  <s id="178.2">And it's gotten me out of so many tough positions like, "When's the last flight out of Chicago?"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p179">
  <s id="179.1">You know.</s>
  <s id="179.2">It's just absolutely amazing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="180">Another thing that really bothers me about cell phones today -- this is probably my biggest pet peeve in all of technology.</s>
 <s id="181">When I call to leave you a message, I get 15 seconds of instructions from a third-grade teacher on Ambien!</s>
 <p id="p182">
  <s id="182.1">(Laughter) "To page this person ... "</s>
  <s id="182.2">Page?</s>
  <s id="182.3">What is this, 1975?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="183">Nobody has pagers anymore.</s>
 <s id="184">"You may begin speaking at the tone.</s>
 <p id="p185">
  <s id="185.1">When you have finished recording, you may hang up."</s>
  <s id="185.2">No!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="186">(Laughter) And then it gets worse: when I call to retrieve my messages, first of all: "You have 87 messages.</s>
 <p id="p187">
  <s id="187.1">To listen to your messages ... "</s>
  <s id="187.2">Why else am I calling?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="188">(Laughter) Of course I want to listen to the messages!</s>
 <p id="p189">
  <s id="189.1">(Laughter) Oh!</s>
  <s id="189.2">You all have cell phones too.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="190">So last year I went to Milan, Italy, and I got to speak to an audience of cellular executives from 200 countries around the world.</s>
 <p id="p191">
  <s id="191.1">And I said as a joke -- as a joke, I said, "I did the math.</s>
  <s id="191.2">Verizon has 70 million customers.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="192">If you check your voicemail twice a day, that's 100 million dollars a year.</s>
 <s id="193">I bet you guys are doing this just to run up our airtime, aren't you?"</s>
 <p id="p194">
  <s id="194.1">No chuckle.</s>
  <s id="194.2">They're like this -- (Laughter) Where is the outrage, people?</s>
  <s id="194.3">Rise up!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p195">
  <s id="195.1">(Laughter) Sorry.</s>
  <s id="195.2">I'm not bitter.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="196">(Laughter) So now I'm going to tell you how to get out of that.</s>
 <s id="197">There are these services that transcribe your voicemail into text.</s>
 <s id="198">And they send it either to your email or as text messages to your phone.</s>
 <s id="199">It is a life-changer.</s>
 <s id="200">And by the way, they don't always get the words right, because it's over the phone and all that.</s>
 <s id="201">So they attach the audio file at the bottom of the email so you can listen to double-check.</s>
 <p id="p202">
  <s id="202.1">The services are called things like Spinvox, Phonetag -- this is the one I use -- Callwave.</s>
  <s id="202.2">A lot of people say, "How are they doing this?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="203">I don't really want people listening in to my calls."</s>
 <s id="204">The executives at these companies told me, "Well we use a proprietary B-to-B, best-of-breed, peer-to-peer soluti -- " you know.</s>
 <s id="205">I think basically it's like these guys in India with headsets, you know, listening in.</s>
 <p id="p206">
  <s id="206.1">The reason I think that is that on the first day I tried one of these services, I got two voicemail messages.</s>
  <s id="206.2">One was from a guy named Michael Stevenson, which shouldn't be that hard to transcribe, and it was misspelled.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p207">
  <s id="207.1">The other was from my video producer at the Times, whose name is Vijaiy Singh, with the silent 'h'.</s>
  <s id="207.2">Nailed that one.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="208">(Laughter) So you be the judge.</s>
 <s id="209">(Laughter) Anyway, this service, Callwave, promises that it's all software -- nobody is listening to your messages.</s>
 <s id="210">And they also promise that they're going to transcribe only the gist of your messages.</s>
 <s id="211">(Laughter) So I thought I'd see how that goes.</s>
 <s id="212">This is me testing it out.</s>
 <s id="213">(Video): Hello, this is Michael.</s>
 <p id="p214">
  <s id="214.1">Hope you're doing well.</s>
  <s id="214.2">I'm fine here.</s>
  <s id="214.3">Everything's good.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="215">Hey, I was walking along the street and the sky was blue.</s>
 <s id="216">And your daughter broke her leg at soccer practice.</s>
 <s id="217">I'm going to have a sandwich for lunch.</s>
 <s id="218">She's in room -- emergency room 53W.</s>
 <s id="219">OK, talk to you later -- bye.</s>
 <s id="220">(Laughter) I love my job.</s>
 <s id="221">(Laughter) So a couple minutes later, this I got by email.</s>
 <p id="p222">
  <s id="222.1">It's a very good transcription.</s>
  <s id="222.2">But a couple minutes after that, I got the text message version.</s>
  <s id="222.3">Now remember, a text message can only be 160 characters long.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="223">So it had better be the gist of the gist, right?</s>
 <p id="p224">
  <s id="224.1">I'm not kidding you.</s>
  <s id="224.2">The message said, "Was walking along the street" and "sky was blue" and "emergency"!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="225">(Laughter) What the f -- ?</s>
 <s id="226">(Laughter) Well I guess that was the gist.</s>
 <s id="227">(Laughter) And lastly, I just have to talk about this one.</s>
 <p id="p228">
  <s id="228.1">This is my favorite of all time.</s>
  <s id="228.2">It's called Popularitydialer.com.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="229">Basically, you're going to go on some iffy date, or a potentially bad meeting.</s>
 <s id="230">So you go and you type in your phone number, and at the exact minute where you want to be called -- (Laughter) And at that moment your phone will ring.</s>
 <p id="p231">
  <s id="231.1">And you're like, "I'm sorry.</s>
  <s id="231.2">I've got to take this."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="232">The really beautiful thing is, you know how when somebody's sitting next to you, sometimes they can sort of hear a little bit of the caller.</s>
 <s id="233">So they give you a choice of what you want to hear on the other end.</s>
 <s id="234">Here's the girlfriend.</s>
 <s id="235">Phone: Hey you, what's going on?</s>
 <s id="236">DP: I'm kinda, like, giving a talk right now.</s>
 <s id="237">Phone: Well, that's good.</s>
 <s id="238">DP: What are you doing?</s>
 <s id="239">Phone: I was just wondering what you were up to.</s>
 <s id="240">DP: Right, I can't really talk right now.</s>
 <s id="241">This is the -- I love this -- the boss call.</s>
 <s id="242">Phone: Hey, this is Mr. Johnson calling from the office.</s>
 <s id="243">DP: Oh, hi, sir.</s>
 <p id="p244">
  <s id="244.1">Phone: Did you complete that thing about a month ago?</s>
  <s id="244.2">That photocopier training?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="245">DP: Oh -- sorry I forgot.</s>
 <s id="246">Phone: Yeah, well so when was the last time you used the photocopier?</s>
 <s id="247">DP: It was like three weeks ago.</s>
 <s id="248">Phone: Well, I don't know if you heard, you might have heard from Lenny, but -- (Laughter) I think the biggest change when Internet met phone was with the iPhone.</s>
 <s id="249">Not my finest moment in New York Times journalism.</s>
 <s id="250">It was when in the fall of 2006, I explained why Apple would never do a cell phone.</s>
 <p id="p251">
  <s id="251.1">(Laughter) I looked like a moron.</s>
  <s id="251.2">However, my logic was good, because -- I don't know if you realize this, but -- until the iPhone came along, the carriers -- Verizon, AT&amp;amp;T, Cingular -- held veto power over every aspect of every design of every phone.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="252">I know the people who worked on the Treo.</s>
 <p id="p253">
  <s id="253.1">They went around to these carriers and said, "Look at these cool features."</s>
  <s id="253.2">And Verizon is like, "Hmm, no.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="254">I don't think so."</s>
 <s id="255">It was not very conducive to innovation.</s>
 <s id="256">What I didn't anticipate was that Steve Jobs went around and said, "Tell you what -- I'll give you a five-year exclusive if you'll let me design this phone in peace -- and you won't even see it till it's done."</s>
 <s id="257">Actually, even so, he was turned down by Verizon and others.</s>
 <s id="258">Finally Cingular said OK.</s>
 <s id="259">I'm going to talk about the effect of the iPhone.</s>
 <p id="p260">
  <s id="260.1">Please don't corner me at the party tonight and go, "What are you?</s>
  <s id="260.2">An Apple fan boy?"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p261">
  <s id="261.1">- you know.</s>
  <s id="261.2">I'm not.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p262">
  <s id="262.1">You can see what I said about it.</s>
  <s id="262.2">It's a flawed masterpiece.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p263">
  <s id="263.1">It's got bad things and good things.</s>
  <s id="263.2">Lets all acknowledge that right now.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p264">
  <s id="264.1">But it did change a few things.</s>
  <s id="264.2">The first thing it changed was that all those carriers saw that they sold 10 million of these things in a year.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="265">And they said, "Oh my gosh, maybe we've been doing it wrong.</s>
 <s id="266">Maybe we should let phone designers design the phones."</s>
 <s id="267">(Applause) Another thing was that it let 10 million people, for the first time, experience being online all the time.</s>
 <s id="268">Not using these 60-dollar-a-month cellular cards for their laptops.</s>
 <s id="269">I don't understand why we're not there yet.</s>
 <p id="p270">
  <s id="270.1">When I'm an old man, I'm going to tell my grandchildren, "When I was your age, if I wanted to check my email, I used to drive around town looking for a coffee shop.</s>
  <s id="270.2">I did!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="271">(Laughter) "We had wireless base stations that could broadcast -- yay, about 150 feet across."</s>
 <p id="p272">
  <s id="272.1">(Laughter) It's absurd.</s>
  <s id="272.2">We have power outlets in every room of every building.</s>
  <s id="272.3">We have running water.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="273">What's the problem?</s>
 <s id="274">Anyway -- but this teaches people what it's like.</s>
 <s id="275">You have to go to YouTube and type in "iPhone Shuffle."</s>
 <s id="276">This guy did a mock video of one that's one inch square, like the real iPod Shuffle.</s>
 <s id="277">It's like, "It only has one button.</s>
 <s id="278">Touch it and it dials a number at random."</s>
 <s id="279">(Laughter) "Who the hell is this?"</s>
 <s id="280">(Laughter) But the other thing it did is it opened up this idea of an app store.</s>
 <s id="281">It downloads right to the phone.</s>
 <s id="282">And you can use the tilt sensor to steer this car using this game.</s>
 <s id="283">These programs can use all the components of the iPhone -- the touch screen.</s>
 <s id="284">This is the Etch-A-Sketch program -- the theme of EG 2008.</s>
 <s id="285">You know how you erase it?</s>
 <p id="p286">
  <s id="286.1">Of course.</s>
  <s id="286.2">You shake it.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p287">
  <s id="287.1">Right, of course.</s>
  <s id="287.2">We shake it to erase, like this.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="288">They have 10,000 of these programs.</s>
 <p id="p289">
  <s id="289.1">This is the translator program.</s>
  <s id="289.2">They have every language in the world.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="290">You type in what you want, and it gives you the translation.</s>
 <p id="p291">
  <s id="291.1">This is amazing.</s>
  <s id="291.2">This is Midomi.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="292">A song is running through your head -- you sing it into the thing: do do do do do, da da da da da da, da dum ...</s>
 <s id="293">OK, you tap, "Done" and it will find out the song and play it for you.</s>
 <p id="p294">
  <s id="294.1">I know.</s>
  <s id="294.2">It's insane, right?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p295">
  <s id="295.1">This is Pandora.</s>
  <s id="295.2">Free Internet radio.</s>
  <s id="295.3">Not just free Internet radio -- you type in a band or a song name.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="296">It will immediately play you that song or that band.</s>
 <s id="297">It has a thumbs-up and a thumbs-down.</s>
 <s id="298">You say if you like this song or not.</s>
 <s id="299">If you like it, it tries another song on you from a different band, with the same instrumentation, vocals, theme and tempo.</s>
 <p id="p300">
  <s id="300.1">If you like that one, or don't like it, you do thumbs-up and thumbs-down.</s>
  <s id="300.2">Over time it tailors the songs so that it completely stops playing bad songs.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="301">It eventually only plays songs you like.</s>
 <p id="p302">
  <s id="302.1">This is Urbanspoon.</s>
  <s id="302.2">You're in a city.</s>
  <s id="302.3">It knows from GPS where you're standing.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p303">
  <s id="303.1">You want to find a place to eat.</s>
  <s id="303.2">You shake it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="304">It proposes a restaurant.</s>
 <s id="305">It gives you the price, and the location and ratings.</s>
 <s id="306">Video: I'm not going all the way to Flushing.</s>
 <s id="307">Anyway, just amazing, amazing things.</s>
 <s id="308">Of course, its not just about the iPhone.</s>
 <s id="309">The iPhone broke the dyke, the wall.</s>
 <p id="p310">
  <s id="310.1">But now it's everybody else.</s>
  <s id="310.2">So Google has done their own Android operating system that will soon be on handsets -- phones from 34 companies.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="311">Touch screen -- very, very nice.</s>
 <s id="312">Also with its own app store, where you can download programs.</s>
 <p id="p313">
  <s id="313.1">This is amazing.</s>
  <s id="313.2">In the wake of all this, Verizon, the most calcified, corporate, conservative carrier of all, said, "You can use any phone you want on our network."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p314">
  <s id="314.1">I love the Wired headline: Pigs Fly, Hell Freezes Over and Verizon Opens Up Its Network -- No.</s>
  <s id="314.2">Really.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p315">
  <s id="315.1">So everything is changing.</s>
  <s id="315.2">We've entered a new world of innovation, where the cell phone becomes your laptop, customized the way you want it.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p316">
  <s id="316.1">Every cell phone is unique.</s>
  <s id="316.2">There is software that you can add on.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p317">
  <s id="317.1">Can I do one more one-minute song?</s>
  <s id="317.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="318">(Applause) Just to round it up -- this is the new Apple Power Music Stand.</s>
 <s id="319">It's only three pounds, or 12 if you install Microsoft Office.</s>
 <s id="320">(Laughter) Sorry, that was mean.</s>
 <s id="321">This is a song I did for the New York Times website as a music video.</s>
 <s id="322">Ladies and gentlemen, for seven blissful hours it was the number one video on YouTube.</s>
 <s id="323">(To the tune of "My Way") And now the end is near.</s>
 <s id="324">I'm sick to death of this old cell phone.</s>
 <s id="325">Bad sound, the signal's weak, the software stinks.</s>
 <s id="326">A made-in-Hell phone.</s>
 <s id="327">I've heard there's something new -- a million times more rad than my phone.</s>
 <s id="328">I too will join the cult.</s>
 <s id="329">I want an iPhone.</s>
 <p id="p330">
  <s id="330.1">Concerns -- I have a few.</s>
  <s id="330.2">It's got some flaws; we may just face it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="331">No keys, no memory card, the battery's sealed -- you can't replace it.</s>
 <s id="332">But God, this thing is sweet.</s>
 <s id="333">A multitouch, iPod, Wi-Fi phone.</s>
 <s id="334">You had me from, "Hello."</s>
 <s id="335">I want an iPhone.</s>
 <s id="336">I want to touch its precious screen.</s>
 <s id="337">I want to wipe the smudges clean.</s>
 <s id="338">I want my friends to look and drool.</s>
 <s id="339">I want to say, "Look -- now I'm cool" I stood in line and I'll get mine.</s>
 <s id="340">I want an iPhone.</s>
 <s id="341">For what is a man?</s>
 <p id="p342">
  <s id="342.1">What has he got?</s>
  <s id="342.2">If not iPhone, then he's got squat.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="343">It's all the things a phone should be.</s>
 <s id="344">Who cares if it's AT&amp;amp;T?</s>
 <s id="345">I took a stand, paid half a grand!</s>
 <s id="346">And I got an iPhone!</s>
 <p id="p347">
  <s id="347.1">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="347.2">Thank you very much.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="348">(Applause)</s>
</text>
