<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I was born in 1993 in the northern part of North Korea, in a town called Hyesan, which is on the border with China.</s>
 <s id="2">I had loving parents and one older sister.</s>
 <s id="3">Before I was even 10 years old, my father was sent to a labor camp for engaging in illegal trading.</s>
 <s id="4">Now, by "illegal trading" -- he was selling clogs, sugar, rice and later copper to feed us.</s>
 <s id="5">In 2007, my sister and I decided to escape.</s>
 <s id="6">She was 16 years old, and I was 13 years old.</s>
 <s id="7">I need you to understand what the word "escape" means in the context of North Korea.</s>
 <s id="8">We were all starving, and hunger means death in North Korea.</s>
 <s id="9">So it was the only option for us.</s>
 <s id="10">I didn't even understand the concept of escape, but I could see the lights from China at night, and I wondered if I go where the light is, I might be able to find a bowl of rice.</s>
 <s id="11">It's not like we had a grand plan or maps.</s>
 <s id="12">We did not know anything about what was going to happen.</s>
 <s id="13">Imagine your apartment building caught fire.</s>
 <s id="14">I mean, what would you do?</s>
 <s id="15">Would you stay there to be burned, or would you jump off out of the window and see what happens?</s>
 <s id="16">That's what we did.</s>
 <s id="17">We jumped out of the house instead of the fire.</s>
 <s id="18">North Korea is unimaginable.</s>
 <s id="19">It's very hard for me when people ask me what it feels like to live there.</s>
 <s id="20">To be honest, I tell you: you can't even imagine it.</s>
 <s id="21">The words in any language can't describe, because it's a totally different planet, as you cannot imagine your life on Mars right now.</s>
 <s id="22">For example, the word "love" has only one meaning: love for the Dear Leader.</s>
 <s id="23">There's no concept of romantic love in North Korea.</s>
 <s id="24">And if you don't know the words, that means you don't understand the concept, and therefore, you don't even realize that concept is even a possibility.</s>
 <s id="25">Let me give you another example.</s>
 <s id="26">Growing up in North Korea, we truly believed that our Dear Leader is an almighty god who can even read my thoughts.</s>
 <s id="27">I was even afraid to think in North Korea.</s>
 <s id="28">We are told that he's starving for us, and he's working tirelessly for us, and my heart just broke for him.</s>
 <s id="29">When I escaped to South Korea, people told me that he was actually a dictator, he had cars, many, many resorts, and he had an ultraluxurious life.</s>
 <s id="30">And then I remember looking at a picture of him, realizing for the first time that he is the largest guy in the picture.</s>
 <s id="31">(Laughter) And it hit me.</s>
 <s id="32">Finally, I realized he wasn't starving.</s>
 <s id="33">But I was never able to see that before, until someone told me that he was fat.</s>
 <s id="34">(Laughter) Really, someone had to teach me that he was fat.</s>
 <s id="35">If you have never practiced critical thinking, then you simply see what you're told to see.</s>
 <s id="36">The biggest question also people ask me is: "Why is there no revolution inside North Korea?</s>
 <s id="37">Are we dumb?</s>
 <s id="38">Why is there no revolution for 70 years of this oppression?"</s>
 <s id="39">And I say: If you don't know you're a slave, if you don't know you're isolated or oppressed, how do you fight to be free?</s>
 <s id="40">I mean, if you know you're isolated, that means you are not isolated.</s>
 <s id="41">Not knowing is the true definition of isolation, and that's why I never knew I was isolated when I was in North Korea.</s>
 <s id="42">I literally thought I was in the center of the universe.</s>
 <s id="43">So here is my idea worth spreading: a lot of people think humans inherently know what is right and wrong, the difference between justice and injustice, what we deserve and we don't deserve.</s>
 <s id="44">I tell them: BS.</s>
 <s id="45">(Laughter) (Applause) Everything, everything must be taught, including compassion.</s>
 <s id="46">If I see someone dying on the street right now, I will do anything to save that person.</s>
 <s id="47">But when I was in North Korea, I saw people dying and dead on the streets.</s>
 <s id="48">I felt nothing.</s>
 <s id="49">Not because I'm a psychopath, but because I never learned the concept of compassion.</s>
 <s id="50">Only, I felt compassion, empathy and sympathy in my heart after I learned the word "compassion" and the concept, and I feel them now.</s>
 <s id="51">Now I live in the United States as a free person.</s>
 <s id="52">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="53">(Applause) And recently, the leader of the free country, our President Trump, met with my former god.</s>
 <s id="54">And he decided human rights is not important enough to include in his agendas, and he did not talk about it.</s>
 <s id="55">And it scares me.</s>
 <s id="56">We live in a world right now where a dictator can be praised for executing his uncle, for killing his half brother, killing thousands of North Koreans.</s>
 <s id="57">And that was worthy of praise.</s>
 <s id="58">And also it made me think: perhaps we all need to be taught something new about freedom now.</s>
 <s id="59">Freedom is fragile.</s>
 <s id="60">I don't want to alarm you, but it is.</s>
 <s id="61">It only took three generations to make North Korea into George Orwell's "1984."</s>
 <s id="62">It took only three generations.</s>
 <s id="63">If we don't fight for human rights for the people who are oppressed right now who don't have a voice, as free people here, who will fight for us when we are not free?</s>
 <p id="p64">
  <s id="64.1">Machines?</s>
  <s id="64.2">Animals?</s>
  <s id="64.3">I don't know.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="65">I think it's wonderful that we care about climate change, animal rights, gender equality, all of these things.</s>
 <s id="66">The fact that we care about animals' rights, that means that's how beautiful our heart is, that we care about someone who cannot speak for themselves.</s>
 <s id="67">And North Koreans right now cannot speak for themselves.</s>
 <s id="68">They don't have internet in the 21st century.</s>
 <s id="69">We don't have electricity, and it is the darkest place on earth right now.</s>
 <s id="70">Now I want to say something to my fellow North Koreans who are living in that darkness.</s>
 <s id="71">They might not believe this, but I want to tell them that an alternative life is possible.</s>
 <s id="72">Be free.</s>
 <s id="73">From my experience, literally anything is possible.</s>
 <s id="74">I was bought, I was sold as a slave.</s>
 <s id="75">But now I'm here, and that is why I believe in miracles.</s>
 <s id="76">The one thing that I learned from history is that nothing is forever in this world.</s>
 <s id="77">And that is why we have every reason to be hopeful.</s>
 <s id="78">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="79">(Applause)</s>
</text>
