<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">We are drowning in news.</s>
 <s id="2">Reuters alone puts out three and a half million news stories a year.</s>
 <s id="3">That's just one source.</s>
 <s id="4">My question is: How many of those stories are actually going to matter in the long run?</s>
 <s id="5">That's the idea behind The Long News.</s>
 <s id="6">It's a project by The Long Now Foundation, which was founded by TEDsters including Kevin Kelly and Stewart Brand.</s>
 <s id="7">And what we're looking for is news stories that might still matter 50 or 100 or 10,000 years from now.</s>
 <s id="8">And when you look at the news through that filter, a lot falls by the wayside.</s>
 <s id="9">To take the top stories from the A.P. this last year, is this going to matter in a decade?</s>
 <s id="10">Or this?</s>
 <s id="11">Or this?</s>
 <s id="12">Really?</s>
 <s id="13">Is this going to matter in 50 or 100 years?</s>
 <s id="14">Okay, that was kind of cool.</s>
 <s id="15">(Laughter) But the top story of this past year was the economy, and I'm just betting that, sooner or later, this particular recession is going to be old news.</s>
 <s id="16">So, what kind of stories might make a difference for the future?</s>
 <s id="17">Well, let's take science.</s>
 <s id="18">Someday, little robots will go through our bloodstreams fixing things.</s>
 <s id="19">That someday is already here if you're a mouse.</s>
 <s id="20">Some recent stories: nanobees zap tumors with real bee venom; they're sending genes into the brain; a robot they built that can crawl through the human body.</s>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">What about resources?</s>
  <s id="21.2">How are we going to feed nine billion people?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="22">We're having trouble feeding six billion today.</s>
 <s id="23">As we heard yesterday, there's over a billion people hungry.</s>
 <s id="24">Britain will starve without genetically modified crops.</s>
 <s id="25">Bill Gates, fortunately, has bet a billion on [agricultural] research.</s>
 <s id="26">What about global politics?</s>
 <s id="27">The world's going to be very different when and if China sets the agenda, and they may.</s>
 <s id="28">They've overtaken the U.S. as the world's biggest car market, they've overtaken Germany as the largest exporter, and they've started doing DNA tests on kids to choose their careers.</s>
 <s id="29">We're finding all kinds of ways to push back the limits of what we know.</s>
 <s id="30">Some recent discoveries: There's an ant colony from Argentina that has now spread to every continent but Antarctica; there's a self-directed robot scientist that's made a discovery -- soon, science may no longer need us, and life may no longer need us either; a microbe wakes up after 120,000 years.</s>
 <s id="31">It seems that with or without us, life will go on.</s>
 <s id="32">But my pick for the top Long News story of this past year was this one: water found on the moon.</s>
 <s id="33">Makes it a lot easier to put a colony up there.</s>
 <s id="34">And if NASA doesn't do it, China might, or somebody in this room might write a big check.</s>
 <s id="35">My point is this: In the long run, some news stories are more important than others.</s>
 <s id="36">(Applause)</s>
</text>
