<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Shah Rukh Khan: The speaker you are about to meet is someone who knows and understands the value of words like no one else does.</s>
 <s id="2">In his writing career spanning over four decades, this man has chosen words with beauty and versatility, like a flower springing to life ...</s>
 <s id="3">like Mr. Bachchan’s memorable punches ...</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) like a best-selling book of Urdu poetry ...</s>
 <s id="5">like well ... what do I say, only Javed Akhtar Sahab.</s>
 <s id="6">(Applause) Please welcome onstage, the one and only Javed Akhtar Sahab.</s>
 <s id="7">(Cheers and applause) Javed Akhtar: Friends, this topic -- the power of words -- is an interesting one, and one that's very close to my heart.</s>
 <s id="8">It’s strange how we often overlook things that are so close to us, near us.</s>
 <s id="9">How many people question, "Why is air transparent?"</s>
 <s id="10">Or, "Why is water wet?"</s>
 <s id="11">How many think about what is it that has passed?</s>
 <p id="p12">
  <s id="12.1">Time has passed.</s>
  <s id="12.2">What came?</s>
  <s id="12.3">What went away?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="13">How many of us wonder?</s>
 <s id="14">Similarly ...</s>
 <s id="15">the words that we speak and hear all day, how many times have we really thought, "What exactly are these words?"</s>
 <s id="16">Words are a strange thing.</s>
 <s id="17">You once saw an animal and decided it’s a "cat."</s>
 <s id="18">But cat is a sound.</s>
 <s id="19">This cat has nothing to do with the animal.</s>
 <s id="20">But I have decided it’s a cat.</s>
 <s id="21">So a cat it is.</s>
 <s id="22">So I gave the sound the identity of this animal.</s>
 <s id="23">After that I made a semicircle, a pyramid, cut into half, then a straight line, then another below it, and wrote: "cat."</s>
 <s id="24">In these criss-crossed lines, I filled a sound and into that sound, a meaning.</s>
 <s id="25">Now like with this cat, even with love, anger, a thought, an idea, pain, suffering, happiness, surprise, everything has been linked with a sound.</s>
 <s id="26">And then sounds were fit into some criss-crossed lines that we call a script.</s>
 <s id="27">So three things that had nothing in common were joined by us to create a word.</s>
 <s id="28">A sound that is actually gibberish has been added onto it.</s>
 <s id="29">And the lines, crooked lines, they formed a word.</s>
 <s id="30">Incredible!</s>
 <s id="31">And I have come to believe that with time, these words have become like human beings.</s>
 <s id="32">A man is known by the company he keeps.</s>
 <s id="33">Similarly, with words, what is the company it has been keeping?</s>
 <s id="34">What are the other words being used with it?</s>
 <s id="35">For an average noun or an average verb, an average mind can quickly create reference.</s>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">Where did they hear it?</s>
  <s id="36.2">See it?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="37">What does it remind them of?</s>
 <p id="p38">
  <s id="38.1">What is its connection?</s>
  <s id="38.2">When was it last used in conversation?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="39">What has been my experience with it?</s>
 <s id="40">A host of memories appear when you hear a word you remember.</s>
 <s id="41">And a good writer or orator is one who knows that when he uses a certain word, an average mind will associate it with a certain reference, specific memories will be evoked.</s>
 <s id="42">Then he can create a world around a word.</s>
 <s id="43">What is the power of a word?</s>
 <s id="44">Be it a mother’s lullaby, a politician’s speech, love letters from your beloved, or a complaint against someone, a protest call ...</s>
 <s id="45">anger, sadness, happiness, surprise, belonging, alienation anything in the world, any feeling in the world, any emotion, any reaction, until it is expressed in a word, it will not have any meaning for you, forget getting across to anyone else.</s>
 <s id="46">Words are not thoughts, just like bricks are not homes.</s>
 <s id="47">But houses are made with bricks.</s>
 <s id="48">If you have less bricks, you will make a small house.</s>
 <s id="49">The more words you have, the clearer your thoughts, and the more clearly you can convey them.</s>
 <s id="50">Nowadays I often hear, especially from young ones, “You know what I mean?"</s>
 <s id="51">No, I don't know what you mean.</s>
 <s id="52">(Laughter) “You know what I mean,” is running out of words.</s>
 <s id="53">Everything is now moving fast so communication has to be fast as well.</s>
 <s id="54">But the tragedy is that we have attained this speed at the cost of depth of words.</s>
 <s id="55">We want to speak faster, so everything is faster, so the language is also faster, hence communication is faster.</s>
 <s id="56">But this speed has affected depth.</s>
 <s id="57">Which means that forget about other people, just look at yourself.</s>
 <s id="58">You are not being able to articulate your own feelings, thoughts or emotions in a detailed manner or clearly.</s>
 <s id="59">And these words, as long as words exist, they aren’t there just for a meaning.</s>
 <s id="60">They are also a conveyer belt of language, words.</s>
 <s id="61">They reflect your culture, your traditions, your inheritance, your cultural wealth accumulated over generations, all of that is carried forward with words.</s>
 <s id="62">If you cut a man off from some words, you cut him off from a culture, a history.</s>
 <s id="63">This is exactly what is happening with us today.</s>
 <s id="64">So language is a very powerful thing.</s>
 <s id="65">Words are extremely powerful.</s>
 <s id="66">But by themselves, they are neither good nor bad.</s>
 <s id="67">If we start loving words and understand their power, we would realize that everything that happens in the world is because of words.</s>
 <s id="68">Or there would be nothing between us and the rest of the creatures, the rest of the animals, although we too are animals.</s>
 <s id="69">The only difference is that we can pass on, through our words, our experience, our learning and our knowledge to the next generation.</s>
 <s id="70">So we don’t only live on instinct but our slowly accumulated experience and knowledge over generations is passed on to the next.</s>
 <p id="p71">
  <s id="71.1">Through what?</s>
  <s id="71.2">Through words.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="72">And if we didn’t have these words our advantage is gradually over other species would diminish over time.</s>
 <s id="73">We advanced only because we have language.</s>
 <s id="74">And if we didn’t have that we wouldn’t be here.</s>
 <s id="75">We would be right where we started.</s>
 <s id="76">So what does language mean?</s>
 <s id="77">Words!</s>
 <s id="78">So learn to respect words.</s>
 <s id="79">Love them.</s>
 <s id="80">Befriend them.</s>
 <s id="81">Listen to them attentively.</s>
 <s id="82">And speak attentively.</s>
 <s id="83">Thank you!</s>
 <s id="84">(Applause) SRK: Thanks a lot, Javed Sahab, for coming here today and sharing such wonderful things with us.</s>
 <s id="85">I have known Javed Sahab since I came to Mumbai about 25 years ago.</s>
 <s id="86">JA: I was really young then.</s>
 <p id="p87">
  <s id="87.1">(Laughter) SRK: Yes.</s>
  <s id="87.2">You are still very young, Sir.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="88">But I have got a lot of my education, my ideologies and many more things from Javed Sahab.</s>
 <s id="89">I’ll share a small incident.</s>
 <s id="90">He got angry with us while working on a film.</s>
 <s id="91">He sometimes gets angry when unlettered people like us give him suggestions that maybe we could use this word or that instead.</s>
 <s id="92">So our film was called "Kuch Kuch Hota Hai."</s>
 <s id="93">(Cheers) And he did not like the title at all.</s>
 <s id="94">So once when he was really mad at us kids, who are like his kids even now, he retorted: "Now my heart remains neither awake nor rests.</s>
 <p id="p95">
  <s id="95.1">What do I do?</s>
  <s id="95.2">Oh!</s>
  <s id="95.3">I feel something strange.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="96">Is that what you want?"</s>
 <s id="97">In fact the entire song, all the words, were thrown at us by Javed Sahab in anger.</s>
 <s id="98">And that song went on to become extremely popular.</s>
 <s id="99">So even when Javed Sahab throws out words in anger, they turn into golden words.</s>
 <s id="100">That’s his gift.</s>
 <s id="101">(Cheers) JA: Well, the incident that Shah Rukh Sahab shared is indeed true.</s>
 <s id="102">So on hearing this title, "'Kuch Kuch Hota Hai," I was shocked.</s>
 <s id="103">I felt it wasn’t dignified enough.</s>
 <s id="104">(Laughter) Though to be honest, I regret leaving such a super hit film over its title.</s>
 <s id="105">So I left the film.</s>
 <s id="106">Later I also felt a little embarrassed, and he too felt bad.</s>
 <s id="107">So we decided to let bygones be bygones and work on some other film.</s>
 <s id="108">Hence, the film "Kal Ho Naa Ho."</s>
 <s id="109">I told him that everything else is still fine but I owe you two kuchs.</s>
 <s id="110">Two kuchs.</s>
 <s id="111">(Laughter) So I’ll write a song and return these two to you.</s>
 <s id="112">I wrote a song specially for this reason called "Kuch to hua hai, kuch ho gaya hai."</s>
 <s id="113">(Cheers and applause) and he returned his two.</s>
 <s id="114">(Applause) Ladies and gentlemen, big round of applause for Javed Akhtar Sahab.</s>
 <s id="115">(Applause)</s>
</text>
