<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So I thought, "I will talk about death."</s>
 <s id="2">Seemed to be the passion today.</s>
 <s id="3">Actually, it's not about death.</s>
 <s id="4">It's inevitable, terrible, but really what I want to talk about is, I'm just fascinated by the legacy people leave when they die.</s>
 <s id="5">That's what I want to talk about.</s>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">So Art Buchwald left his legacy of humor with a video that appeared soon after he died, saying, "Hi!</s>
  <s id="6.2">I'm Art Buchwald, and I just died."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="7">And Mike, who I met at Galapagos, a trip which I won at TED, is leaving notes on cyberspace where he is chronicling his journey through cancer.</s>
 <s id="8">And my father left me a legacy of his handwriting through letters and a notebook.</s>
 <s id="9">In the last two years of his life, when he was sick, he filled a notebook with his thoughts about me.</s>
 <s id="10">He wrote about my strengths, weaknesses, and gentle suggestions for improvement, quoting specific incidents, and held a mirror to my life.</s>
 <s id="11">After he died, I realized that no one writes to me anymore.</s>
 <s id="12">Handwriting is a disappearing art.</s>
 <s id="13">I'm all for email and thinking while typing, but why give up old habits for new?</s>
 <s id="14">Why can't we have letter writing and email exchange in our lives?</s>
 <s id="15">There are times when I want to trade all those years that I was too busy to sit with my dad and chat with him, and trade all those years for one hug.</s>
 <s id="16">But too late.</s>
 <s id="17">But that's when I take out his letters and I read them, and the paper that touched his hand is in mine, and I feel connected to him.</s>
 <s id="18">So maybe we all need to leave our children with a value legacy, and not a financial one.</s>
 <s id="19">A value for things with a personal touch -- an autographed book, a soul-searching letter.</s>
 <s id="20">If a fraction of this powerful TED audience could be inspired to buy a beautiful paper -- John, it'll be a recycled one -- and write a beautiful letter to someone they love, we actually may start a revolution where our children may go to penmanship classes.</s>
 <s id="21">So what do I plan to leave for my son?</s>
 <s id="22">I collect autographed books, and those of you authors in the audience know I hound you for them -- and CDs too, Tracy.</s>
 <s id="23">I plan to publish my own notebook.</s>
 <s id="24">As I witnessed my father's body being swallowed by fire, I sat by his funeral pyre and wrote.</s>
 <s id="25">I have no idea how I'm going to do it, but I am committed to compiling his thoughts and mine into a book, and leave that published book for my son.</s>
 <s id="26">I'd like to end with a few verses of what I wrote at my father's cremation.</s>
 <s id="27">And those linguists, please pardon the grammar, because I've not looked at it in the last 10 years.</s>
 <s id="28">I took it out for the first time to come here.</s>
 <s id="29">"Picture in a frame, ashes in a bottle, boundless energy confined in the bottle, forcing me to deal with reality, forcing me to deal with being grown up.</s>
 <s id="30">I hear you and I know that you would want me to be strong, but right now, I am being sucked down, surrounded and suffocated by these raging emotional waters, craving to cleanse my soul, trying to emerge on a firm footing one more time, to keep on fighting and flourishing just as you taught me.</s>
 <s id="31">Your encouraging whispers in my whirlpool of despair, holding me and heaving me to shores of sanity, to live again and to love again."</s>
 <s id="32">Thank you.</s>
</text>
