<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">On the 30th of May, 1832, a gunshot was heard ringing out across the 13th arrondissement in Paris.</s>
 <s id="2">(Gunshot) A peasant, who was walking to market that morning, ran towards where the gunshot had come from, and found a young man writhing in agony on the floor, clearly shot by a dueling wound.</s>
 <s id="3">The young man's name was Evariste Galois.</s>
 <s id="4">He was a well-known revolutionary in Paris at the time.</s>
 <s id="5">Galois was taken to the local hospital where he died the next day in the arms of his brother.</s>
 <s id="6">And the last words he said to his brother were, "Don't cry for me, Alfred.</s>
 <s id="7">I need all the courage I can muster to die at the age of 20."</s>
 <s id="8">It wasn't, in fact, revolutionary politics for which Galois was famous.</s>
 <s id="9">But a few years earlier, while still at school, he'd actually cracked one of the big mathematical problems at the time.</s>
 <s id="10">And he wrote to the academicians in Paris, trying to explain his theory.</s>
 <s id="11">But the academicians couldn't understand anything that he wrote.</s>
 <s id="12">(Laughter) This is how he wrote most of his mathematics.</s>
 <s id="13">So, the night before that duel, he realized this possibly is his last chance to try and explain his great breakthrough.</s>
 <s id="14">So he stayed up the whole night, writing away, trying to explain his ideas.</s>
 <s id="15">And as the dawn came up and he went to meet his destiny, he left this pile of papers on the table for the next generation.</s>
 <s id="16">Maybe the fact that he stayed up all night doing mathematics was the fact that he was such a bad shot that morning and got killed.</s>
 <s id="17">But contained inside those documents was a new language, a language to understand one of the most fundamental concepts of science -- namely symmetry.</s>
 <s id="18">Now, symmetry is almost nature's language.</s>
 <s id="19">It helps us to understand so many different bits of the scientific world.</s>
 <s id="20">For example, molecular structure.</s>
 <s id="21">What crystals are possible, we can understand through the mathematics of symmetry.</s>
 <s id="22">In microbiology you really don't want to get a symmetrical object, because they are generally rather nasty.</s>
 <s id="23">The swine flu virus, at the moment, is a symmetrical object.</s>
 <s id="24">And it uses the efficiency of symmetry to be able to propagate itself so well.</s>
 <s id="25">But on a larger scale of biology, actually symmetry is very important, because it actually communicates genetic information.</s>
 <s id="26">I've taken two pictures here and I've made them artificially symmetrical.</s>
 <s id="27">And if I ask you which of these you find more beautiful, you're probably drawn to the lower two.</s>
 <s id="28">Because it is hard to make symmetry.</s>
 <s id="29">And if you can make yourself symmetrical, you're sending out a sign that you've got good genes, you've got a good upbringing and therefore you'll make a good mate.</s>
 <s id="30">So symmetry is a language which can help to communicate genetic information.</s>
 <s id="31">Symmetry can also help us to explain what's happening in the Large Hadron Collider in CERN.</s>
 <s id="32">Or what's not happening in the Large Hadron Collider in CERN.</s>
 <s id="33">To be able to make predictions about the fundamental particles we might see there, it seems that they are all facets of some strange symmetrical shape in a higher dimensional space.</s>
 <s id="34">And I think Galileo summed up, very nicely, the power of mathematics to understand the scientific world around us.</s>
 <s id="35">He wrote, "The universe cannot be read until we have learnt the language and become familiar with the characters in which it is written.</s>
 <s id="36">It is written in mathematical language, and the letters are triangles, circles and other geometric figures, without which means it is humanly impossible to comprehend a single word."</s>
 <s id="37">But it's not just scientists who are interested in symmetry.</s>
 <s id="38">Artists too love to play around with symmetry.</s>
 <s id="39">They also have a slightly more ambiguous relationship with it.</s>
 <s id="40">Here is Thomas Mann talking about symmetry in "The Magic Mountain."</s>
 <s id="41">He has a character describing the snowflake, and he says he "shuddered at its perfect precision, found it deathly, the very marrow of death."</s>
 <s id="42">But what artists like to do is to set up expectations of symmetry and then break them.</s>
 <s id="43">And a beautiful example of this I found, actually, when I visited a colleague of mine in Japan, Professor Kurokawa.</s>
 <s id="44">And he took me up to the temples in Nikko.</s>
 <s id="45">And just after this photo was taken we walked up the stairs.</s>
 <s id="46">And the gateway you see behind has eight columns, with beautiful symmetrical designs on them.</s>
 <s id="47">Seven of them are exactly the same, and the eighth one is turned upside down.</s>
 <s id="48">And I said to Professor Kurokawa, "Wow, the architects must have really been kicking themselves when they realized that they'd made a mistake and put this one upside down."</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">And he said, "No, no, no.</s>
  <s id="49.2">It was a very deliberate act."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">And he referred me to this lovely quote from the Japanese "Essays in Idleness" from the 14th century, in which the essayist wrote, "In everything, uniformity is undesirable.</s>
 <s id="51">Leaving something incomplete makes it interesting, and gives one the feeling that there is room for growth."</s>
 <s id="52">Even when building the Imperial Palace, they always leave one place unfinished.</s>
 <s id="53">But if I had to choose one building in the world to be cast out on a desert island, to live the rest of my life, being an addict of symmetry, I would probably choose the Alhambra in Granada.</s>
 <s id="54">This is a palace celebrating symmetry.</s>
 <s id="55">Recently I took my family -- we do these rather kind of nerdy mathematical trips, which my family love.</s>
 <p id="p56">
  <s id="56.1">This is my son Tamer.</s>
  <s id="56.2">You can see he's really enjoying our mathematical trip to the Alhambra.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="57">But I wanted to try and enrich him.</s>
 <s id="58">I think one of the problems about school mathematics is it doesn't look at how mathematics is embedded in the world we live in.</s>
 <s id="59">So, I wanted to open his eyes up to how much symmetry is running through the Alhambra.</s>
 <p id="p60">
  <s id="60.1">You see it already.</s>
  <s id="60.2">Immediately you go in, the reflective symmetry in the water.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="61">But it's on the walls where all the exciting things are happening.</s>
 <s id="62">The Moorish artists were denied the possibility to draw things with souls.</s>
 <s id="63">So they explored a more geometric art.</s>
 <s id="64">And so what is symmetry?</s>
 <s id="65">The Alhambra somehow asks all of these questions.</s>
 <p id="p66">
  <s id="66.1">What is symmetry?</s>
  <s id="66.2">When [there] are two of these walls, do they have the same symmetries?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="67">Can we say whether they discovered all of the symmetries in the Alhambra?</s>
 <s id="68">And it was Galois who produced a language to be able to answer some of these questions.</s>
 <s id="69">For Galois, symmetry -- unlike for Thomas Mann, which was something still and deathly -- for Galois, symmetry was all about motion.</s>
 <s id="70">What can you do to a symmetrical object, move it in some way, so it looks the same as before you moved it?</s>
 <s id="71">I like to describe it as the magic trick moves.</s>
 <p id="p72">
  <s id="72.1">What can you do to something?</s>
  <s id="72.2">You close your eyes.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="73">I do something, put it back down again.</s>
 <s id="74">It looks like it did before it started.</s>
 <s id="75">So, for example, the walls in the Alhambra -- I can take all of these tiles, and fix them at the yellow place, rotate them by 90 degrees, put them all back down again and they fit perfectly down there.</s>
 <s id="76">And if you open your eyes again, you wouldn't know that they'd moved.</s>
 <s id="77">But it's the motion that really characterizes the symmetry inside the Alhambra.</s>
 <s id="78">But it's also about producing a language to describe this.</s>
 <s id="79">And the power of mathematics is often to change one thing into another, to change geometry into language.</s>
 <s id="80">So I'm going to take you through, perhaps push you a little bit mathematically -- so brace yourselves -- push you a little bit to understand how this language works, which enables us to capture what is symmetry.</s>
 <s id="81">So, let's take these two symmetrical objects here.</s>
 <s id="82">Let's take the twisted six-pointed starfish.</s>
 <s id="83">What can I do to the starfish which makes it look the same?</s>
 <s id="84">Well, there I rotated it by a sixth of a turn, and still it looks like it did before I started.</s>
 <s id="85">I could rotate it by a third of a turn, or a half a turn, or put it back down on its image, or two thirds of a turn.</s>
 <s id="86">And a fifth symmetry, I can rotate it by five sixths of a turn.</s>
 <s id="87">And those are things that I can do to the symmetrical object that make it look like it did before I started.</s>
 <s id="88">Now, for Galois, there was actually a sixth symmetry.</s>
 <s id="89">Can anybody think what else I could do to this which would leave it like I did before I started?</s>
 <s id="90">I can't flip it because I've put a little twist on it, haven't I?</s>
 <s id="91">It's got no reflective symmetry.</s>
 <s id="92">But what I could do is just leave it where it is, pick it up, and put it down again.</s>
 <s id="93">And for Galois this was like the zeroth symmetry.</s>
 <s id="94">Actually, the invention of the number zero was a very modern concept, seventh century A.D., by the Indians.</s>
 <s id="95">It seems mad to talk about nothing.</s>
 <p id="p96">
  <s id="96.1">And this is the same idea.</s>
  <s id="96.2">This is a symmetrical -- so everything has symmetry, where you just leave it where it is.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="97">So, this object has six symmetries.</s>
 <s id="98">And what about the triangle?</s>
 <s id="99">Well, I can rotate by a third of a turn clockwise or a third of a turn anticlockwise.</s>
 <s id="100">But now this has some reflectional symmetry.</s>
 <s id="101">I can reflect it in the line through X, or the line through Y, or the line through Z.</s>
 <s id="102">Five symmetries and then of course the zeroth symmetry where I just pick it up and leave it where it is.</s>
 <s id="103">So both of these objects have six symmetries.</s>
 <s id="104">Now, I'm a great believer that mathematics is not a spectator sport, and you have to do some mathematics in order to really understand it.</s>
 <s id="105">So here is a little question for you.</s>
 <s id="106">And I'm going to give a prize at the end of my talk for the person who gets closest to the answer.</s>
 <s id="107">The Rubik's Cube.</s>
 <s id="108">How many symmetries does a Rubik's Cube have?</s>
 <s id="109">How many things can I do to this object and put it down so it still looks like a cube?</s>
 <p id="p110">
  <s id="110.1">Okay?</s>
  <s id="110.2">So I want you to think about that problem as we go on, and count how many symmetries there are.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="111">And there will be a prize for the person who gets closest at the end.</s>
 <s id="112">But let's go back down to symmetries that I got for these two objects.</s>
 <s id="113">What Galois realized: it isn't just the individual symmetries, but how they interact with each other which really characterizes the symmetry of an object.</s>
 <s id="114">If I do one magic trick move followed by another, the combination is a third magic trick move.</s>
 <s id="115">And here we see Galois starting to develop a language to see the substance of the things unseen, the sort of abstract idea of the symmetry underlying this physical object.</s>
 <s id="116">For example, what if I turn the starfish by a sixth of a turn, and then a third of a turn?</s>
 <p id="p117">
  <s id="117.1">So I've given names.</s>
  <s id="117.2">The capital letters, A, B, C, D, E, F, are the names for the rotations.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p118">
  <s id="118.1">B, for example, rotates the little yellow dot to the B on the starfish.</s>
  <s id="118.2">And so on.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="119">So what if I do B, which is a sixth of a turn, followed by C, which is a third of a turn?</s>
 <p id="p120">
  <s id="120.1">Well let's do that.</s>
  <s id="120.2">A sixth of a turn, followed by a third of a turn, the combined effect is as if I had just rotated it by half a turn in one go.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="121">So the little table here records how the algebra of these symmetries work.</s>
 <s id="122">I do one followed by another, the answer is it's rotation D, half a turn.</s>
 <p id="p123">
  <s id="123.1">What I if I did it in the other order?</s>
  <s id="123.2">Would it make any difference?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p124">
  <s id="124.1">Let's see.</s>
  <s id="124.2">Let's do the third of the turn first, and then the sixth of a turn.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="125">Of course, it doesn't make any difference.</s>
 <s id="126">It still ends up at half a turn.</s>
 <s id="127">And there is some symmetry here in the way the symmetries interact with each other.</s>
 <s id="128">But this is completely different to the symmetries of the triangle.</s>
 <s id="129">Let's see what happens if we do two symmetries with the triangle, one after the other.</s>
 <s id="130">Let's do a rotation by a third of a turn anticlockwise, and reflect in the line through X.</s>
 <s id="131">Well, the combined effect is as if I had just done the reflection in the line through Z to start with.</s>
 <s id="132">Now, let's do it in a different order.</s>
 <s id="133">Let's do the reflection in X first, followed by the rotation by a third of a turn anticlockwise.</s>
 <s id="134">The combined effect, the triangle ends up somewhere completely different.</s>
 <s id="135">It's as if it was reflected in the line through Y.</s>
 <s id="136">Now it matters what order you do the operations in.</s>
 <p id="p137">
  <s id="137.1">And this enables us to distinguish why the symmetries of these objects -- they both have six symmetries.</s>
  <s id="137.2">So why shouldn't we say they have the same symmetries?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="138">But the way the symmetries interact enable us -- we've now got a language to distinguish why these symmetries are fundamentally different.</s>
 <s id="139">And you can try this when you go down to the pub, later on.</s>
 <p id="p140">
  <s id="140.1">Take a beer mat and rotate it by a quarter of a turn, then flip it.</s>
  <s id="140.2">And then do it in the other order, and the picture will be facing in the opposite direction.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="141">Now, Galois produced some laws for how these tables -- how symmetries interact.</s>
 <s id="142">It's almost like little Sudoku tables.</s>
 <s id="143">You don't see any symmetry twice in any row or column.</s>
 <s id="144">And, using those rules, he was able to say that there are in fact only two objects with six symmetries.</s>
 <s id="145">And they'll be the same as the symmetries of the triangle, or the symmetries of the six-pointed starfish.</s>
 <s id="146">I think this is an amazing development.</s>
 <s id="147">It's almost like the concept of number being developed for symmetry.</s>
 <s id="148">In the front here, I've got one, two, three people sitting on one, two, three chairs.</s>
 <s id="149">The people and the chairs are very different, but the number, the abstract idea of the number, is the same.</s>
 <s id="150">And we can see this now: we go back to the walls in the Alhambra.</s>
 <s id="151">Here are two very different walls, very different geometric pictures.</s>
 <s id="152">But, using the language of Galois, we can understand that the underlying abstract symmetries of these things are actually the same.</s>
 <s id="153">For example, let's take this beautiful wall with the triangles with a little twist on them.</s>
 <p id="p154">
  <s id="154.1">You can rotate them by a sixth of a turn if you ignore the colors.</s>
  <s id="154.2">We're not matching up the colors.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="155">But the shapes match up if I rotate by a sixth of a turn around the point where all the triangles meet.</s>
 <p id="p156">
  <s id="156.1">What about the center of a triangle?</s>
  <s id="156.2">I can rotate by a third of a turn around the center of the triangle, and everything matches up.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="157">And then there is an interesting place halfway along an edge, where I can rotate by 180 degrees.</s>
 <s id="158">And all the tiles match up again.</s>
 <s id="159">So rotate along halfway along the edge, and they all match up.</s>
 <s id="160">Now, let's move to the very different-looking wall in the Alhambra.</s>
 <s id="161">And we find the same symmetries here, and the same interaction.</s>
 <p id="p162">
  <s id="162.1">So, there was a sixth of a turn.</s>
  <s id="162.2">A third of a turn where the Z pieces meet.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="163">And the half a turn is halfway between the six pointed stars.</s>
 <s id="164">And although these walls look very different, Galois has produced a language to say that in fact the symmetries underlying these are exactly the same.</s>
 <s id="165">And it's a symmetry we call 6-3-2.</s>
 <s id="166">Here is another example in the Alhambra.</s>
 <s id="167">This is a wall, a ceiling, and a floor.</s>
 <p id="p168">
  <s id="168.1">They all look very different.</s>
  <s id="168.2">But this language allows us to say that they are representations of the same symmetrical abstract object, which we call 4-4-2.</s>
  <s id="168.3">Nothing to do with football, but because of the fact that there are two places where you can rotate by a quarter of a turn, and one by half a turn.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="169">Now, this power of the language is even more, because Galois can say, "Did the Moorish artists discover all of the possible symmetries on the walls in the Alhambra?"</s>
 <s id="170">And it turns out they almost did.</s>
 <s id="171">You can prove, using Galois' language, there are actually only 17 different symmetries that you can do in the walls in the Alhambra.</s>
 <s id="172">And they, if you try to produce a different wall with this 18th one, it will have to have the same symmetries as one of these 17.</s>
 <s id="173">But these are things that we can see.</s>
 <s id="174">And the power of Galois' mathematical language is it also allows us to create symmetrical objects in the unseen world, beyond the two-dimensional, three-dimensional, all the way through to the four- or five- or infinite-dimensional space.</s>
 <p id="p175">
  <s id="175.1">And that's where I work.</s>
  <s id="175.2">I create mathematical objects, symmetrical objects, using Galois' language, in very high dimensional spaces.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="176">So I think it's a great example of things unseen, which the power of mathematical language allows you to create.</s>
 <s id="177">So, like Galois, I stayed up all last night creating a new mathematical symmetrical object for you, and I've got a picture of it here.</s>
 <p id="p178">
  <s id="178.1">Well, unfortunately it isn't really a picture.</s>
  <s id="178.2">If I could have my board at the side here, great, excellent.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p179">
  <s id="179.1">Here we are.</s>
  <s id="179.2">Unfortunately, I can't show you a picture of this symmetrical object.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="180">But here is the language which describes how the symmetries interact.</s>
 <s id="181">Now, this new symmetrical object does not have a name yet.</s>
 <s id="182">Now, people like getting their names on things, on craters on the moon or new species of animals.</s>
 <s id="183">So I'm going to give you the chance to get your name on a new symmetrical object which hasn't been named before.</s>
 <s id="184">And this thing -- species die away, and moons kind of get hit by meteors and explode -- but this mathematical object will live forever.</s>
 <s id="185">It will make you immortal.</s>
 <s id="186">In order to win this symmetrical object, what you have to do is to answer the question I asked you at the beginning.</s>
 <s id="187">How many symmetries does a Rubik's Cube have?</s>
 <s id="188">Okay, I'm going to sort you out.</s>
 <p id="p189">
  <s id="189.1">Rather than you all shouting out, I want you to count how many digits there are in that number.</s>
  <s id="189.2">Okay?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="190">If you've got it as a factorial, you've got to expand the factorials.</s>
 <s id="191">Okay, now if you want to play, I want you to stand up, okay?</s>
 <s id="192">If you think you've got an estimate for how many digits, right -- we've already got one competitor here.</s>
 <s id="193">If you all stay down he wins it automatically.</s>
 <p id="p194">
  <s id="194.1">Okay.</s>
  <s id="194.2">Excellent.</s>
  <s id="194.3">So we've got four here, five, six.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p195">
  <s id="195.1">Great.</s>
  <s id="195.2">Excellent.</s>
  <s id="195.3">That should get us going.</s>
  <s id="195.4">All right.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="196">Anybody with five or less digits, you've got to sit down, because you've underestimated.</s>
 <p id="p197">
  <s id="197.1">Five or less digits.</s>
  <s id="197.2">So, if you're in the tens of thousands you've got to sit down.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="198">60 digits or more, you've got to sit down.</s>
 <s id="199">You've overestimated.</s>
 <s id="200">20 digits or less, sit down.</s>
 <s id="201">How many digits are there in your number?</s>
 <p id="p202">
  <s id="202.1">Two?</s>
  <s id="202.2">So you should have sat down earlier.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p203">
  <s id="203.1">(Laughter) Let's have the other ones, who sat down during the 20, up again.</s>
  <s id="203.2">Okay?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="204">If I told you 20 or less, stand up.</s>
 <p id="p205">
  <s id="205.1">Because this one.</s>
  <s id="205.2">I think there were a few here.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="206">The people who just last sat down.</s>
 <s id="207">Okay, how many digits do you have in your number?</s>
 <p id="p208">
  <s id="208.1">(Laughs) 21.</s>
  <s id="208.2">Okay good.</s>
  <s id="208.3">How many do you have in yours?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p209">
  <s id="209.1">18.</s>
  <s id="209.2">So it goes to this lady here.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="210">21 is the closest.</s>
 <s id="211">It actually has -- the number of symmetries in the Rubik's cube has 25 digits.</s>
 <s id="212">So now I need to name this object.</s>
 <s id="213">So, what is your name?</s>
 <p id="p214">
  <s id="214.1">I need your surname.</s>
  <s id="214.2">Symmetrical objects generally -- spell it for me.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p215">
  <s id="215.1">G-H-E-Z No, SO2 has already been used, actually, in the mathematical language.</s>
  <s id="215.2">So you can't have that one.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p216">
  <s id="216.1">So Ghez, there we go.</s>
  <s id="216.2">That's your new symmetrical object.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="217">You are now immortal.</s>
 <s id="218">(Applause) And if you'd like your own symmetrical object, I have a project raising money for a charity in Guatemala, where I will stay up all night and devise an object for you, for a donation to this charity to help kids get into education in Guatemala.</s>
 <s id="219">And I think what drives me, as a mathematician, are those things which are not seen, the things that we haven't discovered.</s>
 <s id="220">It's all the unanswered questions which make mathematics a living subject.</s>
 <s id="221">And I will always come back to this quote from the Japanese "Essays in Idleness": "In everything, uniformity is undesirable.</s>
 <p id="p222">
  <s id="222.1">Leaving something incomplete makes it interesting, and gives one the feeling that there is room for growth."</s>
  <s id="222.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="223">(Applause)</s>
</text>
