<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Now, I'm an ethnobotanist.</s>
 <s id="2">That's a scientist who works in the rainforest to document how people use local plants.</s>
 <s id="3">I've been doing this for a long time, and I want to tell you, these people know these forests and these medicinal treasures better than we do and better than we ever will.</s>
 <s id="4">But also, these cultures, these indigenous cultures, are disappearing much faster than the forests themselves.</s>
 <s id="5">And the greatest and most endangered species in the Amazon Rainforest is not the jaguar, it's not the harpy eagle, it's the isolated and uncontacted tribes.</s>
 <s id="6">Now four years ago, I injured my foot in a climbing accident and I went to the doctor.</s>
 <s id="7">She gave me heat, she gave me cold, aspirin, narcotic painkillers, anti-inflammatories, cortisone shots.</s>
 <s id="8">It didn't work.</s>
 <s id="9">Several months later, I was in the northeast Amazon, walked into a village, and the shaman said, "You're limping."</s>
 <s id="10">And I'll never forget this as long as I live.</s>
 <s id="11">He looked me in the face and he said, "Take off your shoe and give me your machete."</s>
 <s id="12">(Laughter) He walked over to a palm tree and carved off a fern, threw it in the fire, applied it to my foot, threw it in a pot of water, and had me drink the tea.</s>
 <s id="13">The pain disappeared for seven months.</s>
 <s id="14">When it came back, I went to see the shaman again.</s>
 <s id="15">He gave me the same treatment, and I've been cured for three years now.</s>
 <s id="16">Who would you rather be treated by?</s>
 <s id="17">(Applause) Now, make no mistake — Western medicine is the most successful system of healing ever devised, but there's plenty of holes in it.</s>
 <s id="18">Where's the cure for breast cancer?</s>
 <s id="19">Where's the cure for schizophrenia?</s>
 <s id="20">Where's the cure for acid reflux?</s>
 <s id="21">Where's the cure for insomnia?</s>
 <s id="22">The fact is that these people can sometimes, sometimes, sometimes cure things we cannot.</s>
 <s id="23">Here you see a medicine man in the northeast Amazon treating leishmaniasis, a really nasty protozoal disease that afflicts 12 million people around the world.</s>
 <s id="24">Western treatment are injections of antimony.</s>
 <s id="25">They're painful, they're expensive, and they're probably not good for your heart; it's a heavy metal.</s>
 <s id="26">This man cures it with three plants from the Amazon Rainforest.</s>
 <s id="27">This is the magic frog.</s>
 <s id="28">My colleague, the late great Loren McIntyre, discoverer of the source lake of the Amazon, Laguna McIntyre in the Peruvian Andes, was lost on the Peru-Brazil border about 30 years ago.</s>
 <s id="29">He was rescued by a group of isolated Indians called the Matsés.</s>
 <s id="30">They beckoned for him to follow them into the forest, which he did.</s>
 <s id="31">There, they took out palm leaf baskets.</s>
 <s id="32">There, they took out these green monkey frogs — these are big suckers, they're like this — and they began licking them.</s>
 <s id="33">It turns out, they're highly hallucinogenic.</s>
 <s id="34">McIntyre wrote about this and it was read by the editor of High Times magazine.</s>
 <s id="35">You see that ethnobotanists have friends in all sorts of strange cultures.</s>
 <s id="36">This guy decided he would go down to the Amazon and give it a whirl, or give it a lick, and he did, and he wrote, "My blood pressure went through the roof, I lost full control of my bodily functions, I passed out in a heap, I woke up in a hammock six hours later, felt like God for two days."</s>
 <s id="37">(Laughter) An Italian chemist read this and said, "I'm not really interested in the theological aspects of the green monkey frog.</s>
 <s id="38">What's this about the change in blood pressure?"</s>
 <s id="39">Now, this is an Italian chemist who's working on a new treatment for high blood pressure based on peptides in the skin of the green monkey frog, and other scientists are looking at a cure for drug-resistant Staph aureus.</s>
 <s id="40">How ironic if these isolated Indians and their magic frog prove to be one of the cures.</s>
 <s id="41">Here's an ayahuasca shaman in the northwest Amazon, in the middle of a yage ceremony.</s>
 <s id="42">I took him to Los Angeles to meet a foundation officer looking for support for monies to protect their culture.</s>
 <s id="43">This fellow looked at the medicine man, and he said, "You didn't go to medical school, did you?"</s>
 <s id="44">The shaman said, "No, I did not."</s>
 <s id="45">He said, "Well, then what can you know about healing?"</s>
 <p id="p46">
  <s id="46.1">The shaman looked at him and he said, "You know what?</s>
  <s id="46.2">If you have an infection, go to a doctor.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="47">But many human afflictions are diseases of the heart, the mind and the spirit.</s>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">Western medicine can't touch those.</s>
  <s id="48.2">I cure them."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="49">(Applause) But all is not rosy in learning from nature about new medicines.</s>
 <s id="50">This is a viper from Brazil, the venom of which was studied at the Universidade de São Paulo here.</s>
 <s id="51">It was later developed into ACE inhibitors.</s>
 <s id="52">This is a frontline treatment for hypertension.</s>
 <s id="53">Hypertension causes over 10 percent of all deaths on the planet every day.</s>
 <s id="54">This is a $4 billion industry based on venom from a Brazilian snake, and the Brazilians did not get a nickel.</s>
 <s id="55">This is not an acceptable way of doing business.</s>
 <s id="56">The rainforest has been called the greatest expression of life on Earth.</s>
 <s id="57">There's a saying in Suriname that I dearly love: "The rainforests hold answers to questions we have yet to ask."</s>
 <s id="58">But as you all know, it's rapidly disappearing.</s>
 <s id="59">Here in Brazil, in the Amazon, around the world.</s>
 <s id="60">I took this picture from a small plane flying over the eastern border of the Xingu indigenous reserve in the state of Mato Grosso to the northwest of here.</s>
 <s id="61">The top half of the picture, you see where the Indians live.</s>
 <s id="62">The line through the middle is the eastern border of the reserve.</s>
 <s id="63">Top half Indians, bottom half white guys.</s>
 <s id="64">Top half wonder drugs, bottom half just a bunch of skinny-ass cows.</s>
 <s id="65">Top half carbon sequestered in the forest where it belongs, bottom half carbon in the atmosphere where it's driving climate change.</s>
 <s id="66">In fact, the number two cause of carbon being released into the atmosphere is forest destruction.</s>
 <s id="67">But in talking about destruction, it's important to keep in mind that the Amazon is the mightiest landscape of all.</s>
 <s id="68">It's a place of beauty and wonder.</s>
 <s id="69">The biggest anteater in the world lives in the rain forest, tips the scale at 90 pounds.</s>
 <s id="70">The goliath bird-eating spider is the world's largest spider.</s>
 <s id="71">It's found in the Amazon as well.</s>
 <s id="72">The harpy eagle wingspan is over seven feet.</s>
 <s id="73">And the black cayman — these monsters can tip the scale at over half a ton.</s>
 <s id="74">They're known to be man-eaters.</s>
 <s id="75">The anaconda, the largest snake, the capybara, the largest rodent.</s>
 <s id="76">A specimen from here in Brazil tipped the scale at 201 pounds.</s>
 <s id="77">Let's visit where these creatures live, the northeast Amazon, home to the Akuriyo tribe.</s>
 <s id="78">Uncontacted peoples hold a mystical and iconic role in our imagination.</s>
 <s id="79">These are the people who know nature best.</s>
 <s id="80">These are the people who truly live in total harmony with nature.</s>
 <s id="81">By our standards, some would dismiss these people as primitive.</s>
 <s id="82">"They don't know how to make fire, or they didn't when they were first contacted."</s>
 <s id="83">But they know the forest far better than we do.</s>
 <s id="84">The Akuriyos have 35 words for honey, and other Indians look up to them as being the true masters of the emerald realm.</s>
 <s id="85">Here you see the face of my friend Pohnay.</s>
 <s id="86">When I was a teenager rocking out to the Rolling Stones in my hometown of New Orleans, Pohnay was a forest nomad roaming the jungles of the northeast Amazon in a small band, looking for game, looking for medicinal plants, looking for a wife, in other small nomadic bands.</s>
 <s id="87">But it's people like these that know things that we don't, and they have lots of lessons to teach us.</s>
 <s id="88">However, if you go into most of the forests of the Amazon, there are no indigenous peoples.</s>
 <s id="89">This is what you find: rock carvings which indigenous peoples, uncontacted peoples, used to sharpen the edge of the stone axe.</s>
 <s id="90">These cultures that once danced, made love, sang to the gods, worshipped the forest, all that's left is an imprint in stone, as you see here.</s>
 <s id="91">Let's move to the western Amazon, which is really the epicenter of isolated peoples.</s>
 <s id="92">Each of these dots represents a small, uncontacted tribe, and the big reveal today is we believe there are 14 or 15 isolated groups in the Colombian Amazon alone.</s>
 <s id="93">Why are these people isolated?</s>
 <s id="94">They know we exist, they know there's an outside world.</s>
 <s id="95">This is a form of resistance.</s>
 <s id="96">They have chosen to remain isolated, and I think it is their human right to remain so.</s>
 <s id="97">Why are these the tribes that hide from man?</s>
 <s id="98">Here's why.</s>
 <s id="99">Obviously, some of this was set off in 1492.</s>
 <s id="100">But at the turn of the last century was the rubber trade.</s>
 <s id="101">The demand for natural rubber, which came from the Amazon, set off the botanical equivalent of a gold rush.</s>
 <s id="102">Rubber for bicycle tires, rubber for automobile tires, rubber for zeppelins.</s>
 <s id="103">It was a mad race to get that rubber, and the man on the left, Julio Arana, is one of the true thugs of the story.</s>
 <s id="104">His people, his company, and other companies like them killed, massacred, tortured, butchered Indians like the Witotos you see on the right hand side of the slide.</s>
 <s id="105">Even today, when people come out of the forest, the story seldom has a happy ending.</s>
 <p id="p106">
  <s id="106.1">These are Nukaks.</s>
  <s id="106.2">They were contacted in the '80s.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="107">Within a year, everybody over 40 was dead.</s>
 <s id="108">And remember, these are preliterate societies.</s>
 <s id="109">The elders are the libraries.</s>
 <s id="110">Every time a shaman dies, it's as if a library has burned down.</s>
 <s id="111">They have been forced off their lands.</s>
 <s id="112">The drug traffickers have taken over the Nukak lands, and the Nukaks live as beggars in public parks in eastern Colombia.</s>
 <s id="113">From the Nukak lands, I want to take you to the southwest, to the most spectacular landscape in the world: Chiribiquete National Park.</s>
 <s id="114">It was surrounded by three isolated tribes and thanks to the Colombian government and Colombian colleagues, it has now expanded.</s>
 <s id="115">It's bigger than the state of Maryland.</s>
 <s id="116">It is a treasure trove of botanical diversity.</s>
 <s id="117">It was first explored botanically in 1943 by my mentor, Richard Schultes, seen here atop the Bell Mountain, the sacred mountains of the Karijonas.</s>
 <s id="118">And let me show you what it looks like today.</s>
 <s id="119">Flying over Chiribiquete, realize that these lost world mountains are still lost.</s>
 <s id="120">No scientist has been atop them.</s>
 <s id="121">In fact, nobody has been atop the Bell Mountain since Schultes in '43.</s>
 <s id="122">And we'll end up here with the Bell Mountain just to the east of the picture.</s>
 <s id="123">Let me show you what it looks like today.</s>
 <s id="124">Not only is this a treasure trove of botanical diversity, not only is it home to three isolated tribes, but it's the greatest treasure trove of pre-Colombian art in the world: over 200,000 paintings.</s>
 <s id="125">The Dutch scientist Thomas van der Hammen described this as the Sistine Chapel of the Amazon Rainforest.</s>
 <s id="126">But move from Chiribiquete down to the southeast, again in the Colombian Amazon.</s>
 <s id="127">Remember, the Colombian Amazon is bigger than New England.</s>
 <s id="128">The Amazon's a big forest, and Brazil's got a big part of it, but not all of it.</s>
 <s id="129">Moving down to these two national parks, Cahuinari and Puré in the Colombian Amazon — that's the Brazilian border to the right — it's home to several groups of isolated and uncontacted peoples.</s>
 <s id="130">To the trained eye, you can look at the roofs of these malocas, these longhouses, and see that there's cultural diversity.</s>
 <s id="131">These are, in fact, different tribes.</s>
 <s id="132">As isolated as these areas are, let me show you how the outside world is crowding in.</s>
 <s id="133">Here we see trade and transport increased in Putumayo.</s>
 <s id="134">With the diminishment of the Civil War in Colombia, the outside world is showing up.</s>
 <s id="135">To the north, we have illegal gold mining, also from the east, from Brazil.</s>
 <s id="136">There's increased hunting and fishing for commercial purposes.</s>
 <s id="137">We see illegal logging coming from the south, and drug runners are trying to move through the park and get into Brazil.</s>
 <s id="138">This, in the past, is why you didn't mess with isolated Indians.</s>
 <s id="139">And if it looks like this picture is out of focus because it was taken in a hurry, here's why.</s>
 <s id="140">(Laughter) This looks like — (Applause) This looks like a hangar from the Brazilian Amazon.</s>
 <s id="141">This is an art exhibit in Havana, Cuba.</s>
 <s id="142">A group called Los Carpinteros.</s>
 <s id="143">This is their perception of why you shouldn't mess with uncontacted Indians.</s>
 <s id="144">But the world is changing.</s>
 <s id="145">These are Mashco-Piros on the Brazil-Peru border who stumbled out of the jungle because they were essentially chased out by drug runners and timber people.</s>
 <s id="146">And in Peru, there's a very nasty business.</s>
 <s id="147">It's called human safaris.</s>
 <s id="148">They will take you in to isolated groups to take their picture.</s>
 <s id="149">Of course, when you give them clothes, when you give them tools, you also give them diseases.</s>
 <s id="150">We call these "inhuman safaris."</s>
 <s id="151">These are Indians again on the Peru border, who were overflown by flights sponsored by missionaries.</s>
 <s id="152">They want to get in there and turn them into Christians.</s>
 <s id="153">We know how that turns out.</s>
 <s id="154">What's to be done?</s>
 <s id="155">Introduce technology to the contacted tribes, not the uncontacted tribes, in a culturally sensitive way.</s>
 <s id="156">This is the perfect marriage of ancient shamanic wisdom and 21st century technology.</s>
 <s id="157">We've done this now with over 30 tribes, mapped, managed and increased protection of over 70 million acres of ancestral rainforest.</s>
 <s id="158">(Applause) So this allows the Indians to take control of their environmental and cultural destiny.</s>
 <s id="159">They also then set up guard houses to keep outsiders out.</s>
 <s id="160">These are Indians, trained as indigenous park rangers, patrolling the borders and keeping the outside world at bay.</s>
 <s id="161">This is a picture of actual contact.</s>
 <s id="162">These are Chitonahua Indians on the Brazil-Peru border.</s>
 <s id="163">They've come out of the jungle asking for help.</s>
 <s id="164">They were shot at, their malocas, their longhouses, were burned.</s>
 <s id="165">Some of them were massacred.</s>
 <s id="166">Using automatic weapons to slaughter uncontacted peoples is the single most despicable and disgusting human rights abuse on our planet today, and it has to stop.</s>
 <s id="167">(Applause) But let me conclude by saying, this work can be spiritually rewarding, but it's difficult and it can be dangerous.</s>
 <s id="168">Two colleagues of mine passed away recently in the crash of a small plane.</s>
 <s id="169">They were serving the forest to protect those uncontacted tribes.</s>
 <s id="170">So the question is, in conclusion, is what the future holds.</s>
 <s id="171">These are the Uray people in Brazil.</s>
 <s id="172">What does the future hold for them, and what does the future hold for us?</s>
 <s id="173">Let's think differently.</s>
 <s id="174">Let's make a better world.</s>
 <s id="175">If the climate's going to change, let's have a climate that changes for the better rather than the worse.</s>
 <s id="176">Let's live on a planet full of luxuriant vegetation, in which isolated peoples can remain in isolation, can maintain that mystery and that knowledge if they so choose.</s>
 <s id="177">Let's live in a world where the shamans live in these forests and heal themselves and us with their mystical plants and their sacred frogs.</s>
 <s id="178">Thanks again.</s>
 <s id="179">(Applause)</s>
</text>
