<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Hi.</s>
 <s id="2">I've got a question for you: how many people here would say they can draw?</s>
 <s id="3">(Laughter) I think we've got about one or two percent of the hands going up, and it's interesting, isn't it?</s>
 <s id="4">It's a little bit like people think of spelling or singing.</s>
 <s id="5">They think,"You can either do it, or you can't."</s>
 <s id="6">But I think you can.</s>
 <s id="7">Because when people say they can't draw, I think it's more to do with beliefs rather than talent and ability.</s>
 <s id="8">So I think when you say you can't draw, that's just an illusion, and today I'd like to prove that to you.</s>
 <s id="9">When I say "draw", I'm not saying we're all going to draw like Michelangelo.</s>
 <s id="10">We are not going to be painting the Sistine Chapel's ceiling.</s>
 <s id="11">But would you be happy if, by the end of this session, you could draw pictures a little bit like this?</s>
 <s id="12">(Audience murmuring) Oh, yes!</s>
 <s id="13">(Laughter) Or even a little bit like this?</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) Actually, there are only two things you need to do to be able to achieve this.</s>
 <p id="p15">
  <s id="15.1">One is have an open mind.</s>
  <s id="15.2">Are you up for that?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="16">(Audience) Yes!</s>
 <s id="17">And two, just be prepared to have a go.</s>
 <s id="18">So grab a pen and a piece of paper.</s>
 <s id="19">OK, so here's how it's going to work: I’ll show you the first cartoon we're going to do, so just watch to begin with.</s>
 <s id="20">Here we go.</s>
 <s id="21">Just watching.</s>
 <s id="22">That's going to be our first cartoon.</s>
 <s id="23">It's a character called Spike.</s>
 <s id="24">I'd like you to draw along with me.</s>
 <s id="25">I'll draw the first line, you draw, and when you've done that, look up, and I'll know you're ready for the next line.</s>
 <s id="26">Okay, here we go.</s>
 <s id="27">Start with the nose.</s>
 <s id="28">Now the eyes.</s>
 <s id="29">They're like 66s or speech marks.</s>
 <s id="30">That's it.</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">Next, the mouth.</s>
  <s id="31.2">Nice, big smile.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">Now, over here, the ear.</s>
 <s id="33">Next, some spiky hair.</s>
 <s id="34">Next, put the pen to the left to the mouth, little line like that.</s>
 <s id="35">Pen under the ear, drop a line like that.</s>
 <s id="36">Pen to the left of the neck, top of the T-shirt.</s>
 <s id="37">Line to the left, line to the right.</s>
 <s id="38">Just hold your drawings up and show everyone.</s>
 <s id="39">(Laughter) How are we all doing?</s>
 <s id="40">(Laughter) OK.</s>
 <s id="41">OK, fantastic.</s>
 <s id="42">So, it looks like you've just learned to draw one cartoon, but you've actually learned more than that; you've learned a sequence that would enable you to draw hundreds and thousands of different cartoons, because we're just going to do little variations on that sequence.</s>
 <s id="43">Have a go at this.</s>
 <s id="44">Draw along with me.</s>
 <s id="45">Nose.</s>
 <s id="46">Eyes.</s>
 <s id="47">Smile.</s>
 <s id="48">That's it.</s>
 <s id="49">Now some hair.</s>
 <s id="50">Pen to the left of the mouth, under the hair, little V-shape for the top, line to the left, line to the right.</s>
 <p id="p51">
  <s id="51.1">So we've got another character.</s>
  <s id="51.2">Let's call her Thelma.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="52">(Laughter) So, we've got Spike and Thelma.</s>
 <p id="p53">
  <s id="53.1">Let's try another one.</s>
  <s id="53.2">Here we go.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">Another little variation.</s>
  <s id="54.2">You're getting the idea.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">Starting with the nose.</s>
 <s id="56">But this time we'll change the eyes slightly.</s>
 <s id="57">Look, two circles together like that.</s>
 <s id="58">That's it.</s>
 <s id="59">Then, two little dots in for the eyes.</s>
 <p id="p60">
  <s id="60.1">And this time we'll change the mouth slightly.</s>
  <s id="60.2">Watch.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="61">Little circle colored in there.</s>
 <s id="62">Have a go at that.</s>
 <s id="63">Next, the ear.</s>
 <s id="64">Now, we'll have some fun with the hair, watch.</s>
 <s id="65">Nice curly hair.</s>
 <s id="66">Then same thing: pen to the left to the mouth, little line like that.</s>
 <s id="67">Under the ear, drop a line.</s>
 <s id="68">Top of the T-shirt.</s>
 <s id="69">Line to the left, line to the right.</s>
 <s id="70">I think we'll call him Jeff.</s>
 <s id="71">(Laughter) We'll do one more.</s>
 <p id="p72">
  <s id="72.1">One more go.</s>
  <s id="72.2">Here we go.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="73">You're getting the idea.</s>
 <s id="74">(Laughter) So we'll start with a nose again.</s>
 <s id="75">Notice we're doing little variations.</s>
 <s id="76">Now we'll change the eyes, so we've got them apart.</s>
 <s id="77">We'll put some little dots in like that.</s>
 <s id="78">Next, the mouth slightly different.</s>
 <s id="79">Let's put a little V-shape like that.</s>
 <s id="80">Triangle.</s>
 <s id="81">And a little line across, and we'll just color this a little bit in.</s>
 <s id="82">Now, watch this bit carefully; some hair, watch.</s>
 <s id="83">Here we go, little line like that.</s>
 <s id="84">Next, a bit more there.</s>
 <s id="85">And watch, a couple of triangles to make a little bow.</s>
 <s id="86">Triangle at the bottom, rest of the hair.</s>
 <p id="p87">
  <s id="87.1">Pen to the left of the mouth again.</s>
  <s id="87.2">You get the idea.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="88">Drop a line for the neck.</s>
 <s id="89">Now the V-shape.</s>
 <s id="90">Line to the left, line to the right.</s>
 <s id="91">There we go.</s>
 <s id="92">Let's call her Pam.</s>
 <s id="93">(Laughter) So you've done...</s>
 <p id="p94">
  <s id="94.1">(Laughter) So you've done four cartoons.</s>
  <s id="94.2">You can have a little rest now.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="95">(Laughter) Take a rest.</s>
 <p id="p96">
  <s id="96.1">You're getting the idea.</s>
  <s id="96.2">All we're doing is little variations.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="97">I'll just demonstrate a couple to you.</s>
 <s id="98">We could go on all day, couldn't we?</s>
 <s id="99">You could do someone looking unhappy, a bit like that, or you could experiment with, perhaps, someone who is… just draw a straight line, someone looking a bit fed up.</s>
 <s id="100">Or perhaps, you could do anything you like, really, just try things out.</s>
 <p id="p101">
  <s id="101.1">Look at this.</s>
  <s id="101.2">Little squiggle.</s>
  <s id="101.3">There we are.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="102">So, all sorts of things we could do.</s>
 <s id="103">Actually, one more I'll let you do, one more idea.</s>
 <s id="104">This is a great little technique.</s>
 <s id="105">Have a go at this: people with glasses on.</s>
 <s id="106">Just draw a nose a bit like Spike's.</s>
 <s id="107">Next, draw some frames, so two circles like that with a little bit in between.</s>
 <s id="108">Now, just put some dots inside for the eyes like that.</s>
 <s id="109">Next, the ear.</s>
 <s id="110">So it's little bit like we did before, but this time we'll join up the frames.</s>
 <p id="p111">
  <s id="111.1">That's it.</s>
  <s id="111.2">Watch this bit.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p112">
  <s id="112.1">(Laughter) And this bit I really like.</s>
  <s id="112.2">Watch.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="113">(Laughter) And then, little bit there.</s>
 <s id="114">Pencil under the mustache, line down, top of the shirt, left and right.</s>
 <p id="p115">
  <s id="115.1">So there we have it.</s>
  <s id="115.2">We could carry on, couldn't we?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="116">Hopefully, we've done enough to convince you that in fact we can all draw.</s>
 <p id="p117">
  <s id="117.1">And not just people here.</s>
  <s id="117.2">I've worked with… I'm going to give you three examples of other people who've learned to draw, and that actually surprised them, too.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="118">I'm going to save what I think is my favorite, most surprising example until last.</s>
 <s id="119">The first example is: I've worked a lot with children and students in schools.</s>
 <s id="120">Actually the little ones, they just draw fine, but when they get to about 15 or 16, most of them think they can't draw.</s>
 <s id="121">But I worked with them.</s>
 <s id="122">I worked this week in a school where I was coaching them on using pictures for memory.</s>
 <s id="123">A girl was trying to remember what red blood cells do, and she drew this little picture of a red blood cell carrying a handbag with O2 on it to remind her that the red blood cells carry oxygen to all parts of the body.</s>
 <s id="124">That was a great one.</s>
 <s id="125">The other people I worked with are many adults in all walks of life, and particularly in business, and they often will want to make presentations memorable.</s>
 <s id="126">So again, a quick cartoon or sketch could be really good for that.</s>
 <s id="127">And again, most people think they can't draw, but take this example.</s>
 <s id="128">Couple of wavy lines, little boat could be a metaphor to represent we're all in this together.</s>
 <s id="129">So that, if that was just drawn in the presentation, would really stay in the memory, wouldn't it?</s>
 <s id="130">Yeah.</s>
 <s id="131">But the third example is - you shouldn't have favorites, should you?</s>
 <s id="132">This is my favorite.</s>
 <s id="133">Have you ever been at the party when someone asks you what you do?</s>
 <s id="134">It gets a little bit skeptical when people ask me that.</s>
 <s id="135">This lady said to me, well - I said, "I do a little bit of training, and I teach people to draw," and she said, "Would you come along and do some for our group?"</s>
 <s id="136">She said, "I work with some people" - she was a volunteer - a group of people who have suffered strokes.</s>
 <s id="137">So I said, "Sure, I could spare some time for that."</s>
 <s id="138">So I said I would, and I booked the time in.</s>
 <s id="139">Have you ever done that?</s>
 <s id="140">You get near of that time and you think, "What have I let myself in for here?"</s>
 <s id="141">"Will I be able to do it?"</s>
 <s id="142">I thought, "What could I do with them?" you see.</s>
 <p id="p143">
  <s id="143.1">"I know.</s>
  <s id="143.2">I'll do my cartoon drawing.</s>
  <s id="143.3">They'll like that."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="144">But then, as I got near of the time, I got more apprehensive, because then I was thinking, "I've worked with children, with all sorts of adults; I've never worked with a group like this."</s>
 <s id="145">It turns out it was all part of a charity called TALK.</s>
 <s id="146">This TALK charity is a wonderful charity that helps people who've suffered strokes, but have a particular condition known as aphasia.</s>
 <s id="147">You might have heard of aphasia, sometimes called dysphasia.</s>
 <s id="148">The key thing is it affects their ability to communicate.</s>
 <s id="149">So, for example, they might have trouble reading, writing, speaking, or understanding.</s>
 <s id="150">It can be quite an isolating condition; it can be very, very frustrating and can lead to a loss of confidence.</s>
 <s id="151">Anyway, so I prepared all this stuff, what to do for this session - for a couple of hours, tea break in the middle - and I got more apprehensive.</s>
 <s id="152">But actually, I needn't have worried, because I'm going to show you now the work that they did.</s>
 <s id="153">It was one of the best things I've ever done.</s>
 <s id="154">I'm going to show you the first slide.</s>
 <s id="155">I taught them Spike, just like I did for you, and I want you to see the reaction on their faces when they did this.</s>
 <s id="156">(Audience) Oh.</s>
 <s id="157">What you can see here are two of the stroke recoverers on the left and right, and one of the volunteer helpers in the center.</s>
 <s id="158">Each stroke recoverer, there are about 36 in the room with volunteers as well, there's one-to-one helpers.</s>
 <s id="159">You can just see the delight on their faces, can't you?</s>
 <s id="160">Let's look at another picture.</s>
 <s id="161">This is a gentleman called David, and he's holding up his picture, and you can tell it was the picture of Spike, can't you?</s>
 <s id="162">In fact, I think he's drawn Spike even better there.</s>
 <s id="163">But what I didn't realize until even after the session was that the number of the people in this session, including David, were drawing with their wrong hand.</s>
 <s id="164">David's stroke meant that it affected the right side of his body, and he drew with his left hand, as many did.</s>
 <s id="165">Nobody mentioned it to me, nobody complained.</s>
 <s id="166">They just got on with it.</s>
 <s id="167">It was an inspirational session for me.</s>
 <s id="168">It was quite a humbling session, one of the best things I felt I've ever done.</s>
 <s id="169">At the end of it, I had a lovely email from doctor Mike Jordan, and he's the chair of the TALK group; happens to be a medical doctor, but he's the chair of the group.</s>
 <s id="170">He wrote to me, and I'm quoting, he said, "Our recoverers learned today that they can draw.</s>
 <s id="171">It's a bit more than that; this sort of activity really builds their confidence."</s>
 <s id="172">So I was happy, he was happy, everyone was happy, they've invited me back again, and I go in there now about every three or four months.</s>
 <p id="p173">
  <s id="173.1">So it's great.</s>
  <s id="173.2">I thought that was a lovely example to share.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="174">Fancy one more drawing?</s>
 <s id="175">(Audience) Yes.</s>
 <p id="p176">
  <s id="176.1">Here we go.</s>
  <s id="176.2">Grab your pens.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p177">
  <s id="177.1">Here we go.</s>
  <s id="177.2">Right.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="178">I'm going to get you to draw someone that you would recognize.</s>
 <s id="179">So start with a big nose, a bit like Spike's.</s>
 <s id="180">Next, we'll do some eyes, and you might be thinking, "This is also a bit like Spike."</s>
 <s id="181">Watch the next bit.</s>
 <s id="182">You're getting warm.</s>
 <s id="183">There you go.</s>
 <s id="184">Little line down there.</s>
 <s id="185">Down here.</s>
 <s id="186">Little V-shape, line to the left, line to the right.</s>
 <s id="187">And you've got Albert Einstein.</s>
 <s id="188">(Laughter) So you've got the pens with you, you've proved that you can draw.</s>
 <s id="189">You're very welcome to take the pens with you and have a practice at home, even show somebody else.</s>
 <s id="190">But actually, I'd like to leave you with a final thought.</s>
 <s id="191">When you walked in here today, many of you didn't believe you could draw.</s>
 <s id="192">I've got a question for you about that.</s>
 <s id="193">How many other beliefs and limiting thoughts do we all carry around with us every day?</s>
 <s id="194">Beliefs that we could perhaps potentially challenge and think differently about.</s>
 <s id="195">If we did challenge those beliefs and think differently about them, apart from drawing, what else would be possible for us all?</s>
 <s id="196">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="197">(Applause)</s>
</text>
