<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Curiosity: a blessing, or a curse?</s>
 <s id="2">The paradoxical nature of this trait was personified for the ancient Greeks in the mythical figure of Pandora.</s>
 <s id="3">According to legend, she was the first mortal woman, whose blazing curiosity set a chain of earth-shattering events in motion.</s>
 <s id="4">Pandora was breathed into being by Hephaestus, God of fire, who enlisted the help of his divine companions to make her extraordinary.</s>
 <s id="5">From Aphrodite she received the capacity for deep emotion; from Hermes she gained mastery over language.</s>
 <s id="6">Athena gave the gift of fine craftsmanship and attention to detail, and Hermes gave her her name.</s>
 <s id="7">Finally, Zeus bestowed two gifts on Pandora.</s>
 <s id="8">The first was the trait of curiosity, which settled in her spirit and sent her eagerly out into the world.</s>
 <s id="9">The second was a heavy box, ornately curved, heavy to hold – and screwed tightly shut.</s>
 <s id="10">But the contents, Zeus told her, were not for mortal eyes.</s>
 <s id="11">She was not to open the box under any circumstance.</s>
 <s id="12">On earth, Pandora met and fell in love with Epimetheus, a talented titan who had been given the task of designing the natural world by Zeus.</s>
 <s id="13">He had worked alongside his brother Prometheus, who created the first humans but was eternally punished for giving them fire.</s>
 <s id="14">Epimetheus missed his brother desperately, but in Pandora he found another fiery-hearted soul for companionship.</s>
 <s id="15">Pandora brimmed with excitement at life on earth.</s>
 <s id="16">She was also easily distracted and could be impatient, given her thirst for knowledge and desire to question her surroundings.</s>
 <s id="17">Often, her mind wandered to the contents of the sealed box.</s>
 <s id="18">What treasure was so great it could never be seen by human eyes, and why was it in her care?</s>
 <s id="19">Her fingers itched to pry it open.</s>
 <s id="20">Sometimes she was convinced she heard voices whispering and the contents rattling around inside, as if straining to be free.</s>
 <s id="21">Its enigma became maddening.</s>
 <s id="22">Over time, Pandora became more and more obsessed with the box.</s>
 <s id="23">It seemed there was a force beyond her control that drew her to the contents, which echoed her name louder and louder.</s>
 <s id="24">One day she could bear it no longer.</s>
 <s id="25">Stealing away from Epimetheus, she stared at the mystifying box.</s>
 <s id="26">She’d take one glance inside, then be able to rid her mind of it forever...</s>
 <s id="27">But at the first crack of the lid, the box burst open.</s>
 <s id="28">Monstrous creatures and horrendous sounds rushed out in a cloud of smoke and swirled around her, screeching and cackling.</s>
 <s id="29">Filled with terror, Pandora clawed desperately at the air to direct them back into their prison.</s>
 <s id="30">But the creatures surged out in a gruesome cloud.</s>
 <s id="31">She felt a wave of foreboding as they billowed away.</s>
 <s id="32">Zeus had used the box as a vessel for all the forces of evil and suffering he’d created – and once released, they were uncontainable.</s>
 <s id="33">As she wept, Pandora became aware of a sound echoing from within the box.</s>
 <s id="34">This was not the eerie whispering of demons, but a light tinkling that seemed to ease her anguish.</s>
 <s id="35">When she once again lifted the lid and peered in, a warm beam of light rose out and fluttered away.</s>
 <s id="36">As she watched it flickering in the wake of the evil she’d unleashed, Pandora’s pain was eased.</s>
 <s id="37">She knew that opening the box was irreversible – but alongside the strife, she’d set hope forth to temper its effects.</s>
 <s id="38">Today, Pandora’s Box suggests the extreme consequences of tampering with the unknown – but Pandora’s burning curiosity also suggests the duality that lies at the heart of human inquiry.</s>
 <s id="39">Are we bound to investigate everything we don’t know, to mine the earth for more – or are there some mysteries that are better left unsolved?</s>
</text>
