<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">This is a man-made forest.</s>
 <s id="2">It can spread over acres and acres of area, or it could fit in a small space -- as small as your house garden.</s>
 <s id="3">Age of this forest is just two years old.</s>
 <s id="4">I have a forest in the backyard of my own house.</s>
 <s id="5">It attracts a lot of biodiversity.</s>
 <s id="6">(Bird call) I wake up to this every morning, like a Disney princess.</s>
 <s id="7">(Laughter) I am an entrepreneur who facilitates the making of these forests professionally.</s>
 <s id="8">We have helped factories, farms, schools, homes, resorts, apartment buildings, public parks and even a zoo to have one of such forests.</s>
 <s id="9">A forest is not an isolated piece of land where animals live together.</s>
 <s id="10">A forest can be an integral part of our urban existence.</s>
 <s id="11">A forest, for me, is a place so dense with trees that you just can't walk into it.</s>
 <s id="12">It doesn't matter how big or small they are.</s>
 <s id="13">Most of the world we live in today was forest.</s>
 <s id="14">This was before human intervention.</s>
 <s id="15">Then we built up our cities on those forests, like São Paulo, forgetting that we belong to nature as well, as much as 8.4 million other species on the planet.</s>
 <s id="16">Our habitat stopped being our natural habitat.</s>
 <s id="17">But not anymore for some of us.</s>
 <s id="18">A few others and I today make these forests professionally -- anywhere and everywhere.</s>
 <s id="19">I'm an industrial engineer.</s>
 <s id="20">I specialize in making cars.</s>
 <s id="21">In my previous job at Toyota, I learned how to convert natural resources into products.</s>
 <s id="22">To give you an example, we would drip the sap out of a rubber tree, convert it into raw rubber and make a tire out of it -- the product.</s>
 <s id="23">But these products can never become a natural resource again.</s>
 <s id="24">We separate the elements from nature and convert them into an irreversible state.</s>
 <s id="25">That's industrial production.</s>
 <s id="26">Nature, on the other hand, works in a totally opposite way.</s>
 <s id="27">The natural system produces by bringing elements together, atom by atom.</s>
 <s id="28">All the natural products become a natural resource again.</s>
 <s id="29">This is something which I learned when I made a forest in the backyard of my own house.</s>
 <s id="30">And this was the first time I worked with nature, rather than against it.</s>
 <s id="31">Since then, we have made 75 such forests in 25 cities across the world.</s>
 <s id="32">Every time we work at a new place, we find that every single element needed to make a forest is available right around us.</s>
 <s id="33">All we have to do is to bring these elements together and let nature take over.</s>
 <s id="34">To make a forest we start with soil.</s>
 <s id="35">We touch, feel and even taste it to identify what properties it lacks.</s>
 <s id="36">If the soil is made up of small particles it becomes compact -- so compact, that water cannot seep in.</s>
 <s id="37">We mix some local biomass available around, which can help soil become more porous.</s>
 <s id="38">Water can now seep in.</s>
 <s id="39">If the soil doesn't have the capacity to hold water, we will mix some more biomass -- some water-absorbent material like peat or bagasse, so soil can hold this water and it stays moist.</s>
 <s id="40">To grow, plants need water, sunlight and nutrition.</s>
 <s id="41">What if the soil doesn't have any nutrition in it?</s>
 <s id="42">We don't just add nutrition directly to the soil.</s>
 <s id="43">That would be the industrial way.</s>
 <s id="44">It goes against nature.</s>
 <s id="45">We instead add microorganisms to the soil.</s>
 <s id="46">They produce the nutrients in the soil naturally.</s>
 <s id="47">They feed on the biomass we have mixed in the soil, so all they have to do is eat and multiply.</s>
 <s id="48">And as their number grows, the soil starts breathing again.</s>
 <s id="49">It becomes alive.</s>
 <s id="50">We survey the native tree species of the place.</s>
 <s id="51">How do we decide what's native or not?</s>
 <s id="52">Well, whatever existed before human intervention is native.</s>
 <s id="53">That's the simple rule.</s>
 <s id="54">We survey a national park to find the last remains of a natural forest.</s>
 <s id="55">We survey the sacred groves, or sacred forests around old temples.</s>
 <s id="56">And if we don't find anything at all, we go to museums to see the seeds or wood of trees existing there a long time ago.</s>
 <s id="57">We research old paintings, poems and literature from the place, to identify the tree species belonging there.</s>
 <s id="58">Once we know our trees, we divide them in four different layers: shrub layer, sub-tree layer, tree layer and canopy layer.</s>
 <s id="59">We fix the ratios of each layer, and then we decide the percentage of each tree species in the mix.</s>
 <s id="60">If we are making a fruit forest, we increase the percentage of fruit-bearing trees.</s>
 <s id="61">It could be a flowering forest, a forest that attracts a lot of birds or bees, or it could simply be a native, wild evergreen forest.</s>
 <s id="62">We collect the seeds and germinate saplings out of them.</s>
 <s id="63">We make sure that trees belonging to the same layer are not planted next to each other, or they will fight for the same vertical space when they grow tall.</s>
 <s id="64">We plant the saplings close to each other.</s>
 <s id="65">On the surface, we spread a thick layer of mulch, so when it's hot outside the soil stays moist.</s>
 <s id="66">When it's cold, frost formation happens only on the mulch, so soil can still breathe while it's freezing outside.</s>
 <s id="67">The soil is very soft -- so soft, that roots can penetrate into it easily, rapidly.</s>
 <s id="68">Initially, the forest doesn't seem like it's growing, but it's growing under the surface.</s>
 <s id="69">In the first three months, roots reach a depth of one meter.</s>
 <s id="70">These roots form a mesh, tightly holding the soil.</s>
 <s id="71">Microbes and fungi live throughout this network of roots.</s>
 <s id="72">So if some nutrition is not available in the vicinity of a tree, these microbes are going to get the nutrition to the tree.</s>
 <s id="73">Whenever it rains, magically, mushrooms appear overnight.</s>
 <s id="74">And this means the soil below has a healthy fungal network.</s>
 <s id="75">Once these roots are established, forest starts growing on the surface.</s>
 <s id="76">As the forest grows we keep watering it -- for the next two to three years, we water the forest.</s>
 <s id="77">We want to keep all the water and soil nutrition only for our trees, so we remove the weeds growing on the ground.</s>
 <s id="78">As this forest grows, it blocks the sunlight.</s>
 <s id="79">Eventually, the forest becomes so dense that sunlight can't reach the ground anymore.</s>
 <s id="80">Weeds cannot grow now, because they need sunlight as well.</s>
 <s id="81">At this stage, every single drop of water that falls into the forest doesn't evaporate back into the atmosphere.</s>
 <s id="82">This dense forest condenses the moist air and retains its moisture.</s>
 <s id="83">We gradually reduce and eventually stop watering the forest.</s>
 <s id="84">And even without watering, the forest floor stays moist and sometimes even dark.</s>
 <s id="85">Now, when a single leaf falls on this forest floor, it immediately starts decaying.</s>
 <s id="86">This decayed biomass forms humus, which is food for the forest.</s>
 <s id="87">As the forest grows, more leaves fall on the surface -- it means more humus is produced, it means more food so the forest can grow still bigger.</s>
 <s id="88">And this forest keeps growing exponentially.</s>
 <s id="89">Once established, these forests are going to regenerate themselves again and again -- probably forever.</s>
 <s id="90">In a natural forest like this, no management is the best management.</s>
 <s id="91">It's a tiny jungle party.</s>
 <s id="92">(Laughter) This forest grows as a collective.</s>
 <s id="93">If the same trees -- same species -- would have been planted independently, it wouldn't grow so fast.</s>
 <s id="94">And this is how we create a 100-year-old forest in just 10 years.</s>
 <s id="95">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="96">(Applause)</s>
</text>
