<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Tom Green: That's a 4chan thing.</s>
 <s id="2">These kids on the Internet, they have this group of kids and they like to say funny words like "barrel roll."</s>
 <s id="3">It's a video game move from "Star Fox."</s>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">"Star Fox 20"?</s>
  <s id="4.2">(Assistant: "Star Fox 64.")</s>
  <s id="4.3">Tom Green: Yeah.</s>
  <s id="4.4">And they've been dogging me for a year.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="5">I got to tell you, it's driving me nuts, actually.</s>
 <s id="6">Sometimes I wake up in the middle of the night and I scream, "4chan!"</s>
 <s id="7">Christopher Poole: When I was 15, I found this website called Futaba Channel.</s>
 <s id="8">And it was a Japanese forum and imageboard.</s>
 <s id="9">That format of forum, at that time, was not well-known outside of Japan.</s>
 <s id="10">And so what I did is I took it, I translated it into English, and I stuck it up for my friends to use.</s>
 <s id="11">Now, six and a half years later, over seven million people are using it, contributing over 700,000 posts per day.</s>
 <s id="12">And we've gone from one board to 48 boards.</s>
 <s id="13">This is what it looks like.</s>
 <s id="14">So, what's unique about the site is that it's anonymous, and it has no memory.</s>
 <s id="15">There's no archive, there are no barriers, there's no registration.</s>
 <s id="16">These things that we're used to with forums don't exist on 4chan.</s>
 <s id="17">And that's led to this discussion that's completely raw, completely unfiltered.</s>
 <s id="18">What the site's known for, because it has this environment, is it's fostered the creation of a lot of Internet phenomena, viral videos and whatnot, known as "memes."</s>
 <s id="19">Two of the largest memes that have come out of this site some of you might be familiar with are these LOLcats -- just silly pictures of cats with text.</s>
 <s id="20">And this resonates with millions of people, apparently, because there are tens of thousands of these, and there is a whole blogging empire now dedicated to pictures like these.</s>
 <s id="21">And Rick Astley's kind of rebirth these past two years ...</s>
 <s id="22">Rickroll was this bait and switch, really simple, classic bait and switch.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">Somebody says they're linking to something interesting, and you get an '80s pop song.</s>
  <s id="23.2">That's all it was.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="24">And it got big enough to the point where there was a float last year at the Macy's Thanksgiving Day parade, and Rick Astley pops out, and rickrolls millions of people on television.</s>
 <s id="25">(Laughter) There are thousands of memes that come out of the site.</s>
 <s id="26">There are a handful that have escaped into the mainstream, the ones I've just shown you, but every day, every month, people are producing thousands of these.</s>
 <s id="27">So does a site like this have rules?</s>
 <s id="28">We do; they're the codified rules that I've come up with, which are more-or-less ignored by the community.</s>
 <s id="29">And so they've come up with their own set of rules, the "Rules of the Internet."</s>
 <s id="30">And so there are three that I want to show you specifically.</s>
 <s id="31">Rule one is you don't talk about /b/.</s>
 <s id="32">Two is you do not talk about /b/.</s>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">And this one's kind of interesting: "If it exists, there is porn of it.</s>
  <s id="33.2">No exceptions."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="34">(Laughter) And I will spare you that slide.</s>
 <s id="35">I assure you, it is very true.</s>
 <s id="36">/b/ is the first board we started with, and it is, in many ways, the beating heart of the website.</s>
 <s id="37">It is where a third of all the traffic is going.</s>
 <s id="38">And /b/ is known for, more than anything, not just the memes they've created, but the exploits.</s>
 <s id="39">And Chris just touched on one of those a second ago, and that was the Time 100 poll.</s>
 <s id="40">So somebody at Time, at the magazine, thought it would be fun to nominate me for this thing they did last year.</s>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">And so they placed me on it, and the Internet got wind of it.</s>
  <s id="41.2">My community decided they wanted me to win it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">I didn't instruct them to do it; they just decided that that's what they wanted.</s>
 <s id="43">And so, you know, 390 percent approval rating ain't so bad.</s>
 <s id="44">(Laughter) So they broke that poll.</s>
 <s id="45">And I ended up on top.</s>
 <s id="46">I ended up at this really fancy party.</s>
 <s id="47">But that's not what's interesting about this.</s>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">It's that they weren't putting me at the top of this list; they were actually -- it got so sophisticated to the point where they gamed all of the top 21 places to spell "mARBLECAKE.</s>
  <s id="48.2">ALSO, THE GAME."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) The amount of time and effort that went into that is absolutely incredible.</s>
 <s id="50">And "marble cake" is significant because it is the channel that this group called Anonymous organized.</s>
 <s id="51">Anonymous is this group of people that protested, very famously, Scientology.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">The story is, Scientology had this embarrassing video of Tom Cruise.</s>
  <s id="52.2">It went up online.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="53">They got it taken offline and managed to piss off part of the Internet.</s>
 <s id="54">And so these people, over 7,000 people, less than one month later, organized in a hundred cities around the globe and -- this is L.A. -- protested the Church of Scientology, and they have continued to do so, now, two full years after the fact.</s>
 <s id="55">They are still protesting.</s>
 <s id="56">(Laughter) So we've got this activist group that's this grassroots group that's come out of the site.</s>
 <s id="57">And last, I'm going to show you the example, the story of Dusty the cat.</s>
 <s id="58">Dusty is the name that we've given to this cat.</s>
 <s id="59">This young man posted a video of him abusing his cat on YouTube.</s>
 <s id="60">And, you know, this didn't sit well with people, and so there was this outpouring of support for people to do something about this.</s>
 <s id="61">So what they did is they -- I mean, they put CSI to shame here -- the Internet detectives came out.</s>
 <s id="62">They matched, they found his MySpace.</s>
 <s id="63">They took the YouTube video and they mashed everything in the video.</s>
 <s id="64">Within 24 hours, they had his name, and within 48 hours, he was arrested.</s>
 <s id="65">(Applause) And so, what I think is really intriguing about a community like 4chan is just that it's this open place.</s>
 <s id="66">As I said, it's raw, it's unfiltered.</s>
 <s id="67">And sites like it are kind of going the way of the dinosaur right now.</s>
 <s id="68">They're endangered because we're moving towards social networking.</s>
 <s id="69">We're moving towards persistent identity.</s>
 <s id="70">We're moving towards, you know, a lack of privacy, really.</s>
 <s id="71">We're sacrificing a lot of that, and I think in doing so, moving towards those things, we're losing something valuable.</s>
 <s id="72">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="73">(Applause) Chris Anderson: Thank you.</s>
 <s id="74">Got a couple questions for you.</s>
 <s id="75">But if I ask them, is the TED website going to go down?</s>
 <s id="76">CP: You're lucky that this is not being streamed to them live right now.</s>
 <p id="p77">
  <s id="77.1">CA: Well, you never know.</s>
  <s id="77.2">Some of them -- we've got people in 75 countries out there watching.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="78">Don't tell.</s>
 <s id="79">But seriously, this issue on anonymity is -- I mean, you made the case there.</s>
 <s id="80">But anonymity basically allows people to say anything, all the rules gone.</s>
 <s id="81">You've had to wrestle with issues like child pornography.</s>
 <s id="82">And I'm just curious whether you sometimes lie awake in the night worrying that you've opened Pandora's box.</s>
 <s id="83">CP: Yes and no.</s>
 <s id="84">I mean, for as much good that kind of comes out of this environment, there is plenty of bad.</s>
 <s id="85">There are plenty of downsides.</s>
 <s id="86">But I think that the greater good is being served here by just allowing people -- there are very few places, now, where you can go and not have identity, to be completely anonymous and say whatever you'd like.</s>
 <s id="87">And saying whatever you like, I think, is powerful.</s>
 <s id="88">Doing whatever you like is now crossing a line.</s>
 <s id="89">But I think it's important to have these places.</s>
 <s id="90">When I get emails, people say, "Thank you for giving me this place, this outlet, where I can come after work and be myself."</s>
 <s id="91">CA: But words, saying things, you know, can be constructive; it can be really damaging.</s>
 <s id="92">And if you cut the link between what is said and any attribution back to you, I mean, surely there are huge risks with that.</s>
 <s id="93">CP: There are, certainly.</s>
 <s id="94">But -- CA: Tell me about what -- I mean, I think you asked the board what you might say at TED, right?</s>
 <s id="95">CP: Yeah, I posted a thread on Sunday.</s>
 <s id="96">And within 24 hours, it had over 12,000 responses.</s>
 <s id="97">And the thing is, I didn't make it into that presentation because I can't read to you anything that they said, more or less.</s>
 <s id="98">(Laughter) 99 percent of it is just, would have been, you know, bleeped out.</s>
 <s id="99">But there were some good things that came out of that too.</s>
 <s id="100">(Laughter) Love and peace were mentioned.</s>
 <s id="101">CA: Love and peace were mentioned, kind of with quote marks around them, right?</s>
 <s id="102">CP: Cats and dogs were mentioned too.</s>
 <s id="103">CA: And that content is all off the board now.</s>
 <p id="p104">
  <s id="104.1">Right, it's gone?</s>
  <s id="104.2">Or is it still up there?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="105">CP: I stuck that thread so it lasted a few days.</s>
 <s id="106">It went up to about 16,000 posts, and now it has been taken off.</s>
 <s id="107">CA: Okay, well.</s>
 <s id="108">Now, I'm not sure I would have necessarily recommended everyone at TED to go and check it out anyway.</s>
 <p id="p109">
  <s id="109.1">Chris, you yourself?</s>
  <s id="109.2">I mean, you're a figure of some intrigue.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="110">You've got this surprising semi-underground influence, but it's not making you a lot of money, yet.</s>
 <s id="111">What's the commercial picture here?</s>
 <s id="112">CP: The commercial picture is that there really isn't much of one, I guess.</s>
 <s id="113">The site has adult content on it.</s>
 <s id="114">I mean, obviously, it's got some very offensive, obscene content on it, just in terms of language alone.</s>
 <s id="115">And when you've got that, you've pretty much sacrificed any hope of making lots of money.</s>
 <s id="116">CA: But you still live at home, right?</s>
 <s id="117">CP: I actually moved out recently.</s>
 <s id="118">CA: That's very cool.</s>
 <s id="119">(Applause) CP: I got out of Mom's, and I'm back in school right now.</s>
 <s id="120">CA: But what conversations did you or do you have with your mother about 4chan?</s>
 <s id="121">CP: At first, very kind of pained, awkward conversations.</s>
 <s id="122">The content is not dinner table conversation in the least.</s>
 <s id="123">But my parents -- I think part of why they kind of are able to appreciate it is because they don't understand it.</s>
 <s id="124">(Laughter) CA: And they were probably pleased to see you on top of the Time poll.</s>
 <p id="p125">
  <s id="125.1">CP: Yeah.</s>
  <s id="125.2">They still didn't know what to think of that though.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="126">(Laughter) CA: And so, in 10 years' time, what do you picture yourself doing?</s>
 <s id="127">CP: That's a good question.</s>
 <s id="128">As I said, I just went back to school, and I am considering majoring in urban studies and then going on to urban planning, kind of taking whatever I've learned from online communities and trying to adapt that to a physical community.</s>
 <p id="p129">
  <s id="129.1">CA: Chris, thank you.</s>
  <s id="129.2">Absolutely fascinating.</s>
  <s id="129.3">Thank you for coming to TED.</s>
 </p>
</text>
