<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Pre-recorded voice) In order to get a job, convince a client, win over our partner, in short, to persuade, the voice is a decisive factor.</s>
 <s id="2">Well, I think this way of speaking wouldn't have been credible or very convincing, right?</s>
 <s id="3">And that's because I haven't correctly combined the qualities of the voice.</s>
 <s id="4">What a mess!</s>
 <s id="5">Meaning, I haven't played the right piano keys.</s>
 <s id="6">The voice has a very powerful influence in our day to day.</s>
 <s id="7">Basically, because it's the vehicle conveying the message.</s>
 <s id="8">But what happens, since the problem arises if we don't use it correctly, what can happen is what's happening here: the goods don't get there.</s>
 <s id="9">Meaning, in the end, the message doesn't arrive.</s>
 <s id="10">That's why it's important to know it, that's why it's important to exercise it.</s>
 <s id="11">And that's my goal today here.</s>
 <s id="12">explaining how you need to manipulate it in order to achieve your goal.</s>
 <s id="13">That is, for the message to arrive, to persuade.</s>
 <s id="14">And I'll give you some strategies for being credible.</s>
 <s id="15">So, let's start at the beginning.</s>
 <s id="16">We'll get help from our voice box over here.</s>
 <s id="17">The voice has four qualities, which are: the intensity, the tone, the timbre, and the duration.</s>
 <s id="18">Let's start with the first, which is the simplest: the intensity.</s>
 <s id="19">What is intensity?</s>
 <s id="20">Well, it's the volume of our voice.</s>
 <s id="21">Meaning whether I speak more quietly or whether I speak more loudly.</s>
 <s id="22">It's simple to understand.</s>
 <s id="23">On what does the intensity depend?</s>
 <s id="24">Very simply, it depends on our breathing.</s>
 <s id="25">Yes, I said that right, it depends on our breathing.</s>
 <s id="26">Breathing is the foundation of our voice.</s>
 <s id="27">And intensity is nothing more than the force with which we push air towards the vocal cords.</s>
 <s id="28">It's as simple as that.</s>
 <s id="29">And who's responsible for pushing that air, for creating that force?</s>
 <s id="30">Well, it's an organ we have here in the abdominal area, called the diaphragm.</s>
 <s id="31">And what are you going to see in action right now, in this short video?</s>
 <s id="32">You are going to see, this is an exhalation.</s>
 <s id="33">And when we inhale, the lungs fill up and the diaphragm goes down.</s>
 <s id="34">Afterwards, the diaphragm is responsible for expelling that air out of the lungs.</s>
 <s id="35">So that's what exerts the force in the end.</s>
 <s id="36">For you to understand that force, or for you to feel that force, let's all do an exercise together.</s>
 <s id="37">First, I'll explain it to you and then we'll see if we can all do it.</s>
 <s id="38">The idea is that we're going to put our hands on the abdominal area, here, where the diaphragm is.</s>
 <s id="39">And we are going to take a deep breath.</s>
 <s id="40">Trying to carry the air to the lower part of the lungs.</s>
 <s id="41">Let's take a breath in a moment and I'll count to three, we'll blow out.</s>
 <s id="42">Just like that.</s>
 <s id="43">Okay, are you ready?</s>
 <p id="p44">
  <s id="44.1">Let's do it.</s>
  <s id="44.2">It's easy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="45">Let's place our hands on the abdominal area like this, everyone.</s>
 <s id="46">We're going to take a breath in a moment.</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">Good, pause.</s>
  <s id="47.2">I count three...</s>
 </p>
 <s id="48">One, two, three.</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">Well done!</s>
  <s id="49.2">You did it perfectly, without practicing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">That force that you've felt, is the strength of the diaphragm towards the vocal cords.</s>
 <s id="51">So, if that force is low, it's small, then we are going to lower our intensity to down here.</s>
 <s id="52">What we'll have as a result is low intensity.</s>
 <s id="53">(Pre-recorded voice, low intensity) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <s id="54">If we lift the circuit board up and go to high intensity...</s>
 <s id="55">(Pre-recorded voice, high intensity) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <s id="56">There is a small difference, right?</s>
 <s id="57">We've gone from 43 decibels to 79.</s>
 <s id="58">Intensity is measured in decibels, no more than the volume of the voice.</s>
 <s id="59">With which there is a perceptible difference.</s>
 <s id="60">Here comes the question: If I want to appear credible, what will I have to use?</s>
 <s id="61">Low intensity, or high intensity?</s>
 <s id="62">Well, if we think about the voice reflecting our personality, if we think about the voice reflecting our state of mind, and we think that, of course, if I suddenly feel sad, very sad, I'm going to use low intensity.</s>
 <s id="63">If I'm bored, too.</s>
 <s id="64">And people who are introverted use low intensity.</s>
 <s id="65">So of course, if I want to seem credible, of course that won't be the intensity that I have to use.</s>
 <p id="p66">
  <s id="66.1">I have to use an energetic intensity.</s>
  <s id="66.2">It has to sound loud and clear.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p67">
  <s id="67.1">I'm not saying shout.</s>
  <s id="67.2">I'm saying an energetic intensity, more or less this, what I'm doing now.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="68">Therefore, this would be the first tip: energetic intensity.</s>
 <s id="69">Let's go to the second of our qualities.</s>
 <s id="70">The second quality is the tone.</s>
 <s id="71">The tone of the voice is difficult to manage, but it's simple to understand.</s>
 <s id="72">Once the diaphragm pushes the lungs, as you have seen, what it does is expel the air.</s>
 <s id="73">Well, that air comes up here, to the neck.</s>
 <s id="74">Inside the neck is the larynx, and inside the larynx are the vocal cords, which vibrate to the passage of that air.</s>
 <p id="p75">
  <s id="75.1">Oh, my God!</s>
  <s id="75.2">Those are vocal cords?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="76">If the image impresses you a little, I can swear to you that you all have ones like these in your body, that vibrate like this.</s>
 <s id="77">Alright.</s>
 <s id="78">What does having a deeper tone or a more high-pitched tone depend on?</s>
 <s id="79">Easy to understand.</s>
 <s id="80">I have two ropes here.</s>
 <s id="81">If I move them with the same force, that is, with the same intensity, which one moves faster?</s>
 <s id="82">This one, right?</s>
 <s id="83">It moves faster because it is shorter and because it's thinner.</s>
 <s id="84">So, what does you having an average tone of voice or another depend?</s>
 <s id="85">Well, it's simply the length and thickness of your vocal cords.</s>
 <s id="86">When they're shorter, they will vibrate faster, so, you'll have a higher pitched tone.</s>
 <s id="87">And for larger ones, men generally have a deeper tone, they will speak more deeply.</s>
 <s id="88">It's as simple as that.</s>
 <s id="89">But of course, we don't speak in just one tone.</s>
 <s id="90">This is our middle tone, let's say it's the one we use in our day to day, most frequently.</s>
 <s id="91">But of course, we use a range of tones when we speak.</s>
 <s id="92">There are differences between them.</s>
 <s id="93">We'll see what happens if I lower the tone.</s>
 <s id="94">Let's see what it sounds like.</s>
 <s id="95">(Pre-recorded voice, low tone) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <s id="96">On the other hand, if I raise it up...</s>
 <s id="97">(Pre-recorded voice, high tone) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <s id="98">There is also a perceptible difference.</s>
 <s id="99">We have gone from 100 to 190 Hz.</s>
 <s id="100">It's simple to understand.</s>
 <s id="101">It's simply that the vocal cords vibrate more slowly if it's deep, or more quickly if it's high-pitched.</s>
 <s id="102">So, what do you think?</s>
 <s id="103">If we want to sound credible, what kind of tone do we have to use?</s>
 <s id="104">Low, or high-pitched?</s>
 <s id="105">Well, all the studies we've done indicate that, in order to be perceived as attractive and credible, we have to use, as you see in the graph, a low tone rather than a high-pitched tone.</s>
 <s id="106">And because of that, many professionals and many politicians train their voice specifically to lower their voice, to use that lower tessitura of your voice.</s>
 <s id="107">I've brought to you the case of Margaret Thatcher, who trained her voice for a long time, to achieve that goal.</s>
 <p id="p108">
  <s id="108.1">Margaret Thatcher: (high-pitched tone) Oh, very much so.</s>
  <s id="108.2">I've done a good deal, but speaking in the House of Commons is quite different.</s>
  <s id="108.3">It's a unique experience.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="109">Margaret Thatcher: (low tone) I think we shall have to make up our minds about the Cabinet very quickly because, otherwise, the press will discuss it all for me.</s>
 <s id="110">Because of course, an Iron Lady talking like this-- It wouldn't make much sense.</s>
 <s id="111">And this is what she did, trained her voice for this.</s>
 <s id="112">Whenever we train the voice, we must use an expert, because if we don't, we can damage the vocal cords.</s>
 <s id="113">So, we have a range of tones, we have a piano, we have to play them in different ways.</s>
 <s id="114">When we talk, we use that combination of tones, and that combination of tones is what we know as intonation.</s>
 <s id="115">Intonation is relatively complicated to understand, but I'll give you two tips.</s>
 <s id="116">The first is that you can't be monotonous when you speak, because if you're monotonous, then no one will listen to you.</s>
 <s id="117">Basically.</s>
 <s id="118">In order to try to modify that monotony, let's try to start the phrase in a high-pitched tone and end in a low tone.</s>
 <s id="119">As you can hear in this example.</s>
 <s id="120">(Pre-recorded voice, high-pitched to low tone) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <p id="p121">
  <s id="121.1">Good.</s>
  <s id="121.2">It's a way of changing the tones.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="122">What we can never do when we speak in public, when we have a presentation, is sing, because if I sing, I leave everything up, and that doesn't sound credible.</s>
 <s id="123">It's simple to understand.</s>
 <s id="124">And you'll see it in this example.</s>
 <s id="125">(Pre-recorded voice, higher intonation) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <p id="p126">
  <s id="126.1">It's as if something is missing!</s>
  <s id="126.2">Why are you staying up there?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="127">We always have to lower the message down, to be credible.</s>
 <s id="128">(Pre-recorded voice, lower intonation) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <s id="129">And here is where it is competent, it is credible, sounds sure, right?</s>
 <s id="130">Let there be no doubt about this.</s>
 <s id="131">So, always remember not to be monotonous, let's try going up to the higher pitch at the beginning, going down to the low pitch at the end.</s>
 <s id="132">And of course, the idea is not to sing.</s>
 <s id="133">Well, when it comes to tone, what happens is many people say, "Having a low tone, I'm already perceived as credible."</s>
 <s id="134">And I'm not sure that's true.</s>
 <s id="135">(Low pitch, closed timbre) It must have been making you sleepy.</s>
 <s id="136">I believe that this is not an attractive voice.</s>
 <s id="137">But it is a voice in a low tone.</s>
 <s id="138">And that's because Marge Simpson lacks our third quality: timbre.</s>
 <s id="139">The timbre of the voice is very easy to understand.</s>
 <s id="140">It is the combination of the sound that comes out of the vocal cords, plus the one that comes out from our sound box.</s>
 <s id="141">What is this sound box?</s>
 <s id="142">The face, for hearing ourselves, this face we have.</s>
 <s id="143">Having a bigger nose, a smaller mouth, etc.</s>
 <s id="144">That, in the end, gives a specific result in your voice.</s>
 <p id="p145">
  <s id="145.1">And that's why your voice is unique.</s>
  <s id="145.2">The sound of your voice is unique.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="146">It's like your fingerprint, in a way.</s>
 <s id="147">So, if my voice is unique, I'm not going to change my nose, so this is the way my voice is.</s>
 <s id="148">And no, obviously not.</s>
 <s id="149">Because if I modify the resonance organs, meaning my lips, my mouth, my tongue, etc.</s>
 <s id="150">I'm going to get a completely different sound.</s>
 <p id="p151">
  <s id="151.1">Let's focus on that.</s>
  <s id="151.2">Let's do a closed timbre, meaning that the speaker closes his mouth a lot.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="152">(Low pitch, closed timbre) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <s id="153">And we're just going to open it later.</s>
 <s id="154">(Pre-recorded voice, open timbre) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <s id="155">Only the width of the mouth has been modified.</s>
 <s id="156">And that already influences the sound.</s>
 <s id="157">What do we need to have to be credible?</s>
 <s id="158">Obviously, open our mouths enough, so that our voice resonates well.</s>
 <p id="p159">
  <s id="159.1">So, what can we do?</s>
  <s id="159.2">Well, we can do some exercises.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p160">
  <s id="160.1">Let's see.</s>
  <s id="160.2">First, let's inflate the cheeks...</s>
 </p>
 <s id="161">Right.</s>
 <s id="162">Left.</s>
 <s id="163">Very good.</s>
 <p id="p164">
  <s id="164.1">Now, let's make another!</s>
  <s id="164.2">More fun, more optimistic.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="165">Let's make a big smile, pulling the corners of or mouths backwards.</s>
 <s id="166">Let's smile.</s>
 <s id="167">And let's close.</s>
 <s id="168">You're very handsome.</s>
 <s id="169">Just like that, perfect.</s>
 <s id="170">We can also pull on the corners directly.</s>
 <s id="171">Like this.</s>
 <s id="172">And this is how we stretch.</s>
 <s id="173">It's important to warm up these facial muscles for speaking.</s>
 <s id="174">They're the ones that have to move in the end.</s>
 <s id="175">So think about it.</s>
 <s id="176">And the last and most complicated, please do this at home, alone, so that no one sees you.</s>
 <s id="177">I'm going to put four fingers in my mouth.</s>
 <s id="178">Yes, I'm sorry, the fingers, in the mouth.</s>
 <s id="179">Vertically, like this.</s>
 <s id="180">And we are going count from 1 to 10.</s>
 <s id="181">Count with me: One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten.</s>
 <p id="p182">
  <s id="182.1">Very good.</s>
  <s id="182.2">Perfect.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="183">You're all lovely, really, but don't do it with anybody around.</s>
 <s id="184">Do it at home.</s>
 <s id="185">Try it before and after.</s>
 <s id="186">You'll see, really, I promise, that, just before, the voice is very muffled, very closed.</s>
 <s id="187">And then suddenly, you hear everything great.</s>
 <s id="188">So, quite simply, do this before placing yourself in front of an audience, making a presentation, or speaking publicly, in general.</s>
 <s id="189">Perfect!</s>
 <s id="190">Let's go with our last quality, which is the duration.</s>
 <s id="191">Duration is not an acoustic quality, but an expressive one.</s>
 <s id="192">It's important that I speak slowly or that I speak fast.</s>
 <s id="193">And if not, let's test it.</s>
 <s id="194">I'll lower the terminal here to the slow one.</s>
 <s id="195">(Pre-recorded voice, slow duration) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <s id="196">And we'll raise it to the fast one.</s>
 <s id="197">(Pre-recorded voice, fast duration) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <p id="p198">
  <s id="198.1">What do you think?</s>
  <s id="198.2">To be credible, what do we need?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="199">Well, we think that a person talks slowly when they're bored.</s>
 <s id="200">On the other hand, if I'm super excited, I speak quickly.</s>
 <s id="201">Okay, you get the idea.</s>
 <s id="202">The studies we've done, and many others worldwide, indicate that a person, in order to be perceived as credible, has to use a speed tending toward fast.</s>
 <s id="203">People who speak a little faster than usual are perceived as more intelligent, more dynamic, more extroverted.</s>
 <s id="204">And note that I said a little faster than usual.</s>
 <p id="p205">
  <s id="205.1">I didn't say very fast.</s>
  <s id="205.2">If you talk very fast, I don't understand you, you make me nervous.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p206">
  <s id="206.1">I didn't say very fast.</s>
  <s id="206.2">I said tending to fast, or a little bit faster, which is what I am doing now.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="207">Maybe the best advice I can give you, in this context, is that you alter your speed when you speak.</s>
 <s id="208">The most important thing is said slowly.</s>
 <s id="209">What is unimportant is said fast.</s>
 <p id="p210">
  <s id="210.1">That contrast is what makes listeners pay more attention and also helps them understand.</s>
  <s id="210.2">So that is important.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="211">Okay, we now have our four qualities.</s>
 <s id="212">Let's assume now, and this is an important point, because the voice is not just one, as I've been saying, it's a set, it's a combination.</s>
 <s id="213">Let's suppose that we we would like to express joy.</s>
 <s id="214">Actually, you see here that we have the perfect combination.</s>
 <s id="215">We have a high intensity, we have a sharp tone, we have an open timbre, meaning we smiled.</s>
 <s id="216">The smile is very perceptible, and a quick duration.</s>
 <s id="217">And this would be the result.</s>
 <s id="218">(Pre-recorded voice) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <s id="219">Let's suppose now, that we would like to express sadness, which is the complete opposite.</s>
 <s id="220">In this case what we would do to begin with, would be to lower the intensity.</s>
 <s id="221">We had to lower the tone to deep.</s>
 <s id="222">We'd have to close our mouths.</s>
 <s id="223">And moreover, we would have to talk slowly.</s>
 <s id="224">And this would be the result.</s>
 <s id="225">(Pre-recorded voice) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <s id="226">You're already wondering, this is the crux of the issue: What do I have to do to be credible?</s>
 <s id="227">We have already seen it.</s>
 <s id="228">We must have an energetic intensity, like we said.</s>
 <s id="229">We must have a rather serious tone with modulated intonation.</s>
 <s id="230">We need an open timbre, and also a speed tending toward fast.</s>
 <s id="231">The result could be more or less this.</s>
 <s id="232">(Pre-recorded voice) The voice has a powerful influence.</s>
 <s id="233">Once we've already established that we have the credibility combination, let's see if we can fix that bad start we had in this presentation.</s>
 <s id="234">(Pre-recorded voice) In order to get a job, convince a client, win over our partner, in short, to persuade, the voice is a decisive factor.</s>
 <s id="235">I hope we've achieved it.</s>
 <s id="236">The voice is the most important instrument that you have for communicating.</s>
 <s id="237">It's the one that has the most influence on your being perceived as competent and credible.</s>
 <s id="238">Today, I hope that you know how to do that a little bit better.</s>
 <s id="239">Thanks so much for your time.</s>
 <s id="240">(Applause)</s>
</text>
