<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">How much would you pay for a bouquet of tulips?</s>
 <p id="p2">
  <s id="2.1">A few dollars?</s>
  <s id="2.2">A hundred dollars?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="3">How about a million dollars?</s>
 <s id="4">Probably not.</s>
 <s id="5">Well, how much would you pay for this house, or partial ownership of a website that sells pet supplies?</s>
 <s id="6">At different points in time, tulips, real estate and stock in pets.com have all sold for much more than they were worth.</s>
 <s id="7">In each instance, the price rose and rose and then abruptly plummeted.</s>
 <s id="8">Economists call this a bubble.</s>
 <s id="9">So what is exactly is going on with a bubble?</s>
 <s id="10">Well, let's start with the tulips to get a better idea.</s>
 <s id="11">The 17th century saw the Netherlands enter the Dutch golden age.</s>
 <s id="12">By the 1630s, Amsterdam was an important port and commercial center.</s>
 <s id="13">Dutch ships imported spices from Asia in huge quantities to earn profits in Europe.</s>
 <s id="14">So Amsterdam was brimming with wealthy, skilled merchants and traders who displayed their prosperity by living in mansions surrounded by flower gardens.</s>
 <s id="15">And there was one flower in particularly high demand: the tulip.</s>
 <s id="16">The tulip was brought to Europe on trading vessels that sailed from the East.</s>
 <s id="17">Because of this, it was considered an exotic flower that was also difficult to grow, since it could take years for a single tulip to bloom.</s>
 <s id="18">During the 1630s, an outbreak of tulip breaking virus made select flowers even more beautiful by lining petals with multicolor, flame-like streaks.</s>
 <s id="19">A tulip like this was scarcer than a normal tulip and as a result, prices for these flowers started to rise, and with them, the tulip's popularity.</s>
 <s id="20">It wasn't long before the tulip became a nationwide sensation and tulip mania was born.</s>
 <s id="21">A mania occurs when there is an upward movement of price combined with a willingness to pay large sums of money for something valued much lower in intrinsic value.</s>
 <s id="22">A recent example of this is the dot-com mania of the 1990s.</s>
 <s id="23">Stocks in new, exciting websites were like the tulips of the 17th century.</s>
 <s id="24">Everybody wanted some.</s>
 <s id="25">The more people who wanted the tulip, the higher the price could go.</s>
 <s id="26">At one point, a single tulip bulb sold for more than ten times the annual salary of a skilled craftsman.</s>
 <s id="27">In the stock market, the price of stock is based on the supply and demand of investors.</s>
 <s id="28">Stock prices tend to rise when it seems like a company will earn more in the future.</s>
 <s id="29">Investors might then buy more of the stock, raising the prices even further due to an increased demand.</s>
 <s id="30">This can result in a feedback loop where investors get caught up in the hype and ultimately drive prices far above intrinsic value, creating a bubble.</s>
 <s id="31">All that is needed for a mania to end and for a bubble to burst is the collective realization that the price of the stock, or a tulip, far exceeds its worth.</s>
 <s id="32">That's what happened with both manias.</s>
 <s id="33">Suddenly the demand ended.</s>
 <s id="34">Prices were pushed to staggering lows, and pop!</s>
 <s id="35">The bubbles burst, and the market crashed.</s>
 <s id="36">Today, scholars work long and hard trying to predict what causes a bubble and how to avoid them.</s>
 <s id="37">Tulip mania is an effective illustration of the underlying principles at work in a bubble and can help us understand more recent examples like the real estate bubble of the late 2000s.</s>
 <s id="38">The economy will continue to go through phases of booms and busts.</s>
 <s id="39">So while we wait for the next mania to start, and the next bubble to burst, treat yourself to a bouquet of tulips and enjoy the fact that you didn't have to pay an arm and a leg for them.</s>
</text>
