<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In 1943 Allied aircraft swooped over Nazi Germany, raining tens of thousands of leaflets on people below.</s>
 <s id="2">Written by anonymous Germans, the leaflets urged readers to renounce Hitler, to fight furiously for the future— and to never give up hope.</s>
 <s id="3">Their call to action rippled through homes and businesses— and news of their message even reached concentration camps and prisons.</s>
 <s id="4">It was only after the war had ended that the authors’ identities, stories, and tragic fate would come to light.</s>
 <s id="5">When Hitler seized power 10 years earlier, Hans and Sophie Scholl were teenagers in the town of Forchtenberg.</s>
 <s id="6">At that time, fear, propaganda, and surveillance kept all aspects of life for the Scholl family and millions of other Germans under Nazi control.</s>
 <s id="7">The government specifically targeted young people, setting up institutions to regulate their behavior and police their thoughts.</s>
 <s id="8">As teenagers, Hans was a member of the Hitler Youth and Sophie joined The League of German Girls.</s>
 <s id="9">Hans rose through the ranks and oversaw the training and indoctrination of other young people.</s>
 <s id="10">In 1936, he was chosen to carry the flag at a national rally.</s>
 <s id="11">But when he witnessed the zeal of Nazi rhetoric, he began to question it for the first time.</s>
 <s id="12">Meanwhile, Sophie was also starting to doubt the information she was being fed.</s>
 <s id="13">Their parents Robert and Magdalena, who had feared they were losing their children to Nazi ideology, encouraged these misgivings.</s>
 <s id="14">At home, Robert and Magdalena listened to foreign radio stations that the government first discouraged and later banned.</s>
 <s id="15">While the government churned out national broadcasts which denied Nazi atrocities, the Scholls learned shocking truths.</s>
 <s id="16">And yet, they were still subject to the rules of life in Hitler’s Germany.</s>
 <s id="17">After the outbreak of war, Sophie reluctantly worked for the national effort, and Hans had to take on army duties while attending medical school in Munich.</s>
 <s id="18">That was where Hans met Christoph Probst, Willi Graf and Alexander Schmorell.</s>
 <s id="19">Day by day, each grew more sickened by Nazi ideology.</s>
 <s id="20">They longed to share their views.</s>
 <s id="21">But how could they spread them, when it was impossible to know who to trust?</s>
 <s id="22">And so, the friends decided to rebel anonymously.</s>
 <s id="23">They pooled their money and bought printing materials.</s>
 <s id="24">An acquaintance let them use a cellar under his studio.</s>
 <s id="25">In secret, they began drafting their message.</s>
 <s id="26">In June 1942, mysterious anti-Nazi leaflets began appearing all over Munich.</s>
 <s id="27">They were signed: the White Rose.</s>
 <s id="28">The first leaflet denounced Hitler and called for Germans to sabotage the war effort: “Adopt passive resistance… block the functioning of this atheistic war machine before it is too late, before the last city is a heap of rubble… before the last youth of our nation bleeds to death...</s>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">Don’t forget that each people gets the government it deserves!”</s>
  <s id="29.2">At a time when a sarcastic remark could constitute treason, this language was unprecedented.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">It was written mostly by Hans Scholl.</s>
 <s id="31">In 1942, Sophie came to Munich knowing nothing of her brother’s activities.</s>
 <s id="32">She soon encountered the leaflets at school.</s>
 <s id="33">But it was not until she discovered evidence in Han’s room that she realized who’d written them.</s>
 <s id="34">Her shock soon gave way to resolve: she wanted in.</s>
 <s id="35">For both siblings, it was time to escalate the fury that had been brewing for years.</s>
 <s id="36">From June 1942 to February 1943, the group worked feverishly.</s>
 <s id="37">While the Gestapo searched for leads, the White Rose were constantly on guard.</s>
 <p id="p38">
  <s id="38.1">The war raged on.</s>
  <s id="38.2">Regulations tightened, and Munich suffered air raids.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="39">But the White Rose ventured deeper into conspiracy.</s>
 <s id="40">They graffitied buildings and braved trains swarming with Gestapo.</s>
 <s id="41">In the winter of 1942, Hans made a treacherous journey to the Czechoslovakian border to meet anti-Nazi rebels.</s>
 <s id="42">On February 18, 1943, Sophie and Hans brought a suitcase of leaflets to their university.</s>
 <s id="43">A custodian noticed what they were doing and reported them to the Gestapo.</s>
 <s id="44">Both calmly denied any involvement— until the police gathered all the leaflets and placed them back in the empty case, where they fit perfectly.</s>
 <s id="45">When Hans and Sophie confessed, they were immediately led to court and sentenced to death by guillotine.</s>
 <s id="46">Despite a grueling interrogation, the two refused to betray their co-conspirators.</s>
 <s id="47">Before her execution, Sophie declared her fury at the state of her country.</s>
 <s id="48">But she also spoke to a more hopeful future: “How can we expect righteousness to prevail when there is hardly anyone willing to give himself up individually to a righteous cause?</s>
 <s id="49">Such a fine, sunny day, and I have to go, but what does my death matter, if through us, thousands of people are awakened and stirred to action?”</s>
</text>
