<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">What I'm going to try and do in the next 15 minutes or so is tell you about an idea of how we're going to make matter come alive.</s>
 <s id="2">Now this may seem a bit ambitious, but when you look at yourself, you look at your hands, you realize that you're alive.</s>
 <s id="3">So this is a start.</s>
 <s id="4">Now this quest started four billion years ago on planet Earth.</s>
 <s id="5">There's been four billion years of organic, biological life.</s>
 <s id="6">And as an inorganic chemist, my friends and colleagues make this distinction between the organic, living world and the inorganic, dead world.</s>
 <s id="7">And what I'm going to try and do is plant some ideas about how we can transform inorganic, dead matter into living matter, into inorganic biology.</s>
 <s id="8">Before we do that, I want to kind of put biology in its place.</s>
 <s id="9">And I'm absolutely enthralled by biology.</s>
 <s id="10">I love to do synthetic biology.</s>
 <s id="11">I love things that are alive.</s>
 <s id="12">I love manipulating the infrastructure of biology.</s>
 <s id="13">But within that infrastructure, we have to remember that the driving force of biology is really coming from evolution.</s>
 <s id="14">And evolution, although it was established well over 100 years ago by Charles Darwin and a vast number of other people, evolution still is a little bit intangible.</s>
 <s id="15">And when I talk about Darwinian evolution, I mean one thing and one thing only, and that is survival of the fittest.</s>
 <s id="16">And so forget about evolution in a kind of metaphysical way.</s>
 <s id="17">Think about evolution in terms of offspring competing, and some winning.</s>
 <s id="18">So bearing that in mind, as a chemist, I wanted to ask myself the question frustrated by biology: What is the minimal unit of matter that can undergo Darwinian evolution?</s>
 <s id="19">And this seems quite a profound question.</s>
 <s id="20">And as a chemist, we're not used to profound questions every day.</s>
 <s id="21">So when I thought about it, then suddenly I realized that biology gave us the answer.</s>
 <s id="22">And in fact, the smallest unit of matter that can evolve independently is, in fact, a single cell -- a bacteria.</s>
 <s id="23">So this raises three really important questions: What is life?</s>
 <s id="24">Is biology special?</s>
 <s id="25">Biologists seem to think so.</s>
 <s id="26">Is matter evolvable?</s>
 <s id="27">Now if we answer those questions in reverse order, the third question -- is matter evolvable? -- if we can answer that, then we're going to know how special biology is, and maybe, just maybe, we'll have some idea of what life really is.</s>
 <s id="28">So here's some inorganic life.</s>
 <s id="29">This is a dead crystal, and I'm going to do something to it, and it's going to become alive.</s>
 <s id="30">And you can see, it's kind of pollinating, germinating, growing.</s>
 <s id="31">This is an inorganic tube.</s>
 <s id="32">And all these crystals here under the microscope were dead a few minutes ago, and they look alive.</s>
 <s id="33">Of course, they're not alive.</s>
 <s id="34">It's a chemistry experiment where I've made a crystal garden.</s>
 <s id="35">But when I saw this, I was really fascinated, because it seemed lifelike.</s>
 <s id="36">And as I pause for a few seconds, have a look at the screen.</s>
 <s id="37">You can see there's architecture growing, filling the void.</s>
 <s id="38">And this is dead.</s>
 <s id="39">So I was positive that, if somehow we can make things mimic life, let's go one step further.</s>
 <s id="40">Let's see if we can actually make life.</s>
 <s id="41">But there's a problem, because up until maybe a decade ago, we were told that life was impossible and that we were the most incredible miracle in the universe.</s>
 <s id="42">In fact, we were the only people in the universe.</s>
 <s id="43">Now, that's a bit boring.</s>
 <p id="p44">
  <s id="44.1">So as a chemist, I wanted to say, "Hang on.</s>
  <s id="44.2">What is going on here?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="45">Is life that improbable?"</s>
 <s id="46">And this is really the question.</s>
 <s id="47">I think that perhaps the emergence of the first cells was as probable as the emergence of the stars.</s>
 <s id="48">And in fact, let's take that one step further.</s>
 <s id="49">Let's say that if the physics of fusion is encoded into the universe, maybe the physics of life is as well.</s>
 <s id="50">And so the problem with chemists -- and this is a massive advantage as well -- is we like to focus on our elements.</s>
 <s id="51">In biology, carbon takes center stage.</s>
 <s id="52">And in a universe where carbon exists and organic biology, then we have all this wonderful diversity of life.</s>
 <s id="53">In fact, we have such amazing lifeforms that we can manipulate.</s>
 <s id="54">We're awfully careful in the lab to try and avoid various biohazards.</s>
 <s id="55">Well what about matter?</s>
 <s id="56">If we can make matter alive, would we have a matterhazard?</s>
 <s id="57">So think, this is a serious question.</s>
 <s id="58">If your pen could replicate, that would be a bit of a problem.</s>
 <s id="59">So we have to think differently if we're going to make stuff come alive.</s>
 <s id="60">And we also have to be aware of the issues.</s>
 <s id="61">But before we can make life, let's think for a second what life really is characterized by.</s>
 <s id="62">And forgive the complicated diagram.</s>
 <s id="63">This is just a collection of pathways in the cell.</s>
 <s id="64">And the cell is obviously for us a fascinating thing.</s>
 <s id="65">Synthetic biologists are manipulating it.</s>
 <s id="66">Chemists are trying to study the molecules to look at disease.</s>
 <s id="67">And you have all these pathways going on at the same time.</s>
 <s id="68">You have regulation; information is transcribed; catalysts are made; stuff is happening.</s>
 <s id="69">But what does a cell do?</s>
 <s id="70">Well it divides, it competes, it survives.</s>
 <s id="71">And I think that is where we have to start in terms of thinking about building from our ideas in life.</s>
 <s id="72">But what else is life characterized by?</s>
 <s id="73">Well, I like think of it as a flame in a bottle.</s>
 <s id="74">And so what we have here is a description of single cells replicating, metabolizing, burning through chemistries.</s>
 <s id="75">And so we have to understand that if we're going to make artificial life or understand the origin of life, we need to power it somehow.</s>
 <s id="76">So before we can really start to make life, we have to really think about where it came from.</s>
 <s id="77">And Darwin himself mused in a letter to a colleague that he thought that life probably emerged in some warm little pond somewhere -- maybe not in Scotland, maybe in Africa, maybe somewhere else.</s>
 <s id="78">But the real honest answer is, we just don't know, because there is a problem with the origin.</s>
 <s id="79">Imagine way back, four and a half billion years ago, there is a vast chemical soup of stuff.</s>
 <s id="80">And from this stuff we came.</s>
 <s id="81">So when you think about the improbable nature of what I'm going to tell you in the next few minutes, just remember, we came from stuff on planet Earth.</s>
 <s id="82">And we went through a variety of worlds.</s>
 <s id="83">The RNA people would talk about the RNA world.</s>
 <s id="84">We somehow got to proteins and DNA.</s>
 <s id="85">We then got to the last ancestor.</s>
 <s id="86">Evolution kicked in -- and that's the cool bit.</s>
 <s id="87">And here we are.</s>
 <s id="88">But there's a roadblock that you can't get past.</s>
 <s id="89">You can decode the genome, you can look back, you can link us all together by a mitochondrial DNA, but we can't get further than the last ancestor, the last visible cell that we could sequence or think back in history.</s>
 <s id="90">So we don't know how we got here.</s>
 <s id="91">So there are two options: intelligent design, direct and indirect -- so God, or my friend.</s>
 <s id="92">Now talking about E.T. putting us there, or some other life, just pushes the problem further on.</s>
 <s id="93">I'm not a politician, I'm a scientist.</s>
 <s id="94">The other thing we need to think about is the emergence of chemical complexity.</s>
 <s id="95">This seems most likely.</s>
 <s id="96">So we have some kind of primordial soup.</s>
 <s id="97">And this one happens to be a good source of all 20 amino acids.</s>
 <s id="98">And somehow these amino acids are combined, and life begins.</s>
 <s id="99">But life begins, what does that mean?</s>
 <p id="p100">
  <s id="100.1">What is life?</s>
  <s id="100.2">What is this stuff of life?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="101">So in the 1950s, Miller-Urey did their fantastic chemical Frankenstein experiment, where they did the equivalent in the chemical world.</s>
 <s id="102">They took the basic ingredients, put them in a single jar and ignited them and put a lot of voltage through.</s>
 <s id="103">And they had a look at what was in the soup, and they found amino acids, but nothing came out, there was no cell.</s>
 <s id="104">So the whole area's been stuck for a while, and it got reignited in the '80s when analytical technologies and computer technologies were coming on.</s>
 <s id="105">In my own laboratory, the way we're trying to create inorganic life is by using many different reaction formats.</s>
 <s id="106">So what we're trying to do is do reactions -- not in one flask, but in tens of flasks, and connect them together, as you can see with this flow system, all these pipes.</s>
 <s id="107">We can do it microfluidically, we can do it lithographically, we can do it in a 3D printer, we can do it in droplets for colleagues.</s>
 <s id="108">And the key thing is to have lots of complex chemistry just bubbling away.</s>
 <s id="109">But that's probably going to end in failure, so we need to be a bit more focused.</s>
 <s id="110">And the answer, of course, lies with mice.</s>
 <s id="111">This is how I remember what I need as a chemist.</s>
 <s id="112">I say, "Well I want molecules."</s>
 <s id="113">But I need a metabolism, I need some energy.</s>
 <s id="114">I need some information, and I need a container.</s>
 <s id="115">Because if I want evolution, I need containers to compete.</s>
 <s id="116">So if you have a container, it's like getting in your car.</s>
 <s id="117">"This is my car, and I'm going to drive around and show off my car."</s>
 <s id="118">And I imagine you have a similar thing in cellular biology with the emergence of life.</s>
 <s id="119">So these things together give us evolution, perhaps.</s>
 <s id="120">And the way to test it in the laboratory is to make it minimal.</s>
 <s id="121">So what we're going to try and do is come up with an inorganic Lego kit of molecules.</s>
 <s id="122">And so forgive the molecules on the screen, but these are a very simple kit.</s>
 <s id="123">There's only maybe three or four different types of building blocks present.</s>
 <s id="124">And we can aggregate them together and make literally thousands and thousands of really big nano-molecular molecules the same size of DNA and proteins, but there's no carbon in sight.</s>
 <s id="125">Carbon is banned.</s>
 <s id="126">And so with this Lego kit, we have the diversity required for complex information storage without DNA.</s>
 <s id="127">But we need to make some containers.</s>
 <s id="128">And just a few months ago in my lab, we were able to take these very same molecules and make cells with them.</s>
 <s id="129">And you can see on the screen a cell being made.</s>
 <s id="130">And we're now going to put some chemistry inside and do some chemistry in this cell.</s>
 <s id="131">And all I wanted to show you is we can set up molecules in membranes, in real cells, and then it sets up a kind of molecular Darwinism, a molecular survival of the fittest.</s>
 <s id="132">And this movie here shows this competition between molecules.</s>
 <s id="133">Molecules are competing for stuff.</s>
 <s id="134">They're all made of the same stuff, but they want their shape to win.</s>
 <s id="135">They want their shape to persist.</s>
 <s id="136">And that is the key.</s>
 <s id="137">If we can somehow encourage these molecules to talk to each other and make the right shapes and compete, they will start to form cells that will replicate and compete.</s>
 <s id="138">If we manage to do that, forget the molecular detail.</s>
 <s id="139">Let's zoom out to what that could mean.</s>
 <s id="140">So we have this special theory of evolution that applies only to organic biology, to us.</s>
 <s id="141">If we could get evolution into the material world, then I propose we should have a general theory of evolution.</s>
 <s id="142">And that's really worth thinking about.</s>
 <s id="143">Does evolution control the sophistication of matter in the universe?</s>
 <s id="144">Is there some driving force through evolution that allows matter to compete?</s>
 <s id="145">So that means we could then start to develop different platforms for exploring this evolution.</s>
 <s id="146">So you imagine, if we're able to create a self-sustaining artificial life form, not only will this tell us about the origin of life -- that it's possible that the universe doesn't need carbon to be alive; it can use anything -- we can then take [it] one step further and develop new technologies, because we can then use software control for evolution to code in.</s>
 <s id="147">So imagine we make a little cell.</s>
 <s id="148">We want to put it out in the environment, and we want it to be powered by the Sun.</s>
 <s id="149">What we do is we evolve it in a box with a light on.</s>
 <p id="p150">
  <s id="150.1">And we don't use design anymore.</s>
  <s id="150.2">We find what works.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="151">We should take our inspiration from biology.</s>
 <s id="152">Biology doesn't care about the design unless it works.</s>
 <s id="153">So this will reorganize the way we design things.</s>
 <s id="154">But not only just that, we will start to think about how we can start to develop a symbiotic relationship with biology.</s>
 <s id="155">Wouldn't it be great if you could take these artificial biological cells and fuse them with biological ones to correct problems that we couldn't really deal with?</s>
 <s id="156">The real issue in cellular biology is we are never going to understand everything, because it's a multidimensional problem put there by evolution.</s>
 <s id="157">Evolution cannot be cut apart.</s>
 <s id="158">You need to somehow find the fitness function.</s>
 <s id="159">And the profound realization for me is that, if this works, the concept of the selfish gene gets kicked up a level, and we really start talking about selfish matter.</s>
 <s id="160">And what does that mean in a universe where we are right now the highest form of stuff?</s>
 <s id="161">You're sitting on chairs.</s>
 <s id="162">They're inanimate, they're not alive.</s>
 <s id="163">But you are made of stuff, and you are using stuff, and you enslave stuff.</s>
 <s id="164">So using evolution in biology, and in inorganic biology, for me is quite appealing, quite exciting.</s>
 <s id="165">And we're really becoming very close to understanding the key steps that makes dead stuff come alive.</s>
 <s id="166">And again, when you're thinking about how improbable this is, remember, five billion years ago, we were not here, and there was no life.</s>
 <s id="167">So what will that tell us about the origin of life and the meaning of life?</s>
 <s id="168">But perhaps, for me as a chemist, I want to keep away from general terms; I want to think about specifics.</s>
 <s id="169">So what does it mean about defining life?</s>
 <s id="170">We really struggle to do this.</s>
 <s id="171">And I think, if we can make inorganic biology, and we can make matter become evolvable, that will in fact define life.</s>
 <s id="172">I propose to you that matter that can evolve is alive, and this gives us the idea of making evolvable matter.</s>
 <s id="173">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="174">(Applause) Chris Anderson: Just a quick question on timeline.</s>
 <s id="175">You believe you're going to be successful in this project?</s>
 <s id="176">When?</s>
 <s id="177">Lee Cronin: So many people think that life took millions of years to kick in.</s>
 <s id="178">We're proposing to do it in just a few hours, once we've set up the right chemistry.</s>
 <s id="179">CA: And when do you think that will happen?</s>
 <s id="180">LC: Hopefully within the next two years.</s>
 <s id="181">CA: That would be a big story.</s>
 <s id="182">(Laughter) In your own mind, what do you believe the chances are that walking around on some other planet is non-carbon-based life, walking or oozing or something?</s>
 <s id="183">LC: I think it's 100 percent.</s>
 <s id="184">Because the thing is, we are so chauvinistic to biology, if you take away carbon, there's other things that can happen.</s>
 <s id="185">So the other thing that if we were able to create life that's not based on carbon, maybe we can tell NASA what really to look for.</s>
 <s id="186">Don't go and look for carbon, go and look for evolvable stuff.</s>
 <p id="p187">
  <s id="187.1">CA: Lee Cronin, good luck.</s>
  <s id="187.2">(LC: Thank you very much.)</s>
  <s id="187.3">(Applause)</s>
 </p>
</text>
