<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">After decades of research and billions of dollars spent in clinical trials, we still have a problem with cancer drug delivery.</s>
 <s id="2">We still give patients chemotherapy, which is so non-specific that even though it kills the cancer cells, it kind of kills the rest of your body, too.</s>
 <s id="3">And yes, we have developed more selective drugs, but it's still a challenge to get them into the tumor, and they end up accumulating in the other organs as well or passing through your urine, which is a total waste.</s>
 <s id="4">And fields like mine have emerged where we try to encapsulate these drugs to protect them as they travel through the body.</s>
 <s id="5">But these modifications cause problems that we make more modifications to fix.</s>
 <s id="6">So what I'm really trying to say is we need a better drug delivery system.</s>
 <s id="7">And I propose, rather than using solely human design, why not use nature's?</s>
 <s id="8">Immune cells are these versatile vehicles that travel throughout our body, patrolling for signs of disease and arriving at a wound mere minutes after injury.</s>
 <s id="9">So I ask you guys: If immune cells are already traveling to places of injury or disease in our bodies, why not add an extra passenger?</s>
 <s id="10">Why not use immune cells to deliver drugs to cure some of our biggest problems in disease?</s>
 <s id="11">I am a biomedical engineer, and I want to tell you guys a story about how I use immune cells to target one of the largest problems in cancer.</s>
 <s id="12">Did you know that over 90 percent of cancer deaths can be attributed to its spread?</s>
 <s id="13">So if we can stop these cancer cells from going from the primary tumor to a distant site, we can stop cancer right in its tracks and give people more of their lives back.</s>
 <s id="14">To do this special mission, we decided to deliver a nanoparticle made of lipids, which are the same materials that compose your cell membrane.</s>
 <s id="15">And we've added two special molecules.</s>
 <s id="16">One is called e-selectin, which acts as a glue that binds the nanoparticle to the immune cell.</s>
 <s id="17">And the second one is called trail.</s>
 <s id="18">Trail is a therapeutic drug that kills cancer cells but not normal cells.</s>
 <s id="19">Now, when you put both of these together, you have a mean killing machine on wheels.</s>
 <s id="20">To test this, we ran an experiment in a mouse.</s>
 <s id="21">So what we did was we injected the nanoparticles, and they bound almost immediately to the immune cells in the bloodstream.</s>
 <s id="22">And then we injected the cancer cells to mimic a process through which cancer cells spread throughout our bodies.</s>
 <s id="23">And we found something very exciting.</s>
 <s id="24">We found that in our treated group, over 75 percent of the cancer cells we initially injected were dead or dying, in comparison to only around 25 percent.</s>
 <s id="25">So just imagine: these fewer amount of cells were available to actually be able to spread to a different part of the body.</s>
 <s id="26">And this is only after two hours of treatment.</s>
 <s id="27">Our results were amazing, and we had some pretty interesting press.</s>
 <s id="28">My favorite title was actually, "Sticky balls may stop the spread of cancer."</s>
 <s id="29">(Laughter) I can't tell you just how smug my male colleagues were, knowing that their sticky balls might one day cure cancer.</s>
 <s id="30">(Laughter) But I can tell you they made some pretty, pretty, exciting, pretty ballsy t-shirts.</s>
 <s id="31">This was also my first experience talking to patients where they asked how soon our therapy would be available.</s>
 <s id="32">And I keep these stories with me to remind me of the importance of the science, the scientists and the patients.</s>
 <s id="33">Now, our fast-acting results were pretty interesting, but we still had one lingering question: Can our sticky balls, our particles actually attached to the immune cells, actually stop the spread of cancer?</s>
 <s id="34">So we went to our animal model, and we found three important parts.</s>
 <s id="35">Our primary tumors were smaller in our treated animals, there were fewer cells in circulation, and there was little to no tumor burden in the distant organs.</s>
 <s id="36">Now, this wasn't just a victory for us and our sticky balls.</s>
 <s id="37">This was also a victory to me in drug delivery, and it represents a paradigm shift, a revolution -- to go from just using drugs, just injecting them and hoping they go to the right places in the body, to using immune cells as special delivery drivers in your body.</s>
 <s id="38">For this example, we used two molecules, e-selectin and trail, but really, the possibility of drugs you can use are endless.</s>
 <s id="39">And I talked about cancer, but where disease goes, so do immune cells.</s>
 <s id="40">So this could be used for any disease.</s>
 <s id="41">Imagine using immune cells to deliver crucial wound-healing agents after a spinal cord injury, or using immune cells to deliver drugs past the blood-brain barrier to treat Parkinson's or Alzheimer's disease.</s>
 <s id="42">These are the ideas that excite me about science the most.</s>
 <s id="43">And from where I stand, I see so much promise and opportunity.</s>
 <s id="44">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="45">(Applause)</s>
</text>
