<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Imagine spending seven years at MIT and research laboratories, only to find out that you're a performance artist.</s>
 <s id="2">(Laughter) I'm also a software engineer, and I make lots of different kinds of art with the computer.</s>
 <s id="3">And I think the main thing that I'm interested in is trying to find a way of making the computer into a personal mode of expression.</s>
 <s id="4">And many of you out there are the heads of Macromedia and Microsoft, and in a way those are my bane: I think there's a great homogenizing force that software imposes on people and limits the way they think about what's possible on the computer.</s>
 <s id="5">Of course, it's also a great liberating force that makes possible, you know, publishing and so forth, and standards, and so on.</s>
 <s id="6">But, in a way, the computer makes possible much more than what most people think, and my art has just been about trying to find a personal way of using the computer, and so I end up writing software to do that.</s>
 <s id="7">Chris has asked me to do a short performance, and so I'm going to take just this time -- maybe 10 minutes -- to do that, and hopefully at the end have just a moment to show you a couple of my other projects in video form.</s>
 <s id="8">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="9">(Applause) We've got about a minute left.</s>
 <s id="10">I'd just like to show a clip from a most recent project.</s>
 <s id="11">I did a performance with two singers who specialize in making strange noises with their mouths.</s>
 <s id="12">And this just came off last September at ARS Electronica; we repeated it in England.</s>
 <s id="13">And the idea is to visualize their speech and song behind them with a large screen.</s>
 <s id="14">We used a computer vision tracking system in order to know where they were.</s>
 <s id="15">And since we know where their heads are, and we have a wireless mic on them that we're processing the sound from, we're able to create visualizations which are linked very tightly to what they're doing with their speech.</s>
 <s id="16">This will take about 30 seconds or so.</s>
 <s id="17">He's making a, kind of, cheek-flapping sound.</s>
 <s id="18">Well, suffice it to say it's not all like that, but that's part of it.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">Thanks very much.</s>
  <s id="19.2">There's always lots more.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">I'm overtime, so I just wanted to say you can, if you're in New York, you can check out my work at the Whitney Biennial next week, and also at Bitforms Gallery in Chelsea.</s>
 <s id="21">And with that, I think I should give up the stage, so, thank you so much.</s>
</text>
