<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <p id="p1">
  <s id="1.1">(Music) (Music ends) (Applause) (Applause ends) Hi, everyone.</s>
  <s id="1.2">I'm Sirena.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="2">I'm 11 years old and from Connecticut.</s>
 <s id="3">(Audience cheers) (Applause) Well, I'm not really sure why I'm here.</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) I mean, what does this have to do with technology, entertainment and design?</s>
 <s id="5">Well, I count my iPod, cellphone and computer as technology, but this has nothing to do with that.</s>
 <s id="6">So I did a little research on it.</s>
 <s id="7">Well, this is what I found.</s>
 <s id="8">Of course, I hope I can memorize it.</s>
 <s id="9">(Clears throat) The violin is made of a wood box and four metal strings.</s>
 <s id="10">By pulling a string, it vibrates and produces a sound wave, which passes through a piece of wood called a bridge, and goes down to the wood box and gets amplified, but ... let me think.</s>
 <s id="11">(Laughter) Placing your finger at different places on the fingerboard changes the string length, and that changes the frequency of the sound wave.</s>
 <s id="12">(Sighs) Oh, my gosh!</s>
 <s id="13">(Laughter) OK, this is sort of technology, but I can call it a 16th-century technology.</s>
 <s id="14">But actually, the most fascinating thing that I found was that even the audio system or wave transmission nowadays are still based on the same principle of producing and projecting sound.</s>
 <s id="15">Isn't that cool?</s>
 <s id="16">(Laughter) (Applause) Design -- I love its design.</s>
 <s id="17">I remember when I was little, my mom asked me, "Would you like to play the violin or the piano?"</s>
 <s id="18">I looked at that giant monster and said to myself -- "I am not going to lock myself on that bench the whole day!"</s>
 <s id="19">(Laughter) This is small and lightweight.</s>
 <s id="20">I can play from standing, sitting or walking.</s>
 <s id="21">And, you know what?</s>
 <s id="22">The best of all is that if I don't want to practice, (Whispering) I can hide it.</s>
 <s id="23">(Laughter) The violin is very beautiful.</s>
 <s id="24">Some people relate it as the shape of a lady.</s>
 <s id="25">But whether you like it or not, it's been so for more than 400 years, unlike modern stuff [that] easily looks dated.</s>
 <s id="26">But I think it's very personal and unique that, although each violin looks pretty similar, no two violins sound the same -- even from the same maker or based on the same model.</s>
 <s id="27">Entertainment -- I love the entertainment.</s>
 <s id="28">But actually, the instrument itself isn't very entertaining.</s>
 <s id="29">I mean, when I first got my violin and tried to play around on it, it was actually really bad, because it didn't sound the way I'd heard from other kids -- it was so horrible and so scratchy.</s>
 <s id="30">So, it wasn't entertaining at all.</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">But besides, my brother found this very funny: Yuk!</s>
  <s id="31.2">Yuk!</s>
  <s id="31.3">Yuk!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">(Laughter) A few years later, I heard a joke about the greatest violinist, Jascha Heifetz.</s>
 <s id="33">After Mr. Heifetz's concert, a lady came over and complimented him: "Oh, Mr. Heifetz, your violin sounded so great tonight!"</s>
 <s id="34">And Mr. Heifetz was a very cool person, so he picked up his violin and said, "Funny -- I don't hear anything."</s>
 <s id="35">(Laughter) Now I realize that as the musician, we human beings, with our great mind, artistic heart and skill, can change this 16th-century technology and a legendary design to a wonderful entertainment.</s>
 <s id="36">Now I know why I'm here.</s>
 <s id="37">(Music) (Music ends) (Applause) At first, I thought I was just going to be here to perform, but unexpectedly, I learned and enjoyed much more.</s>
 <s id="38">But ... although some of the talks were quite up there for me.</s>
 <s id="39">(Laughter) Like the multi-dimension stuff.</s>
 <s id="40">I mean, honestly, I'd be happy enough if I could actually get my two dimensions correct in school.</s>
 <s id="41">(Laughter) But actually, the most impressive thing to me is that -- well, actually, I would also like to say this for all children is to say thank you to all adults, for actually caring for us a lot, and to make our future world much better.</s>
 <s id="42">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="43">(Applause) (Music) (Music ends) (Applause) (Applause ends) (Music) (Music ends) (Applause)</s>
</text>
