<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">As a boy, I loved cars.</s>
 <s id="2">When I turned 18, I lost my best friend to a car accident.</s>
 <s id="3">Like this.</s>
 <s id="4">And then I decided I'd dedicate my life to saving one million people every year.</s>
 <s id="5">Now I haven't succeeded, so this is just a progress report, but I'm here to tell you a little bit about self-driving cars.</s>
 <s id="6">I saw the concept first in the DARPA Grand Challenges where the U.S. government issued a prize to build a self-driving car that could navigate a desert.</s>
 <s id="7">And even though a hundred teams were there, these cars went nowhere.</s>
 <s id="8">So we decided at Stanford to build a different self-driving car.</s>
 <s id="9">We built the hardware and the software.</s>
 <s id="10">We made it learn from us, and we set it free in the desert.</s>
 <s id="11">And the unimaginable happened: it became the first car to ever return from a DARPA Grand Challenge, winning Stanford 2 million dollars.</s>
 <s id="12">Yet I still hadn't saved a single life.</s>
 <s id="13">Since, our work has focused on building driving cars that can drive anywhere by themselves -- any street in California.</s>
 <s id="14">We've driven 140,000 miles.</s>
 <s id="15">Our cars have sensors by which they magically can see everything around them and make decisions about every aspect of driving.</s>
 <s id="16">It's the perfect driving mechanism.</s>
 <s id="17">We've driven in cities, like in San Francisco here.</s>
 <s id="18">We've driven from San Francisco to Los Angeles on Highway 1.</s>
 <s id="19">We've encountered joggers, busy highways, toll booths, and this is without a person in the loop; the car just drives itself.</s>
 <s id="20">In fact, while we drove 140,000 miles, people didn't even notice.</s>
 <s id="21">Mountain roads, day and night, and even crooked Lombard Street in San Francisco.</s>
 <s id="22">(Laughter) Sometimes our cars get so crazy, they even do little stunts.</s>
 <s id="23">(Video) Man: Oh, my God.</s>
 <s id="24">What?</s>
 <s id="25">Second Man: It's driving itself.</s>
 <s id="26">Sebastian Thrun: Now I can't get my friend Harold back to life, but I can do something for all the people who died.</s>
 <s id="27">Do you know that driving accidents are the number one cause of death for young people?</s>
 <s id="28">And do you realize that almost all of those are due to human error and not machine error, and can therefore be prevented by machines?</s>
 <s id="29">Do you realize that we could change the capacity of highways by a factor of two or three if we didn't rely on human precision on staying in the lane -- improve body position and therefore drive a little bit closer together on a little bit narrower lanes, and do away with all traffic jams on highways?</s>
 <s id="30">Do you realize that you, TED users, spend an average of 52 minutes per day in traffic, wasting your time on your daily commute?</s>
 <s id="31">You could regain this time.</s>
 <s id="32">This is four billion hours wasted in this country alone.</s>
 <s id="33">And it's 2.4 billion gallons of gasoline wasted.</s>
 <s id="34">Now I think there's a vision here, a new technology, and I'm really looking forward to a time when generations after us look back at us and say how ridiculous it was that humans were driving cars.</s>
 <s id="35">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="36">(Applause)</s>
</text>
