<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">We're seen as the organization that is the bucket for failed social policy.</s>
 <s id="2">I can't define who comes to us or how long they stay.</s>
 <s id="3">We get the people for whom nothing else has worked, people who have fallen through all of the other social safety nets.</s>
 <s id="4">They can't contain them, so we must.</s>
 <s id="5">That's our job: contain them, control them.</s>
 <s id="6">Over the years, as a prison system, as a nation, and as a society, we've become very good at that, but that shouldn't make you happy.</s>
 <s id="7">Today we incarcerate more people per capita than any other country in the world.</s>
 <s id="8">We have more black men in prison today than were under slavery in 1850.</s>
 <s id="9">We house the parents of almost three million of our community's children, and we've become the new asylum, the largest mental health provider in this nation.</s>
 <s id="10">When we lock someone up, that is no small thing.</s>
 <s id="11">And yet, we are called the Department of Corrections.</s>
 <s id="12">Today I want to talk about changing the way we think about corrections.</s>
 <s id="13">I believe, and my experience tells me, that when we change the way we think, we create new possibilities, or futures, and prisons need a different future.</s>
 <s id="14">I've spent my entire career in corrections, over 30 years.</s>
 <s id="15">I followed my dad into this field.</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">He was a Vietnam veteran.</s>
  <s id="16.2">Corrections suited him.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="17">He was strong, steady, disciplined.</s>
 <s id="18">I was not so much any of those things, and I'm sure that worried him about me.</s>
 <s id="19">Eventually I decided, if I was going to end up in prison, I'd better end up on the right side of the bars, so I thought I'd check it out, take a tour of the place my dad worked, the McNeil Island Penitentiary.</s>
 <s id="20">Now this was the early '80s, and prisons weren't quite what you see on TV or in the movies.</s>
 <s id="21">In many ways, it was worse.</s>
 <s id="22">I walked into a cell house that was five tiers high.</s>
 <s id="23">There were eight men to a cell.</s>
 <s id="24">there were 550 men in that living unit.</s>
 <s id="25">And just in case you wondered, they shared one toilet in those small confines.</s>
 <s id="26">An officer put a key in a lockbox, and hundreds of men streamed out of their cells.</s>
 <s id="27">Hundreds of men streamed out of their cells.</s>
 <s id="28">I walked away as fast as I could.</s>
 <s id="29">Eventually I went back and I started as an officer there.</s>
 <s id="30">My job was to run one of those cell blocks and to control those hundreds of men.</s>
 <s id="31">When I went to work at our receptions center, I could actually hear the inmates roiling from the parking lot, shaking cell doors, yelling, tearing up their cells.</s>
 <s id="32">Take hundreds of volatile people and lock them up, and what you get is chaos.</s>
 <s id="33">Contain and control — that was our job.</s>
 <s id="34">One way we learned to do this more effectively was a new type of housing unit called the Intensive Management Unit, IMU, a modern version of a "hole."</s>
 <s id="35">We put inmates in cells behind solid steel doors with cuff ports so we could restrain them and feed them.</s>
 <s id="36">Guess what?</s>
 <s id="37">It got quieter.</s>
 <s id="38">Disturbances died down in the general population.</s>
 <s id="39">Places became safer because those inmates who were most violent or disruptive could now be isolated.</s>
 <s id="40">But isolation isn't good.</s>
 <s id="41">Deprive people of social contact and they deteriorate.</s>
 <s id="42">It was hard getting them out of IMU, for them and for us.</s>
 <s id="43">Even in prison, it's no small thing to lock someone up.</s>
 <s id="44">My next assignment was to one of the state's deep-end prisons where some of our more violent or disruptive inmates are housed.</s>
 <s id="45">By then, the industry had advanced a lot, and we had different tools and techniques to manage disruptive behavior.</s>
 <s id="46">We had beanbag guns and pepper spray and plexiglass shields, flash bangs, emergency response teams.</s>
 <s id="47">We met violence with force and chaos with chaos.</s>
 <s id="48">We were pretty good at putting out fires.</s>
 <s id="49">While I was there, I met two experienced correctional workers who were also researchers, an anthropologist and a sociologist.</s>
 <s id="50">One day, one of them commented to me and said, "You know, you're pretty good at putting out fires.</s>
 <s id="51">Have you ever thought about how to prevent them?"</s>
 <s id="52">I was patient with them, explaining our brute force approach to making prisons safer.</s>
 <s id="53">They were patient with me.</s>
 <s id="54">Out of those conversations grew some new ideas and we started some small experiments.</s>
 <s id="55">First, we started training our officers in teams rather than sending them one or two at a time to the state training academy.</s>
 <s id="56">Instead of four weeks of training, we gave them 10.</s>
 <s id="57">Then we experimented with an apprenticeship model where we paired new staff with veteran staff.</s>
 <s id="58">They both got better at the work.</s>
 <s id="59">Second, we added verbal de-escalation skills into the training continuum and made it part of the use of force continuum.</s>
 <s id="60">It was the non-force use of force.</s>
 <s id="61">And then we did something even more radical.</s>
 <s id="62">We trained the inmates on those same skills.</s>
 <s id="63">We changed the skill set, reducing violence, not just responding to it.</s>
 <s id="64">Third, when we expanded our facility, we tried a new type of design.</s>
 <s id="65">Now the biggest and most controversial component of this design, of course, was the toilet.</s>
 <s id="66">There were no toilets.</s>
 <s id="67">Now that might not sound significant to you here today, but at the time, it was huge.</s>
 <s id="68">No one had ever heard of a cell without a toilet.</s>
 <s id="69">We all thought it was dangerous and crazy.</s>
 <s id="70">Even eight men to a cell had a toilet.</s>
 <s id="71">That small detail changed the way we worked.</s>
 <s id="72">Inmates and staff started interacting more often and openly and developing a rapport.</s>
 <s id="73">It was easier to detect conflict and intervene before it escalated.</s>
 <s id="74">The unit was cleaner, quieter, safer and more humane.</s>
 <s id="75">This was more effective at keeping the peace than any intimidation technique I'd seen to that point.</s>
 <s id="76">Interacting changes the way you behave, both for the officer and the inmate.</s>
 <s id="77">We changed the environment and we changed the behavior.</s>
 <s id="78">Now, just in case I hadn't learned this lesson, they assigned me to headquarters next, and that's where I ran straight up against system change.</s>
 <s id="79">Now, many things work against system change: politics and politicians, bills and laws, courts and lawsuits, internal politics.</s>
 <s id="80">System change is difficult and slow, and oftentimes it doesn't take you where you want to go.</s>
 <s id="81">It's no small thing to change a prison system.</s>
 <s id="82">So what I did do is I reflected on my earlier experiences and I remembered that when we interacted with offenders, the heat went down.</s>
 <s id="83">When we changed the environment, the behavior changed.</s>
 <s id="84">And these were not huge system changes.</s>
 <s id="85">These were small changes, and these changes created new possibilities.</s>
 <s id="86">So next, I got reassigned as superintendent of a small prison.</s>
 <s id="87">And at the same time, I was working on my degree at the Evergreen State College.</s>
 <s id="88">I interacted with a lot of people who were not like me, people who had different ideas and came from different backgrounds.</s>
 <s id="89">One of them was a rainforest ecologist.</s>
 <s id="90">She looked at my small prison and what she saw was a laboratory.</s>
 <s id="91">We talked and discovered how prisons and inmates could actually help advance science by helping them complete projects they couldn't complete on their own, like repopulating endangered species: frogs, butterflies, endangered prairie plants.</s>
 <s id="92">At the same time, we found ways to make our operation more efficient through the addition of solar power, rainwater catchment, organic gardening, recycling.</s>
 <s id="93">This initiative has led to many projects that have had huge system-wide impact, not just in our system, but in other state systems as well, small experiments making a big difference to science, to the community.</s>
 <s id="94">The way we think about our work changes our work.</s>
 <s id="95">The project just made my job more interesting and exciting.</s>
 <p id="p96">
  <s id="96.1">I was excited.</s>
  <s id="96.2">Staff were excited.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p97">
  <s id="97.1">Officers were excited.</s>
  <s id="97.2">Inmates were excited.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="98">They were inspired.</s>
 <s id="99">Everybody wanted to be part of this.</s>
 <s id="100">They were making a contribution, a difference, one they thought was meaningful and important.</s>
 <s id="101">Let me be clear on what's going on here, though.</s>
 <s id="102">Inmates are highly adaptive.</s>
 <s id="103">They have to be.</s>
 <s id="104">Oftentimes, they know more about our own systems than the people who run them.</s>
 <s id="105">And they're here for a reason.</s>
 <s id="106">I don't see my job as to punish them or forgive them, but I do think they can have decent and meaningful lives even in prison.</s>
 <s id="107">So that was the question: Could inmates live decent and meaningful lives, and if so, what difference would that make?</s>
 <s id="108">So I took that question back to the deep end, where some of our most violent offenders are housed.</s>
 <s id="109">Remember, IMUs are for punishment.</s>
 <s id="110">You don't get perks there, like programming.</s>
 <s id="111">That was how we thought.</s>
 <s id="112">But then we started to realize that if any inmates needed programming, it was these particular inmates.</s>
 <s id="113">In fact, they needed intensive programming.</s>
 <s id="114">So we changed our thinking 180 degrees, and we started looking for new possibilities.</s>
 <s id="115">What we found was a new kind of chair.</s>
 <s id="116">Instead of using the chair for punishment, we put it in classrooms.</s>
 <p id="p117">
  <s id="117.1">Okay, we didn't forget our responsibility to control, but now inmates could interact safely, face-to-face with other inmates and staff, and because control was no longer an issue, everybody could focus on other things, like learning.</s>
  <s id="117.2">Behavior changed.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="118">We changed our thinking, and we changed what was possible, and this gives me hope.</s>
 <s id="119">Now, I can't tell you that any of this stuff will work.</s>
 <s id="120">What I can tell you, though, it is working.</s>
 <s id="121">Our prisons are getting safer for both staff and inmates, and when our prisons are safe, we can put our energies into a lot more than just controlling.</s>
 <s id="122">Reducing recidivism may be our ultimate goal, but it's not our only goal.</s>
 <s id="123">To be honest with you, preventing crime takes so much more from so many more people and institutions.</s>
 <s id="124">If we rely on just prisons to reduce crime, I'm afraid we'll never get there.</s>
 <s id="125">But prisons can do some things we never thought they could do.</s>
 <s id="126">Prisons can be the source of innovation and sustainability, repopulating endangered species and environmental restoration.</s>
 <s id="127">Inmates can be scientists and beekeepers, dog rescuers.</s>
 <s id="128">Prisons can be the source of meaningful work and opportunity for staff and the inmates who live there.</s>
 <s id="129">We can contain and control and provide humane environments.</s>
 <s id="130">These are not opposing qualities.</s>
 <s id="131">We can't wait 10 to 20 years to find out if this is worth doing.</s>
 <s id="132">Our strategy is not massive system change.</s>
 <s id="133">Our strategy is hundreds of small changes that take place in days or months, not years.</s>
 <s id="134">We need more small pilots where we learn as we go, pilots that change the range of possibility.</s>
 <s id="135">We need new and better ways to measure impacts on engagement, on interaction, on safe environments.</s>
 <s id="136">We need more opportunities to participate in and contribute to our communities, your communities.</s>
 <s id="137">Prisons need to be secure, yes, safe, yes.</s>
 <s id="138">We can do that.</s>
 <s id="139">Prisons need to provide humane environments where people can participate, contribute, and learn meaningful lives.</s>
 <s id="140">We're learning how to do that.</s>
 <s id="141">That's why I'm hopeful.</s>
 <s id="142">We don't have to stay stuck in old ideas about prison.</s>
 <p id="p143">
  <s id="143.1">We can define that.</s>
  <s id="143.2">We can create that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="144">And when we do that thoughtfully and with humanity, prisons can be more than the bucket for failed social policy.</s>
 <s id="145">Maybe finally, we will earn our title: a department of corrections.</s>
 <s id="146">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="147">(Applause)</s>
</text>
