<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Your rich, eccentric uncle just passed away, and you and your 99 nasty relatives have been invited to the reading of his will.</s>
 <s id="2">He wanted to leave all of his money to you, but he knew that if he did, your relatives would pester you forever.</s>
 <s id="3">So he is banking on the fact that he taught you everything you need to know about riddles.</s>
 <s id="4">Your uncle left the following note in his will: "I have created a puzzle.</s>
 <s id="5">If all 100 of you answer it together, you will share the money evenly.</s>
 <s id="6">However, if you are the first to find the pattern and solve the problem without going through all of the leg work, you will get the entire inheritance all to yourself.</s>
 <s id="7">Good luck."</s>
 <s id="8">The lawyer takes you and your 99 relatives to a secret room in the mansion that contains 100 lockers, each hiding a single word.</s>
 <s id="9">He explains: Every relative is assigned a number from 1 to 100.</s>
 <s id="10">Heir 1 will open every locker.</s>
 <s id="11">Heir 2 will then close every second locker.</s>
 <s id="12">Heir 3 will change the status of every third locker, specifically if it's open, she'll close it, but if it's closed, she'll open it.</s>
 <s id="13">This pattern will continue until all 100 of you have gone.</s>
 <s id="14">The words in the lockers that remain open at the end will help you crack the code for the safe.</s>
 <s id="15">Before cousin Thaddeus can even start down the line, you step forward and tell the lawyer you know which lockers will remain open.</s>
 <s id="16">But how?</s>
 <s id="17">Pause the video now if you want to figure it out for yourself!</s>
 <s id="18">Answer in: 3 Answer in: 2 Answer in: 1 The key is realizing that the number of times a locker is touched is the same as the number of factors in the locker number.</s>
 <s id="19">For example, in locker #6, Person 1 will open it, Person 2 will close it, Person 3 will open it, and Person 6 will close it.</s>
 <s id="20">The numbers 1, 2, 3, and 6 are the factors of 6.</s>
 <s id="21">So when a locker has an even number of factors it will remain closed, and when it has an odd number of factors, it will remain open.</s>
 <s id="22">Most of the lockers have an even number of factors, which makes sense because factors naturally pair up.</s>
 <s id="23">In fact, the only lockers that have an odd number of factors are perfect squares because those have one factor that when multiplied by itself equals the number.</s>
 <s id="24">For Locker 9, 1 will open it, 3 will close, and 9 will open it.</s>
 <s id="25">3 x 3 = 9, but the 3 can only be counted once.</s>
 <s id="26">Therefore, every locker that is a perfect square will remain open.</s>
 <s id="27">You know that these ten lockers are the solution, so you open them immediately and read the words inside: "The code is the first five lockers touched only twice."</s>
 <s id="28">You realize that the only lockers touched twice have to be prime numbers since each only has two factors: 1 and itself.</s>
 <s id="29">So the code is 2-3-5-7-11.</s>
 <s id="30">The lawyer brings you to the safe, and you claim your inheritance.</s>
 <s id="31">Too bad your relatives were always too busy being nasty to each other to pay attention to your eccentric uncle's riddles.</s>
</text>
