<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In the depths of their underwater kingdom, the mighty Dragon Lords quaked with fear.</s>
 <s id="2">Before them pranced Sun Wukong, the Monkey King.</s>
 <s id="3">The legendary troublemaker been hatched from a stone, schooled in divine magic, and was currently brandishing the Dragon Lord’s most treasured weapon.</s>
 <s id="4">This magical staff, originally large enough to measure the depth of a great flood, now obeyed the Monkey King’s will and shrank at his touch.</s>
 <s id="5">Terrified of this bewildering power, the Dragons graciously allowed Sun Wukong to keep the staff.</s>
 <s id="6">The Monkey King stowed the weapon away, and gleefully sped back to his kingdom to show this treasure to his tribe of warrior monkeys.</s>
 <s id="7">After a lavish celebration, Sun Wukong fell into a deep sleep.</s>
 <s id="8">But just as he began to dream, the Monkey King quickly realized two things.</s>
 <s id="9">The first was that this was no ordinary slumber.</s>
 <s id="10">The second was that he wasn’t alone.</s>
 <s id="11">Suddenly, he found himself caught in the clutches of two grisly figures.</s>
 <s id="12">At first the Monkey King didn’t know who his captors were.</s>
 <s id="13">But as they dragged him toward their city’s gates, Sun Wukong realized his deathly predicament.</s>
 <s id="14">These were soul collectors tasked with transporting mortals to the Realm of the Dead.</s>
 <s id="15">This was the domain of the Death Lords, who mercilessly sorted souls and designed gruesome punishments.</s>
 <s id="16">From here, the kingdom of death was laid out before him.</s>
 <s id="17">He could see the Death Lord’s palaces, and the fabled bridge across the river Nai He.</s>
 <s id="18">Manning the bridge was an old woman who offered worthy souls a bowl of soup.</s>
 <s id="19">After drinking, the spirits forgot their previous life, and were sent back to the world of the living in a new form.</s>
 <s id="20">Further below were the souls not worthy of reincarnation.</s>
 <s id="21">In this twisting maze of chambers, unfortunate spirits endured endless rooms of punishment— from mountains spiked with sharp blades, to pools of blood and vats of boiling oil.</s>
 <s id="22">But Sun Wukong was not about to accept torture or reincarnation.</s>
 <s id="23">As the soul collectors attempted to drag him through the gates, the Monkey King whipped out his staff and swung himself out of their clutches.</s>
 <s id="24">His battle cries and the clang of weapons echoed throughout the underworld.</s>
 <s id="25">Sensing a disturbance, the ten Death Lords swooped upon him.</s>
 <s id="26">But they had never met such resistance from a mortal soul.</s>
 <s id="27">What was this unusual creature?</s>
 <s id="28">And was he a mortal, a god— or something else?</s>
 <s id="29">The Lords consulted the Book of Death and Life— a tome which showed the time of every living soul’s death.</s>
 <s id="30">Not knowing what category this strange being was under, the Death Lords struggled to find Sun Wukong at first; but the Monkey King knew just where to look.</s>
 <s id="31">Unfortunately, the records confirmed the Death Lord’s claim— Sun Wukong was scheduled to die this very night.</s>
 <s id="32">But the Monkey King was not afraid.</s>
 <s id="33">This was far from the first time he’d defied destiny in his quest for wisdom and power.</s>
 <s id="34">His past rebellions had earned him the power to transfigure his body, ride clouds at dizzying speeds, and govern his tribe with magic and martial arts.</s>
 <s id="35">In this crisis, he saw yet another opportunity.</s>
 <s id="36">With a flash of his nimble fingers, the Monkey King struck his own name from the Book.</s>
 <s id="37">Before the Death Lords could respond, he found the names of his monkey tribe and swept them away as well.</s>
 <s id="38">Liberated from the bonds of death, Sun Wukong began to battle his way out of the underworld.</s>
 <s id="39">He deftly defeated endless swarms of angry spirits— before tripping on his way out of the kingdom.</s>
 <s id="40">Just before he hit the ground, Sun Wukong suddenly awoke in his bed.</s>
 <s id="41">At first he thought the journey might have been a dream, but the Monkey King felt his new immortality surging from the top of his head to the tip of his tail.</s>
 <s id="42">With a cry of triumph, he woke his warriors to share his latest adventure— and commence another round of celebration.</s>
</text>
