<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Shah Rukh Khan: Be it Mumbai or Delhi, Chennai or Kolkata, all our big cities have one great thing in common, they happily welcome people from smaller places arriving in search of work.</s>
 <s id="2">What is also true is that this warm welcome leads to consequences.</s>
 <s id="3">Problems like housing in these cities are born.</s>
 <s id="4">Today we have with us a human settlement expert and researcher: Dr. Gautam Bhan, who is re-imagining a solution to this increasing problem.</s>
 <s id="5">He will share with us the new picture of urban India that he can see.</s>
 <s id="6">TED Talks India New Thoughts welcomes Dr. Gautam Bhan.</s>
 <s id="7">Dr. Gautam Bhan, everyone.</s>
 <s id="8">(Applause) Gautam Bhan: In this country, until a few years ago, if you asked someone: "Where are you from?"</s>
 <s id="9">the answer would be Delhi, Mumbai, Kolkata.</s>
 <s id="10">You'd immediately ask again: "Where do you belong?"</s>
 <s id="11">Until recently in India, nobody was from a city; people only migrated to the city.</s>
 <s id="12">This is changing.</s>
 <s id="13">Urbanization is changing India, but are our cities prepared?</s>
 <s id="14">Let's assume you were born somewhere else.</s>
 <s id="15">Your parents worked as laborers all day.</s>
 <s id="16">Then you too would have come to a city for progress.</s>
 <s id="17">Or maybe, like it happens today, you were born in the city itself.</s>
 <s id="18">One day you go out looking for an accommodation in the city, to buy or maybe just to rent.</s>
 <s id="19">Will you be able find an affordable home?</s>
 <s id="20">The government says we are falling short of at least 20 million homes.</s>
 <s id="21">20 million homes, that's 100 million people.</s>
 <s id="22">And this is not the shortage of &lt;i&gt;3 BHKs&lt;/i&gt; (bedroom hall kitchen).</s>
 <s id="23">95 percent of the shortage is for people earning 10 to 15,000 rupees per month.</s>
 <s id="24">Will you be able to find an affordable home in this budget?</s>
 <s id="25">If this happened with you, what would you do?</s>
 <s id="26">Home is not a car or some sort of jewellery.</s>
 <s id="27">Home is food and clothes.</s>
 <s id="28">Nobody can live without it.</s>
 <s id="29">If you couldn't find a home in a city to either buy or rent, you too would be driven to do what most people end up doing.</s>
 <s id="30">Make a home wherever possible.</s>
 <s id="31">You too would make a &lt;i&gt;settlement.&lt;/i&gt; The government may keep calling it a &lt;i&gt;slum,&lt;/i&gt; but like the people living there, I too will call it a settlement.</s>
 <s id="32">One hundred million are not homeless.</s>
 <s id="33">They have homes.</s>
 <s id="34">Homes they built on their own.</s>
 <s id="35">But most of these homes are in settlements.</s>
 <s id="36">This is the truth of an affordable home in India.</s>
 <s id="37">The homes in settlements are cheap, but not sturdy.</s>
 <s id="38">The homes outside are sturdy, but not cheap.</s>
 <s id="39">(Applause) We will have to lay the foundation of a new thought from here itself.</s>
 <s id="40">A settlement is not a problem; it is a solution.</s>
 <s id="41">We just have to make it secure and sturdy.</s>
 <s id="42">To fulfill the shortage of 20 million homes you cannot make 20 million 25 square foot flats, and neither should you be making them.</s>
 <s id="43">For example take the Karnataka government.</s>
 <s id="44">They have a very good record in this.</s>
 <s id="45">By 2020, Karnataka needs 2.6 million homes.</s>
 <s id="46">In the last ten years they have managed to make 350,000 homes.</s>
 <s id="47">Even if a government tries with complete sincerity, it cannot fulfill this need in the next couple of lifetimes.</s>
 <s id="48">If we do not make new homes, then what is the next solution?</s>
 <s id="49">How to make a settlement secure?</s>
 <s id="50">Firstly, eviction needs to be stopped.</s>
 <s id="51">Bulldozing needs to be stopped.</s>
 <s id="52">Never has that resulted in progress in the past, nor will it in the future.</s>
 <s id="53">(Applause) We have to start believing that the laborers who build and run the city have a right over the land of that city.</s>
 <s id="54">(Applause) I know you are thinking that settlements are made on illegally captured land, but capturing of land never happens in the dead of the night.</s>
 <s id="55">Whether the land belongs to the government or not, a settlement is never formed secretly.</s>
 <s id="56">It is inhabited over time.</s>
 <s id="57">The government also agrees that the settlements in our cities have been there for over 10, 20, 30, even 40 years.</s>
 <s id="58">What kind of illegally captured land is this, which was ignored for 30 years and suddenly a day before eviction is declared illegal?</s>
 <s id="59">A settlement can easily accommodate 15 to 60 percent of a city's population by using just one, two or maximum ten percent of the land.</s>
 <s id="60">Can such a huge number of people not have a right over this small bit of land?</s>
 <s id="61">A city's progress is often measured by the cost of its land.</s>
 <s id="62">How do you ascribe a cost to the life of a person living on a piece of land?</s>
 <s id="63">A settlement is not asking you for shiny homes; all it's asking for is basic necessities: electricity, roads, water, toilets and drainage.</s>
 <s id="64">We call this &lt;i&gt;upgradation.&lt;/i&gt; Here's an example of upgradation.</s>
 <s id="65">In Ahmedabad, they started a program where for ten years, 44 settlements were promised there wouldn't be any eviction.</s>
 <s id="66">Only a promise.</s>
 <s id="67">Nothing written, no documents.</s>
 <s id="68">And basic necessities were provided to them.</s>
 <s id="69">In ten years that slum changed into a locality, a place, a world of its own.</s>
 <s id="70">The government didn't have to build even a single new home.</s>
 <s id="71">(Applause) Thailand launched this program at national scale, benefiting 100,000 people in 137 cities.</s>
 <s id="72">And every person was given the right to live over that land.</s>
 <s id="73">But pay attention here.</s>
 <s id="74">Not the right to sell, but the right to live there, use it, settle on it.</s>
 <s id="75">The whole world knows now that to move forward, we cannot remove settlements.</s>
 <s id="76">We can only advance when we think of ways to make settlements secure and sturdy.</s>
 <s id="77">But just one thing.</s>
 <s id="78">If we know it, then why doesn't it happen?</s>
 <s id="79">To apply this new thinking to settlements, we, that is you and me, need to look deep within and get rid of the disgust, disrespect and apprehensions that we have.</s>
 <s id="80">Actually I should not be standing here in front of you today.</s>
 <s id="81">A person from the settlement who lives there should be standing here.</s>
 <s id="82">But if someone like that came here, you wouldn't have listened to him.</s>
 <s id="83">You are listening to me, because you think I am not from a settlement.</s>
 <s id="84">This is the very thought that needs to be changed.</s>
 <s id="85">Thank you.</s>
 <p id="p86">
  <s id="86.1">(Applause) SRK: Thank you very much.</s>
  <s id="86.2">Thank you, Dr. Gautam Bhan.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="87">Thanks a lot.</s>
 <s id="88">Please tell me, you just gave an example of Thailand and the big thing there is the homes are for people to settle in, not to sell.</s>
 <s id="89">They cannot be used for sale.</s>
 <s id="90">Is there a similar thought process or program in our country too, inspired by your talks and those of people around you?</s>
 <s id="91">GB: I wouldn't say by me, but by the people movement who are fighting for rights in the city.</s>
 <s id="92">That is making a difference.</s>
 <s id="93">For instance, in Odisha the Chief Minister, Mr. Patnaik, announced the same scheme: that all the people in settlements will have rights over that land.</s>
 <s id="94">(Applause) And I think this scheme shouldn't be called populism; it should be called an economic development strategy.</s>
 <s id="95">Because economic development does not happen from the top, but from the bottom.</s>
 <p id="p96">
  <s id="96.1">(Applause) SRK: I too promise I will only say settlements, and not slums, ever again.</s>
  <s id="96.2">100 percent.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="97">(Applause) Dr. Bhan you came here and said such wonderful things.</s>
 <p id="p98">
  <s id="98.1">There is a song.</s>
  <s id="98.2">I will not sing it, as I am a terrible singer.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="99">GB: I too am a terrible singer.</s>
 <s id="100">SRK: But we can't keep shut also, because we are saying wonderful things.</s>
 <s id="101">(laughter) So we will just say it.</s>
 <s id="102">Slowly the heart will find settlement.</s>
 <s id="103">GB: Slowly the heart will find settlement.</s>
 <s id="104">SRK: Only then will life be filled with love and fun times.</s>
 <p id="p105">
  <s id="105.1">(Applause) Ladies and gentlemen, Dr. Gautam Bhan.</s>
  <s id="105.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="106">(Applause) Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="107">(Applause)</s>
</text>
