<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Music) [music by Moby] [Grand Canyon] Narrator: Many of the tests are conducted while Yves is strapped onto the wing, because Yves' body is an integral part of the aircraft.</s>
 <s id="2">[Wind tunnel tests] Narrator: The wing has no steering controls, no flaps, no rudder.</s>
 <s id="3">Yves uses his body to steer the wing.</s>
 <s id="4">Stefan Von Bergen: Well, he turns by just putting his head on one or the other side.</s>
 <s id="5">And sometimes he assists that with his hands, sometimes even with the leg.</s>
 <s id="6">He's acting as a human fuselage, so to say.</s>
 <s id="7">And that's quite unique.</s>
 <s id="8">Narrator: When he arches his back, he gains altitude.</s>
 <s id="9">When he pushes his shoulders forward, he goes into a dive.</s>
 <s id="10">[Swiss Alps] [Strait of Gibraltar crossing] [English Channel crossing] Commentator One: There he goes.</s>
 <s id="11">There is Yves Rossy.</s>
 <s id="12">And I think the wing is open.</s>
 <s id="13">So our first critical moment, it's open.</s>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">He is down.</s>
  <s id="14.2">Is he flying?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="15">Commentator Two: It looks like he's stabilized.</s>
 <s id="16">He's starting to make his climb.</s>
 <s id="17">Commentator One: There's that 90 degree turn.</s>
 <s id="18">He's out over the channel.</s>
 <s id="19">There is Yves Rossy.</s>
 <s id="20">There is no turning back now.</s>
 <s id="21">He is over the English Channel and under way.</s>
 <s id="22">Ladies and gentlemen, a historic flight has begun.</s>
 <s id="23">[Images: National Geographic] Commentator Two: And as he approaches the ground, he's going to pull down on those toggles to flare, slow himself down just a little bit, and then come in for a nice landing.</s>
 <s id="24">Commentator One: There he is.</s>
 <s id="25">Yves Rossy has landed in England.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">Bruno Giussani: And now he's in Edinburgh.</s>
  <s id="26.2">Yves Rossy!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">(Applause) (Applause ends) And his equipment as well.</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">Yves, welcome.</s>
  <s id="28.2">It is quite amazing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">Those sequences were shot over the last three years in various moments of your activities.</s>
 <s id="30">And there were many, many others.</s>
 <s id="31">So it's possible to fly almost like a bird.</s>
 <s id="32">What is it like to be up there?</s>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">Yves Rossy: It's fun.</s>
  <s id="33.2">It's fun.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="34">(Laughter) I don't have feathers.</s>
 <s id="35">But I feel like a bird sometimes.</s>
 <s id="36">It's really an unreal feeling, because normally you have a big thing, a plane, around you.</s>
 <s id="37">And when I strap just this little harness, this little wing, I really have the feeling of being a bird.</s>
 <s id="38">BG: How did you start to become Jetman?</s>
 <s id="39">YR: It was about 20 years ago, when I discovered free falling.</s>
 <s id="40">When you go out of an airplane, you are almost naked.</s>
 <s id="41">You take a position like that.</s>
 <s id="42">And especially when you take a tracking position, you have the feeling that you are flying.</s>
 <s id="43">And that's the nearest thing to the dream.</s>
 <s id="44">You have no machine around you.</s>
 <s id="45">You are just in the element.</s>
 <s id="46">It's very short and only in one direction.</s>
 <s id="47">(Laughter) So the idea was, okay, keep that feeling of freedom, but change the vector and increase the time.</s>
 <s id="48">BG: So I'm kind of curious, what's your top speed?</s>
 <s id="49">YR: It's about 300 km per hour before looping.</s>
 <s id="50">That means about 190 miles per hour.</s>
 <s id="51">BG: What's the weight of the equipment you're carrying?</s>
 <s id="52">YR: When I exit full of kerosene, I'm about 55 kilos.</s>
 <s id="53">I have 55 kilos on my back.</s>
 <s id="54">BG: And you're not piloting?</s>
 <s id="55">There is no handle, no steering, nothing?</s>
 <s id="56">It is purely your body, and the wings become part of the body and vice versa?</s>
 <s id="57">YR: That's really the goal, because if you put in steering, then you reinvent the airplane.</s>
 <s id="58">And I wanted to keep this freedom of movement.</s>
 <s id="59">And it's really like the kid playing the airplane.</s>
 <s id="60">I want to go down like that.</s>
 <s id="61">And up I climb, I turn.</s>
 <s id="62">It's really pure flying.</s>
 <s id="63">It's not steering, it's flight.</s>
 <s id="64">BG: What kind of training do you do, you personally, for that?</s>
 <s id="65">YR: Actually, I try to stay just fit.</s>
 <s id="66">I don't do special physical training.</s>
 <s id="67">I just try to keep my mobility through new activities.</s>
 <s id="68">For example, last winter I began with kite surfing.</s>
 <s id="69">So, new things.</s>
 <s id="70">So you have to adapt.</s>
 <s id="71">I'm quite an experienced manager of systems as a pilot, but this is, really -- You need fluidity, you need to be agile and also to adapt really fast.</s>
 <s id="72">BG: Somebody in the audience asked me, "How does he breathe up there?"</s>
 <s id="73">Because you're going fast and you're up at 3,000 meters or so.</s>
 <s id="74">YR: Okay, up to 3,000 meters, it's not such a big problem with oxygen.</s>
 <s id="75">But for example, bikers, they have the same speed.</s>
 <s id="76">Just with the helmet, integral helmet, it's really no problem to breathe.</s>
 <s id="77">BG: Describe for me the equipment, since you have it here.</s>
 <s id="78">So Breitling's four engines.</s>
 <s id="79">YR: Yeah, two-meter span.</s>
 <s id="80">Ultra-stable profile.</s>
 <s id="81">Four little engines, 22 kilos thrust each, turbines, working with kerosene.</s>
 <s id="82">Harness, parachute.</s>
 <s id="83">My only instruments are an altimeter and time.</s>
 <s id="84">I know I have about eight minutes fuel.</s>
 <s id="85">So I just check before it's finished.</s>
 <s id="86">(Laughter) And yeah, that's all.</s>
 <s id="87">Two parachutes.</s>
 <s id="88">That means, if I have a problem with the first one I pull, I still have the possibility to open the second one.</s>
 <s id="89">And this is my life.</s>
 <s id="90">That's the real important thing about safety.</s>
 <s id="91">I did use that during these last 15 years about 20 times.</s>
 <s id="92">Never with that type of wing, but at the beginning.</s>
 <s id="93">I can release my wing when I am in a spin or unstable.</s>
 <s id="94">BG: We saw the 2009 crossing of the Gibraltar Strait where you lost control and then you dived down into the clouds and in the ocean.</s>
 <s id="95">So that was one of those cases where you let the wings go, right?</s>
 <p id="p96">
  <s id="96.1">YR: Yeah.</s>
  <s id="96.2">I did try in the clouds, but you lose orientation completely.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="97">So I did try to take, again, a climb altitude.</s>
 <s id="98">I thought, okay, I will go out.</s>
 <s id="99">But most probably, I did something like that.</s>
 <s id="100">(Laughter) BG: Something that is not very safe, the image.</s>
 <s id="101">YR: You feel great, but -- (Laughter) But you have not the right altitude.</s>
 <s id="102">So the next thing I saw was just blue.</s>
 <s id="103">It was the sea.</s>
 <s id="104">I have also an audible altimeter.</s>
 <s id="105">So I was at my minimum altitude in that vector -- fast -- so I pulled that.</s>
 <s id="106">And then I did open my chute.</s>
 <s id="107">BG: So the wings have their own parachute, and you have your two parachutes.</s>
 <p id="p108">
  <s id="108.1">YR: Exactly.</s>
  <s id="108.2">There is a rescue parachute for the wing for two reasons: so I can repair it afterward and especially so nobody takes that, just on his head.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p109">
  <s id="109.1">BG: I see.</s>
  <s id="109.2">Maybe come back here.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="110">This is risky stuff indeed.</s>
 <s id="111">People have died trying to do this kind of thing.</s>
 <s id="112">And you don't look like a crazy guy; you're a Swiss airline pilot, so you're rather a checklist kind of guy.</s>
 <s id="113">I assume you have standards.</s>
 <p id="p114">
  <s id="114.1">YR: Yeah.</s>
  <s id="114.2">I have no checklist for that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="115">(Laughter) BG: Let's not tell your employer.</s>
 <s id="116">(Laughter) YR: No, that's really two worlds.</s>
 <s id="117">Civil aviation is something that we know very well.</s>
 <s id="118">We have a hundred years of experience.</s>
 <s id="119">And you can adapt really precisely.</s>
 <s id="120">With that, I have to adapt to something new.</s>
 <s id="121">That means improvise.</s>
 <s id="122">So it's really a play between these two approaches.</s>
 <s id="123">Something that I know very well, these principles.</s>
 <s id="124">For example, we have two engines on an Airbus; with only one engine, you can fly it.</s>
 <s id="125">So plan B, always a plan B.</s>
 <s id="126">In a fighter, you have an ejection seat.</s>
 <s id="127">That's my ejection seat.</s>
 <s id="128">So I have the approach of a professional pilot with the respect of a pioneer in front of Mother Nature.</s>
 <s id="129">BG: It's well said.</s>
 <s id="130">What happens if one of the engines stops?</s>
 <s id="131">YR: I do a roll.</s>
 <s id="132">And then I stabilize, and according to my altitude, I continue on two or three engines.</s>
 <s id="133">It's sometimes possible.</s>
 <s id="134">It's quite complicated to explain, but according to which regime I was, I can continue on two and try to get a nice place to land, and then I open my parachute.</s>
 <s id="135">BG: So the beginning of the flight is actually you jump off a plane or a helicopter, and you go on a dive and accelerate the engines, and then you basically take off mid-air somewhere.</s>
 <s id="136">And then the landing, as we have seen, arriving on this side of the Channel, is through a parachute.</s>
 <s id="137">So just as a curiosity, where did you land when you flew over the Grand Canyon?</s>
 <s id="138">Did you land on the rim, down at the bottom?</s>
 <s id="139">YR: It was down on the bottom.</s>
 <s id="140">And I came back afterward on the sled of the helicopter back.</s>
 <s id="141">But it was too stony and full of cactus on top.</s>
 <s id="142">(Laughter) BG: That's exactly why I asked the question.</s>
 <s id="143">YR: And also, the currents are quite funny there.</s>
 <s id="144">There is big thermal activity, big difference in altitude also.</s>
 <s id="145">So it was much safer for me to land at the bottom.</s>
 <s id="146">BG: I think that right now, many people are asking, "When are you developing a double-seater so they can fly with you?"</s>
 <s id="147">YR: I have a standard answer.</s>
 <s id="148">Have you ever seen tandem birds?</s>
 <s id="149">(Laughter) BG: Perfect answer.</s>
 <s id="150">(Applause) (Applause ends) BG: Yves, one last question.</s>
 <p id="p151">
  <s id="151.1">What's next for you?</s>
  <s id="151.2">What's next for Jetman?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="152">YR: First, to instruct a younger guy.</s>
 <s id="153">I want to share it, to do formation flights.</s>
 <s id="154">And I plan to start from a cliff, like catapulted from a cliff.</s>
 <s id="155">BG: So instead of jumping off a plane, yes?</s>
 <s id="156">YR: Yes, with the final goal to take off, but with initial speed.</s>
 <s id="157">Really, I go step by step.</s>
 <s id="158">It seems a little bit crazy, but it's not.</s>
 <s id="159">It's possible to start already now, it's just too dangerous.</s>
 <s id="160">(Laughter) Thanks to the increasing technology, better technology, it will be safe.</s>
 <s id="161">And I hope it will be for everybody.</s>
 <p id="p162">
  <s id="162.1">BG: Yves, thank you very much.</s>
  <s id="162.2">Yves Rossy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="163">(Applause)</s>
</text>
