<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Just between your chest and abdomen is where you’ll find one of the most important muscles you probably didn't know you had: the lower esophageal sphincter, or LES.</s>
 <s id="2">When functioning properly, this ring of tissue plays a crucial role in helping us eat.</s>
 <s id="3">But when the LES malfunctions, it becomes the main player in heartburn --a searing, sometimes sour-tasting chest-spasm that many people will experience at some point in their lives.</s>
 <s id="4">We know that humans have been battling heartburn for hundreds, if not thousands of years.</s>
 <s id="5">But recently the incidence has risen, making it a common stomach complaint worldwide.</s>
 <s id="6">When the symptoms of heartburn become more more regular and intense —such as twice a week or more-- it’s diagnosed as Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease, or GERD.</s>
 <s id="7">But what causes this problem, and how can it be stopped?</s>
 <s id="8">Heartburn starts in an area called the gastroesophageal junction, where the LES resides.</s>
 <s id="9">This smooth, muscular ring of the LES is moderated by an intricate tree of nerve roots that connect to the brain, the heart, and the lungs.</s>
 <s id="10">After food enters the stomach from the esophagus, the muscle’s task is to stop it from surging back up again.</s>
 <s id="11">The LES contracts, squeezing the stomach entrance and creating a high pressure zone that prevents digestive acids from seeping out.</s>
 <s id="12">But if the LES relaxes at the wrong moment or gradually weakens, it becomes like a faulty, ill-fitting lid, causing the area to depressurize.</s>
 <s id="13">That allows burning stomach acid-- and even chunks of food--to spurt into the esophagus, sometimes going as far up as the mouth.</s>
 <s id="14">The cause of all this internal drama has long been put down to diet.</s>
 <s id="15">Foods like caffeine and peppermint contain ingredients that may have a relaxing affect on the LES, which makes it incapable of doing its job.</s>
 <s id="16">Other acidic foods, like citrus and tomatoes, can worsen irritation of the esophagus when they leach out with stomach acid.</s>
 <s id="17">Carbonated beverages can similarly bubble up in the stomach, forcing open the valve.</s>
 <s id="18">But researchers have discovered that food isn’t the only trigger.</s>
 <s id="19">Smoking poses a risk, because the nicotine in cigarettes relaxes the LES.</s>
 <s id="20">Consuming excessive amounts of alcohol may have a similar effect.</s>
 <s id="21">Pregnant women often experience more heartburn due to the pressure of a growing baby on their stomachs.</s>
 <s id="22">and the levels of certain hormones in their bodies.</s>
 <s id="23">Obesity can cause hernias that disrupt the anti-reflux barrier of the gastroesophageal junction that normally protects against heartburn.</s>
 <s id="24">Numerous medications, including those for asthma, high blood pressure, birth control, and depression can also have unintended effects on the LES.</s>
 <s id="25">An occasional bout of heartburn isn't necessarily something to worry about.</s>
 <s id="26">But, if heartburn starts happening regularly, it can weaken the LES muscle over time, letting more and more acid escape.</s>
 <s id="27">And if it goes untreated, this can cause bigger problems.</s>
 <s id="28">Over time, constant acid leakage from heartburn may form scar tissue which narrows the esophageal tube, making it harder to swallow food.</s>
 <s id="29">Ongoing reflux can also damage the cells lining the esophagus--a rare condition called Barrett’s esophagus, which can elevate the risk of esophageal cancer.</s>
 <s id="30">Luckily, heartburn is often treatable with a range of medicines that can help neutralize or reduce stomach acid.</s>
 <s id="31">In extreme cases, some people have surgery to tighten the LES to minimize their distress.</s>
 <s id="32">But we can often stop heartburn before it reaches that point.</s>
 <s id="33">Reducing the consumption of certain foods, not smoking, and maintaining a healthy weight can all dramatically reduce reflux.</s>
 <s id="34">With proper care we can help our LES’s keep the chemical fountain of our stomachs in proper order and avoid having to feel the burn.</s>
</text>
