<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm a creative technologist and the focus of my work is on public installations.</s>
 <s id="2">One of my driving passions is this idea of exploring nature, and trying to find hidden data within nature.</s>
 <s id="3">It seems to me that there is this latent potential everywhere, all around us.</s>
 <s id="4">Everything gives out some kind of data, whether it's sound or smell or vibration.</s>
 <s id="5">Through my work, I've been trying to find ways to harness and unveil this.</s>
 <s id="6">And so this basically led me to a subject called cymatics.</s>
 <s id="7">Now, cymatics is the process of visualizing sound by basically vibrating a medium such as sand or water, as you can see there.</s>
 <s id="8">So, if we have a quick look at the history of cymatics beginning with the observations of resonance, by Da Vinci, Galileo, the English scientist Robert Hook and then Ernest Chladni.</s>
 <s id="9">He created an experiment using a metal plate, covering it with sand and then bowing it to create the Chladni patterns that you see here on the right.</s>
 <s id="10">Moving on from this, the next person to explore this field was a gentleman called Hans Jenny in the 1970s.</s>
 <s id="11">He actually coined the term cymatics.</s>
 <s id="12">Then bringing us into the present day is a fellow collaborator of mine and cymatics expert, John Stewart Reed.</s>
 <s id="13">He's kindly recreated for us the Chladni experiment.</s>
 <s id="14">What we can see here is the metal sheet, this time connected to a sound driver and being fed by a frequency generator.</s>
 <s id="15">As the frequencies increase, so do the complexities of the patterns that appear on the plate.</s>
 <s id="16">As you can see with your own eyes.</s>
 <s id="17">(Applause) So, what excites me about cymatics?</s>
 <s id="18">Well, for me cymatics is an almost magical tool.</s>
 <s id="19">It's like a looking glass into a hidden world.</s>
 <s id="20">Through the numerous ways that we can apply cymatics, we can actually start to unveil the substance of things not seen.</s>
 <s id="21">Devices like the cymascope, which you can see here, have been used to scientifically observe cymatic patterns.</s>
 <s id="22">And the list of scientific applications is growing every day.</s>
 <s id="23">For example, in oceanography, a lexicon of dolphin language is actually being created by basically visualizing the sonar beams that the dolphins emit.</s>
 <s id="24">And hopefully in the future we'll be able to gain some deeper understanding of how they communicate.</s>
 <s id="25">We can also use cymatics for healing and education.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">This is an installation developed with school children, where their hands are tracked.</s>
  <s id="26.2">It allows them to control and position cymatic patterns and the reflections that are caused by them.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">We can also use cymatics as a beautiful natural art form.</s>
 <s id="28">This image here is created from a snippet of Beethoven's Ninth Symphony playing through a cymatic device.</s>
 <s id="29">So it kind of flips things on its head a little bit.</s>
 <s id="30">This is Pink Floyd's "Machine" playing in real time through the cymascope.</s>
 <s id="31">We can also use cymatics as a looking glass into nature.</s>
 <s id="32">And we can actually recreate the archetypal forms of nature.</s>
 <s id="33">So, for example, here on the left we can see a snowflake as it would appear in nature.</s>
 <s id="34">Then on the right we can see a cymatically created snowflake.</s>
 <s id="35">And here is a starfish and a cymatic starfish.</s>
 <s id="36">And there is thousands of these.</s>
 <s id="37">So what does this all mean?</s>
 <p id="p38">
  <s id="38.1">Well, there is still a lot to explore in its early days.</s>
  <s id="38.2">And there's not many people working in this field.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="39">But consider for a moment that sound does have form.</s>
 <s id="40">We've seen that it can affect matter and cause form within matter.</s>
 <s id="41">Then sort of take a leap and think about the universe forming.</s>
 <s id="42">And think about the immense sound of the universe forming.</s>
 <s id="43">And if we kind of ponder on that, then perhaps cymatics had an influence on the formation of the universe itself.</s>
 <s id="44">And here is some eye candy for you, from a range of DIY scientists and artists from all over the globe.</s>
 <s id="45">Cymatics is accessible to everybody.</s>
 <s id="46">I want to urge everybody here to apply your passion, your knowledge and your skills to areas like cymatics.</s>
 <s id="47">I think collectively we can build a global community.</s>
 <s id="48">We can inspire each other.</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">And we can evolve this exploration of the substance of things not seen.</s>
  <s id="49.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">(Applause)</s>
</text>
