<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Music) What you just heard are the interactions of barometric pressure, wind and temperature readings that were recorded of Hurricane Noel in 2007.</s>
 <s id="2">The musicians played off a three-dimensional graph of weather data like this.</s>
 <s id="3">Every single bead, every single colored band, represents a weather element that can also be read as a musical note.</s>
 <s id="4">I find weather extremely fascinating.</s>
 <s id="5">Weather is an amalgam of systems that is inherently invisible to most of us.</s>
 <s id="6">So I use sculpture and music to make it, not just visible, but also tactile and audible.</s>
 <s id="7">All of my work begins very simple.</s>
 <s id="8">I extract information from a specific environment using very low-tech data collecting devices -- generally anything I can find in the hardware store.</s>
 <s id="9">I then compare my information to the things I find on the Internet -- satellite images, weather data from weather stations as well as offshore buoys.</s>
 <s id="10">That's both historical as well as real data.</s>
 <s id="11">And then I compile all of these numbers on these clipboards that you see here.</s>
 <s id="12">These clipboards are filled with numbers.</s>
 <s id="13">And from all of these numbers, I start with only two or three variables.</s>
 <s id="14">That begins my translation process.</s>
 <s id="15">My translation medium is a very simple basket.</s>
 <s id="16">A basket is made up of horizontal and vertical elements.</s>
 <s id="17">When I assign values to the vertical and horizontal elements, I can use the changes of those data points over time to create the form.</s>
 <s id="18">I use natural reed, because natural reed has a lot of tension in it that I cannot fully control.</s>
 <s id="19">That means that it is the numbers that control the form, not me.</s>
 <s id="20">What I come up with are forms like these.</s>
 <s id="21">These forms are completely made up of weather data or science data.</s>
 <s id="22">Every colored bead, every colored string, represents a weather element.</s>
 <s id="23">And together, these elements, not only construct the form, but they also reveal behavioral relationships that may not come across through a two-dimensional graph.</s>
 <s id="24">When you step closer, you actually see that it is indeed all made up of numbers.</s>
 <s id="25">The vertical elements are assigned a specific hour of the day.</s>
 <s id="26">So all the way around, you have a 24-hour timeline.</s>
 <s id="27">But it's also used to assign a temperature range.</s>
 <s id="28">On that grid, I can then weave the high tide readings, water temperature, air temperature and Moon phases.</s>
 <s id="29">I also translate weather data into musical scores.</s>
 <s id="30">And musical notation allows me a more nuanced way of translating information without compromising it.</s>
 <s id="31">So all of these scores are made up of weather data.</s>
 <s id="32">Every single color, dot, every single line, is a weather element.</s>
 <s id="33">And together, these variables construct a score.</s>
 <s id="34">I use these scores to collaborate with musicians.</s>
 <s id="35">This is the 1913 Trio performing one of my pieces at the Milwaukee Art Museum.</s>
 <s id="36">Meanwhile, I use these scores as blueprints to translate into sculptural forms like this, that function still in the sense of being a three-dimensional weather visualization, but now they're embedding the visual matrix of the musical score, so it can actually be read as a musical score.</s>
 <s id="37">What I love about this work is that it challenges our assumptions of what kind of visual vocabulary belongs in the world of art, versus science.</s>
 <s id="38">This piece here is read very differently depending on where you place it.</s>
 <s id="39">You place it in an art museum, it becomes a sculpture.</s>
 <s id="40">You place it in a science museum, it becomes a three-dimensional visualization of data.</s>
 <s id="41">You place it in a music hall, it all of a sudden becomes a musical score.</s>
 <s id="42">And I really like that, because the viewer is really challenged as to what visual language is part of science versus art versus music.</s>
 <s id="43">The other reason why I really like this is because it offers an alternative entry point into the complexity of science.</s>
 <s id="44">And not everyone has a Ph.D. in science.</s>
 <s id="45">So for me, that was my way into it.</s>
 <s id="46">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="47">(Applause)</s>
</text>
