<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">When I was a kid, my mom and I made this deal.</s>
 <s id="2">I was allowed to take three mental health rest days every semester as long as I continued to do well in school.</s>
 <s id="3">This was because I started my mental health journey when I was only six years old.</s>
 <s id="4">I was always what my grade-school teachers would call "a worrier," but later on we found out that I have trauma-induced anxiety and clinical depression.</s>
 <s id="5">This made growing up pretty hard.</s>
 <s id="6">I was worried about a lot of things that other kids weren't, and school got really overwhelming sometimes.</s>
 <s id="7">This resulted in a lot of breakdowns, panic attacks -- sometimes I was super productive, and other days I couldn't get anything done.</s>
 <s id="8">This was all happening during a time when mental health wasn't being talked about as much as it is now, especially youth mental health.</s>
 <s id="9">Some semesters I used all of those rest days to the fullest.</s>
 <s id="10">Others, I didn't need any at all.</s>
 <s id="11">But the fact that they were always an option is what kept me a happy, healthy and successful student.</s>
 <s id="12">Now I'm using those skills that I learned as a kid to help other students with mental health challenges.</s>
 <s id="13">I'm here today to offer you some insight into the world of teenage mental health: what's going on, how did we get here and what can we do?</s>
 <s id="14">But first you need to understand that while not everyone has a diagnosed mental illness like I do, absolutely everyone -- all of you have mental health.</s>
 <s id="15">All of us have a brain that needs to be cared for in similar ways that we care for our physical well-being.</s>
 <s id="16">Our head and our body are connected by much more than just our neck after all.</s>
 <s id="17">Mental illness even manifests itself in some physical ways, such as nausea, headaches, fatigue and shortness of breath.</s>
 <s id="18">So since mental health affects all of us, shouldn't we be coming up with solutions that are accessible to all of us?</s>
 <s id="19">That brings me to my second part of my story.</s>
 <s id="20">When I was in high school I had gotten pretty good at managing my own mental health.</s>
 <s id="21">I was a successful student, and I was president of the Oregon Association of Student Councils.</s>
 <s id="22">But it was around this time that I began to realize mental health was much a bigger problem than just for me personally.</s>
 <s id="23">Unfortunately, my hometown was touched by multiple suicides during my first year in high school.</s>
 <s id="24">I saw those tragedies shake our entire community, and as the president of a statewide group, I began hearing more and more stories from students where this had also happened in their town.</s>
 <s id="25">So in 2018 at our annual summer camp, we held a forum with about 100 high school students to discuss teenage mental health.</s>
 <s id="26">What could we do?</s>
 <s id="27">We approached this conversation with an enormous amount of empathy and honesty, and the results were astounding.</s>
 <s id="28">What struck me the most was that every single one of my peers had a story about a mental health crisis in their school, no matter if they were from a tiny town in eastern Oregon or the very heart of Portland.</s>
 <s id="29">This was happening everywhere.</s>
 <s id="30">We even did some research, and we found out that suicide is the second leading cause of death for youth ages 10 to 24 in Oregon.</s>
 <s id="31">The second leading cause.</s>
 <s id="32">We knew we had to do something.</s>
 <s id="33">So over the next few months, we made a committee called Students for a Healthy Oregon, and we set out to end the stigma against mental health.</s>
 <s id="34">We also wanted to prioritize mental health in schools.</s>
 <s id="35">With the help of some lobbyists and a few mental health professionals, we put forth House Bill 2191.</s>
 <s id="36">This bill allows students to take mental health days off from school the same way you would a physical health day.</s>
 <s id="37">Because oftentimes that day off is the difference between feeling a whole lot better and a whole lot worse -- kind of like those days my mom gave me when I was younger.</s>
 <s id="38">So over the next few months, we lobbied and researched and campaigned for our bill, and in June of 2019 it was finally signed into law.</s>
 <s id="39">(Applause and cheers) This was a groundbreaking moment for Oregon students.</s>
 <s id="40">Here's an example of how this is playing out now.</s>
 <s id="41">Let's say a student is having a really hard month.</s>
 <s id="42">They're overwhelmed, overworked, they're falling behind in school, and they know they need help.</s>
 <s id="43">Maybe they've never talked about mental health with their parents before, but now they have a law on their side to help initiate that conversation.</s>
 <s id="44">The parent still needs to be the one to call the school and excuse the absence, so it's not like it's a free pass for the kids, but most importantly, now that school has that absence recorded as a mental health day, so they can keep track of just how many students take how many mental health days.</s>
 <s id="45">If a student takes too many, they'll be referred to the school counselor for a check-in.</s>
 <s id="46">This is important because we can catch students who are struggling before it's too late.</s>
 <s id="47">One of the main things we heard at that forum in 2018 is that oftentimes stepping forward and getting help is the hardest step.</s>
 <s id="48">We're hoping that this law can help with that.</s>
 <s id="49">This not only will start teaching kids young how to take care of themselves and practice self-care and stress management, but it could also literally save lives.</s>
 <s id="50">Now students from multiple other states are also trying to pass these laws.</s>
 <s id="51">I'm currently working with students in both California and Colorado to do the same, because we believe that students everywhere deserve a chance to feel better.</s>
 <s id="52">Aside from all the practical reasons and technicalities, House Bill 2191 is really special because of the core concept behind it: that physical and mental health are equal and should be treated as such.</s>
 <s id="53">In fact, they're connected.</s>
 <s id="54">Take health care for example.</s>
 <s id="55">Think about CPR.</s>
 <s id="56">If you were put in a situation where you had to administer CPR, would you know at least a little bit of what to do?</s>
 <s id="57">Think to yourself -- most likely yes because CPR trainings are offered in most schools, workplaces and even online.</s>
 <s id="58">We even have songs that go with it.</s>
 <s id="59">But how about mental health care?</s>
 <s id="60">I know I was trained in CPR in my seventh-grade health class.</s>
 <s id="61">What if I was trained in seventh grade how to manage my mental health or how to respond to a mental health crisis?</s>
 <s id="62">I'd love to see a world where each of us has a toolkit of skills to help a friend, coworker, family member or even stranger going through a mental health crisis.</s>
 <s id="63">And these resources should be especially available in schools because that's where students are struggling the most.</s>
 <s id="64">The other concept that I sincerely hope you take with you today is that it is always OK to not be OK, and it is always OK to take a break.</s>
 <s id="65">It doesn't have to be a whole day; sometimes that's not realistic.</s>
 <s id="66">But it can be a few moments here and there to check in with yourself.</s>
 <s id="67">Think of life like a race ...</s>
 <s id="68">like a long-distance race.</s>
 <s id="69">If you sprint in the very beginning you're going to get burnt out.</s>
 <s id="70">You may even hurt yourself from pushing too hard.</s>
 <s id="71">But if you pace yourself, if you take it slow, sometimes intentionally, and you push yourself other times, you are sure to be way more successful.</s>
 <s id="72">So please, look after each other, look after the kids and teens in your life especially the ones that look like they have it all together.</s>
 <s id="73">Mental health challenges are not going away, but as a society, we can learn how to manage them by looking after one another.</s>
 <s id="74">And look after yourself, too.</s>
 <s id="75">As my mom would say, "Once in a while, take a break."</s>
 <s id="76">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="77">(Applause)</s>
</text>
