<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The way we tell stories has naturally changed since Aristotle defined the rules of tragedy about 2,500 years ago.</s>
 <s id="2">According to him, the role of storytelling is to mimic life and make us feel emotions.</s>
 <s id="3">And that's exactly what storytelling as we know it has done very well since then.</s>
 <s id="4">But there is a dimension of life that storytelling could never really reproduce.</s>
 <s id="5">It is the notion of choices.</s>
 <s id="6">Choices are a very important part of our lives.</s>
 <s id="7">We as individuals are defined by the choices we make.</s>
 <s id="8">Some of our decisions can have very significant consequences and totally change the courses of our lives.</s>
 <s id="9">But in a play, a novel or a film, the writer makes all the decisions in advance for the characters, and as the audience, we can only watch, passively, the consequences of his decisions.</s>
 <s id="10">As a storyteller, I've always been fascinated with the idea of recreating this notion of choices in fiction.</s>
 <s id="11">My dream was to put the audience in the shoes of the main protagonists, let them make their own decisions, and by doing so, let them tell their own stories.</s>
 <s id="12">Finding a way to achieve this is what I did in the past 20 years of my life.</s>
 <s id="13">Today, I would like to introduce you to this new way of telling stories, a way that has interactivity at its heart.</s>
 <s id="14">Rather than exposing the theory behind it, which could have been kind of abstract and probably a little bit boring, I thought it would be a great opportunity to do a little experiment.</s>
 <s id="15">I would like you, the people here at TED, to tell your own story.</s>
 <s id="16">So I came with an interactive scene that we are going to play together.</s>
 <s id="17">I've asked Vicky -- hello, Vicky -- to control the main character for us.</s>
 <s id="18">And your role -- you, the audience -- will be to make the choices.</s>
 <s id="19">So Vicky and I don't know what's going to happen, because it will all be based on your decisions.</s>
 <s id="20">This scene comes from our next game, called "Detroit: Become Human," and we are in the near future, where technology made possible the creation of androids that look exactly like human beings.</s>
 <s id="21">We are in the shoes of this character called Connor, who is an android, and he can do very fancy things with coins, as you can see.</s>
 <s id="22">He has this blue triangle on this chest, as all androids do, and now Vicky is in control of this character.</s>
 <s id="23">She can walk around, she can go anywhere, she can look around, she can interact with her environment, and now she can tell her own stories by making choices.</s>
 <s id="24">So here we have our first choice.</s>
 <s id="25">There is a fish on the ground.</s>
 <s id="26">What should we do?</s>
 <s id="27">Should we save it or should we leave it?</s>
 <s id="28">Remember, we are under time pressure, so we'd better be fast.</s>
 <s id="29">What should we do?</s>
 <s id="30">Audience: Save it!</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">David Cage: Save it?</s>
  <s id="31.2">Save the fish?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">(Video) (Fish plops) DC: There we go.</s>
 <s id="33">OK, we have an android who likes animals.</s>
 <s id="34">OK, let's move on.</s>
 <s id="35">Remember, we have a hostage situation.</s>
 <s id="36">(Video) Woman: Please, please, you've got to save my little girl!</s>
 <s id="37">Wait -- you're sending an android?</s>
 <s id="38">Officer: All right, ma'am, you need to go.</s>
 <s id="39">W: You can't do that!</s>
 <s id="40">Why aren't you sending a real person?</s>
 <s id="41">DC: OK, she's not really happy.</s>
 <s id="42">Her daughter's been taken hostage by an android, and of course, she's in a state of shock.</s>
 <s id="43">Now we can continue to explore this apartment.</s>
 <s id="44">We see all the SWAT forces in place.</s>
 <s id="45">But we need to find this Captain Allen first.</s>
 <s id="46">That's the first thing we need to do.</s>
 <s id="47">So, again, we can go anywhere.</s>
 <s id="48">Vicky's still in control of the character.</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">Let's see -- oh, I think this is Captain Allen.</s>
  <s id="49.2">He's on the phone.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">(Video) Connor: Captain Allen, my name is Connor.</s>
 <s id="51">I'm the android sent by CyberLife.</s>
 <s id="52">Captain Allen: Let's fire at everything that moves.</s>
 <s id="53">It already shot down two of my men.</s>
 <s id="54">We could easily get it, but they're on the edge of the balcony -- it if falls, she falls.</s>
 <s id="55">DC: OK, now we need to decide what we want to ask the captain.</s>
 <s id="56">What should be our choice?</s>
 <p id="p57">
  <s id="57.1">Deviant's name?</s>
  <s id="57.2">Deviant's behavior?</s>
  <s id="57.3">Emotional shock?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="58">(Video) C: Has it experienced an emotional shock recently?</s>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">Capt A: I haven't got a clue.</s>
  <s id="59.2">Does it matter?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="60">C: I need information to determine the best approach.</s>
 <p id="p61">
  <s id="61.1">DC: OK, a second choice.</s>
  <s id="61.2">Maybe we can learn something.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="62">What should we choose?</s>
 <s id="63">Audience: Behavior.</s>
 <s id="64">DC: OK, deviant behavior, Vicky.</s>
 <s id="65">(Video) C: Do you know if it's been behaving strangely before this?</s>
 <s id="66">Capt A: Listen ... saving that kid is all that matters.</s>
 <s id="67">DC: OK, we are not going to learn anything from this guy.</s>
 <s id="68">We need to do something.</s>
 <s id="69">Let's try to go back in the lobby.</s>
 <s id="70">Oh, wait -- there's a room over there on your right, Vicky, I think.</s>
 <s id="71">Maybe there's something we can learn here.</s>
 <s id="72">Oh, there's a tablet.</s>
 <s id="73">Let's have a look.</s>
 <s id="74">(Video) Girl: This is Daniel, the coolest android in the world.</s>
 <s id="75">Say "Hi," Daniel.</s>
 <s id="76">Daniel: Hello!</s>
 <s id="77">G: You're my bestie, we'll always be together!</s>
 <s id="78">DC: That was just one way of playing the scenes, but there are many other ways of playing it.</s>
 <s id="79">Depending on the choices you make, we could have seen many different actions, many different consequences, many different outcomes.</s>
 <s id="80">So that gives you an idea of what my work is about as an interactive writer.</s>
 <s id="81">Where a linear writer needs to deal with time and space, as an interactive writer, I need to deal with time, space and possibilities.</s>
 <s id="82">I have to manage massive tree structures, where each branch is a new variation of the story.</s>
 <s id="83">I need to think about all the possibilities in a given scene and try to imagine everything that can happen.</s>
 <s id="84">I need to deal with thousands and thousands of variables, conditions and possibilities.</s>
 <s id="85">As a consequence, where a film script is about 100 pages, an interactive script like this is between four and five thousand pages.</s>
 <s id="86">So that gives you an idea of what this work is about.</s>
 <s id="87">But I think, in the end, the experience is very unique, because it is the result of the collaboration between a writer creating this narrative landscape and the player making his own decisions, telling his own story and becoming the cowriter but also the coactor and the codirector of the story.</s>
 <s id="88">Interactive storytelling is a revolution in the way we tell stories.</s>
 <s id="89">With the emergence of new platforms like interactive television, virtual reality and video games, it can become a new form of entertainment and maybe even a new form of art.</s>
 <s id="90">I am convinced that in the coming years, we will see more and more moving and meaningful interactive experiences, created by a new generation of talents.</s>
 <s id="91">This is a medium waiting for its Orson Welles or its Stanley Kubrick, and I have no doubt that they will soon emerge and be recognized as such.</s>
 <s id="92">I believe that interactive storytelling can be what cinema was in the 20th century: an art that deeply changes its time.</s>
 <s id="93">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="94">(Applause)</s>
</text>
