<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Every day of your life, you move through systems of power that other people made.</s>
 <s id="2">Do you sense them?</s>
 <s id="3">Do you understand power?</s>
 <s id="4">Do you realize why it matters?</s>
 <s id="5">Power is something we are often uncomfortable talking about.</s>
 <s id="6">That's especially true in civic life, how we live together in community.</s>
 <s id="7">In a democracy, power is supposed to reside with the people, period.</s>
 <s id="8">Any further talk about power and who really has it seems a little dirty, maybe even evil.</s>
 <s id="9">But power is no more inherently good or evil than fire or physics.</s>
 <s id="10">It just is.</s>
 <s id="11">It governs how any form of government works.</s>
 <s id="12">It determines who gets to determine the rules of the game.</s>
 <s id="13">So learning how power operates is key to being effective, being taken seriously, and not being taken advantage of.</s>
 <s id="14">In this lesson, we'll look at where power comes from, how it's exercised and what you can do to become more powerful in public life.</s>
 <s id="15">Let's start with a basic definition.</s>
 <s id="16">Power is the ability to make others do what you would have them do.</s>
 <s id="17">Of course, this plays out in all arenas of life, from family to the workplace to our relationships.</s>
 <s id="18">Our focus is on the civic arena, where power means getting a community to make the choices and to take the actions that you want.</s>
 <s id="19">There are six main sources of civic power.</s>
 <s id="20">First, there's physical force and a capacity for violence.</s>
 <s id="21">Control of the means of force, whether in the police or a militia, is power at its most primal.</s>
 <s id="22">A second core source of power is wealth.</s>
 <s id="23">Money creates the ability to buy results and to buy almost any other kind of power.</s>
 <s id="24">The third form of power is state action, government.</s>
 <s id="25">This is the use of law and bureaucracy to compel people to do or not do certain things.</s>
 <s id="26">In a democracy, for example, we the people, theoretically, give government its power through elections.</s>
 <s id="27">In a dictatorship, state power emerges from the threat of force, not the consent of the governed.</s>
 <s id="28">The fourth type of power is social norms or what other people think is okay.</s>
 <s id="29">Norms don't have the centralized machinery of government.</s>
 <s id="30">They operate in a softer way, peer to peer.</s>
 <s id="31">They can certainly make people change behavior and even change laws.</s>
 <s id="32">Think about how norms around marriage equality today are evolving.</s>
 <s id="33">The fifth form of power is ideas.</s>
 <s id="34">An idea, individual liberties, say, or racial equality, can generate boundless amounts of power if it motivates enough people to change their thinking and actions.</s>
 <s id="35">And so the sixth source of power is numbers, lots of humans.</s>
 <s id="36">A vocal mass of people creates power by expressing collective intensity of interest and by asserting legitimacy.</s>
 <s id="37">Think of the Arab Spring or the rise of the Tea Party.</s>
 <s id="38">Crowds count.</s>
 <s id="39">These are the six main sources of power, what power is.</s>
 <s id="40">So now, let's think about how power operates.</s>
 <s id="41">There are three laws of power worth examining.</s>
 <s id="42">Law number one: power is never static.</s>
 <s id="43">It's always either accumulating or decaying in a civic arena.</s>
 <s id="44">So if you aren't taking action, you're being acted upon.</s>
 <s id="45">Law number two: power is like water.</s>
 <s id="46">It flows like a current through everyday life.</s>
 <s id="47">Politics is the work of harnessing that flow in a direction you prefer.</s>
 <s id="48">Policymaking is an effort to freeze and perpetuate a particular flow of power.</s>
 <s id="49">Policy is power frozen.</s>
 <s id="50">Law number three: power compounds.</s>
 <s id="51">Power begets more power, and so does powerlessness.</s>
 <s id="52">The only thing that keeps law number three from leading to a situation where only one person has all the power is how we apply laws one and two.</s>
 <s id="53">What rules do we set up so that a few people don't accumulate too much power, and so that they can't enshrine their privilege in policy?</s>
 <s id="54">That's the question of democracy, and you can see each of these laws at work in any news story.</s>
 <s id="55">Low wage workers organize to get higher pay.</s>
 <s id="56">Oil companies push to get a big pipeline approved.</s>
 <s id="57">Gay and lesbian couples seek the legal right to marry.</s>
 <s id="58">Urban parents demand school vouchers.</s>
 <s id="59">You may support these efforts or not.</s>
 <s id="60">Whether you get what you want depends on how adept you are with power, which brings us finally to what you can do to become more powerful in public life.</s>
 <s id="61">Here, it's useful to think in terms of literacy.</s>
 <s id="62">Your challenge is to learn how to read power and write power.</s>
 <s id="63">To read power means to pay attention to as many texts of power as you can.</s>
 <s id="64">I don't mean books only.</s>
 <s id="65">I mean seeing society as a set of texts.</s>
 <s id="66">Don't like how things are in your campus or city or country?</s>
 <s id="67">Map out who has what kind of power, arrayed in what systems.</s>
 <s id="68">Understand why it turned out this way, who's made it so, and who wants to keep it so.</s>
 <s id="69">Study the strategies others in such situations used: frontal attack or indirection, coalitions or charismatic authority.</s>
 <s id="70">Read so you may write.</s>
 <s id="71">To write power requires first that you believe you have the right to write, to be an author of change.</s>
 <s id="72">You do.</s>
 <s id="73">As with any kind of writing, you learn to express yourself, speak up in a voice that's authentic.</s>
 <s id="74">Organize your ideas, then organize other people.</s>
 <s id="75">Practice consensus building.</s>
 <s id="76">Practice conflict.</s>
 <s id="77">As with writing, it's all about practice.</s>
 <s id="78">Every day you have a chance to practice, in your neighborhood and beyond.</s>
 <s id="79">Set objectives, then bigger ones.</s>
 <s id="80">Watch the patterns, see what works.</s>
 <s id="81">Adapt, repeat.</s>
 <s id="82">This is citizenship.</s>
 <s id="83">In this short lesson, we've explored where civic power comes from, how it works and what you can do to exercise it.</s>
 <s id="84">One big question remaining is the "why" of power.</s>
 <s id="85">Do you want power to benefit everyone or only you?</s>
 <s id="86">Are your purposes pro-social or anti-social?</s>
 <s id="87">This question isn't about strategy.</s>
 <s id="88">It's about character, and that's another set of lessons.</s>
 <s id="89">But remember this: Power plus character equals a great citizen, and you have the power to be one.</s>
</text>
