<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Can any of you remember what you wanted to be when you were 17?</s>
 <s id="2">Do you know what I wanted to be?</s>
 <s id="3">I wanted to be a biker chick.</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) I wanted to race cars, and I wanted to be a cowgirl, and I wanted to be Mowgli from "The Jungle Book."</s>
 <s id="5">Because they were all about being free, the wind in your hair -- just to be free.</s>
 <s id="6">And on my seventeenth birthday, my parents, knowing how much I loved speed, gave me one driving lesson for my seventeenth birthday.</s>
 <s id="7">Not that we could have afforded I drive, but to give me the dream of driving.</s>
 <s id="8">And on my seventeenth birthday, I accompanied my little sister in complete innocence, as I always had all my life -- my visually impaired sister -- to go to see an eye specialist.</s>
 <s id="9">Because big sisters are always supposed to support their little sisters.</s>
 <s id="10">And my little sister wanted to be a pilot -- God help her.</s>
 <s id="11">So I used to get my eyes tested just for fun.</s>
 <s id="12">And on my seventeenth birthday, after my fake eye exam, the eye specialist just noticed it happened to be my birthday.</s>
 <s id="13">And he said, "So what are you going to do to celebrate?"</s>
 <s id="14">And I took that driving lesson, and I said, "I'm going to learn how to drive."</s>
 <s id="15">And then there was a silence -- one of those awful silences when you know something's wrong.</s>
 <s id="16">And he turned to my mother, and he said, "You haven't told her yet?"</s>
 <s id="17">On my seventeenth birthday, as Janis Ian would best say, I learned the truth at 17.</s>
 <s id="18">I am, and have been since birth, legally blind.</s>
 <s id="19">And you know, how on earth did I get to 17 and not know that?</s>
 <s id="20">Well, if anybody says country music isn't powerful, let me tell you this: I got there because my father's passion for Johnny Cash and a song, "A Boy Named Sue."</s>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">I'm the eldest of three.</s>
  <s id="21.2">I was born in 1971.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="22">And very shortly after my birth, my parents found out I had a condition called ocular albinism.</s>
 <s id="23">And what the hell does that mean to you?</s>
 <s id="24">So let me just tell you, the great part of all of this?</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">I can't see this clock and I can't see the timing, so holy God, woohoo!</s>
  <s id="25.2">(Laughter) I might buy some more time.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">But more importantly, let me tell you -- I'm going to come up really close here.</s>
  <s id="26.2">Don't freak out, Pat.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">Hey.</s>
 <s id="28">See this hand?</s>
 <s id="29">Beyond this hand is a world of Vaseline.</s>
 <s id="30">Every man in this room, even you, Steve, is George Clooney.</s>
 <s id="31">(Laughter) And every woman, you are so beautiful.</s>
 <s id="32">And when I want to look beautiful, I step three feet away from the mirror, and I don't have to see these lines etched in my face from all the squinting I've done all my life from all the dark lights.</s>
 <s id="33">The really strange part is that, at three and a half, just before I was going to school, my parents made a bizarre, unusual and incredibly brave decision.</s>
 <s id="34">No special needs schools.</s>
 <s id="35">No labels.</s>
 <s id="36">No limitations.</s>
 <s id="37">My ability and my potential.</s>
 <s id="38">And they decided to tell me that I could see.</s>
 <s id="39">So just like Johnny Cash's Sue, a boy given a girl's name, I would grow up and learn from experience how to be tough and how to survive, when they were no longer there to protect me, or just take it all away.</s>
 <s id="40">But more significantly, they gave me the ability to believe, totally, to believe that I could.</s>
 <s id="41">And so when I heard that eye specialist tell me all the things, a big fat "no," everybody imagines I was devastated.</s>
 <s id="42">And don't get me wrong, because when I first heard it -- aside from the fact that I thought he was insane -- I got that thump in my chest, just that "huh?"</s>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">But very quickly I recovered.</s>
  <s id="43.2">It was like that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">The first thing I thought about was my mom, who was crying over beside me.</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">And I swear to God, I walked out of his office, "I will drive.</s>
  <s id="45.2">I will drive.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p46">
  <s id="46.1">You're mad.</s>
  <s id="46.2">I'll drive.</s>
  <s id="46.3">I know I can drive."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="47">And with the same dogged determination that my father had bred into me since I was such a child -- he taught me how to sail, knowing I could never see where I was going, I could never see the shore, and I couldn't see the sails, and I couldn't see the destination.</s>
 <s id="48">But he told me to believe and feel the wind in my face.</s>
 <s id="49">And that wind in my face made me believe that he was mad and I would drive.</s>
 <s id="50">And for the next 11 years, I swore nobody would ever find out that I couldn't see, because I didn't want to be a failure, and I didn't want to be weak.</s>
 <s id="51">And I believed I could do it.</s>
 <s id="52">So I rammed through life as only a Casey can do.</s>
 <s id="53">And I was an archeologist, and then I broke things.</s>
 <s id="54">And then I managed a restaurant, and then I slipped on things.</s>
 <p id="p55">
  <s id="55.1">And then I was a masseuse.</s>
  <s id="55.2">And then I was a landscape gardener.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="56">And then I went to business school.</s>
 <s id="57">And you know, disabled people are hugely educated.</s>
 <s id="58">And then I went in and I got a global consulting job with Accenture.</s>
 <s id="59">And they didn't even know.</s>
 <s id="60">And it's extraordinary how far belief can take you.</s>
 <s id="61">In 1999, two and a half years into that job, something happened.</s>
 <s id="62">Wonderfully, my eyes decided, enough.</s>
 <s id="63">And temporarily, very unexpectedly, they dropped.</s>
 <s id="64">And I'm in one of the most competitive environments in the world, where you work hard, play hard, you gotta be the best, you gotta be the best.</s>
 <s id="65">And two years in, I really could see very little.</s>
 <s id="66">And I found myself in front of an HR manager in 1999, saying something I never imagined that I would say.</s>
 <s id="67">I was 28 years old.</s>
 <s id="68">I had built a persona all around what I could and couldn't do.</s>
 <s id="69">And I simply said, "I'm sorry.</s>
 <s id="70">I can't see, and I need help."</s>
 <s id="71">Asking for help can be incredibly difficult.</s>
 <p id="p72">
  <s id="72.1">And you all know what it is.</s>
  <s id="72.2">You don't need to have a disability to know that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="73">We all know how hard it is to admit weakness and failure.</s>
 <s id="74">And it's frightening, isn't it?</s>
 <s id="75">But all that belief had fueled me so long.</s>
 <s id="76">And can I tell you, operating in the sighted world when you can't see, it's kind of difficult -- it really is.</s>
 <s id="77">Can I tell you, airports are a disaster.</s>
 <s id="78">Oh, for the love of God.</s>
 <s id="79">And please, any designers out there?</s>
 <s id="80">OK, designers, please put up your hands, even though I can't even see you.</s>
 <s id="81">I always end up in the gents' toilets.</s>
 <s id="82">And there's nothing wrong with my sense of smell.</s>
 <s id="83">But can I just tell you, the little sign for a gents' toilet or a ladies' toilet is determined by a triangle.</s>
 <s id="84">Have you ever tried to see that if you have Vaseline in front of your eyes?</s>
 <s id="85">It's such a small thing, right?</s>
 <s id="86">And you know how exhausting it can be to try to be perfect when you're not, or to be somebody that you aren't?</s>
 <s id="87">And so after admitting I couldn't see to HR, they sent me off to an eye specialist.</s>
 <s id="88">And I had no idea that this man was going to change my life.</s>
 <s id="89">But before I got to him, I was so lost.</s>
 <s id="90">I had no idea who I was anymore.</s>
 <s id="91">And that eye specialist, he didn't bother testing my eyes.</s>
 <s id="92">God no, it was therapy.</s>
 <s id="93">And he asked me several questions, of which many were, "Why?</s>
 <s id="94">Why are you fighting so hard not to be yourself?</s>
 <s id="95">And do you love what you do, Caroline?"</s>
 <p id="p96">
  <s id="96.1">And you know, when you go to a global consulting firm, they put a chip in your head, and you're like, "I love Accenture.</s>
  <s id="96.2">I love Accenture.</s>
  <s id="96.3">I love my job.</s>
  <s id="96.4">I love Accenture.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p97">
  <s id="97.1">I love Accenture.</s>
  <s id="97.2">I love Accenture.</s>
  <s id="97.3">I love my job.</s>
  <s id="97.4">I love Accenture."</s>
  <s id="97.5">(Laughter) To leave would be failure.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="98">And he said, "Do you love it?"</s>
 <s id="99">I couldn't even speak I was so choked up.</s>
 <s id="100">I just was so -- how do I tell him?</s>
 <s id="101">And then he said to me, "What did you want to be when you were little?"</s>
 <s id="102">Now listen, I wasn't going to say to him, "Well, I wanted to race cars and motorbikes."</s>
 <s id="103">Hardly appropriate at this moment in time.</s>
 <s id="104">He thought I was mad enough anyway.</s>
 <s id="105">And as I left his office, he called me back and he said, "I think it's time.</s>
 <s id="106">I think it's time to stop fighting and do something different."</s>
 <s id="107">And that door closed.</s>
 <s id="108">And that silence just outside a doctor's office, that many of us know.</s>
 <s id="109">And my chest ached.</s>
 <p id="p110">
  <s id="110.1">And I had no idea where I was going.</s>
  <s id="110.2">I had no idea.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="111">But I did know the game was up.</s>
 <s id="112">And I went home, and, because the pain in my chest ached so much, I thought, "I'll go out for a run."</s>
 <s id="113">Really not a very sensible thing to do.</s>
 <s id="114">And I went on a run that I know so well.</s>
 <s id="115">I know this run so well, by the back of my hand.</s>
 <s id="116">I always run it perfectly fine.</s>
 <s id="117">I count the steps and the lampposts and all those things that visually impaired people have a tendency to have a lot of meetings with.</s>
 <s id="118">And there was a rock that I always missed.</s>
 <s id="119">And I'd never fallen on it, never.</s>
 <s id="120">And there I was crying away, and smash, bash on my rock.</s>
 <s id="121">Broken, fallen over on this rock in the middle of March in 2000, typical Irish weather on a Wednesday -- gray, snot, tears everywhere, ridiculously self-pitying.</s>
 <s id="122">And I was floored, and I was broken, and I was angry.</s>
 <s id="123">And I didn't know what to do.</s>
 <s id="124">And I sat there for quite some time going, "How am I going to get off this rock and go home?</s>
 <s id="125">Because who am I going to be?</s>
 <s id="126">What am I going to be?"</s>
 <s id="127">And I thought about my dad, and I thought, "Good God, I'm so not Sue now."</s>
 <p id="p128">
  <s id="128.1">And I kept thinking over and over in my mind, what had happened?</s>
  <s id="128.2">Where did it go wrong?</s>
  <s id="128.3">Why didn't I understand?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="129">And you know, the extraordinary part of it is I just simply had no answers.</s>
 <s id="130">I had lost my belief.</s>
 <s id="131">Look where my belief had brought me to.</s>
 <p id="p132">
  <s id="132.1">And now I had lost it.</s>
  <s id="132.2">And now I really couldn't see.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="133">I was crumpled.</s>
 <p id="p134">
  <s id="134.1">And then I remember thinking about that eye specialist asking me, "What do you want to be?</s>
  <s id="134.2">What do you want to be?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p135">
  <s id="135.1">What did you want to be when you were little?</s>
  <s id="135.2">Do you love what you do?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p136">
  <s id="136.1">Do something different.</s>
  <s id="136.2">What do you want to be?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p137">
  <s id="137.1">Do something different.</s>
  <s id="137.2">What do you want to be?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="138">And really slowly, slowly, slowly, it happened.</s>
 <s id="139">And it did happen this way.</s>
 <s id="140">And then the minute it came, it blew up in my head and bashed in my heart -- something different.</s>
 <s id="141">"Well, how about Mowgli from 'The Jungle Book'?</s>
 <s id="142">You don't get more different than that."</s>
 <p id="p143">
  <s id="143.1">And the moment, and I mean the moment, the moment that hit me, I swear to God, it was like woo hoo!</s>
  <s id="143.2">You know -- something to believe in.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="144">And nobody can tell me no.</s>
 <s id="145">Yes, you can say I can't be an archeologist.</s>
 <s id="146">But you can't tell me, no, I can't be Mowgli, because guess what?</s>
 <s id="147">Nobody's ever done it before, so I'm going to go do it.</s>
 <s id="148">And it doesn't matter whether I'm a boy or a girl, I'm just going to scoot.</s>
 <s id="149">And so I got off that rock, and, oh my God, did I run home.</s>
 <s id="150">And I sprinted home, and I didn't fall, and I didn't crash.</s>
 <s id="151">And I ran up the stairs, and there was one of my favorite books of all time, "Travels on My Elephant" by Mark Shand -- I don't know if any of you know it.</s>
 <s id="152">And I grabbed this book off, and I'm sitting on the couch going, "I know what I'm going to do.</s>
 <s id="153">I know how to be Mowgli.</s>
 <s id="154">I'm going to go across India on the back of an elephant.</s>
 <s id="155">I'm going to be an elephant handler."</s>
 <s id="156">And I had no idea how I was going to be an elephant handler.</s>
 <s id="157">From global management consultant to elephant handler.</s>
 <p id="p158">
  <s id="158.1">I had no idea how.</s>
  <s id="158.2">I had no idea how you hire an elephant, get an elephant.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p159">
  <s id="159.1">I didn't speak Hindi.</s>
  <s id="159.2">I'd never been to India.</s>
  <s id="159.3">Hadn't a clue.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="160">But I knew I would.</s>
 <s id="161">Because, when you make a decision at the right time and the right place, God, that universe makes it happen for you.</s>
 <s id="162">Nine months later, after that day on snot rock, I had the only blind date in my life with a seven and a half foot elephant called Kanchi.</s>
 <s id="163">And together we would trek a thousand kilometers across India.</s>
 <p id="p164">
  <s id="164.1">(Applause) The most powerful thing of all, it's not that I didn't achieve before then.</s>
  <s id="164.2">Oh my God, I did.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="165">But you know, I was believing in the wrong thing.</s>
 <s id="166">Because I wasn't believing in me, really me, all the bits of me -- all the bits of all of us.</s>
 <s id="167">Do you know how much of us all pretend to be somebody we're not?</s>
 <s id="168">And you know what, when you really believe in yourself and everything about you, it's extraordinary what happens.</s>
 <s id="169">And you know what, that trip, that thousand kilometers, it raised enough money for 6,000 cataract eye operations.</s>
 <s id="170">Six thousand people got to see because of that.</s>
 <s id="171">When I came home off that elephant, do you know what the most amazing part was?</s>
 <s id="172">I chucked in my job at Accenture.</s>
 <s id="173">I left, and I became a social entrepreneur, and I set up an organization with Mark Shand called Elephant Family, which deals with Asian elephant conservation.</s>
 <s id="174">And I set up Kanchi, because my organization was always going to be named after my elephant, because disability is like the elephant in the room.</s>
 <s id="175">And I wanted to make you see it in a positive way -- no charity, no pity.</s>
 <s id="176">But I wanted to work only and truly with business and media leadership to totally reframe disability in a way that was exciting and possible.</s>
 <s id="177">It was extraordinary.</s>
 <s id="178">That's what I wanted to do.</s>
 <s id="179">And I never thought about noes anymore, or not seeing, or any of that kind of nothing.</s>
 <s id="180">It just seemed that it was possible.</s>
 <s id="181">And you know, the oddest part is, when I was on my way traveling here to TED, I'll be honest, I was petrified.</s>
 <s id="182">And I speak, but this is an amazing audience, and what am I doing here?</s>
 <s id="183">But as I was traveling here, you'll be very happy to know, I did use my white symbol stick cane, because it's really good to skip queues in the airport.</s>
 <s id="184">And I got my way here being happily proud that I couldn't see.</s>
 <s id="185">And the one thing is that a really good friend of mine, he texted me on the way over, knowing I was scared.</s>
 <s id="186">Even though I present confident, I was scared.</s>
 <s id="187">He said, "Be you."</s>
 <s id="188">And so here I am.</s>
 <s id="189">This is me, all of me.</s>
 <s id="190">(Applause) And I have learned, you know what, cars and motorbikes and elephants, that's not freedom.</s>
 <s id="191">Being absolutely true to yourself is freedom.</s>
 <s id="192">And I never needed eyes to see -- never.</s>
 <s id="193">I simply needed vision and belief.</s>
 <s id="194">And if you truly believe -- and I mean believe from the bottom of your heart -- you can make change happen.</s>
 <s id="195">And we need to make it happen, because every single one of us -- woman, man, gay, straight, disabled, perfect, normal, whatever -- everyone of us must be the very best of ourselves.</s>
 <s id="196">I no longer want anybody to be invisible.</s>
 <s id="197">We all have to be included.</s>
 <s id="198">And stop with the labels, the limiting.</s>
 <s id="199">Losing of labels, because we are not jam jars.</s>
 <s id="200">We are extraordinary, different, wonderful people.</s>
 <s id="201">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="202">(Applause)</s>
</text>
