<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Music) (Applause) (Applause) (Music) (Applause) (Music) (Applause) Chris Anderson: You guys were amazing.</s>
 <s id="2">That's amazing.</s>
 <s id="3">(Applause) You just don't hear that every day.</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) Usman, the official story is that you learned to play the guitar by watching Jimmy Page on YouTube.</s>
 <p id="p5">
  <s id="5.1">Usman Riaz: Yes, that was the first one.</s>
  <s id="5.2">And then I -- That was the first thing I learned, and then I started progressing to other things.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="6">And I started watching Kaki King a lot, and she would always cite Preston Reed as a big influence, so then I started watching his videos, and it's very surreal right now to be -- (Laughter) (Applause) CA: Was that piece just now, that was one of his songs that you learned, or how did that happen?</s>
 <s id="7">UR: I'd never learned it before, but he told me that we would be playing that on stage, so I was familiar with it, so that's why I had so much more fun learning it.</s>
 <s id="8">And it finally happened, so ...</s>
 <s id="9">(Laughter) CA: Preston, from your point of view, I mean, you invented this like 20 years ago, right?</s>
 <s id="10">How does it feel to see someone like this come along taking your art and doing so much with it?</s>
 <s id="11">Preston Reed: It's mind-blowing, and I feel really proud, really honored.</s>
 <s id="12">And he's a wonderful musician, so it's cool.</s>
 <s id="13">(Laughter) CA: I guess, I don't think there is like a one-minute other piece you guys can do?</s>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">Can you?</s>
  <s id="14.2">Do you jam?</s>
  <s id="14.3">Do you have anything else?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="15">PR: We haven't prepared anything.</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">CA: There isn't.</s>
  <s id="16.2">I'll tell you what.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">If you have another 30 or 40 seconds, and you have another 30 or 40 seconds, and we just see that, I just think -- I can feel it.</s>
  <s id="17.2">We want to hear a little more.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="18">And if it goes horribly wrong, no worries.</s>
 <s id="19">(Applause) (Laughter) (Music) (Applause)</s>
</text>
