<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I've been living in rural East Africa for about 10 years, and I want to share a field perspective with you on global poverty.</s>
 <s id="2">I believe that the greatest failure of the human race is the fact that we've left more than one billion of our members behind.</s>
 <s id="3">Hungry, extreme poverty: these often seem like gigantic, insurmountable problems, too big to solve.</s>
 <s id="4">But as a field practitioner, I believe these are actually very solvable problems if we just take the right strategies.</s>
 <s id="5">Archimedes was an ancient Greek thinker, and he taught us that if we lean on the right levers, we can move the world.</s>
 <s id="6">In the fight against extreme poverty, I believe there are three powerful levers that we can lean on.</s>
 <s id="7">This talk is all about those levers, and why they make poverty a winnable fight in our lifetimes.</s>
 <s id="8">What is extreme poverty?</s>
 <s id="9">When I first moved to rural East Africa, I stayed overnight with a farm family.</s>
 <s id="10">They were wonderful people.</s>
 <p id="p11">
  <s id="11.1">They invited me into their home.</s>
  <s id="11.2">We sang songs together and ate a simple dinner.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="12">They gave me a blanket to sleep on the floor.</s>
 <s id="13">In the morning, however, there was nothing to eat.</s>
 <s id="14">And then at lunchtime, I watched with an increasingly sick feeling as the eldest girl in the family cooked porridge as a substitute for lunch.</s>
 <s id="15">For that meal, every child drank one cup to survive.</s>
 <s id="16">And I cannot tell you how ashamed I felt when they handed one of those cups to me, and I knew I had to accept their hospitality.</s>
 <s id="17">Children need food not only to survive but also to grow physically and mentally.</s>
 <s id="18">Every day they fail to eat, they lose a little bit of their future.</s>
 <s id="19">Amongst the extreme poor, one in three children are permanently stunted from a lifetime of not eating enough.</s>
 <s id="20">When that's combined with poor access to health care, one in 10 extremely poor children die before they reach age five.</s>
 <s id="21">And only one quarter of children complete high school because they lack school fees.</s>
 <s id="22">Hunger and extreme poverty curb human potential in every possible way.</s>
 <s id="23">We see ourselves as a thinking, feeling and moral human race, but until we solve these problems for all of our members, we fail that standard, because every person on this planet matters.</s>
 <s id="24">This child matters.</s>
 <s id="25">These children matter.</s>
 <s id="26">This girl matters.</s>
 <s id="27">You know, we see things like this, and we're upset by them, but they seem like such big problems.</s>
 <s id="28">We don't know how to take effective action.</s>
 <s id="29">But remember our friend Archimedes.</s>
 <s id="30">Global poverty has powerful levers.</s>
 <s id="31">It's a problem like any other.</s>
 <s id="32">I live and work in the field, and as a practitioner, I believe these are very solvable problems.</s>
 <s id="33">So for the next 10 minutes, let's not be sad about the state of the world.</s>
 <s id="34">Let's engage our brains.</s>
 <s id="35">Let's engage our collective passion for problem-solving and figure out what those levers are.</s>
 <s id="36">Lever number one: most of the world's poor are farmers.</s>
 <s id="37">Think about how extraordinary this is.</s>
 <s id="38">If this picture represents the world's poor, then more than half engage in farming as a major source of income.</s>
 <s id="39">This gets me really excited.</s>
 <s id="40">All of these people, one profession.</s>
 <s id="41">Think how powerful this is.</s>
 <s id="42">When farmers become more productive, then more than half the world's poor earn more money and climb out of poverty.</s>
 <s id="43">And it gets better.</s>
 <s id="44">The product of farming is, of course, food.</s>
 <s id="45">So when farmers become more productive, they earn more food, and they don't just help themselves, but they help to feed healthy communities and thriving economies.</s>
 <s id="46">And when farmers become more productive, they reduce environmental pressure.</s>
 <s id="47">We only have two ways we can feed the world: we can either make our existing farmland a lot more productive, or we can clear cut forest and savannah to make more farmland, which would be environmentally disastrous.</s>
 <s id="48">Farmers are basically a really important leverage point.</s>
 <s id="49">When farmers become more productive, they earn more income, they climb out of poverty, they feed their communities and they reduce environmental land pressure.</s>
 <s id="50">Farmers stand at the center of the world.</s>
 <s id="51">And not a farmer like this one, but rather this lady.</s>
 <s id="52">Most of the farmers I know are actually women.</s>
 <s id="53">Look at the strength and the will radiating from this woman.</s>
 <s id="54">She is physically strong, mentally tough, and she will do whatever it takes to earn a better life for her children.</s>
 <s id="55">If we're going to put the future of humanity in one person's hands, then I'm really glad it's her.</s>
 <s id="56">(Applause) There's just one problem: many smallholder farmers lack access to basic tools and knowledge.</s>
 <s id="57">Currently, they take a little bit of saved food grain from the prior year, they plant it in the ground and they till it with a manual hand hoe.</s>
 <s id="58">These are tools and techniques that date to the Bronze Age, and it's why many farmers are still very poor.</s>
 <s id="59">But good news, again.</s>
 <s id="60">Lever number two: humanity actually solved the problem of agricultural poverty a century ago.</s>
 <s id="61">Let me walk you through the three most basic factors in farming.</s>
 <s id="62">First, hybrid seed is created when you cross two seeds together.</s>
 <s id="63">If you naturally pollinate a high-yielding variety together with a drought-resistant variety, you get a hybrid that inherits positive traits from both of its parents.</s>
 <s id="64">Next, conventional fertilizer, if used responsibly, is environmentally sustainable.</s>
 <s id="65">If you micro-dose just a pinch of fertilizer to a plant that's taller than I am, you unlock enormous yield gain.</s>
 <s id="66">These are known as farm inputs.</s>
 <s id="67">Farm inputs need to be combined with good practice.</s>
 <s id="68">When you space your seeds and plant with massive amounts of compost, farmers multiply their harvests.</s>
 <s id="69">These proven tools and practices have more than tripled agricultural productivity in every major region of the world, moving mass numbers of people out of poverty.</s>
 <s id="70">We just haven't finished delivering these things to everybody just yet, particularly in Sub-Saharan Africa.</s>
 <s id="71">So overall, this is amazing news.</s>
 <s id="72">Humanity actually solved agricultural poverty a century ago, in theory.</s>
 <s id="73">We just haven't delivered these things to everybody just yet.</s>
 <s id="74">In this century, the reason that people remain poor is because maybe they live in remote places.</s>
 <s id="75">They lack access to these things.</s>
 <s id="76">Therefore, ending poverty is simply a matter of delivering proven goods and services to people.</s>
 <s id="77">We don't need more genius types right now.</s>
 <s id="78">The humble delivery guy is going to end global poverty in our lifetime.</s>
 <s id="79">So these are the three levers, and the most powerful lever is simply delivery.</s>
 <s id="80">Wherever the world's companies, governments and nonprofits set up delivery networks for life-improving goods, we eliminate poverty.</s>
 <s id="81">OK, so that sounds really nice in theory, but what about in practice?</s>
 <s id="82">What do these delivery networks look like?</s>
 <s id="83">I want to share the concrete example that I know best, my organization, One Acre Fund.</s>
 <s id="84">We only serve the farmer, and our job is to provide her with the tools that she needs to succeed.</s>
 <s id="85">We start off by delivering farm inputs to really rural places.</s>
 <p id="p86">
  <s id="86.1">Now, this may appear initially very challenging, but it's pretty possible.</s>
  <s id="86.2">Let me show you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="87">We buy farm inputs with the combined power of our farmer network, and store it in 20 warehouses like this.</s>
 <s id="88">Then, during input delivery, we rent hundreds of 10-ton trucks and send them out to where farmers are waiting in the field.</s>
 <s id="89">They then get their individual orders and walk it home to their farms.</s>
 <s id="90">It's kind of like Amazon for rural farmers.</s>
 <s id="91">Importantly, realistic delivery also includes finance, a way to pay.</s>
 <s id="92">Farmers pay us little by little over time, covering most of our expenses.</s>
 <s id="93">And then we surround all that with training.</s>
 <s id="94">Our rural field officers deliver practical, hands-on training to farmers in the field every two weeks.</s>
 <s id="95">Wherever we deliver our services, farmers use these tools to climb out of poverty.</s>
 <s id="96">This is a farmer in our program, Consolata.</s>
 <s id="97">Look at the pride on her face.</s>
 <s id="98">She has achieved a modest prosperity that I believe is the human right of every hardworking person on the planet.</s>
 <s id="99">Today, I'm proud to say that we're serving about 400,000 farmers like Consolata.</s>
 <s id="100">(Applause) The key to doing this is scalable delivery.</s>
 <s id="101">In any given area, we hire a rural field officer who delivers our services to 200 farmers, on average, with more than 1,000 people living in those families.</s>
 <s id="102">Today, we have 2,000 of these rural field officers growing very quickly.</s>
 <s id="103">This is our delivery army, and we're just one organization.</s>
 <s id="104">There are many companies, governments and nonprofits that have delivery armies just like this.</s>
 <s id="105">And I believe we stand at a moment in time where collectively, we are capable of delivering farm services to all farmers.</s>
 <s id="106">Let me show you how possible this is.</s>
 <s id="107">This is a map of Sub-Saharan Africa, with a map of the United States for scale.</s>
 <s id="108">I chose Sub-Saharan Africa because this is a huge delivery territory.</s>
 <s id="109">It's very challenging.</s>
 <s id="110">But we analyzed every 50-mile by 50-mile block on the continent, and we found that half of farmers live in just these shaded regions.</s>
 <s id="111">That's a remarkably small area overall.</s>
 <s id="112">If you were to lay these boxes next to each other within a map of the United States, they would only cover the Eastern United States.</s>
 <s id="113">You can order pizza anywhere in this territory and it'll arrive to your house hot, fresh and delicious.</s>
 <s id="114">If America can deliver pizza to an area of this size, then Africa's companies, governments and non-profits can deliver farm services to all of her farmers.</s>
 <s id="115">This is possible.</s>
 <s id="116">I'm going to wrap up by generalizing beyond just farming.</s>
 <s id="117">In every field of human development, humanity has already invented effective tools to end poverty.</s>
 <s id="118">We just need to deliver them.</s>
 <s id="119">So again, in every area of human development, super-smart people a long time ago invented inexpensive, highly effective tools.</s>
 <s id="120">Humanity is armed to the teeth with simple, effective solutions to poverty.</s>
 <s id="121">We just need to deliver these to a pretty small area.</s>
 <s id="122">Again using the map of Sub-Saharan Africa as an example, remember that rural poverty is concentrated in these blue shaded areas.</s>
 <s id="123">Urban poverty is even more concentrated, in these green little dots.</s>
 <s id="124">Again, using a map of the United States for scale, this is what I would call a highly achievable delivery zone.</s>
 <s id="125">In fact, for the first time in human history, we have a vast amount of delivery infrastructure available to us.</s>
 <s id="126">The world's companies, governments and non-profits have delivery armies that are fully capable of covering this relatively small area.</s>
 <s id="127">We just lack the will.</s>
 <s id="128">If we are willing, every one of us has a role to play.</s>
 <s id="129">We first need more people to pursue careers in human development, especially if you live in a developing nation.</s>
 <s id="130">We need more front line health workers, teachers, farmer trainers, sales agents for life-improving goods.</s>
 <s id="131">These are the delivery people that dedicate their careers to improving the lives of others.</s>
 <s id="132">But we also need a lot of support roles.</s>
 <s id="133">These are roles available at just my organization alone, and we're just one out of many.</s>
 <s id="134">This may surprise you, but no matter what your technical specialty, there is a role for you in this fight.</s>
 <s id="135">And no matter how logistically possible it is to end poverty, we need a lot more resources.</s>
 <s id="136">This is our number one constraint.</s>
 <s id="137">For private investors, we need a big expansion of venture capital, private equity, working capital, available in emerging markets.</s>
 <s id="138">But there are also limits to what private business can accomplish.</s>
 <s id="139">Private businesses often struggle to profitably serve the extreme poor, so philanthropy still has a major role to play.</s>
 <s id="140">Anybody can give, but we need more leadership.</s>
 <s id="141">We need more visionary philanthropists and global leaders who will take problems in human development and lead humanity to wipe them off the face of the planet.</s>
 <s id="142">If you're interested in these ideas, check out this website.</s>
 <s id="143">We need more leaders.</s>
 <s id="144">Humanity has put people on the moon.</s>
 <s id="145">We've invented supercomputers that fit into our pockets and connect us with anybody on the planet.</s>
 <s id="146">We've run marathons at a five-minute mile pace.</s>
 <s id="147">We are an exceptional people.</s>
 <s id="148">But we've left more than one billion of our members behind.</s>
 <s id="149">Until every girl like this one has an opportunity to earn her full human potential, we have failed to become a truly moral and just human race.</s>
 <s id="150">Logistically speaking, it's incredibly possible to end extreme poverty.</s>
 <s id="151">We just need to deliver proven goods and services to everybody.</s>
 <s id="152">If we have the will, every one of us has a role to play.</s>
 <s id="153">Let's deploy our time, our careers, our collective wealth.</s>
 <s id="154">Let us deliver an end to extreme poverty in this lifetime.</s>
 <s id="155">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="156">(Applause)</s>
</text>
