<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Along the ancient path of the Monongahela River, Braddock, Pennsylvania sits in the eastern region of Allegheny County, approximately nine miles outside of Pittsburgh.</s>
 <s id="2">An industrial suburb, Braddock is home to Andrew Carnegie's first steel mill, the Edgar Thomson Works.</s>
 <s id="3">Operating since 1875, it is the last functioning steel mill in the region.</s>
 <s id="4">For 12 years, I have produced collaborative portraits, still lifes, landscapes and aerial views in order to build a visual archive to address the intersection of the steel industry, the environment, and the health care system's impact on the bodies of my family and community.</s>
 <s id="5">The tradition and grand narrative of Braddock is mostly comprised of stories of industrialists and trade unions.</s>
 <s id="6">Currently, the new narrative about Braddock, a poster child for Rust Belt revitalization, is a story of urban pioneers discovering a new frontier.</s>
 <s id="7">Mass media has omitted the fact that Braddock is predominantly black.</s>
 <s id="8">Our existence has been co-opted, silenced and erased.</s>
 <s id="9">Fourth generation in a lineage of women, I was raised under the protection and care of Grandma Ruby, off 8th Street at 805 Washington Avenue.</s>
 <s id="10">She worked as a manager for Goodwill.</s>
 <s id="11">Mom was a nurse's aid.</s>
 <s id="12">She watched the steel mills close and white flight to suburban developments.</s>
 <s id="13">By the time my generation walked the streets, disinvestment at the local, state and federal level, eroded infrastructure, and the War on Drugs dismantled my family and community.</s>
 <s id="14">Grandma Ruby's stepfather Gramps was one of few black men to retire from Carnegie's mill with his pension.</s>
 <s id="15">He worked in high temperatures, tearing down and rebuilding furnaces, cleaning up spilt metal and slag.</s>
 <s id="16">The history of a place is written on the body and the landscape.</s>
 <s id="17">Areas of heavy truck traffic, exposure to benzene and atomized metals, risk cancer and lupus.</s>
 <s id="18">One hundred twenty-three licensed beds, 652 employees, rehabilitation programs decimated.</s>
 <s id="19">A housing discrimination lawsuit against Allegheny County removed where the projects Talbot Towers once stood.</s>
 <s id="20">Recent rezoning for more light industry has since appeared.</s>
 <s id="21">Google Maps and Google Earth pixelations conceal the flammable waste being used to squeeze the Bunn family off their home and land.</s>
 <s id="22">In 2013, I chartered a helicopter with my cameras to document this aggressive dispossession.</s>
 <s id="23">In flight, my observation reveals thousands of plastic white bundles owned by a conservation industry that claims it's eco-friendly and recycles millions of tires to preserve people's lives and to improve people's lives.</s>
 <s id="24">My work spirals from the micro to the macro level, excavating hidden histories.</s>
 <s id="25">Recently, at the Seattle Art Museum, Isaac Bunn and I mounted this exhibition, and the exhibition was used as a platform to launch his voice.</s>
 <s id="26">Through reclamation of our narrative, we will continue to fight historic erasure and socioeconomic inequality.</s>
 <s id="27">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="28">(Applause)</s>
</text>
