<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The philosopher Plato once said, "Music gives a soul to the universe, wings to the mind, flight to the imagination and life to everything."</s>
 <s id="2">Music has always been a big part of my life.</s>
 <s id="3">To create and to perform music connects you to people countries and lifetimes away.</s>
 <s id="4">It connects you to the people you're playing with, to your audience and to yourself.</s>
 <s id="5">When I'm happy, when I'm sad, when I'm bored, when I'm stressed, I listen to and I create music.</s>
 <s id="6">When I was younger, I played piano; later, I took up guitar.</s>
 <s id="7">And as I started high school, music became a part of my identity.</s>
 <s id="8">I was in every band, I was involved with every musical fine arts event.</s>
 <s id="9">Music surrounded me.</s>
 <s id="10">It made me who I was, and it gave me a place to belong.</s>
 <s id="11">Now, I've always had this thing with rhythms.</s>
 <s id="12">I remember being young, I would walk down the hallways of my school and I would tap rhythms to myself on my leg with my hands, or tapping my teeth.</s>
 <s id="13">It was a nervous habit, and I was always nervous.</s>
 <s id="14">I think I liked the repetition of the rhythm -- it was calming.</s>
 <s id="15">Then in high school, I started music theory, and it was the best class I've ever taken.</s>
 <s id="16">We were learning about music -- things I didn't know, like theory and history.</s>
 <s id="17">It was a class where we basically just listened to a song, talked about what it meant to us and analyzed it, and figured out what made it tick.</s>
 <s id="18">Every Wednesday, we did something called "rhythmic dictation," and I was pretty good at it.</s>
 <s id="19">Our teacher would give us an amount of measures and a time signature, and then he would speak a rhythm to us and we would have to write it down with the proper rests and notes.</s>
 <s id="20">Like this: ta ta tuck-a tuck-a ta, ta tuck-a-tuck-a-tuck-a, tuck-a.</s>
 <s id="21">And I loved it.</s>
 <s id="22">The simplicity of the rhythm -- a basic two- to four- measure line -- and yet each of them almost told a story, like they had so much potential, and all you had to do was add a melody.</s>
 <s id="23">(Guitar) Rhythms set a foundation for melodies and harmonies to play on top of.</s>
 <s id="24">It gives structure and stability.</s>
 <s id="25">Now, music has these parts -- rhythm, melody and harmony -- just like our lives.</s>
 <s id="26">Where music has rhythm, we have routines and habits -- things that help us to remember what to do and to stay on track, and to just keep going.</s>
 <s id="27">And you may not notice it, but it's always there.</s>
 <s id="28">(Guitar) And it may seem simple, it may seem dull by itself, but it gives tempo and heartbeat.</s>
 <s id="29">And then things in your life add on to it, giving texture -- that's your friends and your family, and anything that creates a harmonic structure in your life and in your song, like harmonies, cadences and anything that makes it polyphonic.</s>
 <s id="30">And they create beautiful chords and patterns.</s>
 <s id="31">(Guitar) And then there's you.</s>
 <s id="32">You play on top of everything else, on top of the rhythms and the beat because you're the melody.</s>
 <s id="33">And things may change and develop, but no matter what we do, we're still the same people.</s>
 <s id="34">Throughout a song melodies develop, but it's still the same song.</s>
 <s id="35">No matter what you do, the rhythms are still there: the tempo and the heartbeat ...</s>
 <s id="36">until I left, and I went to college and everything disappeared.</s>
 <s id="37">When I first arrived at university, I felt lost.</s>
 <s id="38">And don't get me wrong -- sometimes I loved it and it was great, but other times, I felt like I had been left alone to fend for myself.</s>
 <s id="39">It's like I had been taken out of my natural environment, and put somewhere new, where the rhythms and the harmonies and the form had gone away, and it was just me -- (Guitar) silence and my melody.</s>
 <s id="40">And even that began to waver, because I didn't know what I was doing.</s>
 <s id="41">I didn't have any chords to structure myself, or a rhythm or a beat to know the tempo.</s>
 <s id="42">(Guitar) And then I began to hear all these other sounds.</s>
 <s id="43">(Guitar) And they were off-time and off-key.</s>
 <s id="44">And the more I was around them, the more my melody started to sound like theirs.</s>
 <s id="45">And slowly I began to lose myself, like I was being washed away.</s>
 <s id="46">But then the next moment -- (Guitar) I could hear it.</s>
 <s id="47">And I could feel it.</s>
 <s id="48">And it was me.</s>
 <s id="49">And I was here.</s>
 <s id="50">And it was different, but not worse off.</s>
 <s id="51">Just changed a little.</s>
 <s id="52">Music is my way of coping with the changes in my life.</s>
 <s id="53">There's a beautiful connection between music and life.</s>
 <s id="54">It can bind us to reality at the same time it allows us to escape it.</s>
 <s id="55">Music is something that lives inside of you.</s>
 <s id="56">You create it and you're created by it.</s>
 <s id="57">Our lives are not only conducted by music, they're also composed of it.</s>
 <s id="58">So this may seem like a bit of a stretch, but hear me out: music is a fundamental part of what we are and of everything around us.</s>
 <s id="59">Now, music is my passion, but physics also used to be an interest of mine.</s>
 <s id="60">And the more I learned, the more I saw connections between the two -- especially regarding string theory.</s>
 <s id="61">I know this is only one of many theories, but it spoke to me.</s>
 <s id="62">So, one aspect of string theory, at its simplest form, is this: matter is made up of atoms, which are made up of protons and neutrons and electrons, which are made up of quark.</s>
 <s id="63">And here's where the string part comes in.</s>
 <s id="64">This quark is supposedly made up of little coiled strings, and it's the vibrations of these strings that make everything what it is.</s>
 <s id="65">Michio Kaku once explained this in a lecture called, "The Universe in a Nutshell," where he says, "String theory is the simple idea that the four forces of the universe -- gravity, the electromagnetic force, and the two strong forces -- can be viewed as music.</s>
 <s id="66">The music of tiny little rubber bands."</s>
 <s id="67">In this lecture, he goes on to explain physics as the laws of harmony between these strings; chemistry, as the melodies you can play on these strings; and he states that the universe is a "symphony of strings."</s>
 <s id="68">These strings dictate the universe; they make up everything we see and everything we know.</s>
 <s id="69">They're musical notes, but they make us what we are and they hold us together.</s>
 <s id="70">So you see, everything is music.</s>
 <s id="71">(Guitar) When I look at the world, I see music all around us.</s>
 <s id="72">When I look at myself, I see music.</s>
 <s id="73">And my life has been defined by music.</s>
 <s id="74">I found myself through music.</s>
 <s id="75">Music is everywhere, and it is in everything.</s>
 <s id="76">And it changes and it builds and it diminishes.</s>
 <s id="77">But it's always there, supporting us, connecting us to each other and showing us the beauty of the universe.</s>
 <s id="78">So if you ever feel lost, stop and listen for your song.</s>
 <s id="79">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="80">(Applause)</s>
</text>
