<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">What is love?</s>
 <s id="2">It's a hard term to define in so far as it has a very wide application.</s>
 <s id="3">I can love jogging.</s>
 <s id="4">I can love a book, a movie.</s>
 <s id="5">I can love escalopes.</s>
 <s id="6">I can love my wife.</s>
 <s id="7">(Laughter) But there's a great difference between an escalope and my wife, for instance.</s>
 <s id="8">That is, if I value the escalope, the escalope, on the other hand, it doesn't value me back.</s>
 <s id="9">Whereas my wife, she calls me the star of her life.</s>
 <s id="10">(Laughter) Therefore, only another desiring conscience can conceive me as a desirable being.</s>
 <s id="11">I know this, that's why love can be defined in a more accurate way as the desire of being desired.</s>
 <s id="12">Hence the eternal problem of love: how to become and remain desirable?</s>
 <s id="13">The individual used to find an answer to this problem by submitting his life to community rules.</s>
 <s id="14">You had a specific part to play according to your sex, your age, your social status, and you only had to play your part to be valued and loved by the whole community.</s>
 <s id="15">Think about the young woman who must remain chaste before marriage.</s>
 <s id="16">Think about the youngest son who must obey the eldest son, who in turn must obey the patriarch.</s>
 <s id="17">But a phenomenon started in the 13th century, mainly in the Renaissance, in the West, that caused the biggest identity crisis in the history of humankind.</s>
 <s id="18">This phenomenon is modernity.</s>
 <s id="19">We can basically summarize it through a triple process.</s>
 <s id="20">First, a process of rationalization of scientific research, which has accelerated technical progress.</s>
 <s id="21">Next, a process of political democratization, which has fostered individual rights.</s>
 <s id="22">And finally, a process of rationalization of economic production and of trade liberalization.</s>
 <s id="23">These three intertwined processes have completely annihilated all the traditional bearings of Western societies, with radical consequences for the individual.</s>
 <s id="24">Now individuals are free to value or disvalue any attitude, any choice, any object.</s>
 <s id="25">But as a result, they are themselves confronted with this same freedom that others have to value or disvalue them.</s>
 <s id="26">In other words, my value was once ensured by submitting myself to the traditional authorities.</s>
 <s id="27">Now it is quoted in the stock exchange.</s>
 <s id="28">On the free market of individual desires, I negotiate my value every day.</s>
 <s id="29">Hence the anxiety of contemporary man.</s>
 <p id="p30">
  <s id="30.1">He is obsessed: "Am I desirable?</s>
  <s id="30.2">How desirable?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="31">How many people are going to love me?"</s>
 <s id="32">And how does he respond to this anxiety?</s>
 <s id="33">Well, by hysterically collecting symbols of desirability.</s>
 <s id="34">(Laughter) I call this act of collecting, along with others, seduction capital.</s>
 <s id="35">Indeed, our consumer society is largely based on seduction capital.</s>
 <s id="36">It is said about this consumption that our age is materialistic.</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">But it's not true!</s>
  <s id="37.2">We only accumulate objects in order to communicate with other minds.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="38">We do it to make them love us, to seduce them.</s>
 <s id="39">Nothing could be less materialistic, or more sentimental, than a teenager buying brand new jeans and tearing them at the knees, because he wants to please Jennifer.</s>
 <s id="40">(Laughter) Consumerism is not materialism.</s>
 <s id="41">It is rather what is swallowed up and sacrificed in the name of the god of love, or rather in the name of seduction capital.</s>
 <s id="42">In light of this observation on contemporary love, how can we think of love in the years to come?</s>
 <s id="43">We can envision two hypotheses: The first one consists of betting that this process of narcissistic capitalization will intensify.</s>
 <s id="44">It is hard to say what shape this intensification will take, because it largely depends on social and technical innovations, which are by definition difficult to predict.</s>
 <s id="45">But we can, for instance, imagine a dating website which, a bit like those loyalty points programs, uses seduction capital points that vary according to my age, my height/weight ratio, my degree, my salary, or the number of clicks on my profile.</s>
 <s id="46">We can also imagine a chemical treatment for breakups that weakens the feelings of attachment.</s>
 <s id="47">By the way, there's a program on MTV already in which seduction teachers treat heartache as a disease.</s>
 <s id="48">These teachers call themselves "pick-up artists."</s>
 <s id="49">"Artist" in French is easy, it means "artiste."</s>
 <s id="50">"Pick-up" is to pick someone up, but not just any picking up -- it's picking up chicks.</s>
 <s id="51">So they are artists of picking up chicks.</s>
 <s id="52">(Laughter) And they call heartache "one-itis."</s>
 <s id="53">In English, "itis" is a suffix that signifies infection.</s>
 <s id="54">One-itis can be translated as "an infection from one."</s>
 <p id="p55">
  <s id="55.1">It's a bit disgusting.</s>
  <s id="55.2">Indeed, for the pick-up artists, falling in love with someone is a waste of time, it's squandering your seduction capital, so it must be eliminated like a disease, like an infection.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="56">We can also envision a romantic use of the genome.</s>
 <s id="57">Everyone would carry it around and present it like a business card to verify if seduction can progress to reproduction.</s>
 <s id="58">(Laughter) Of course, this race for seduction, like every fierce competition, will create huge disparities in narcissistic satisfaction, and therefore a lot of loneliness and frustration too.</s>
 <s id="59">So we can expect that modernity itself, which is the origin of seduction capital, would be called into question.</s>
 <s id="60">I'm thinking particularly of the reaction of neo-fascist or religious communes.</s>
 <s id="61">But such a future doesn't have to be.</s>
 <s id="62">Another path to thinking about love may be possible.</s>
 <s id="63">But how?</s>
 <s id="64">How to renounce the hysterical need to be valued?</s>
 <s id="65">Well, by becoming aware of my uselessness.</s>
 <s id="66">(Laughter) Yes, I'm useless.</s>
 <s id="67">But rest assured: so are you.</s>
 <s id="68">(Laughter) (Applause) We are all useless.</s>
 <s id="69">This uselessness is easily demonstrated, because in order to be valued I need another to desire me, which shows that I do not have any value of my own.</s>
 <s id="70">I don't have any inherent value.</s>
 <s id="71">We all pretend to have an idol; we all pretend to be an idol for someone else, but actually we are all impostors, a bit like a man on the street who appears totally cool and indifferent, while he has actually anticipated and calculated so that all eyes are on him.</s>
 <s id="72">I think that becoming aware of this general imposture that concerns all of us would ease our love relationships.</s>
 <s id="73">It is because I want to be loved from head to toe, justified in my every choice, that the seduction hysteria exists.</s>
 <s id="74">And therefore I want to seem perfect so that another can love me.</s>
 <s id="75">I want them to be perfect so that I can be reassured of my value.</s>
 <s id="76">It leads to couples obsessed with performance who will break up, just like that, at the slightest underachievement.</s>
 <s id="77">In contrast to this attitude, I call upon tenderness -- love as tenderness.</s>
 <s id="78">What is tenderness?</s>
 <s id="79">To be tender is to accept the loved one's weaknesses.</s>
 <s id="80">It's not about becoming a sad couple of orderlies.</s>
 <s id="81">(Laughter) That's pretty bad.</s>
 <s id="82">On the contrary, there's plenty of charm and happiness in tenderness.</s>
 <s id="83">I refer specifically to a kind of humor that is unfortunately underused.</s>
 <s id="84">It is a sort of poetry of deliberate awkwardness.</s>
 <s id="85">I refer to self-mockery.</s>
 <s id="86">For a couple who is no longer sustained, supported by the constraints of tradition, I believe that self-mockery is one of the best means for the relationship to endure.</s>
</text>
