<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">After breaking Ethic out of prison, Hedge flies them both towards a frontier settlement in the shadow of the Bradbarrier, the great wall that encircles the nation.</s>
 <s id="2">All the settlers there will soon gather for the monthly feeding.</s>
 <s id="3">The people of the wall spend their days gathering up works of art and literature, from all across the land.</s>
 <s id="4">On feeding day, the furnace-bots arrive, ravenous.</s>
 <s id="5">If they eat, the lights stay on, and the food gets delivered.</s>
 <s id="6">If they starve, the people do too.</s>
 <s id="7">Hedge’s fuel supply runs out just as he and Ethic reach the outskirts of town, and they come in for a crash landing.</s>
 <s id="8">Luckily, everyone is too busy preparing for the feeding to notice.</s>
 <s id="9">Today’s feeding is where Ethic can find the leader of an underground resistance movement.</s>
 <s id="10">This person knows the location of the first of three powerful artifacts.</s>
 <s id="11">The problem is, Hedge and Ethic don’t know the resistance leader’s name or appearance.</s>
 <s id="12">But Hedge has gathered the following information: The leader has green eyes.</s>
 <s id="13">If the leader has red hair, their name has at least one consecutive double letter.</s>
 <s id="14">If the leader wear glasses, their name has exactly 2 vowels.</s>
 <s id="15">Otherwise, their name has exactly 3 vowels.</s>
 <s id="16">There is exactly one person for whom these are all true.</s>
 <s id="17">As a fugitive, Ethic can’t sneak into the crowd without drawing attention to herself.</s>
 <s id="18">But she can give instructions to Hedge.</s>
 <s id="19">And one tool she has is what programmers call a conditional.</s>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">That’s a statement of the form “If A, then B.”</s>
  <s id="20.2">Flowcharts are great illustrations of how those work.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="21">This conditional translates to: if A is true, carry out instruction B.</s>
 <s id="22">There are also conditionals that account for different possibilities.</s>
 <s id="23">This says, “If A is true, perform instruction B.</s>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">Otherwise, carry out instruction C.”</s>
  <s id="24.2">So what instructions does she give Hedge so he can find the resistance leader?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="25">Pause now to figure it out for yourself.</s>
 <s id="26">With a problem like this, it can help to simplify first.</s>
 <s id="27">What if Hedge just has to examine this one person?</s>
 <s id="28">What information does he need to collect about her?</s>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">He might ask, “Does she have green eyes?”</s>
  <s id="29.2">What other questions should Hedge ask to find the resistance leader, and how can he track those answers?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">Pause now to figure it out for yourself.</s>
 <s id="31">It may seem intuitive how you’d approach this problem as a human.</s>
 <s id="32">But Hedge isn’t a human, and so the challenge comes from needing to give him systematic instructions that will work in any scenario.</s>
 <s id="33">Hedge needs to examine the settlers, one at a time, until he discovers the right person.</s>
 <s id="34">In other words, like with the lock on the prison cell, this is a loop that repeats the same instructions.</s>
 <s id="35">Only this time the loop will involve a series of questions in the form of conditionals, and will end as soon as Hedge finds his target.</s>
 <s id="36">But first, you’ll want to organize your information.</s>
 <s id="37">Each person has a set of characteristics: Eye color, hair color, glasses, and name.</s>
 <s id="38">Does this person have green eyes?</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">If so, mark a check next to “eye color."</s>
  <s id="39.2">If not, mark an X there.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">If they have red hair, does their name contain a double letter?</s>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">If so, mark a check next to “hair color.”</s>
  <s id="41.2">If they don’t have a double letter, mark an X next to “hair color.”</s>
  <s id="41.3">Anyone with red hair and no double letter can’t be the resistance leader.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">But notice that if they have blue hair, Hedge will skip this question and go on to the next one.</s>
 <s id="43">For the last question, we can say, “If they wear glasses, does their name have exactly 2 vowels?</s>
 <p id="p44">
  <s id="44.1">If they don’t have glasses, does their name have exactly 3 vowels?”</s>
  <s id="44.2">There will be people in the crowd with glasses and 1 vowel, or no glasses and 2 vowels.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="45">But they’re not who we’re looking for, so they’ll get X’s.</s>
 <s id="46">The resistance leader must be someone with either check marks or blanks next to every question.</s>
 <s id="47">Blanks are ok, because if someone has blue hair, the rule about red hair doesn’t apply to them.</s>
 <s id="48">You could have Hedge ask every question about every person, and then choose the person with only checks and blanks.</s>
 <s id="49">But there’s a way to save yourself lots of time: as soon as Hedge marks an X, have him move on to the next person.</s>
 <s id="50">You don’t need to know the answer to every question; just one X means they’re not the target of your search.</s>
 <s id="51">Hedge buzzes through the crowd, and within minutes finds Adila, the resistance leader, and brings her back to Ethic.</s>
 <s id="52">Adila agrees to help them steal the first artifact— the node of power— but under one condition: that Ethic and Hedge jump-start the revolution by reprogramming the furnace-bots that terrorize the town.</s>
 <s id="53">And right on cue, the robots descend.</s>
</text>
