<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Adrian Kohler: Well, we're here today to talk about the evolution of a puppet horse.</s>
 <s id="2">Basil Jones: But actually we're going to start this evolution with a hyena.</s>
 <s id="3">AK: The ancestor of the horse.</s>
 <s id="4">Okay, we'll do something with it.</s>
 <s id="5">(Laughter) Hahahaha.</s>
 <s id="6">The hyena is the ancestor of the horse because it was part of a production called "Faustus in Africa," a Handspring Production from 1995, where it had to play draughts with Helen of Troy.</s>
 <s id="7">This production was directed by South African artist and theater director, William Kentridge.</s>
 <s id="8">So it needed a very articulate front paw.</s>
 <s id="9">But, like all puppets, it has other attributes.</s>
 <s id="10">BJ: One of them is breath, and it kind of breathes.</s>
 <s id="11">AK: Haa haa haaa.</s>
 <s id="12">BJ: Breath is really important for us.</s>
 <s id="13">It's the kind of original movement for any puppet for us onstage.</s>
 <s id="14">It's the thing that distinguishes the puppet -- AK: Oops.</s>
 <s id="15">BJ: From an actor.</s>
 <s id="16">Puppets always have to try to be alive.</s>
 <s id="17">It's their kind of ur-story onstage, that desperation to live.</s>
 <s id="18">AK: Yeah, it's basically a dead object, as you can see, and it only lives because you make it.</s>
 <s id="19">An actor struggles to die onstage, but a puppet has to struggle to live.</s>
 <s id="20">And in a way that's a metaphor for life.</s>
 <s id="21">BJ: So every moment it's on the stage, it's making the struggle.</s>
 <s id="22">So we call this a piece of emotional engineering that uses up-to-the-minute 17th century technology -- (Laughter) to turn nouns into verbs.</s>
 <s id="23">AK: Well actually I prefer to say that it's an object constructed out of wood and cloth with movement built into it to persuade you to believe that it has life.</s>
 <s id="24">BJ: Okay so.</s>
 <s id="25">AK: It has ears that move passively when the head goes.</s>
 <s id="26">BJ: And it has these bulkheads made out of plywood, covered with fabric -- curiously similar, in fact, to the plywood canoes that Adrian's father used to make when he was a boy in their workshop.</s>
 <s id="27">AK: In Port Elizabeth, the village outside Port Elizabeth in South Africa.</s>
 <s id="28">BJ: His mother was a puppeteer.</s>
 <s id="29">And when we met at art school and fell in love in 1971, I hated puppets.</s>
 <s id="30">I really thought they were so beneath me.</s>
 <s id="31">I wanted to become an avant-garde artist -- and Punch and Judy was certainly not where I wanted to go.</s>
 <s id="32">And, in fact, it took about 10 years to discover the Bambara Bamana puppets of Mali in West Africa, where there's a fabulous tradition of puppetry, to learn a renewed, or a new, respect for this art form.</s>
 <s id="33">AK: So in 1981, I persuaded Basil and some friends of mine to form a puppet company.</s>
 <s id="34">And 20 years later, miraculously, we collaborated with a company from Mali, the Sogolon Marionette Troupe of Bamako, where we made a piece about a tall giraffe.</s>
 <s id="35">It was just called "Tall Horse," which was a life-sized giraffe.</s>
 <s id="36">BJ: And here again, you see the same structure.</s>
 <s id="37">The bulkheads have now turned into hoops of cane, but it's ultimately the same structure.</s>
 <s id="38">It's got two people inside it on stilts, which give them the height, and somebody in the front who's using a kind of steering wheel to move that head.</s>
 <s id="39">AK: The person in the hind legs is also controlling the tail, a bit like the hyena -- same mechanism, just a bit bigger.</s>
 <s id="40">And he's controlling the ear movement.</s>
 <s id="41">BJ: So this production was seen by Tom Morris of the National Theatre in London.</s>
 <s id="42">And just around that time, his mother had said, "Have you seen this book by Michael Morpurgo called 'War Horse'?"</s>
 <s id="43">AK: It's about a boy who falls in love with a horse.</s>
 <s id="44">The horse is sold to the First World War, and he joins up to find his horse.</s>
 <s id="45">BJ: So Tom gave us a call and said, "Do you think you could make us a horse for a show to happen at the National Theatre?"</s>
 <s id="46">AK: It seemed a lovely idea.</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">BJ: But it had to ride.</s>
  <s id="47.2">It had to have a rider.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="48">AK: It had to have a rider, and it had to participate in cavalry charges.</s>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) A play about early 20th century plowing technology and cavalry charges was a little bit of a challenge for the accounting department at the National Theatre in London.</s>
 <s id="50">But they agreed to go along with it for a while.</s>
 <s id="51">So we began with a test.</s>
 <s id="52">BJ: This is Adrian and Thys Stander, who went on to actually design the cane system for the horse, and our next-door neighbor Katherine, riding on a ladder.</s>
 <s id="53">The weight is really difficult when it's up above your head.</s>
 <s id="54">AK: And once we put Katherine through that particular brand of hell, we knew that we might be able to make a horse, which could be ridden.</s>
 <s id="55">So we made a model.</s>
 <s id="56">This is a cardboard model, a little bit smaller than the hyena.</s>
 <s id="57">You'll notice that the legs are plywood legs and the canoe structure is still there.</s>
 <s id="58">BJ: And the two manipulators are inside.</s>
 <s id="59">But we didn't realize at the time that we actually needed a third manipulator, because we couldn't manipulate the neck from inside and walk the horse at the same time.</s>
 <s id="60">AK: We started work on the prototype after the model was approved, and the prototype took a bit longer than we anticipated.</s>
 <s id="61">We had to throw out the plywood legs and make new cane ones.</s>
 <s id="62">And we had a crate built for it.</s>
 <s id="63">It had to be shipped to London.</s>
 <s id="64">We were going to test-drive it on the street outside of our house in Cape Town, and it got to midnight and we hadn't done that yet.</s>
 <s id="65">BJ: So we got a camera, and we posed the puppet in various galloping stances.</s>
 <s id="66">And we sent it off to the National Theatre, hoping that they believed that we created something that worked.</s>
 <s id="67">(Laughter) AK: A month later, we were there in London with this big box and a studio full of people about to work with us.</s>
 <s id="68">BJ: About 40 people.</s>
 <s id="69">AK: We were terrified.</s>
 <s id="70">We opened the lid, we took the horse out, and it did work; it walked and it was able to be ridden.</s>
 <s id="71">Here I have an 18-second clip of the very first walk of the prototype.</s>
 <s id="72">This is in the National Theatre studio, the place where they cook new ideas.</s>
 <s id="73">It had by no means got the green light yet.</s>
 <s id="74">The choreographer, Toby Sedgwick, invented a beautiful sequence where the baby horse, which was made out of sticks and bits of twigs, grew up into the big horse.</s>
 <s id="75">And Nick Starr, the director of the National Theatre, saw that particular moment, he was standing next to me -- he nearly wet himself.</s>
 <s id="76">And so the show was given the green light.</s>
 <s id="77">And we went back to Cape Town and redesigned the horse completely.</s>
 <s id="78">Here is the plan.</s>
 <s id="79">(Laughter) And here is our factory in Cape Town where we make horses.</s>
 <s id="80">You can see quite a lot of skeletons in the background there.</s>
 <s id="81">The horses are completely handmade.</s>
 <s id="82">There is very little 20th century technology in them.</s>
 <s id="83">We used a bit of laser cutting on the plywood and some of the aluminum pieces.</s>
 <s id="84">But because they have to be light and flexible, and each one of them is different, they can't be mass-produced, unfortunately.</s>
 <s id="85">So here are some half-finished horses ready to be worked in London.</s>
 <s id="86">And now we would like to introduce you to Joey.</s>
 <s id="87">Joey boy, you there?</s>
 <s id="88">Joey.</s>
 <s id="89">(Applause) (Applause) Joey.</s>
 <s id="90">Joey, come here.</s>
 <s id="91">No, no, I haven't got it.</s>
 <s id="92">He's got it; it's in his pocket.</s>
 <s id="93">BJ: Joey.</s>
 <s id="94">AK: Joey, Joey, Joey, Joey.</s>
 <p id="p95">
  <s id="95.1">Come here.</s>
  <s id="95.2">Stand here where people can see you.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p96">
  <s id="96.1">Move around.</s>
  <s id="96.2">Come on.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p97">
  <s id="97.1">I'd just like to describe -- I won't talk too loud.</s>
  <s id="97.2">He might get irritated.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="98">Here, Craig is working the head.</s>
 <s id="99">He has bicycle brake cables going down to the head control in his hand.</s>
 <s id="100">Each one of them operates either an ear, separately, or the head, up and down.</s>
 <s id="101">But he also controls the head directly by using his hand.</s>
 <s id="102">The ears are obviously a very important emotional indicator of the horse.</s>
 <s id="103">When they point right back, the horse is fearful or angry, depending upon what's going on in front of him, around him.</s>
 <s id="104">Or, when he's more relaxed, the head comes down and the ears listen, either side.</s>
 <s id="105">Horses' hearing is very important.</s>
 <s id="106">It's almost more important than their eyesight.</s>
 <s id="107">Over here, Tommy's got what you call the heart position.</s>
 <s id="108">He's working the leg.</s>
 <s id="109">You see the string tendon from the hyena, the hyena's front leg, automatically pulls the hoop up.</s>
 <s id="110">(Laughter) Horses are so unpredictable.</s>
 <s id="111">(Laughter) The way a hoof comes up with a horse immediately gives you the feeling that it's a convincing horse action.</s>
 <s id="112">The hind legs have got the same action.</s>
 <s id="113">BJ: And Mikey also has, in his fingers, the ability to move the tail from left to right, and up and down with the other hand.</s>
 <s id="114">And together, there's quite a complex possibility of tail expression.</s>
 <s id="115">AK: You want to say something about the breathing?</s>
 <s id="116">BJ: We had a big challenge with breathing.</s>
 <s id="117">Adrian thought that he was going to have to split the chest of the puppet in two and make it breathe like that -- because that's how a horse would breathe, with an expanded chest.</s>
 <s id="118">But we realized that, if that were to be happening, you wouldn't, as an audience, see the breath.</s>
 <s id="119">So he made a channel in here, and the chest moves up and down in that channel.</s>
 <s id="120">So it's anti-naturalistic really, the up and down movement, but it feels like breath.</s>
 <s id="121">And it's very, very simple because all that happens is that the puppeteer breathes with his knees.</s>
 <s id="122">AK: Other emotional stuff.</s>
 <s id="123">If I were to touch the horse here on his skin, the heart puppeteer can shake the body from inside and get the skin to quiver.</s>
 <s id="124">You'll notice, of course, that the puppet is made out of cane lines.</s>
 <s id="125">And I would like you to believe that it was an aesthetic choice, that I was making a three-dimensional drawing of a horse that somehow moves in space.</s>
 <s id="126">But of course, it was the cane is light, the cane is flexible, the cane is durable and the cane is moldable.</s>
 <s id="127">And so it was a very practical reason why it was made of cane.</s>
 <s id="128">The skin itself is made out of a see-through nylon mesh, which, if the lighting designer wants the horse to almost disappear, she can light the background and the horse becomes ghostlike.</s>
 <s id="129">You see the skeletal structure of it.</s>
 <s id="130">Or if you light it from above, it becomes more solid.</s>
 <s id="131">Again, that was a practical consideration.</s>
 <s id="132">The guys inside the horse have to be able to see out.</s>
 <s id="133">They have to be able to act along with their fellow actors in the production.</s>
 <s id="134">And it's very much an in-the-moment activity that they're engaged in.</s>
 <s id="135">It's three heads making one character.</s>
 <s id="136">But now we would like you to put Joey through some paces.</s>
 <s id="137">And plant.</s>
 <s id="138">(Whinny) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="139">And now just -- (Applause) All the way from sunny California we have Zem Joaquin who's going to ride the horse for us.</s>
 <s id="140">(Applause) (Applause) (Music) So we would like to stress that the performance you see in the horse is three guys who have studied horse behavior incredibly thoroughly.</s>
 <s id="141">BJ: Not being able to talk to one another while they're onstage because they're mic'd.</s>
 <s id="142">The sound that that very large chest makes, of the horse -- the whinnying and the nickering and everything -- that starts usually with one performer, carries on with a second person and ends with a third.</s>
 <s id="143">AK: Mikey Brett from Leicestershire.</s>
 <s id="144">(Applause) Mikey Brett, Craig, Leo, Zem Joaquin and Basil and me.</s>
 <p id="p145">
  <s id="145.1">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="145.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="146">(Applause)</s>
</text>
