<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">This is a sculpture I made, which is a way of, kind of, freeing a form into an object that has different degrees of freedom.</s>
 <s id="2">So, it can balance on a point.</s>
 <s id="3">This is a bronze ball, an aluminum arm here, and then this wooden disk.</s>
 <s id="4">And the wooden disk was really thought about as something that you'd want to hold on to, and that would glide easily through your hands.</s>
 <s id="5">The aluminum is because it's very light.</s>
 <s id="6">The bronze is nice hard, durable material that could roll on the ground.</s>
 <s id="7">Inside of the bronze ball there's a lead weight that is free-swinging on an axle that's on two bearings that pass in between, across it, like this, that counterbalance this weight.</s>
 <s id="8">So it allows it to roll.</s>
 <s id="9">And the sphere has that balance property that it always sort of stays still and looks the same from every direction.</s>
 <p id="p10">
  <s id="10.1">But if you put something on top of it, it disbalances it.</s>
  <s id="10.2">And so it would tip over.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="11">But in this case because the interior is free-swinging in relation to the sphere, it can stand up on one point.</s>
 <s id="12">And then there was a second level to this object, which is that it -- I wanted it to convey some proportions that I was interested in, which is the diameter of the Moon and the diameter of the Earth in proportion to each other.</s>
 <s id="13">I was exploring, really early on, wanting to make things float in the air.</s>
 <s id="14">And I thought up a lot of ideas.</s>
 <s id="15">This is sculpture that I made that -- it's magnetically levitated.</s>
 <s id="16">The thing is, is that it's slightly dangerous.</s>
 <s id="17">Normally it's sort of cordoned off when it's in a museum.</s>
 <s id="18">But it's uh -- let's see if I can manipulate it a little bit without, um -- oops.</s>
 <s id="19">So this is just floating, floating on a permanent magnetic field, which stabilizes it in all directions.</s>
 <s id="20">Except there is a slight tether here, which keeps it from going over the top of its field.</s>
 <s id="21">It's sort of surfing on a magnetic field at the crest of a wave.</s>
 <s id="22">And that's what supports the object and keeps it stable.</s>
 <s id="23">I think we could roll the tape, admin.</s>
 <s id="24">I have a sort of a collection of videos that I took of different installations, which I could narrate.</s>
 <s id="25">This is a sculpture of the Sun and the Earth, in proportion.</s>
 <s id="26">Representing that eight and a half minutes that it takes light and gravity to connect the two.</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">So here is the Earth.</s>
  <s id="27.2">It's a little less than a millimeter that was turned of solid bronze.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="28">And here is a similar sculpture.</s>
 <s id="29">That's the Sun at that end.</s>
 <s id="30">And then in a series of 55 balls, it reduces, proportionately -- each ball and the spaces between them reduce proportionately, until they get down to this little Earth.</s>
 <s id="31">This is in a sculpture park in Taejon.</s>
 <s id="32">This one is about the Moon and then the distance to the Earth, in proportion also.</s>
 <s id="33">This is a little stone ball, floating.</s>
 <s id="34">As you can see the little tether, that it's also magnetically levitated.</s>
 <s id="35">And then this is the first part of -- this is 109 spheres, since the Sun is 109 times the diameter of the Earth.</s>
 <s id="36">And so this is the size of the Sun.</s>
 <s id="37">And then each of these little spheres is the size of the Earth in proportion to the Sun.</s>
 <p id="p38">
  <s id="38.1">It's made up of 16 concentric shells.</s>
  <s id="38.2">Each one has 92 spheres.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="39">This is in the courtyard of a twelfth-century alchemist.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">I was thinking that the Sun is kind of the ultimate alchemist.</s>
  <s id="40.2">(Laughter) So this, again, is on the subject -- a slice from the equator of the Earth.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">And then the Moon in the center, and it's floating.</s>
  <s id="41.2">And this is in France.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">This is in Sapporo.</s>
 <s id="43">It's balancing on a shaft and a ball, right at the center of gravity, or just slightly above the center of gravity, which means that the lower half of the object is just a little bit more weighty.</s>
 <s id="44">So you can see it rotating here.</s>
 <s id="45">It weighs about a ton or over a ton.</s>
 <s id="46">It's made of stainless steel, quite thick.</s>
 <s id="47">But it's being balanced like that in equilibrium.</s>
 <s id="48">It's susceptible to motion by the air currents.</s>
 <s id="49">This is another species of work that I do.</s>
 <p id="p50">
  <s id="50.1">These are these arrays.</s>
  <s id="50.2">These spheres are all suspended, but they have magnets horizontally in them that make them all like compasses.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="51">So all the red sides, for example, face one direction: south.</s>
 <s id="52">And the blue side, the compliment, faces the other way.</s>
 <s id="53">So as you turn around you're seeing different colors.</s>
 <s id="54">This is based on the structure of a diamond.</s>
 <s id="55">It was a diamond cell structure was the point of departure.</s>
 <s id="56">And then there were kind of large spaces in the hollows between the atoms.</s>
 <s id="57">And so I placed one more element of each one of them.</s>
 <s id="58">These were white spheres.</s>
 <s id="59">Then I had video projectors that were projecting intermittently onto the spheres.</s>
 <s id="60">So they would catch parts of the images, and make sort of three-dimensional color volumes, as you walk through it, through the object.</s>
 <s id="61">This is something I did of a tactile communication system.</s>
 <s id="62">It was the idea of isolating the tactile component of sculpture, and then putting it into a communication system.</s>
 <s id="63">This is an idea of moving a sculpture, a ball, that would be directed around the room by a computer.</s>
 <s id="64">This is a clock I designed.</s>
 <s id="65">It has Buckminster Fuller's Dymaxion Map edited here.</s>
 <s id="66">It turns once per day in synchrony with the Earth.</s>
 <s id="67">And then, this is like projects that are harder to build.</s>
 <s id="68">(Laughter) This has a diamond-bottomed lake.</s>
 <s id="69">So it's a floating island with water, fresh water, that can fly from place to place.</s>
 <s id="70">This would be grown, I suppose, with nanotechnology in the future sometime.</s>
 <s id="71">In the course of doing my work I sort of have a broad range of interests.</s>
 <s id="72">And some of it is just the idea of creating media -- media as a sculpture, something that would keep the sculpture fresh and ever-changing, by just creating the media that the sculpture is made of.</s>
 <s id="73">And I had a lot of -- always interested in the concept of a crystal ball.</s>
 <s id="74">And the idea that you could see things inside of a crystal ball and predict the future -- or a television set, where it's sort of like a magic box where anything can appear.</s>
 <s id="75">I had thought about, a long time ago, in the late '60s -- when I was just starting out, I was under the influence of thinking about Buckminster Fuller's grand project for an electric globe across from the United Nations -- and other things that were happening, the space program at that time, and Whole Earth Catalog, things like that.</s>
 <s id="76">I was thinking about mass produced spherical television sets that could be linked to orbiting camera satellites.</s>
 <s id="77">So if we could roll the next film here.</s>
 <s id="78">This has evolved over the years in a lot of different iterations.</s>
 <s id="79">But this the current version of it, is a flying airship that is about 35 meters in diameter, about 110 feet in diameter.</s>
 <s id="80">The whole surface of it is covered with 60 million diodes, red, blue, and green, that allow you to have a high-resolution picture, visible in daylight.</s>
 <s id="81">I came with a plan.</s>
 <s id="82">I brought it to Paul MacCready's company AeroVironment to do a feasibility study, and they analyzed it, and came up with a lot of innovative ideas about how to propel it.</s>
 <s id="83">So we have a physical plan of how to make this actually happen.</s>
 <s id="84">This is the control room inside of the ship.</s>
 <s id="85">The idea of this air genie is, it's something that can just transform and become anything.</s>
 <s id="86">It's like a traveling show.</s>
 <p id="p87">
  <s id="87.1">It has speakers on it.</s>
  <s id="87.2">And it has cameras over the surface of it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="88">So it can see its environment, and then it can mimic its environment and disappear.</s>
 <s id="89">Here the legs are retracting.</s>
 <s id="90">The cabin is open or closed, as you like.</s>
 <s id="91">It weighs about 20 tons.</s>
 <s id="92">It has on-board generators.</s>
 <s id="93">It can generate about a million kilowatts, in order to be bright enough to be visible in daylight.</s>
 <s id="94">The idea of it is to make a kind of a traveling show.</s>
 <s id="95">It really would be dedicated to the arts and to interacting.</s>
 <s id="96">There would be on board a crew of artists, musicians, that would allow the thing to become actually kind of a conscious object that would respond to the moment, and to interact as an entity that was aware, that could communicate.</s>
 <s id="97">It's completely silent and nonpolluting.</s>
 <s id="98">It has electric motors with a novel propulsion system.</s>
 <s id="99">It could be interacted with large crowds in different ways.</s>
 <s id="100">Primarily I would be interested in how it would interact with, say, going to a college campus, and then being used as a way of talking about the earth sciences, the world, the situation of the globe.</s>
 <s id="101">The default image on the object would probably be a high-resolution Earth image.</s>
 <s id="102">But then one could interact with that and show plate tectonics or global warming issues, or migrations -- all of the things that we're concerned with today.</s>
 <s id="103">And then at night the idea is that it would be used as kind of a rave situation, where the people could cut loose, and the music and the lights, and everything.</s>
 <s id="104">So it could land in a park, for example.</s>
 <s id="105">Or this could represent a college green.</s>
 <s id="106">And then it would have a corresponding website that would show the itinerary of this.</s>
 <s id="107">And so interacting with the same kind of imagery.</s>
 <s id="108">It would also be able to be an open code, so people could interact with it.</s>
 <s id="109">It would be forum for people's ideas about what they would like to see on a giant screen of this type.</s>
 <s id="110">So that's pretty much it.</s>
 <p id="p111">
  <s id="111.1">Okay.</s>
  <s id="111.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="112">(Applause)</s>
</text>
