<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">What's the worst bug on the planet?</s>
 <s id="2">You might vote for the horsefly or perhaps the wasp, but for many people, the worst offender is by far the mosquito.</s>
 <s id="3">The buzzing, the biting, the itching, the mosquito is one of the most commonly detested pests in the world.</s>
 <s id="4">In Alaska, swarms of mosquitos can get so thick that they actually asphyxiate caribou.</s>
 <s id="5">And mosquito-borne diseases kill millions of people every year.</s>
 <s id="6">The scourge that is the mosquito isn't new.</s>
 <s id="7">Mosquitoes have been around for over a hundred million years and over that time have coevolved with all sorts of species, including our own.</s>
 <s id="8">There are actually thousands of species of mosquitos in the world, but they all share one insidious quality: they suck blood, and they're really, really good at sucking blood.</s>
 <s id="9">Here's how they do it.</s>
 <s id="10">After landing, a mosquito will slather some saliva onto the victim's skin, which works like an antiseptic, numbing the spot so we don't notice their attack.</s>
 <s id="11">This is what causes the itchy, red bumps, by the way.</s>
 <s id="12">Then the bug will use its serrated mandibles to carve a little hole in your skin, allowing it to probe around with its proboscis, searching for a blood vessel.</s>
 <s id="13">When it hits one, the lucky parasite can suck two to three times its weight in blood.</s>
 <s id="14">Turns out we don't really like that too much.</s>
 <s id="15">In fact, humans hate mosquitos so much that we spend billions of dollars worldwide to keep them away from us -- from citronella candles to bug sprays to heavy-duty agricultural pesticides.</s>
 <s id="16">But it's not just that mosquitos are annoying, they're also deadly.</s>
 <s id="17">Mosquitos can transmit everything from malaria to yellow fever to West Nile virus to dengue.</s>
 <s id="18">Over a million people worldwide die every year from mosquito-borne diseases, and that's just people.</s>
 <s id="19">Horses, dogs, cats, they can all get diseases from mosquitoes too.</s>
 <s id="20">So, if these bugs are so dastardly, why don't we just get rid of them?</s>
 <s id="21">We are humans after all, and we're pretty good at getting rid of species.</s>
 <s id="22">Well, it's not quite so simple.</s>
 <s id="23">Getting rid of the mosquito removes a food source for lots of organisms, like frogs and fish and birds.</s>
 <s id="24">Without them, plants would lose a pollinator.</s>
 <s id="25">But some scientists say that mosquitos aren't actually all that important.</s>
 <s id="26">If we got rid of them, they argue, another species would simply take their place and we'd probably have far fewer deaths from malaria.</s>
 <s id="27">The problem is that nobody knows what would happen if we killed off all the mosquitos.</s>
 <s id="28">Something better might take their spot or perhaps something even worse.</s>
 <s id="29">The question is, are we willing to take that risk?</s>
 <s id="30">(Buzzing)</s>
</text>
