<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm an Iranian-American Muslim female, like all of you.</s>
 <s id="2">And I'm also a social justice comedian, something that I insist is an actual job.</s>
 <s id="3">To explain what that is, let me tell you how I got here.</s>
 <s id="4">I've performed all over the country.</s>
 <s id="5">And let me tell you, America is majestic, right?</s>
 <s id="6">It's got breathtaking nature, waffle houses and diabetes as far as the eye can see.</s>
 <s id="7">It is really something.</s>
 <s id="8">Now, the American population can be broken up into three main categories: there's mostly wonderful people, haters and Florida.</s>
 <s id="9">(Laughter) Besides Florida, the most troubling category here are the Haters.</s>
 <s id="10">They are a minority, but they overcompensate by being extra loud.</s>
 <s id="11">They have the Napoleon complex of demographics, and yes, some of the men do wear heels.</s>
 <s id="12">As a social justice comedian, it's my goal to convert these haters, because they hate a lot of things, which leads to negative outcomes, like racism, violence and Ted Nugent.</s>
 <s id="13">This is not an exhaustive list; I'm probably missing 3-7 items.</s>
 <s id="14">But the point is, we have to reckon with the haters.</s>
 <s id="15">But there's variance within this group and it's not efficient to go after all of them, right?</s>
 <s id="16">So what I've done is created a highly scientific Taxonomy of Haters.</s>
 <s id="17">I basically took all of the haters, I put them in a petri dish, like a scientist, and this is what I found.</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) First off, we have the trolls.</s>
 <s id="19">These are your garden-variety digital haters.</s>
 <s id="20">They're the people who quit their jobs so they can post on YouTube videos all day long.</s>
 <s id="21">There's also the drive-by haters.</s>
 <s id="22">Now, these people will be at a stoplight, they'll wait for the light to turn green and when it does, they yell, "Go back to your own country!"</s>
 <s id="23">Now back in the day, they would've actually gotten out of their cars and hated you to your face.</s>
 <s id="24">But they just don't make them like they used to -- which is another sign of the decline in America.</s>
 <s id="25">(Laughter) The next category is the mission-oriented-bigot- whose-group-affiliation- gives-them-cover-for-hating hater.</s>
 <s id="26">These guys like to hate via a seemingly nice organization, like a church or a nonprofit, and they oftentimes like to speak in an old-timey voice.</s>
 <s id="27">But the group I'm most interested in is the swing hater.</s>
 <s id="28">The swing hater is sister to the swing voter -- they just can't decide!</s>
 <s id="29">They're like ideological sluts who move from hating to not hating.</s>
 <s id="30">And they do it because they don't have enough information.</s>
 <s id="31">This is the group I like to target with social justice comedy.</s>
 <s id="32">Why comedy?</s>
 <s id="33">Because on a scale of comedy to brochure, the average American prefers comedy, as you can see from this graph.</s>
 <s id="34">(Laughter) Comedy is very popular.</s>
 <s id="35">And by the way, this is a mathematically accurate graph, generated from fake numbers.</s>
 <s id="36">(Laughter) Now, the question is: Why does social justice comedy work?</s>
 <s id="37">Because, first off, it makes you laugh.</s>
 <s id="38">And when you're laughing, you enter into a state of openness.</s>
 <s id="39">And in that moment of openness, a good social justice comedian can stick in a whole bunch of information, and if they're really skilled, a rectal exam.</s>
 <s id="40">(Laughter) Here are some ground rules for social justice comedy: first off, it's not partisan.</s>
 <s id="41">This isn't political comedy, this is about justice, and no one is against justice.</s>
 <s id="42">Two, it's inviting and warm, it makes you feel like you're sitting inside of a burrito.</s>
 <s id="43">Three, it's funny but sneaky, like you could be hearing an interesting treatise on income inequality, that's encased in a really sophisticated poop joke.</s>
 <s id="44">(Laughter) Here's how I see social justice comedy working.</s>
 <s id="45">A few years ago, I rounded up a bunch of Muslim-American comedians -- in a non-violent way -- (Laughter) And we went around the country to places like Alabama, Arizona, Tennessee, Georgia -- places where they love the Muzzies -- and we did stand-up shows.</s>
 <s id="46">We called the tour "The Muslims Are Coming!"</s>
 <s id="47">(Laughter) We turned this into a movie, and then after the movie came out, a known hate group spent 300,000 dollars on an anti-Muslim poster campaign with the MTA -- that's the New York City subway system.</s>
 <s id="48">Now, the posters were truly offensive, not to mentioned poorly designed -- I mean, if you're going to be bigoted, you might as well use a better font.</s>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) But we decided, why not launch our own poster campaign that says nice things about Muslims, while promoting the movie.</s>
 <s id="50">So myself and fellow comedian Dean Obeidallah decided to launch the fighting-bigotry- with-delightful-posters campaign.</s>
 <s id="51">We raised the money, worked with the MTA for over 5 months, got the posters approved, and two days after they were supposed to go up, the MTA decided to ban the posters, citing political content.</s>
 <s id="52">Let's take a look at a couple of those posters.</s>
 <s id="53">Here's one.</s>
 <s id="54">Facts about Muslims: Muslims invented the concept of a hospital.</s>
 <s id="55">OK.</s>
 <s id="56">Fact: Grown-up Muslims can do more push-ups than baby Muslims.</s>
 <s id="57">(Laughter) Fact: Muslims invented Justin Timberlake.</s>
 <s id="58">(Laughter) Let's take a look at another one.</s>
 <s id="59">The ugly truth about Muslims: they have great frittata recipes.</s>
 <s id="60">Now clearly, frittatas are considered political by the MTA.</s>
 <s id="61">Either that, or the mere mention of Muslims in a positive light was considered political -- but it isn't.</s>
 <s id="62">It's about justice.</s>
 <s id="63">So we decided to change our fighting-bigortry- with-delightful-posters campaign and turn it into the fighting-bigotry- with-a-delightful-lawsuit campaign.</s>
 <s id="64">(Laughter) So basically, what I'm saying is a couple of dirt-bag comedians took on a major New York City agency and the comedians won.</s>
 <s id="65">(Applause and cheers) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="66">Victory was a very weird feeling.</s>
 <s id="67">I was like, "Is this what blonde girls feel like all the time?</s>
 <s id="68">'Cause this is amazing!"</s>
 <s id="69">(Laughter) Here's another example.</s>
 <s id="70">I'm asked everywhere I go: "Why don't Muslims denounce terrorism?"</s>
 <p id="p71">
  <s id="71.1">We do.</s>
  <s id="71.2">But OK, I'll take the bait.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="72">So I decided to launch thedailydenouncer.com.</s>
 <s id="73">It's a website that denounces terrorism every day of the week, while taking the weekends off.</s>
 <s id="74">Let's take a look at an example.</s>
 <p id="p75">
  <s id="75.1">They generally appear as single-panel cartoons, "I denounce terrorism!</s>
  <s id="75.2">I also denounce people who never fill the paper tray!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="76">The point of the website is that it denounces terrorism while recognizing that it's ridiculous that we have to constantly denounce terrorism.</s>
 <s id="77">But if bigotry isn't your thing, social justice comedy is useful for all sorts of issues.</s>
 <s id="78">For example, myself and fellow comedian Lee Camp went to the Cayman Islands to investigate offshore banking.</s>
 <s id="79">Now, the United States loses something like 300 billion dollars a year in these offshore tax havens.</s>
 <s id="80">Not to brag, but at the end of every month, I have something like 5-15 dollars in disposable income.</s>
 <s id="81">So we walked into these banks in the Cayman Islands and asked if we could open up a bank account with eight dollars and 27 cents.</s>
 <s id="82">(Laughter) The bank managers would indulge us for 30-45 seconds before calling security.</s>
 <s id="83">Security would come out, brandish their weapons, and then we would squeal with fear and run away, because -- and this is the last rule of social justice comedy -- sometimes it makes you want to take a dump in your pants.</s>
 <s id="84">Most of my work is meant to be fun.</s>
 <s id="85">It's meant to generate a connection and laughter.</s>
 <s id="86">But yes, sometimes I get run off the grounds by security.</s>
 <s id="87">Sometimes I get mean tweets and hate mail.</s>
 <s id="88">Sometimes I get voice mails saying that if I continue telling my jokes, they'll kill me and they'll kill my family.</s>
 <s id="89">And those death threats are definitely not funny.</s>
 <s id="90">But despite the occasional danger, I still think that social justice comedy is one of our best weapons.</s>
 <s id="91">I mean, we've tried a lot of approaches to social justice, like war and competitive ice dancing.</s>
 <s id="92">But still, a lot of things are still kind of awful.</s>
 <s id="93">So I think it's time we try and tell a really good poop joke.</s>
 <s id="94">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="95">(Applause)</s>
</text>
