<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">This may sound strange, but I'm a big fan of the concrete block.</s>
 <s id="2">The first concrete blocks were manufactured in 1868 with a very simple idea: modules made of cement of a fixed measurement that fit together.</s>
 <s id="3">Very quickly concrete blocks became the most-used construction unit in the world.</s>
 <s id="4">They enabled us to to build things that were larger than us, buildings, bridges, one brick at a time.</s>
 <s id="5">Essentially concrete blocks had become the building block of our time.</s>
 <s id="6">Almost a hundred years later in 1947, LEGO came up with this.</s>
 <s id="7">It was called the Automatic Binding Brick.</s>
 <s id="8">And in a few short years, LEGO bricks took place in every household.</s>
 <s id="9">It's estimated that over 400 billion bricks have been produced -- or 75 bricks for every person on the planet.</s>
 <s id="10">You don't have to be an engineer to make beautiful houses, beautiful bridges, beautiful buildings.</s>
 <s id="11">LEGO made it accessible.</s>
 <s id="12">LEGO has essentially taken the concrete block, the building block of the world, and made it into the building block of our imagination.</s>
 <s id="13">Meanwhile the exact same year, at Bell Labs the next revolution was about to be announced, the next building block.</s>
 <s id="14">The transistor was a small plastic unit that would take us from a world of static bricks piled on top of each other to a world where everything was interactive.</s>
 <s id="15">Like the concrete block, the transistor allows you to build much larger, more complex circuits, one brick at a time.</s>
 <s id="16">But there's a main difference: The transistor was only for experts.</s>
 <s id="17">I personally don't accept this, that the building block of our time is reserved for experts, so I decided to change that.</s>
 <s id="18">Eight years ago when I was at the Media Lab, I started exploring this idea of how to put the power of engineers in the hands of artists and designers.</s>
 <s id="19">A few years ago I started developing littleBits.</s>
 <s id="20">Let me show you how they work.</s>
 <s id="21">LittleBits are electronic modules with each one specific function.</s>
 <s id="22">They're pre-engineered to be light, sound, motors and sensors.</s>
 <s id="23">And the best part about it is they snap together with magnets.</s>
 <s id="24">So you can't put them the wrong way.</s>
 <s id="25">The bricks are color-coded.</s>
 <s id="26">Green is output, blue is power, pink is input and orange is wire.</s>
 <s id="27">So all you need to do is snap a blue to a green and very quickly you can start making larger circuits.</s>
 <s id="28">You put a blue to a green, you can make light.</s>
 <s id="29">You can put a knob in between and now you've made a little dimmer.</s>
 <s id="30">Switch out the knob for a pulse module, which is here, and now you've made a little blinker.</s>
 <s id="31">Add this buzzer for some extra punch and you've created a noise machine.</s>
 <s id="32">I'm going to stop that.</s>
 <s id="33">So beyond simple play, littleBits are actually pretty powerful.</s>
 <s id="34">Instead of having to program, to wire, to solder, littleBits allow you to program using very simple intuitive gestures.</s>
 <s id="35">So to make this blink faster or slower, you would just turn this knob and basically make it pulse faster or slower.</s>
 <s id="36">The idea behind littleBits is that it's a growing library.</s>
 <s id="37">We want to make every single interaction in the world into a ready-to-use brick.</s>
 <s id="38">Lights, sounds, solar panels, motors -- everything should be accessible.</s>
 <s id="39">We've been giving littleBits to kids and seeing them play with them.</s>
 <s id="40">And it's been an incredible experience.</s>
 <s id="41">The nicest thing is how they start to understand the electronics around them from everyday that they don't learn at schools.</s>
 <s id="42">For example, how a nightlight works, or why an elevator door stays open, or how an iPod responds to touch.</s>
 <s id="43">We've also been taking littleBits to design schools.</s>
 <s id="44">So for example, we've had designers with no experience with electronics whatsoever start to play with littleBits as a material.</s>
 <s id="45">Here you see, with felt and paper water bottles, we have Geordie making ...</s>
 <s id="46">(Clanging) (Buzzing) A few weeks ago we took littleBits to RISD and gave them to some designers with no experience in engineering whatsoever -- just cardboard, wood and paper -- and told them "Make something."</s>
 <s id="47">Here's an example of a project they made, a motion-activated confetti canon ball.</s>
 <s id="48">(Laughter) But wait, this is actually my favorite project.</s>
 <s id="49">It's a lobster made of playdough that's afraid of the dark.</s>
 <s id="50">(Laughter) To these non-engineers, littleBits became another material, electronics became just another material.</s>
 <s id="51">And we want to make this material accessible to everyone.</s>
 <s id="52">So littleBits is open-source.</s>
 <s id="53">You can go on the website, download all the design files, make them yourself.</s>
 <s id="54">We want to encourage a world of creators, of inventors, of contributors, because this world that we live in, this interactive world, is ours.</s>
 <s id="55">So go ahead and start inventing.</s>
 <s id="56">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="57">(Applause)</s>
</text>
