<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In medieval times, alchemists tried to achieve the seemingly impossible.</s>
 <s id="2">They wanted to transform lowly lead into gleaming gold.</s>
 <s id="3">History portrays these people as aged eccentrics, but if only they'd known that their dreams were actually achievable.</s>
 <s id="4">Indeed, today we can manufacture gold on Earth thanks to modern inventions that those medieval alchemists missed by a few centuries.</s>
 <s id="5">But to understand how this precious metal became embedded in our planet to start with, we have to gaze upwards at the stars.</s>
 <s id="6">Gold is extraterrestrial.</s>
 <s id="7">Instead of arising from the planet's rocky crust, it was actually cooked up in space and is present on Earth because of cataclysmic stellar explosions called supernovae.</s>
 <s id="8">Stars are mostly made up of hydrogen, the simplest and lightest element.</s>
 <s id="9">The enormous gravitational pressure of so much material compresses and triggers nuclear fusion in the star's core.</s>
 <s id="10">This process releases energy from the hydrogen, making the star shine.</s>
 <s id="11">Over many millions of years, fusion transforms hydrogen into heavier elements: helium, carbon, and oxygen, burning subsequent elements faster and faster to reach iron and nickel.</s>
 <s id="12">However, at that point nuclear fusion no longer releases enough energy, and the pressure from the core peters out.</s>
 <s id="13">The outer layers collapse into the center, and bouncing back from this sudden injection of energy, the star explodes forming a supernova.</s>
 <s id="14">The extreme pressure of a collapsing star is so high, that subatomic protons and electrons are forced together in the core, forming neutrons.</s>
 <s id="15">Neutrons have no repelling electric charge so they're easily captured by the iron group elements.</s>
 <s id="16">Multiple neutron captures enable the formation of heavier elements that a star under normal circumstances can't form, from silver to gold, past lead and on to uranium.</s>
 <s id="17">In extreme contrast to the million year transformation of hydrogen to helium, the creation of the heaviest elements in a supernova takes place in only seconds.</s>
 <s id="18">But what becomes of the gold after the explosion?</s>
 <s id="19">The expanding supernova shockwave propels its elemental debris through the interstellar medium, triggering a swirling dance of gas and dust that condenses into new stars and planets.</s>
 <s id="20">Earth's gold was likely delivered this way before being kneaded into veins by geothermal activity.</s>
 <s id="21">Billions of years later, we now extract this precious product by mining it, an expensive process that's compounded by gold's rarity.</s>
 <s id="22">In fact, all of the gold that we've mined in history could be piled into just three Olympic-size swimming pools, although this represents a lot of mass because gold is about 20 times denser than water.</s>
 <s id="23">So, can we produce more of this coveted commodity?</s>
 <s id="24">Actually, yes.</s>
 <s id="25">Using particle accelerators, we can mimic the complex nuclear reactions that create gold in stars.</s>
 <s id="26">But these machines can only construct gold atom by atom.</s>
 <s id="27">So it would take almost the age of the universe to produce one gram at a cost vastly exceeding the current value of gold.</s>
 <s id="28">So that's not a very good solution.</s>
 <s id="29">But if we were to reach a hypothetical point where we'd mined all of the Earth's buried gold, there are other places we could look.</s>
 <s id="30">The ocean holds an estimated 20 million tons of dissolved gold but at extremely miniscule concentrations making its recovery too costly at present.</s>
 <s id="31">Perhaps one day, we'll see gold rushes to tap the mineral wealth of the other planets of our solar system.</s>
 <s id="32">And who knows?</s>
 <s id="33">Maybe some future supernova will occur close enough to shower us with its treasure and hopefully not eradicate all life on Earth in the process.</s>
</text>
