<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">We are going to talk today about the sequel of "Inconvenient Truth."</s>
 <s id="2">It's time again to talk about "Inconvenient Truth," a truth that everyone is concerned about, but nobody is willing to talk about.</s>
 <s id="3">Somebody has to take the lead, and I decided to do it.</s>
 <s id="4">If you are scared by global warming, wait until we learn about local warming.</s>
 <s id="5">We will talk today about local warming.</s>
 <s id="6">Important health message: blogging may be hazardous to your health, especially if you are a male.</s>
 <s id="7">This message is given as a public service.</s>
 <p id="p8">
  <s id="8.1">Blogging affects your posture.</s>
  <s id="8.2">We start with the posture.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="9">This is the posture of ladies who are not blogging; this is the posture of ladies who are blogging.</s>
 <s id="10">(Laughter) This is the natural posture of a man sitting, squatting for ventilation purposes.</s>
 <s id="11">(Laughter) And this is the natural posture of a standing man, and I think this picture inspired Chris to insert me into the lateral thinking session.</s>
 <s id="12">This is male blogging posture sitting, and the result is, "For greater comfort, men naturally sit with their legs farther apart than women, when working on laptop.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">However, they will adopt a less natural posture in order to balance it on their laps, which resulted in a significant rise of body heat between their thighs."</s>
  <s id="13.2">This is the issue of local warming.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">(Laughter) This is a very serious newspaper; it's Times of England -- very serious.</s>
  <s id="14.2">This is a very -- (Laughter) -- gentlemen and ladies, be serious.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="15">This is a very serious research, that you should read the underline.</s>
 <s id="16">And be careful, your genes are in danger.</s>
 <s id="17">Will geeks become endangered species?</s>
 <s id="18">The fact: population growth in countries with high laptop -- (Laughter) I need Hans Rosling to give me a graph.</s>
 <s id="19">(Applause) Global warming fun.</s>
 <s id="20">(Laughter) But let's keep things in proportion.</s>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">How to take care in five easy steps: first of all, you can use natural ventilation.</s>
  <s id="21.2">You can use body breath.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="22">You should stay cool with the appropriate clothing.</s>
 <s id="23">You should care about your posture -- this is not right.</s>
 <s id="24">Can you extract from Chris another minute and a half for me, because I have a video I have to show you.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">(Applause) You are great.</s>
  <s id="25.2">This is the correct posture.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">Another benefit of Wi-Fi, we learned yesterday about the benefits of Wi-Fi.</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">Wi-Fi enables you to avoid the processor.</s>
  <s id="27.2">And there are some enhanced protection measures, which I would like to share with you, and I would like, in a minute, to thank Philips for helping.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="28">This is a research which was done in '86, but it's still valid.</s>
 <s id="29">Scrotal temperature reflects intratesticular temperature and is lowered by shaving.</s>
 <s id="30">By the way, I must admit, my English is not so good, I didn't know what is scrotal; I understand it's a scrotum.</s>
 <s id="31">I guess in plural it's scrotal, like medium and media.</s>
 <s id="32">Digital scrotum, digital media.</s>
 <s id="33">And only last year I recognized that I'm a proud scrotum owner.</s>
 <s id="34">(Laughter) And this research is being precipitated by the U.S. government, so you can see that your tax man is working for good causes.</s>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">Video: Man: The Philips Bodygroom has a sleek, ergonomic design for a safe and easy way to trim those scruffy underarm hairs, the untidy curls on and around your [bleep], as well as the hard to reach locks on the underside of your [bleep] and [bleep].</s>
  <s id="35.2">Once you use the Bodygroom, the world looks different.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">And so does your [bleep].</s>
  <s id="36.2">These days, with a hair-free back, well-groomed shoulders and an extra optical inch on my [bleep], well, let's just say life has gotten pretty darn cozy.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">Yossi Vardi: This is one of the most popular viral advertisement of last year, known as the optical inch by Philips.</s>
  <s id="37.2">Let's applaud Philips -- (Applause) -- for this gesture for humanity.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p38">
  <s id="38.1">And this is how they are promoting the product.</s>
  <s id="38.2">This is -- I didn't touch it, this is original.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">Laptop use to solve overpopulation.</s>
  <s id="39.2">And if everything failed, there are some secondary uses.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">And then our next talk, our next TED if you invite me will be why you should not carry a cell phone in your pocket.</s>
 <s id="41">And this is what the young generation says.</s>
 <s id="42">(Applause) And I just want to show you that I'm not just preaching, but I also practice.</s>
 <s id="43">(Laughter) 4 am in the morning.</s>
 <s id="44">(Laughter) You cannot use this picture.</s>
 <s id="45">(Applause) Now, I have some mini TED Prizes, this is the Philips Bodygroom, one for our leader.</s>
 <s id="46">(Applause) Anybody feels threatened, anybody really need it?</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">(Laughter) Any lady, any lady?</s>
  <s id="47.2">Thank you very much.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="48">(Applause)</s>
</text>
