<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In the 1600s the Dutch East India Company employed hundreds of ships to trade gold, porcelain, spices, and silks around the globe.</s>
 <s id="2">But running this massive operation wasn’t cheap.</s>
 <s id="3">In order to fund their expensive voyages, the company turned to private citizens– individuals who could invest money to support the trip in exchange for a share of the ship’s profits.</s>
 <s id="4">This practice allowed the company to afford even grander voyages, increasing profits for both themselves and their savvy investors.</s>
 <s id="5">Selling these shares in coffee houses and shipping ports across the continent, the Dutch East India Company unknowingly invented the world’s first stock market.</s>
 <s id="6">Since then, companies have been collecting funds from willing investors to support all kinds of businesses.</s>
 <s id="7">And today, the stock market has schools, careers, and even whole television channels dedicated to understanding it.</s>
 <s id="8">But the modern stock market is significantly more complicated than its original incarnation.</s>
 <s id="9">So how do companies and investors use the market today?</s>
 <s id="10">Let’s imagine a new coffee company that decides to launch on the market.</s>
 <s id="11">First, the company will advertise itself to big investors.</s>
 <s id="12">If they think the company is a good idea, they get the first crack at investing, and then sponsor the company’s initial public offering, or IPO.</s>
 <s id="13">This launches the company onto the official public market, where any company or individual who believes the business could be profitable might buy a stock.</s>
 <s id="14">Buying stocks makes those investors partial owners in the business.</s>
 <s id="15">Their investment helps the company to grow, and as it becomes more successful, more buyers may see potential and start buying stocks.</s>
 <s id="16">As demand for those stocks increases, so does their price, increasing the cost for prospective buyers, and raising the value of the company's stocks people already own.</s>
 <s id="17">For the company, this increased interest helps fund new initiatives, and also boosts its overall market value by showing how many people are willing to invest in their idea.</s>
 <s id="18">However, if for some reason a company starts to seem less profitable the reverse can also happen.</s>
 <s id="19">If investors think their stock value is going to decline, they’ll sell their stocks with the hopes of making a profit before the company loses more value.</s>
 <s id="20">As stocks are sold and demand for the stock goes down, the stock price falls, and with it, the company’s market value.</s>
 <s id="21">This can leave investors with big losses– unless the company starts to look profitable again.</s>
 <s id="22">This see-saw of supply and demand is influenced by many factors.</s>
 <s id="23">Companies are under the unavoidable influence of market forces– such as the fluctuating price of materials, changes in production technology, and the shifting costs of labor.</s>
 <s id="24">Investors may be worried about changes in leadership, bad publicity, or larger factors like new laws and trade policies.</s>
 <s id="25">And of course, plenty of investors are simply ready to sell valuable stocks and pursue personal interests.</s>
 <s id="26">All these variables cause day-to-day noise in the market, which can make companies appear more or less successful.</s>
 <s id="27">And in the stock market, appearing to lose value often leads to losing investors, and in turn, losing actual value.</s>
 <s id="28">Human confidence in the market has the power to trigger everything from economic booms to financial crises.</s>
 <s id="29">And this difficult-to-track variable is why most professionals promote reliable long term investing over trying to make quick cash.</s>
 <s id="30">However, experts are constantly building tools in efforts to increase their chances of success in this highly unpredictable system.</s>
 <s id="31">But the stock market is not just for the rich and powerful.</s>
 <s id="32">With the dawn of the Internet, everyday investors can buy stocks in many of the exact same ways a large investor would.</s>
 <s id="33">And as more people educate themselves about this complex system they too can trade stocks, support the businesses they believe in, and pursue their financial goals.</s>
 <s id="34">The first step is getting invested.</s>
</text>
