<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So I'm a neurosurgeon.</s>
 <s id="2">And like most of my colleagues, I have to deal, every day, with human tragedies.</s>
 <s id="3">I realize how your life can change from one second to the other after a major stroke or after a car accident.</s>
 <s id="4">And what is very frustrating for us neurosurgeons is to realize that unlike other organs of the body, the brain has very little ability for self-repair.</s>
 <s id="5">And after a major injury of your central nervous system, the patients often remain with a severe handicap.</s>
 <s id="6">And that's probably the reason why I've chosen to be a functional neurosurgeon.</s>
 <s id="7">What is a functional neurosurgeon?</s>
 <s id="8">It's a doctor who is trying to improve a neurological function through different surgical strategies.</s>
 <s id="9">You've certainly heard of one of the famous ones called deep brain stimulation, where you implant an electrode in the depths of the brain in order to modulate a circuit of neurons to improve a neurological function.</s>
 <s id="10">It's really an amazing technology in that it has improved the destiny of patients with Parkinson's disease, with severe tremor, with severe pain.</s>
 <s id="11">However, neuromodulation does not mean neuro-repair.</s>
 <s id="12">And the dream of functional neurosurgeons is to repair the brain.</s>
 <s id="13">I think that we are approaching this dream.</s>
 <s id="14">And I would like to show you that we are very close to this.</s>
 <s id="15">And that with a little bit of help, the brain is able to help itself.</s>
 <s id="16">So the story started 15 years ago.</s>
 <s id="17">At that time, I was a chief resident working days and nights in the emergency room.</s>
 <s id="18">I often had to take care of patients with head trauma.</s>
 <s id="19">You have to imagine that when a patient comes in with a severe head trauma, his brain is swelling and he's increasing his intracranial pressure.</s>
 <s id="20">And in order to save his life, you have to decrease this intracranial pressure.</s>
 <s id="21">And to do that, you sometimes have to remove a piece of swollen brain.</s>
 <s id="22">So instead of throwing away these pieces of swollen brain, we decided with Jean-François Brunet, who is a colleague of mine, a biologist, to study them.</s>
 <s id="23">What do I mean by that?</s>
 <s id="24">We wanted to grow cells from these pieces of tissue.</s>
 <s id="25">It's not an easy task.</s>
 <s id="26">Growing cells from a piece of tissue is a bit the same as growing very small children out from their family.</s>
 <s id="27">So you need to find the right nutrients, the warmth, the humidity and all the nice environments to make them thrive.</s>
 <s id="28">So that's exactly what we had to do with these cells.</s>
 <s id="29">And after many attempts, Jean-François did it.</s>
 <s id="30">And that's what he saw under his microscope.</s>
 <s id="31">And that was, for us, a major surprise.</s>
 <s id="32">Why?</s>
 <s id="33">Because this looks exactly the same as a stem cell culture, with large green cells surrounding small, immature cells.</s>
 <s id="34">And you may remember from biology class that stem cells are immature cells, able to turn into any type of cell of the body.</s>
 <s id="35">The adult brain has stem cells, but they're very rare and they're located in deep and small niches in the depths of the brain.</s>
 <s id="36">So it was surprising to get this kind of stem cell culture from the superficial part of swollen brain we had in the operating theater.</s>
 <s id="37">And there was another intriguing observation: Regular stem cells are very active cells -- cells that divide, divide, divide very quickly.</s>
 <s id="38">And they never die, they're immortal cells.</s>
 <s id="39">But these cells behave differently.</s>
 <s id="40">They divide slowly, and after a few weeks of culture, they even died.</s>
 <s id="41">So we were in front of a strange new cell population that looked like stem cells but behaved differently.</s>
 <s id="42">And it took us a long time to understand where they came from.</s>
 <s id="43">They come from these cells.</s>
 <s id="44">These blue and red cells are called doublecortin-positive cells.</s>
 <s id="45">All of you have them in your brain.</s>
 <s id="46">They represent four percent of your cortical brain cells.</s>
 <s id="47">They have a very important role during the development stage.</s>
 <s id="48">When you were fetuses, they helped your brain to fold itself.</s>
 <s id="49">But why do they stay in your head?</s>
 <s id="50">This, we don't know.</s>
 <s id="51">We think that they may participate in brain repair because we find them in higher concentration close to brain lesions.</s>
 <s id="52">But it's not so sure.</s>
 <s id="53">But there is one clear thing -- that from these cells, we got our stem cell culture.</s>
 <s id="54">And we were in front of a potential new source of cells to repair the brain.</s>
 <s id="55">And we had to prove this.</s>
 <s id="56">So to prove it, we decided to design an experimental paradigm.</s>
 <s id="57">The idea was to biopsy a piece of brain in a non-eloquent area of the brain, and then to culture the cells exactly the way Jean-François did it in his lab.</s>
 <s id="58">And then label them, to put color in them in order to be able to track them in the brain.</s>
 <s id="59">And the last step was to re-implant them in the same individual.</s>
 <s id="60">We call these autologous grafts -- autografts.</s>
 <s id="61">So the first question we had, "What will happen if we re-implant these cells in a normal brain, and what will happen if we re-implant the same cells in a lesioned brain?"</s>
 <s id="62">Thanks to the help of professor Eric Rouiller, we worked with monkeys.</s>
 <s id="63">So in the first-case scenario, we re-implanted the cells in the normal brain and what we saw is that they completely disappeared after a few weeks, as if they were taken from the brain, they go back home, the space is already busy, they are not needed there, so they disappear.</s>
 <s id="64">In the second-case scenario, we performed the lesion, we re-implanted exactly the same cells, and in this case, the cells remained -- and they became mature neurons.</s>
 <s id="65">And that's the image of what we could observe under the microscope.</s>
 <s id="66">Those are the cells that were re-implanted.</s>
 <s id="67">And the proof they carry, these little spots, those are the cells that we've labeled in vitro, when they were in culture.</s>
 <s id="68">But we could not stop here, of course.</s>
 <s id="69">Do these cells also help a monkey to recover after a lesion?</s>
 <s id="70">So for that, we trained monkeys to perform a manual dexterity task.</s>
 <s id="71">They had to retrieve food pellets from a tray.</s>
 <s id="72">They were very good at it.</s>
 <s id="73">And when they had reached a plateau of performance, we did a lesion in the motor cortex corresponding to the hand motion.</s>
 <s id="74">So the monkeys were plegic, they could not move their hand anymore.</s>
 <s id="75">And exactly the same as humans would do, they spontaneously recovered to a certain extent, exactly the same as after a stroke.</s>
 <s id="76">Patients are completely plegic, and then they try to recover due to a brain plasticity mechanism, they recover to a certain extent, exactly the same for the monkey.</s>
 <s id="77">So when we were sure that the monkey had reached his plateau of spontaneous recovery, we implanted his own cells.</s>
 <s id="78">So on the left side, you see the monkey that has spontaneously recovered.</s>
 <s id="79">He's at about 40 to 50 percent of his previous performance before the lesion.</s>
 <s id="80">He's not so accurate, not so quick.</s>
 <s id="81">And look now when we re-implant the cells: Two months after re-implantation, the same individual.</s>
 <s id="82">(Applause) It was also very exciting results for us, I tell you.</s>
 <s id="83">Since that time, we've understood much more about these cells.</s>
 <s id="84">We know that we can cryopreserve them, we can use them later on.</s>
 <s id="85">We know that we can apply them in other neuropathological models, like Parkinson's disease, for example.</s>
 <s id="86">But our dream is still to implant them in humans.</s>
 <s id="87">And I really hope that I'll be able to show you soon that the human brain is giving us the tools to repair itself.</s>
 <s id="88">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="89">(Applause) Bruno Giussani: Jocelyne, this is amazing, and I'm sure that right now, there are several dozen people in the audience, possibly even a majority, who are thinking, "I know somebody who can use this."</s>
 <s id="90">I do, in any case.</s>
 <s id="91">And of course the question is, what are the biggest obstacles before you can go into human clinical trials?</s>
 <p id="p92">
  <s id="92.1">Jocelyne Bloch: The biggest obstacles are regulations.</s>
  <s id="92.2">(Laughs) So, from these exciting results, you need to fill out about two kilograms of papers and forms to be able to go through these kind of trials.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="93">BG: Which is understandable, the brain is delicate, etc.</s>
 <s id="94">JB: Yes, it is, but it takes a long time and a lot of patience and almost a professional team to do it, you know?</s>
 <s id="95">BG: If you project yourself -- having done the research and having tried to get permission to start the trials, if you project yourself out in time, how many years before somebody gets into a hospital and this therapy is available?</s>
 <s id="96">JB: So, it's very difficult to say.</s>
 <s id="97">It depends, first, on the approval of the trial.</s>
 <s id="98">Will the regulation allow us to do it soon?</s>
 <s id="99">And then, you have to perform this kind of study in a small group of patients.</s>
 <s id="100">So it takes, already, a long time to select the patients, do the treatment and evaluate if it's useful to do this kind of treatment.</s>
 <s id="101">And then you have to deploy this to a multicentric trial.</s>
 <s id="102">You have to really prove first that it's useful before offering this treatment up for everybody.</s>
 <p id="p103">
  <s id="103.1">BG: And safe, of course.</s>
  <s id="103.2">JB: Of course.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="104">BG: Jocelyne, thank you for coming to TED and sharing this.</s>
 <s id="105">BG: Thank you.</s>
 <s id="106">(Applause)</s>
</text>
