<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Back home, my friends call me nicknames, such as "The Giant Clam Girl," "Clam Queen," or, "The Mother of Clams."</s>
 <s id="2">(Laughter) This is because every time I see them, I talk nonstop about giant clams all day, every day.</s>
 <s id="3">Giant clams are these massive and colorful shelled marine animals, the largest of its kind.</s>
 <s id="4">Just look at this shell.</s>
 <s id="5">The biggest recorded individual was four-and-a-half-feet long and weighed about 550 pounds.</s>
 <s id="6">That is almost as heavy as three baby elephants.</s>
 <s id="7">South Pacific legends once described giant clams as man-eaters that would lie in wait on the seabed to trap unsuspecting divers.</s>
 <s id="8">A story goes that a diver had lost his legs while trying to retrieve a pearl from a giant clam.</s>
 <s id="9">I thought, "Really?"</s>
 <s id="10">So out of curiosity, I did an experiment using myself as bait.</s>
 <s id="11">(Laughter) I carefully placed my hand into the clam's mouth and waited.</s>
 <s id="12">Hmm ...</s>
 <s id="13">I still have my hand.</s>
 <s id="14">It seems that these gentle giants would rather retreat and protect their fleshy bodies than feed on me.</s>
 <s id="15">So much for those killer clam myths!</s>
 <s id="16">Unfortunately, the reality is, we are the giant clams' biggest threat.</s>
 <s id="17">Considered a delicacy throughout the Western Pacific and Indian Oceans, giant clams have been traditionally fished as seafood.</s>
 <s id="18">Fishermen are particularly interested in their adductor muscles, which are organs that hold the two shells together like a hinge.</s>
 <s id="19">Just for their muscles, giant clams were almost hunted to extinction between the 1960s and 1980s.</s>
 <s id="20">Clamshells are also popular in the ornamental trade as jewelry and for display.</s>
 <s id="21">In the South China Sea, fishermen went out of their way to collect fossilized clamshells by digging through large areas of coral reefs.</s>
 <s id="22">These were later carved and sold as so-called "ivory handicrafts" in China.</s>
 <s id="23">Giant clams, dead or alive, are not safe from us.</s>
 <s id="24">It's a "clamity!"</s>
 <s id="25">(Laughter) (Applause) With the spotlight on more charismatic marine animals such as the whales and coral reefs, it is easy to forget that other marine life needs our help, too.</s>
 <s id="26">My fascination with giant clams got me started on conservation research to fill in the knowledge gaps on their ecology and behavior.</s>
 <s id="27">One of the discoveries that we made was that giant clams could walk across the seafloor.</s>
 <s id="28">Yes, you heard me right: they can walk.</s>
 <s id="29">To find out, we placed numerous baby clams on a grid.</s>
 <s id="30">Now watch what happens over 24 hours.</s>
 <s id="31">We think that walking is important for getting away from predators and finding mates for breeding.</s>
 <s id="32">While it can hard to imagine any movement in these enormous animals, giant clams up to 400 pounds can still walk, they just move slower.</s>
 <s id="33">During my PhD, I discovered more secrets about the giant clams.</s>
 <s id="34">But there was something missing in my work.</s>
 <s id="35">I found myself asking, "Why should people care about conserving giant clams?" -- other than myself, of course.</s>
 <s id="36">(Laughter) It turns out that giant clams have a giant impact on coral reefs.</s>
 <s id="37">These multitasking clams are reef builders, food factories, shelters for shrimps and crabs and water filters, all rolled into one.</s>
 <s id="38">In a nutshell, giant clams play a major contributing role as residents of their own reef home, and just having them around keeps the reef healthy.</s>
 <s id="39">And because they can live up to 100 years old, giant clams make vital indicators of coral reef health.</s>
 <s id="40">So when giant clams start to disappear from coral reefs, their absence can serve as an alarm bell for scientists to start paying attention, similar to the canary in a coal mine.</s>
 <s id="41">But giant clams are endangered.</s>
 <s id="42">The largest clam in the world is facing the threat of extinction, with more than 50 percent of the wild population severely depleted.</s>
 <s id="43">And the ecological benefits of having giant clams on coral reefs are likely to continue only if populations are healthy, making their conservation paramount.</s>
 <s id="44">So I stand here today to give a voice to the giant clams, because I care a whole lot for these amazing animals, and they deserve to be cared for.</s>
 <s id="45">It is time for the giant clams to step out of their shells, and show the world that they, too, can be the heroes of the oceans.</s>
 <s id="46">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="47">(Applause)</s>
</text>
