<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In 1925, Frida Kahlo was on her way home from school in Mexico City when the bus she was riding collided with a streetcar.</s>
 <s id="2">She suffered near-fatal injuries to her spine, pelvis and hips, and was bedridden for months afterward.</s>
 <s id="3">During her recovery, she had a special easel attached to her bed so she could practice painting techniques.</s>
 <s id="4">When she set to work, she began to paint the world according to her own singular vision.</s>
 <s id="5">Over the course of her life, she would establish herself as the creator and muse behind extraordinary art.</s>
 <s id="6">Though you may have met Kahlo's gaze before, her work provides an opportunity to see the world through her eyes.</s>
 <s id="7">She painted friends and family, still lives and spiritual scenes; but it was her mesmerizing self-portraits which first caught the world’s attention.</s>
 <s id="8">In an early work, "Self Portrait with Velvet Dress," the focus is on her strong brows, facial hair, long neck and formidable stare.</s>
 <s id="9">Such features remained, but Kahlo soon began to present herself in more unusual ways.</s>
 <s id="10">For example, "The Broken Column" uses symbolism, religious imagery and a ruptured landscape to reveal her physical and mental state.</s>
 <s id="11">In 1928, Kahlo started dating fellow painter Diego Rivera.</s>
 <s id="12">They became lifelong partners and cultivated an eccentric celebrity.</s>
 <s id="13">Together, they traveled the world and dedicated themselves to art, Communist politics and Mexican nationalism.</s>
 <s id="14">Kahlo and Rivera shared a deep affinity with Mexicanidad, a movement which celebrated indigenous culture after the Revolution.</s>
 <s id="15">In her daily life, Kahlo wore traditional Tehuana dress and immersed herself in native spirituality.</s>
 <s id="16">And in her work, she constantly referenced Mexican folk painting, incorporating its bright colors and references to death, religion and nature.</s>
 <s id="17">With her imagery of giant floating flowers, undulating landscapes, transplanted body parts and billowing clouds of demons, Kahlo has often been associated with Surrealism.</s>
 <s id="18">But while surrealists used dreamlike images to explore the unconscious mind, Kahlo used them to represent her physical body and life experiences.</s>
 <s id="19">Two of her most-explored experiences were her physical disabilities and her marriage.</s>
 <s id="20">As a result of the bus accident, she experienced life-long health complications and endured many hospitalizations.</s>
 <s id="21">She often contemplated the physical and psychological effects of disability in her work; painting herself in agony, recuperating from operations, or including objects such as her back brace and wheelchair.</s>
 <s id="22">Meanwhile, her relationship with Rivera was tempestuous, marked by infidelity on both sides.</s>
 <s id="23">At one point they even divorced, then remarried a year later.</s>
 <s id="24">During this period, she painted the double self-portrait "The Two Fridas," which speaks to the anguish of loss and a splintered sense of self.</s>
 <s id="25">The Frida to the left has a broken heart, which drips blood onto her old-fashioned Victorian dress.</s>
 <s id="26">She symbolizes a version of the artist who is wounded by the past– but is also connected by an artery to a second self.</s>
 <s id="27">This Frida is dressed in Tehuana attire– and although she remembers Diego with the tiny portrait in her hand, her heart remains intact.</s>
 <s id="28">Together, the two suggest a position caught between past and present, individuality and dependency.</s>
 <s id="29">Kahlo died in 1954 at the age of 47.</s>
 <s id="30">In the years after her death, she experienced a surge in popularity that has lasted to this day.</s>
 <s id="31">And although her image has proliferated, Kahlo’s body of work reminds us that there are no simple truths about the life, work and legacy of the woman behind the icon.</s>
 <s id="32">Rather, she put multiple versions of her reality on display– and provided us with a few entry-ways into the contents of her soul.</s>
</text>
