<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">OK, today we're going to talk about the mole.</s>
 <s id="2">Now, I know what you're thinking: "I know what a mole is, it's a small furry creature that digs holes in the ground and destroys gardens."</s>
 <s id="3">And some of you might be thinking that it's a growth on your aunt's face with hairs sticking out of it.</s>
 <s id="4">Well, in this case, a mole is a concept that we use in chemistry to count molecules, atoms, just about anything extremely small.</s>
 <s id="5">Have you ever wondered how many atoms there are in the universe?</s>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">Or in your body?</s>
  <s id="6.2">Or even in a grain of sand?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="7">Scientists have wanted to answer that question, but how do you count something as small as an atom?</s>
 <s id="8">Well, in 1811, someone had an idea that if you had equal volumes of gases, at the same temperature and pressure, they would contain an equal number of particles.</s>
 <s id="9">His name was Lorenzo Romano Amedeo Carlo Avogadro.</s>
 <s id="10">I wonder how long it took him to sign autographs.</s>
 <s id="11">Unfortunately for Avogadro, most scientists didn't accept the idea of the atom, and there was no way to prove he was right.</s>
 <s id="12">There was no clear difference between atoms and molecules.</s>
 <s id="13">Most scientists looked at Avogadro's work as purely hypothetical, and didn't give it much thought.</s>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">But it turned out he was right!</s>
  <s id="14.2">By late 1860, Avogadro was proven correct, and his work helped lay the foundation for the atomic theory.</s>
  <s id="14.3">Unfortunately, Avogadro died in 1856.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p15">
  <s id="15.1">Now the thing is that the amount of particles in even small samples is tremendous.</s>
  <s id="15.2">For example, If you have a balloon of any gas at zero degrees Celcius, and at a pressure of one atmosphere, then you have precisely six hundred and two sextillion gas particles.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="16">That is, you have six with 23 zeros after it particles of gas in the container.</s>
 <s id="17">Or in scientific notation, 6.02 times 10 to the 23rd particles.</s>
 <s id="18">This example is a little misleading, because gases take up a lot of space due to the high kinetic energy of the gas particles, and it leaves you thinking atoms are bigger than they really are.</s>
 <s id="19">Instead, think of water molecules.</s>
 <s id="20">If you pour 18.01 grams of water into a glass, which is 18.01 milliliters, which is like three and a half teaspoons of water, you'll have 602 sextillion molecules of water.</s>
 <s id="21">Since Lorenzo Romano - uh, never mind - Avogadro was the first one to come up with this idea, scientists named the number 6.02 times 10 to the 23rd after him.</s>
 <s id="22">It is simply known as Avogadros's number.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">Now, back to the mole.</s>
  <s id="23.2">Not that mole.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">This mole.</s>
  <s id="24.2">Yep, this number has a second name.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">The mole.</s>
  <s id="25.2">Chemists use the term mole to refer to the quantities that are at the magnitude of 602 sextillion.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">This is known as a molar quantity.</s>
 <s id="27">Atoms and molecules are so small, that chemists have bundled them into groups called moles.</s>
 <s id="28">Moles are hard for students to understand because they have a hard time picturing the size of a mole, or of 602 sextillion.</s>
 <s id="29">It's just too big to wrap our brains around.</s>
 <s id="30">Remember our 18.01 milliliters of water?</s>
 <s id="31">Well, that's a mole of water.</s>
 <s id="32">But how much is that?</s>
 <s id="33">Exactly what does 602 sextillion look like?</s>
 <s id="34">Maybe this'll help.</s>
 <s id="35">Exchange the water particles for donuts.</s>
 <s id="36">If you had a mole of donuts, they would cover the entire earth to a depth of eight kilometers, which is about five miles.</s>
 <s id="37">You really need a lot of coffee for that.</s>
 <s id="38">If you had a mole of basketballs, you could create a new planet the size of the earth.</s>
 <s id="39">If you received a mole of pennies on the day you were born and spent a million dollars a second until the day you died at the age of 100, you would still have more than 99.99% of your money in the bank.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">OK.</s>
  <s id="40.2">Now we sort of have an idea how large the mole is.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="41">So how do we use it?</s>
 <s id="42">You might be surprised to know that chemists use it the same way you use pounds to buy grapes, deli meat, or eggs.</s>
 <s id="43">When you go to the grocery store, you don't go to the deli counter and ask for 43 slices of salami, you buy your salami by the pound.</s>
 <s id="44">When you buy your eggs, you buy a dozen eggs.</s>
 <s id="45">When we hear the word dozen, we probably think of the number 12.</s>
 <s id="46">We also know that a pair is two, a baker's dozen is 13, a gross is 144, and a ream of paper is - anybody?</s>
 <s id="47">A ream is 500.</s>
 <s id="48">Well, a mole is really the same thing.</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">For a chemist, a mole conjures up the number 6.02 times 10 to the 23rd, not a fuzzy little animal.</s>
  <s id="49.2">The only difference is that the other quantities are more familiar to us.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">So there you have it - the story of the mole, Avogadro, basketballs, and how to buy salami at the grocery store.</s>
</text>
