<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'd like to talk about my dad.</s>
 <s id="2">My dad has Alzheimer's disease.</s>
 <s id="3">He started showing the symptoms about 12 years ago, and he was officially diagnosed in 2005.</s>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">Now he's really pretty sick.</s>
  <s id="4.2">He needs help eating, he needs help getting dressed, he doesn't really know where he is or when it is, and it's been really, really hard.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="5">My dad was my hero and my mentor for most of my life, and I've spent the last decade watching him disappear.</s>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">My dad's not alone.</s>
  <s id="6.2">There's about 35 million people globally living with some kind of dementia, and by 2030 they're expecting that to double to 70 million.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="7">That's a lot of people.</s>
 <p id="p8">
  <s id="8.1">Dementia scares us.</s>
  <s id="8.2">The confused faces and shaky hands of people who have dementia, the big numbers of people who get it, they frighten us.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="9">And because of that fear, we tend to do one of two things: We go into denial: "It's not me, it has nothing to do with me, it's never going to happen to me."</s>
 <s id="10">Or, we decide that we're going to prevent dementia, and it will never happen to us because we're going to do everything right and it won't come and get us.</s>
 <s id="11">I'm looking for a third way: I'm preparing to get Alzheimer's disease.</s>
 <s id="12">Prevention is good, and I'm doing the things that you can do to prevent Alzheimer's.</s>
 <s id="13">I'm eating right, I'm exercising every day, I'm keeping my mind active, that's what the research says you should do.</s>
 <s id="14">But the research also shows that there's nothing that will 100 percent protect you.</s>
 <s id="15">If the monster wants you, the monster's gonna get you.</s>
 <s id="16">That's what happened with my dad.</s>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">My dad was a bilingual college professor.</s>
  <s id="17.2">His hobbies were chess, bridge and writing op-eds.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) He got dementia anyway.</s>
 <s id="19">If the monster wants you, the monster's gonna get you.</s>
 <s id="20">Especially if you're me, 'cause Alzheimer's tends to run in families.</s>
 <s id="21">So I'm preparing to get Alzheimer's disease.</s>
 <s id="22">Based on what I've learned from taking care of my father, and researching what it's like to live with dementia, I'm focusing on three things in my preparation: I'm changing what I do for fun, I'm working to build my physical strength, and -- this is the hard one -- I'm trying to become a better person.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">Let's start with the hobbies.</s>
  <s id="23.2">When you get dementia, it gets harder and harder to enjoy yourself.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="24">You can't sit and have long talks with your old friends, because you don't know who they are.</s>
 <s id="25">It's confusing to watch television, and often very frightening.</s>
 <s id="26">And reading is just about impossible.</s>
 <s id="27">When you care for someone with dementia, and you get training, they train you to engage them in activities that are familiar, hands-on, open-ended.</s>
 <s id="28">With my dad, that turned out to be letting him fill out forms.</s>
 <s id="29">He was a college professor at a state school; he knows what paperwork looks like.</s>
 <s id="30">He'll sign his name on every line, he'll check all the boxes, he'll put numbers in where he thinks there should be numbers.</s>
 <s id="31">But it got me thinking, what would my caregivers do with me?</s>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">I'm my father's daughter.</s>
  <s id="32.2">I read, I write, I think about global health a lot.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="33">Would they give me academic journals so I could scribble in the margins?</s>
 <s id="34">Would they give me charts and graphs that I could color?</s>
 <s id="35">So I've been trying to learn to do things that are hands-on.</s>
 <s id="36">I've always liked to draw, so I'm doing it more even though I'm really very bad at it.</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">I am learning some basic origami.</s>
  <s id="37.2">I can make a really great box.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="38">(Laughter) And I'm teaching myself to knit, which so far I can knit a blob.</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">But, you know, it doesn't matter if I'm actually good at it.</s>
  <s id="39.2">What matters is that my hands know how to do it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">Because the more things that are familiar, the more things my hands know how to do, the more things that I can be happy and busy doing when my brain's not running the show anymore.</s>
 <s id="41">They say that people who are engaged in activities are happier, easier for their caregivers to look after, and it may even slow the progress of the disease.</s>
 <s id="42">That all seems like win to me.</s>
 <s id="43">I want to be as happy as I can for as long as I can.</s>
 <p id="p44">
  <s id="44.1">A lot of people don't know that Alzheimer's actually has physical symptoms, as well as cognitive symptoms.</s>
  <s id="44.2">You lose your sense of balance, you get muscle tremors, and that tends to lead people to being less and less mobile.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">They get scared to walk around.</s>
  <s id="45.2">They get scared to move.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="46">So I'm doing activities that will build my sense of balance.</s>
 <s id="47">I'm doing yoga and tai chi to improve my balance, so that when I start to lose it, I'll still be able to be mobile.</s>
 <s id="48">I'm doing weight-bearing exercise, so that I have the muscle strength so that when I start to wither, I have more time that I can still move around.</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">Finally, the third thing.</s>
  <s id="49.2">I'm trying to become a better person.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">My dad was kind and loving before he had Alzheimer's, and he's kind and loving now.</s>
 <s id="51">I've seen him lose his intellect, his sense of humor, his language skills, but I've also seen this: He loves me, he loves my sons, he loves my brother and my mom and his caregivers.</s>
 <s id="52">And that love makes us want to be around him, even now.</s>
 <s id="53">even when it's so hard.</s>
 <s id="54">When you take away everything that he ever learned in this world, his naked heart still shines.</s>
 <s id="55">I was never as kind as my dad, and I was never as loving.</s>
 <s id="56">And what I need now is to learn to be like that.</s>
 <s id="57">I need a heart so pure that if it's stripped bare by dementia, it will survive.</s>
 <s id="58">I don't want to get Alzheimer's disease.</s>
 <s id="59">What I want is a cure in the next 20 years, soon enough to protect me.</s>
 <s id="60">But if it comes for me, I'm going to be ready.</s>
 <s id="61">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="62">(Applause)</s>
</text>
