<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Those of you who know me know how passionate I am about opening the space frontier.</s>
 <s id="2">So when I had the chance to give the world's expert in gravity the experience of zero gravity, it was incredible.</s>
 <s id="3">And I want to tell you that story.</s>
 <s id="4">I first met him through the Archon X PRIZE for Genomics.</s>
 <s id="5">It's a competition we're holding, the second X PRIZE, for the first team to sequence 100 human genomes in 10 days.</s>
 <s id="6">We have something called the Genome 100 -- 100 individuals we're sequencing as part of that.</s>
 <s id="7">Craig Venter chairs that event.</s>
 <s id="8">And I met Professor Hawking, and he said his dream was to travel into space.</s>
 <s id="9">And I said, "I can't take you there, but I can take you into weightlessness into zero-g.</s>
 <s id="10">And he said, on the spot, "Absolutely, yes."</s>
 <s id="11">Well, the only way to experience zero-g on Earth is actually with parabolic flight, weightless flight.</s>
 <s id="12">You take an airplane, you fly over the top, you're weightless for 25 seconds.</s>
 <s id="13">Come back down, you weigh twice as much.</s>
 <s id="14">You do it again and again.</s>
 <s id="15">You can get eight, 10 minutes of weightlessness -- how NASA's trained their astronauts for so long.</s>
 <s id="16">We set out to do this.</s>
 <s id="17">It took us 11 years to become operational.</s>
 <s id="18">And we announced that we were going to fly Stephen Hawking.</s>
 <s id="19">We had one government agency and one company aircraft operator say, you're crazy, don't do that, you're going kill the guy.</s>
 <s id="20">(Laughter) And he wanted to go.</s>
 <s id="21">We worked hard to get all the permissions.</s>
 <s id="22">And six months later, we sat down at Kennedy Space Center.</s>
 <s id="23">We had a press conference, we announced our intent to do one zero-g parabola, give him 25 seconds of zero-g.</s>
 <s id="24">And if it went really well, we might do three parabolas.</s>
 <s id="25">Well, we asked him why he wanted to go up and do this.</s>
 <s id="26">And what he said, for me, was very moving.</s>
 <s id="27">He said, "Life on Earth is at an ever-increasing risk of being wiped out by disaster ...</s>
 <s id="28">I think the human race doesn't have a future if it doesn't go into space.</s>
 <s id="29">I therefore want to encourage public interest in space."</s>
 <s id="30">We took him out to the Kennedy Space Center, up inside the NASA vehicle, into the back of the zero-g airplane.</s>
 <s id="31">We had about 20 people who made donations -- we raised $150,000 in donations for children's charities -- who flew with us.</s>
 <s id="32">A few TEDsters here.</s>
 <s id="33">We set up a whole ER.</s>
 <s id="34">We had four emergency room doctors and two nurses on board the airplane.</s>
 <s id="35">We were monitoring his PO2 of his blood, his heart rate, his blood pressure.</s>
 <s id="36">We had everything all set in case of an emergency; God knows, you don't want to hurt this world-renowned expert.</s>
 <s id="37">We took off from the shuttle landing facility, where the shuttle takes off and lands.</s>
 <s id="38">And my partner Byron Lichtenberg and I carefully suspended him into zero-g.</s>
 <s id="39">Once he was there, [we] let him go to experience what weightlessness was truly like.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">And after that first parabola, you know, the doc said everything is great.</s>
  <s id="40.2">He was smiling, and we said go.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="41">So we did a second parabola.</s>
 <s id="42">(Laughter) (Applause) And a third.</s>
 <s id="43">(Applause) We actually floated an apple in homage to Sir Isaac Newton because Professor Hawking holds the same chair at Cambridge that Isaac Newton did.</s>
 <s id="44">And we did a fourth, and a fifth and a sixth.</s>
 <s id="45">(Laughter) And a seventh and an eighth.</s>
 <s id="46">And this man does not look like a 65-year-old wheelchair-bound man.</s>
 <s id="47">(Laughter) He was so happy.</s>
 <s id="48">We are living on a precious jewel, and it's during our lifetime that we're moving off this planet.</s>
 <s id="49">Please join us in this epic adventure.</s>
 <s id="50">Thank you so much.</s>
 <s id="51">(Applause)</s>
</text>
