<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I just came back from a community that holds the secret to human survival.</s>
 <s id="2">It's a place where women run the show, have sex to say hello, and play rules the day -- where fun is serious business.</s>
 <s id="3">And no, this isn't Burning Man or San Francisco.</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) Ladies and gentlemen, meet your cousins.</s>
 <s id="5">This is the world of wild bonobos in the jungles of Congo.</s>
 <s id="6">Bonobos are, together with chimpanzees, your living closest relative.</s>
 <s id="7">That means we all share a common ancestor, an evolutionary grandmother, who lived around six million years ago.</s>
 <s id="8">Now, chimpanzees are well-known for their aggression.</s>
 <s id="9">(Laughter) But unfortunately, we have made too much of an emphasis of this aspect in our narratives of human evolution.</s>
 <s id="10">But bonobos show us the other side of the coin.</s>
 <s id="11">While chimpanzees are dominated by big, scary guys, bonobo society is run by empowered females.</s>
 <s id="12">These guys have really worked something out, since this leads to a highly tolerant society where fatal violence has not been observed yet.</s>
 <s id="13">But unfortunately, bonobos are the least understood of the great apes.</s>
 <s id="14">They live in the depths of the Congolese jungle, and it has been very difficult to study them.</s>
 <s id="15">The Congo is a paradox -- a land of extraordinary biodiversity and beauty, but also the heart of darkness itself -- the scene of a violent conflict that has raged for decades and claimed nearly as many lives as the First World War.</s>
 <s id="16">Not surprisingly, this destruction also endangers bonobo survival.</s>
 <s id="17">Bushmeat trades and forest loss means we couldn't fill a small stadium with all the bonobos that are left in the world -- and we're not even sure of that to be honest.</s>
 <s id="18">Yet, in this land of violence and chaos, you can hear hidden laughter swaying the trees.</s>
 <s id="19">Who are these cousins?</s>
 <s id="20">We know them as the "make love, not war" apes since they have frequent, promiscuous and bisexual sex to manage conflict and solve social issues.</s>
 <s id="21">Now, I'm not saying this is the solution to all of humanity's problems -- since there's more to bonobo life than the Kama Sutra.</s>
 <s id="22">Bonobos, like humans, love to play throughout their entire lives.</s>
 <s id="23">Play is not just child's games.</s>
 <s id="24">For us and them, play is foundational for bonding relationships and fostering tolerance.</s>
 <s id="25">It's where we learn to trust and where we learn about the rules of the game.</s>
 <s id="26">Play increases creativity and resilience, and it's all about the generation of diversity -- diversity of interactions, diversity of behaviors, diversity of connections.</s>
 <s id="27">And when you watch bonobo play, you're seeing the very evolutionary roots of human laughter, dance and ritual.</s>
 <s id="28">Play is the glue that binds us together.</s>
 <s id="29">Now, I don't know how you play, but I want to show you a couple of unique clips fresh from the wild.</s>
 <s id="30">First, it's a ball game bonobo-style -- and I do not mean football.</s>
 <s id="31">So here, we have a young female and a male engaged in a chase game.</s>
 <s id="32">Have a look what she's doing.</s>
 <s id="33">It might be the evolutionary origin of the phrase, "she's got him by the balls."</s>
 <s id="34">(Laughter) Only I think that he's rather loving it here, right?</s>
 <s id="35">Yeah.</s>
 <s id="36">(Laughter) So sex play is common in both bonobos and humans.</s>
 <s id="37">And this video is really interesting because it shows -- this video's really interesting because it shows the inventiveness of bringing unusual elements into play -- such as testicles -- and also how play both requires trust and fosters trust -- while at the same time being tremendous fun.</s>
 <s id="38">But play's a shapeshifter.</s>
 <s id="39">(Laughter) Play's a shapeshifter, and it can take many forms, some of which are more quiet, imaginative, curious -- maybe where wonder is discovered anew.</s>
 <s id="40">And I want you to see, this is Fuku, a young female, and she is quietly playing with water.</s>
 <s id="41">I think, like her, we sometimes play alone, and we explore the boundaries of our inner and our outer worlds.</s>
 <s id="42">And it's that playful curiosity that drives us to explore, drives us to interact, and then the unexpected connections we form are the real hotbed for creativity.</s>
 <s id="43">So these are just small tasters into the insights that bonobo give us to our past and present.</s>
 <s id="44">But they also hold a secret for our future, a future where we need to adapt to an increasingly challenging world through greater creativity and greater cooperation.</s>
 <s id="45">The secret is that play is the key to these capacities.</s>
 <s id="46">In other words, play is our adaptive wildcard.</s>
 <s id="47">In order to adapt successfully to a changing world, we need to play.</s>
 <s id="48">But will we make the most of our playfulness?</s>
 <s id="49">Play is not frivolous.</s>
 <s id="50">Play's essential.</s>
 <s id="51">For bonobos and humans alike, life is not just red in tooth and claw.</s>
 <s id="52">In times when it seems least appropriate to play, it might be the times when it is most urgent.</s>
 <s id="53">And so, my fellow primates, let us embrace this gift from evolution and play together, as we rediscover creativity, fellowship and wonder.</s>
 <s id="54">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="55">(Applause)</s>
</text>
