<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So this is my niece.</s>
 <s id="2">Her name is Yahli.</s>
 <s id="3">She is nine months old.</s>
 <s id="4">Her mum is a doctor, and her dad is a lawyer.</s>
 <s id="5">By the time Yahli goes to college, the jobs her parents do are going to look dramatically different.</s>
 <s id="6">In 2013, researchers at Oxford University did a study on the future of work.</s>
 <s id="7">They concluded that almost one in every two jobs have a high risk of being automated by machines.</s>
 <s id="8">Machine learning is the technology that's responsible for most of this disruption.</s>
 <s id="9">It's the most powerful branch of artificial intelligence.</s>
 <s id="10">It allows machines to learn from data and mimic some of the things that humans can do.</s>
 <s id="11">My company, Kaggle, operates on the cutting edge of machine learning.</s>
 <s id="12">We bring together hundreds of thousands of experts to solve important problems for industry and academia.</s>
 <s id="13">This gives us a unique perspective on what machines can do, what they can't do and what jobs they might automate or threaten.</s>
 <s id="14">Machine learning started making its way into industry in the early '90s.</s>
 <s id="15">It started with relatively simple tasks.</s>
 <s id="16">It started with things like assessing credit risk from loan applications, sorting the mail by reading handwritten characters from zip codes.</s>
 <s id="17">Over the past few years, we have made dramatic breakthroughs.</s>
 <s id="18">Machine learning is now capable of far, far more complex tasks.</s>
 <s id="19">In 2012, Kaggle challenged its community to build an algorithm that could grade high-school essays.</s>
 <s id="20">The winning algorithms were able to match the grades given by human teachers.</s>
 <s id="21">Last year, we issued an even more difficult challenge.</s>
 <s id="22">Can you take images of the eye and diagnose an eye disease called diabetic retinopathy?</s>
 <s id="23">Again, the winning algorithms were able to match the diagnoses given by human ophthalmologists.</s>
 <s id="24">Now, given the right data, machines are going to outperform humans at tasks like this.</s>
 <s id="25">A teacher might read 10,000 essays over a 40-year career.</s>
 <s id="26">An ophthalmologist might see 50,000 eyes.</s>
 <s id="27">A machine can read millions of essays or see millions of eyes within minutes.</s>
 <s id="28">We have no chance of competing against machines on frequent, high-volume tasks.</s>
 <s id="29">But there are things we can do that machines can't do.</s>
 <s id="30">Where machines have made very little progress is in tackling novel situations.</s>
 <s id="31">They can't handle things they haven't seen many times before.</s>
 <s id="32">The fundamental limitations of machine learning is that it needs to learn from large volumes of past data.</s>
 <s id="33">Now, humans don't.</s>
 <s id="34">We have the ability to connect seemingly disparate threads to solve problems we've never seen before.</s>
 <s id="35">Percy Spencer was a physicist working on radar during World War II, when he noticed the magnetron was melting his chocolate bar.</s>
 <s id="36">He was able to connect his understanding of electromagnetic radiation with his knowledge of cooking in order to invent -- any guesses? -- the microwave oven.</s>
 <s id="37">Now, this is a particularly remarkable example of creativity.</s>
 <s id="38">But this sort of cross-pollination happens for each of us in small ways thousands of times per day.</s>
 <s id="39">Machines cannot compete with us when it comes to tackling novel situations, and this puts a fundamental limit on the human tasks that machines will automate.</s>
 <s id="40">So what does this mean for the future of work?</s>
 <s id="41">The future state of any single job lies in the answer to a single question: To what extent is that job reducible to frequent, high-volume tasks, and to what extent does it involve tackling novel situations?</s>
 <s id="42">On frequent, high-volume tasks, machines are getting smarter and smarter.</s>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">Today they grade essays.</s>
  <s id="43.2">They diagnose certain diseases.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">Over coming years, they're going to conduct our audits, and they're going to read boilerplate from legal contracts.</s>
 <s id="45">Accountants and lawyers are still needed.</s>
 <s id="46">They're going to be needed for complex tax structuring, for pathbreaking litigation.</s>
 <s id="47">But machines will shrink their ranks and make these jobs harder to come by.</s>
 <s id="48">Now, as mentioned, machines are not making progress on novel situations.</s>
 <s id="49">The copy behind a marketing campaign needs to grab consumers' attention.</s>
 <s id="50">It has to stand out from the crowd.</s>
 <s id="51">Business strategy means finding gaps in the market, things that nobody else is doing.</s>
 <s id="52">It will be humans that are creating the copy behind our marketing campaigns, and it will be humans that are developing our business strategy.</s>
 <s id="53">So Yahli, whatever you decide to do, let every day bring you a new challenge.</s>
 <s id="54">If it does, then you will stay ahead of the machines.</s>
 <s id="55">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="56">(Applause)</s>
</text>
