<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">By now, I'm sure you know that in just about anything you do in life, you need numbers.</s>
 <s id="2">In particular, though, some fields don't just need a few numbers, they need lots of them.</s>
 <s id="3">How do you keep track of all those numbers?</s>
 <s id="4">Well, mathematicians dating back as early as ancient China came up with a way to represent arrays of many numbers at once.</s>
 <s id="5">Nowadays we call such an array a "matrix," and many of them hanging out together, "matrices".</s>
 <s id="6">Matrices are everywhere.</s>
 <s id="7">They are all around us, even now in this very room.</s>
 <s id="8">Sorry, let's get back on track.</s>
 <s id="9">Matrices really are everywhere, though.</s>
 <s id="10">They are used in business, economics, cryptography, physics, electronics, and computer graphics.</s>
 <s id="11">One reason matrices are so cool is that we can pack so much information into them and then turn a huge series of different problems into one single problem.</s>
 <s id="12">So, to use matrices, we need to learn how they work.</s>
 <s id="13">It turns out, you can treat matrices just like regular numbers.</s>
 <s id="14">You can add them, subtract them, even multiply them.</s>
 <s id="15">You can't divide them, but that's a rabbit hole of its own.</s>
 <s id="16">Adding matrices is pretty simple.</s>
 <s id="17">All you have to do is add the corresponding entries in the order they come.</s>
 <s id="18">So the first entries get added together, the second entries, the third, all the way down.</s>
 <s id="19">Of course, your matrices have to be the same size, but that's pretty intuitive anyway.</s>
 <s id="20">You can also multiply the whole matrix by a number, called a scalar.</s>
 <s id="21">Just multiply every entry by that number.</s>
 <s id="22">But wait, there's more!</s>
 <s id="23">You can actually multiply one matrix by another matrix.</s>
 <s id="24">It's not like adding them, though, where you do it entry by entry.</s>
 <s id="25">It's more unique and pretty cool once you get the hang of it.</s>
 <s id="26">Here's how it works.</s>
 <s id="27">Let's say you have two matrices.</s>
 <s id="28">Let's make them both two by two, meaning two rows by two columns.</s>
 <s id="29">Write the first matrix to the left and the second matrix goes next to it and translated up a bit, kind of like we are making a table.</s>
 <s id="30">The product we get when we multiply the matrices together will go right between them.</s>
 <s id="31">We'll also draw some gridlines to help us along.</s>
 <s id="32">Now, look at the first row of the first matrix and the first column of the second matrix.</s>
 <s id="33">See how there's two numbers in each?</s>
 <s id="34">Multiply the first number in the row by the first number in the column: 1 times 2 is 2.</s>
 <s id="35">Now do the next ones: 3 times 3 is 9.</s>
 <s id="36">Now add them up: 2 plus 9 is 11.</s>
 <s id="37">Let's put that number in the top-left position so that it matches up with the rows and columns we used to get it.</s>
 <s id="38">See how that works?</s>
 <s id="39">You can do the same thing to get the other entries.</s>
 <s id="40">-4 plus 0 is -4.</s>
 <s id="41">4 plus -3 is 1.</s>
 <s id="42">-8 plus 0 is -8.</s>
 <s id="43">So, here's your answer.</s>
 <s id="44">Not all that bad, is it?</s>
 <s id="45">There's one catch, though.</s>
 <s id="46">Just like with addition, your matrices have to be the right size.</s>
 <s id="47">Look at these two matrices.</s>
 <s id="48">2 times 8 is 16.</s>
 <s id="49">3 times 4 is 12.</s>
 <s id="50">3 times wait a minute, there are no more rows in the second matrix.</s>
 <s id="51">We ran out of room.</s>
 <s id="52">So, these matrices can't be multiplied.</s>
 <s id="53">The number of columns in the first matrix has to be the same as the number of rows in the second matrix.</s>
 <s id="54">As long as you're careful to match up your dimensions right, though, it's pretty easy.</s>
 <s id="55">Understanding matrix multiplication is just the beginning, by the way.</s>
 <s id="56">There's so much you can do with them.</s>
 <s id="57">For example, let's say you want to encrypt a secret message.</s>
 <s id="58">Let's say it's "Math rules".</s>
 <s id="59">Though, why anybody would want to keep this a secret is beyond me.</s>
 <s id="60">Letting numbers stand for letters, you can put the numbers in a matrix and then an encryption key in another.</s>
 <s id="61">Multiply them together and you've got a new encoded matrix.</s>
 <s id="62">The only way to decode the new matrix and read the message is to have the key, that second matrix.</s>
 <s id="63">There's even a branch of mathematics that uses matrices constantly, called Linear Algebra.</s>
 <s id="64">If you ever get a chance to study Linear Algebra, do it, it's pretty awesome.</s>
 <s id="65">But just remember, once you know how to use matrices, you can do pretty much anything.</s>
</text>
