<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I have quite an issue with truth and conversations.</s>
 <s id="2">I'm a scientist but I ended up taking some weird paths.</s>
 <s id="3">Science is a way of asking questions to the world and of listening to the answers.</s>
 <s id="4">We will never know everything.</s>
 <s id="5">But that doesn't mean we know nothing.</s>
 <s id="6">There's a lot that we already know.</s>
 <s id="7">However, the evidence is sometimes set aside when making decisions or forming an idea of the world.</s>
 <s id="8">For example, we already know that climate change is real, but some still deny it.</s>
 <s id="9">We already know that vaccines work and are safe.</s>
 <s id="10">But some still doubt about it.</s>
 <s id="11">That was my first disappointment.</s>
 <s id="12">Evidence is necessary but not sufficient.</s>
 <s id="13">This opened up a new path for me.</s>
 <s id="14">I thought the problem was education.</s>
 <s id="15">So I left the lab and I turned to teaching.</s>
 <s id="16">I love teaching.</s>
 <s id="17">The classroom is one of my favorite places.</s>
 <s id="18">But there I found the same problem.</s>
 <s id="19">I was teaching on vaccines and one student said she didn't get vaccinated because vaccines seemed dangerous.</s>
 <s id="20">My hunch was, "She says this because she doesn't know, if I explain, she will change her mind."</s>
 <s id="21">I explained to her, but it didn't work.</s>
 <s id="22">The evidence is not enough.</s>
 <s id="23">Education is not enough.</s>
 <s id="24">Second disappointment.</s>
 <s id="25">This that happened with my student was my first personal experience with post-truth.</s>
 <s id="26">It's what happens when, although the information is there, it's set aside and emotions or beliefs ensue.</s>
 <s id="27">With this, another new path opened up.</s>
 <s id="28">Maybe, it's a communication problem?</s>
 <s id="29">Given that science is a tool, I used it to study post-truth.</s>
 <s id="30">I started having conversations with people who don't trust vaccines, while meeting doctors and journalists in an attempt to improve communication on this subject.</s>
 <s id="31">And there I realized that I had never learned to talk with those who think differently.</s>
 <s id="32">For example, how do we dialogue when the problem is not the evidence but an ideological disagreement?</s>
 <s id="33">Experiments show that when people talk only with those who think alike their opinions become more extreme and homogeneous.</s>
 <s id="34">But in order to have a healthy democracy, don't we need that those who think differently engage in broad, honest and deep conversations?</s>
 <s id="35">This is far from happening.</s>
 <s id="36">Every discussion, every disagreement, every conversation looks like a battle between good and evil.</s>
 <s id="37">Our opinions, instead of being temporary, bridges to communicate with others, are immovable, a ditch that we dig and tells apart those on our side from the others.</s>
 <s id="38">Dialogue disappears, agreements are impossible, and the world shatters in an explosive combination of aggression and distrust.</s>
 <s id="39">Can we do something about this?</s>
 <s id="40">Not all opinions are born equal.</s>
 <s id="41">Some are weak, or short-lived.</s>
 <s id="42">Others are intense, or long-lasting.</s>
 <s id="43">And others become part of our identity.</s>
 <s id="44">When that happens, any doubt on what we think becomes a doubt on who we are.</s>
 <s id="45">And that is unbearable.</s>
 <s id="46">In addition, the need to protect our integrity makes us team up with those in our same situation.</s>
 <s id="47">This is tribalism.</s>
 <s id="48">That's why sometimes neither evidence nor education works.</s>
 <s id="49">We don't think something, we are that something.</s>
 <s id="50">(Applause) Let me ask you a question.</s>
 <s id="51">Did it ever happen to you of going to a meet up with people you don't know and thinking something like, "Mm, I don't know what these people think, I better not talk about this or that"?</s>
 <s id="52">Did it ever happen to you?</s>
 <s id="53">Let's see, raise your hand those who lived something like that.</s>
 <s id="54">Look at you.</s>
 <s id="55">The harm of tribalism is not only that it creates a climate of permanent conflict but that it also creates silence.</s>
 <s id="56">Some of us withdraw from the debate, not because we don't have opinions or we don't care about what happens.</s>
 <s id="57">We are not halfhearted.</s>
 <s id="58">It's the atmosphere of aggression, it's things not moving forward, it's fear, exhaustion, and the social punishment of dissent.</s>
 <s id="59">It's for one or more of these reasons that we leave conversations in silence.</s>
 <s id="60">A loud silence.</s>
 <s id="61">And so, the inability to dialogue causes the number of voices to go down.</s>
 <s id="62">Until there is only one left, sometimes.</s>
 <s id="63">Silence is confused with agreement.</s>
 <s id="64">And the illusion of consensus is created.</s>
 <s id="65">Because one opinion is heard, there seem to be only one.</s>
 <s id="66">And then any other opinion is not only different, but dissonant, alien, and must be eliminated.</s>
 <s id="67">In general, we think of censorship as a power which bans from above.</s>
 <s id="68">But there is another, more subtle way.</s>
 <s id="69">Censorship from below.</s>
 <s id="70">Through tools of social discipline, such as raising the tone of the fight, it makes us withdraw.</s>
 <s id="71">This is a threat to free expression.</s>
 <s id="72">And it makes me think that it's also a problem for democracy.</s>
 <s id="73">Both in our small environment and on a large scale.</s>
 <s id="74">It would seem then that we only have two options.</s>
 <s id="75">Whether we share our ideas despising those who don't think alike, or we shut up.</s>
 <s id="76">And by doing that, we give up control to those who speak up.</s>
 <s id="77">But this is a false dilemma.</s>
 <s id="78">There is another option, but we need to make it evident, because it is hidden in this sea of tribalism.</s>
 <s id="79">We can have defined positions, even very intense ones, without riding on the dynamics of intolerant speech.</s>
 <s id="80">It's one of the things I learned when talking to people who doubt vaccines.</s>
 <s id="81">To break tribalism, to find more voices, to break this "friends or foes" dynamics, I propose to distinguish between what we believe in and how we believe it.</s>
 <s id="82">And if we make this "how" non-tribal, we can raise our opinions without allowing what we think to become who we are.</s>
 <s id="83">The nuances reappear and conversations become possible.</s>
 <s id="84">And from that point we can build consensus which are the product of agreements, despite our differences.</s>
 <s id="85">However, when I talk about these ideas I usually get some criticism.</s>
 <s id="86">It seems that in order to avoid conflict I suggest that we let consensus happen anytime.</s>
 <s id="87">No, that is not what I mean.</s>
 <s id="88">If we don't express ourselves because we feel alienated or expelled we are not taking part in decision making.</s>
 <s id="89">But we all live with the consequences of those decisions.</s>
 <s id="90">So, since we do care, we need to talk.</s>
 <s id="91">But if we don't want to talk in this hostile atmosphere because it's exhausting and we see that it leads nowhere, let's try to move past tribal mode.</s>
 <s id="92">Beyond what we think.</s>
 <s id="93">We may have more in common with those who think differently yet want to talk, than with those who share with us same opinions but are intolerant.</s>
 <s id="94">(Applause) They also usually tell me that there isn't much we can do on the individual level to move past tribal mode.</s>
 <s id="95">But I think there are some very concrete things to do.</s>
 <s id="96">And I have three suggestions that could help.</s>
 <s id="97">First, look for pluralism.</s>
 <s id="98">Promote it actively.</s>
 <s id="99">So dissent becomes visible and this is important because only if we include dissent we can achieve a true consensus.</s>
 <s id="100">For this to happen we need to be able to talk without feeling that we are socially punished.</s>
 <s id="101">But it also requires listening to voices we don't like.</s>
 <s id="102">The moment to defend freedom of expression is now.</s>
 <s id="103">Taking care of it is easier than recovering it.</s>
 <s id="104">Learn to have better conversations.</s>
 <s id="105">To find better ways of disagreeing.</s>
 <s id="106">A conversation is not waiting for our turn to talk, trying to impose our ideas by force or insistence.</s>
 <s id="107">It's about listening to understand others.</s>
 <s id="108">Without listening there's no conversation.</s>
 <s id="109">Third, separate ideas from people.</s>
 <s id="110">Under tribalism, attacking an idea makes the person feel threatened because they feel attacked as a person.</s>
 <s id="111">But how are we going to improve ideas with that attitude?</s>
 <s id="112">We need to discuss them, so that the best survive.</s>
 <s id="113">People deserve respect.</s>
 <s id="114">Ideas have to earn it.</s>
 <s id="115">Humans are inventors.</s>
 <s id="116">At some point, somewhere, we invented the idea of sitting by the fire to talk.</s>
 <s id="117">And at some point, both conversations and fire look alike.</s>
 <s id="118">Both are always in between two dangers.</s>
 <s id="119">The danger of dying or growing out of control.</s>
 <s id="120">It took us time but we learned to handle fire.</s>
 <s id="121">We learned to keep it alive so it doesn't go out.</s>
 <s id="122">And to handle it so it doesn't destroy us.</s>
 <s id="123">Maybe, it's time to learn to do the same with conversations.</s>
 <s id="124">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="125">(Applause)</s>
</text>
