<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So the first antidepressants were made from, of all things, rocket fuel, left over after World War II.</s>
 <s id="2">Which is fitting, seeing as today, one in five soldiers develop depression, or post-traumatic stress disorder or both.</s>
 <s id="3">But it's not just soldiers that are at high risk for these diseases.</s>
 <s id="4">It's firefighters, ER doctors, cancer patients, aid workers, refugees -- anyone exposed to trauma or major life stress.</s>
 <s id="5">And yet, despite how commonplace these disorders are, our current treatments, if they work at all, only suppress symptoms.</s>
 <s id="6">In 1798, when Edward Jenner discovered the first vaccine -- it happened to be for smallpox -- he didn't just discover a prophylactic for a disease, but a whole new way of thinking: that medicine could prevent disease.</s>
 <s id="7">However, for over 200 years, this prevention was not believed to extend to psychiatric diseases.</s>
 <s id="8">Until 2014, when my colleague and I accidentally discovered the first drugs that might prevent depression and PTSD.</s>
 <s id="9">We discovered the drugs in mice, and we're currently studying whether they work in humans.</s>
 <s id="10">And these preventative psychopharmaceuticals are not antidepressants.</s>
 <s id="11">They are a whole new class of drug.</s>
 <s id="12">And they work by increasing stress resilience, so let's call them resilience enhancers.</s>
 <s id="13">So think back to a stressful time that you've since recovered from.</s>
 <s id="14">Maybe a breakup or an exam, you missed a flight.</s>
 <s id="15">Stress resilience is the active biological process that allows us to bounce back after stress.</s>
 <s id="16">Similar to if you have a cold and your immune system fights it off.</s>
 <s id="17">And insufficient resilience in the face of a significant enough stressor, can result in a psychiatric disorder, such as depression.</s>
 <s id="18">In fact, most cases of major depressive disorder are initially triggered by stress.</s>
 <s id="19">And from what we've seen so far in mice, resilience enhancers can protect against purely biological stressors, like stress hormones, and social and psychological stressors, like bullying and isolation.</s>
 <s id="20">So here is an example where we gave mice three weeks of high levels of stress hormones.</s>
 <s id="21">So, in other words, a biological stressor without a psychological component.</s>
 <s id="22">And this causes depressive behavior.</s>
 <s id="23">And if we give three weeks of antidepressant treatment beforehand, it has no beneficial effects.</s>
 <s id="24">But a single dose of a resilience enhancer given a week before completely prevents the depressive behavior.</s>
 <s id="25">Even after three weeks of stress.</s>
 <s id="26">This is the first time a drug has ever been shown to prevent the negative effects of stress.</s>
 <s id="27">Depression and PTSD are chronic, often lifelong, clinical diseases.</s>
 <s id="28">They also increase the risk of substance abuse, homelessness, heart disease, Alzheimer's, suicide.</s>
 <s id="29">The global cost of depression alone is over three trillion dollars per year.</s>
 <s id="30">But now, imagine a scenario where we know someone is predictively at high risk for exposure to extreme stress.</s>
 <s id="31">Say, a red cross volunteer going into an earthquake zone.</s>
 <s id="32">In addition to the typhoid vaccine, we could give her a pill or an injection of a resilience enhancer before she leaves.</s>
 <s id="33">So when she is held at gunpoint by looters or worse, she would at least be protected against developing depression or PTSD after the fact.</s>
 <s id="34">It won't prevent her from experiencing the stress, but it will allow her to recover from it.</s>
 <s id="35">And that's what's revolutionary here.</s>
 <s id="36">By increasing resiliency, we can dramatically reduce her susceptibility to depression and PTSD, possibly saving her from losing her job, her home, her family or even her life.</s>
 <s id="37">After Jenner discovered the smallpox vaccine, a lot of other vaccines rapidly followed.</s>
 <s id="38">But it was over 150 years before a tuberculosis vaccine was widely available.</s>
 <s id="39">Why?</s>
 <s id="40">In part because society believed that tuberculosis made people more sensitive and creative and empathetic.</s>
 <s id="41">And that it was caused by constitution and not biology.</s>
 <s id="42">And similar things are still said today about depression.</s>
 <s id="43">And just as Jenner's discovery opened the door for all of the vaccines that followed after, the drugs we've discovered open the possibility of a whole new field: preventative psychopharmacology.</s>
 <s id="44">But whether that's 15 years away, or 150 years away, depends not just on the science, but on what we as a society choose to do with it.</s>
 <s id="45">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="46">(Applause)</s>
</text>
