<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">When I first arrived in beautiful Zimbabwe, it was difficult to understand that 35 percent of the population is HIV positive.</s>
 <s id="2">It really wasn't until I was invited to the homes of people that I started to understand the human toll of the epidemic.</s>
 <s id="3">For instance, this is Herbert with his grandmother.</s>
 <s id="4">When I first met him, he was sitting on his grandmother's lap.</s>
 <s id="5">He has been orphaned, as both of his parents died of AIDS, and his grandmother took care of him until he too died of AIDS.</s>
 <s id="6">He liked to sit on her lap because he said that it was painful for him to lie in his own bed.</s>
 <s id="7">When she got up to make tea, she placed him in my own lap and I had never felt a child that was that emaciated.</s>
 <s id="8">Before I left, I actually asked him if I could get him something.</s>
 <s id="9">I thought he would ask for a toy, or candy, and he asked me for slippers, because he said that his feet were cold.</s>
 <s id="10">This is Joyce who's -- in this picture -- 21.</s>
 <s id="11">Single mother, HIV positive.</s>
 <s id="12">I photographed her before and after the birth of her beautiful baby girl, Issa.</s>
 <s id="13">And I was last week walking on Lafayette Street in Manhattan and got a call from a woman who I didn't know, but she called to tell me that Joyce had passed away at the age of 23.</s>
 <s id="14">Joyce's mother is now taking care of her daughter, like so many other Zimbabwean children who've been orphaned by the epidemic.</s>
 <s id="15">So a few of the stories.</s>
 <s id="16">With every picture, there are individuals who have full lives and stories that deserve to be told.</s>
 <s id="17">All these pictures are from Zimbabwe.</s>
 <s id="18">Chris Anderson: Kirsten, will you just take one minute, just to tell your own story of how you got to Africa?</s>
 <s id="19">Kirsten Ashburn: Mmm, gosh.</s>
 <s id="20">CA: Just -- KA: Actually, I was working at the time, doing production for a fashion photographer.</s>
 <s id="21">And I was constantly reading the New York Times, and stunned by the statistics, the numbers.</s>
 <s id="22">It was just frightening.</s>
 <s id="23">So I quit my job and decided that that's the subject that I wanted to tackle.</s>
 <s id="24">And I first actually went to Botswana, where I spent a month -- this is in December 2000 -- then went to Zimbabwe for a month and a half, and then went back again this March 2002 for another month and a half in Zimbabwe.</s>
 <s id="25">CA: That's an amazing story, thank you.</s>
 <s id="26">KB: Thanks for letting me show these.</s>
</text>
