<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In the summer of 1895, crowds flooded the Coney Island boardwalk to see the latest marvel of roller coaster technology: the Flip Flap Railway.</s>
 <s id="2">This was America’s first-ever looping coaster – but its thrilling flip came at a price.</s>
 <s id="3">The ride caused numerous cases of severe whiplash, neck injury and even ejections, all due to its signature loop.</s>
 <s id="4">Today, coasters can pull off far more exciting tricks, without resorting to the “thrill” of a hospital visit.</s>
 <s id="5">But what exactly are roller coasters doing to your body, and how have they managed to get scarier and safer at the same time?</s>
 <s id="6">At the center of every roller coaster design is gravity.</s>
 <s id="7">Unlike cars or transit trains, most coasters are propelled around their tracks almost entirely by gravitational energy.</s>
 <s id="8">After the coaster crests the initial lift hill, it begins an expertly engineered cycle – building potential energy on ascents and expending kinetic energy on descents.</s>
 <s id="9">This rhythm repeats throughout the ride, acting out the coaster engineer’s choreographed dance of gravitational energy.</s>
 <s id="10">But there’s a key variable in this cycle that wasn’t always so carefully considered: you.</s>
 <s id="11">In the days of the Flip-Flap, ride designers were most concerned with coasters getting stuck somewhere along the track.</s>
 <s id="12">This led early builders to overcompensate, hurling trains down hills and pulling on the brakes when they reached the station.</s>
 <s id="13">But as gravity affects the cars, it also affects the passengers.</s>
 <s id="14">And under the intense conditions of a coaster, gravity’s effects are multiplied.</s>
 <s id="15">There’s a common unit used by jet pilots, astronauts, and coaster designers called “g force”.</s>
 <s id="16">One G force is the familiar tug of gravity you feel when standing on Earth – this is the force of Earth’s gravitational pull on our bodies.</s>
 <s id="17">But as riders accelerate and decelerate, they experience more or less gravitational force.</s>
 <s id="18">Modern ride designers know that the body can handle up to roughly 5 Gs, but the Flip-Flap and its contemporaries routinely reached up to 12 Gs.</s>
 <s id="19">At those levels of gravitational pressure, blood is sent flying from your brain to your feet, leading to light-headedness or blackouts as the brain struggles to stay conscious.</s>
 <s id="20">And oxygen deprivation in the retinal cells impairs their ability to process light, causing greyed out vision or temporary blindness.</s>
 <s id="21">If the riders are upside down, blood can flood the skull, causing a bout of crimson vision called a “redout”.</s>
 <s id="22">Conversely, negative G’s create weightlessness.</s>
 <s id="23">Within the body, short-term weightlessness is mostly harmless.</s>
 <s id="24">It can contribute to a rider’s motion sickness by suspending the fluid in their inner ears which coordinates balance.</s>
 <s id="25">But the bigger potential danger – and thrill – comes from what ride designers call airtime.</s>
 <s id="26">This is when riders typically experience seat separation, and, without the proper precautions, ejection.</s>
 <s id="27">The numerous belts and harnesses of modern coasters have largely solved this issue, but the passenger’s ever-changing position can make it difficult to determine what needs to be strapped down.</s>
 <s id="28">Fortunately, modern ride designers are well aware of what your body, and the coaster, can handle.</s>
 <s id="29">Coaster engineers play these competing forces against each other, to relieve periods of intense pressure with periods of no pressure at all.</s>
 <s id="30">And since a quick transition from positive to negative G-force can result in whiplash, headaches, and back and neck pain, they avoid the extreme changes in speed and direction so common in thrill rides of old.</s>
 <s id="31">Modern rides are also much sturdier, closely considering the amount of gravity they need to withstand.</s>
 <s id="32">At 5 G’s, your body feels 5 times heavier; so if you weigh 100lbs, you’d exert the weight of 500 lbs on the coaster.</s>
 <s id="33">Engineers have to account for the multiplied weight of every passenger when designing a coaster’s supports.</s>
 <s id="34">Still, these rides aren’t for everyone.</s>
 <s id="35">The floods of adrenaline, light-headedness, and motion sickness aren’t going anywhere soon.</s>
 <s id="36">But today’s redundant restraints, 3D modeling and simulation software have made roller coasters safer and more thrilling than ever.</s>
 <s id="37">Our precise knowledge about the limits of the human body have helped us build coasters that are faster, taller, and loopier – and all without going off the rails.</s>
</text>
