<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Hercules, the strongest man alive with a mighty heart to match.</s>
 <s id="2">Orpheus, charmer of nature and master of music.</s>
 <s id="3">Castor and Pollux, the twin tricksters hatched from an egg.</s>
 <s id="4">The Boreads, sons of the North Wind who could hurtle through the air.</s>
 <s id="5">For untold times these heroes had roamed ancient Greece, creating new legends wherever they went.</s>
 <s id="6">But none of their adventures was so great as when they joined forces for the sake of a young man named Jason.</s>
 <s id="7">Years before, Jason’s uncle Pelias had ruthlessly usurped the throne of Thessaly from Jason’s grandfather.</s>
 <s id="8">When Jason returned to his father’s stolen court, the cowardly king set him a seemingly impossible task: cross the teeming seas to Colchis, and steal the golden fleece of a flying ram under King Aeetes’ nose.</s>
 <s id="9">If Jason retrieved the Fleece, Pelias promised to relinquish the throne.</s>
 <s id="10">Touched by his heroic mission, the Gods spread Jason’s call for help, and soon he had assembled a not-so-motley crew.</s>
 <s id="11">These heroes, alongside countless sailors, soothsayers, and rebel demigods, named themselves the Argonauts after their sturdy ship.</s>
 <s id="12">But the path ahead was marked with untold terrors– enough to test even the fiercest heroes.</s>
 <s id="13">Their first stop was Lemnos, an isle of women who had killed all the island’s men.</s>
 <s id="14">As punishment, Aphrodite had cursed them with a sickening stench– but that didn’t stop Jason fathering twins with the queen.</s>
 <s id="15">The rest of the crew also found themselves embroiled in new romances; until Hercules chastised them for not behaving like heroes.</s>
 <s id="16">Eventually, they sailed on to the Mount of Bears, an island where a group of ancient, six-armed monsters lived alongside the peaceful Doliones.</s>
 <s id="17">While the clan welcomed the Argonauts with open arms, the monsters surged down from the mountains and hurled rocks at the docked ship.</s>
 <s id="18">Hercules held them off single-handedly, before his comrades joined the fray.</s>
 <s id="19">Bolstered by their victory, the triumphant heroes sailed onward– only to be blown back to the island several stormy nights later.</s>
 <s id="20">In the tempest, the Doliones thought these new arrivals invaders.</s>
 <s id="21">The Argonauts were similarly unaware of their surroundings, and fought blunderingly in the dark, slaying wave after wave of foe.</s>
 <s id="22">But the morning light revealed a horrible truth: their victims were none other than their previous hosts.</s>
 <s id="23">Yet again, Jason had allowed the crew to be distracted, this time at a terrible cost.</s>
 <s id="24">Ashamed at his conduct, he resolved to focus only on the Fleece, but even this haste proved ruinous.</s>
 <s id="25">When Hercules’ squire was abducted by a water nymph, Jason sailed on– oblivious to the absence of his most powerful crewmate.</s>
 <s id="26">The remaining Argonauts continued their quest, until stopping at the sight of an old man surrounded by a swirl of harpies.</s>
 <s id="27">This was Phineas, a seer cursed by Zeus to endure old age, blindness, and endless torture for giving away his prophecies.</s>
 <s id="28">Moved by his plight, the wind brothers set upon the flock, providing Phineas with a brief respite from his punishment.</s>
 <s id="29">In return, the seer told them how to overcome the terrifying trial that lay ahead: the Symplegades, a pair clashing rocks that reduced ships to splinters.</s>
 <s id="30">But first, the Argonauts would have to maneuver past the mouth of hell, around the island of the bloodthirsty Amazons, and under psychedelic skies.</s>
 <s id="31">These adventures cost the crew both in men and morale– and some feared they might be losing their minds.</s>
 <s id="32">Upon reaching the clashing rocks, the exhausted crew quaked with fear.</s>
 <s id="33">But Phineas’ advice rang in their heads.</s>
 <s id="34">The Argonauts released a single dove and sped through in its wake to emerge unscathed.</s>
 <s id="35">With this narrow escape, the Argonauts finally had Colchis in their sights.</s>
 <s id="36">Yet while Jason rested and celebrated with his crew, he could feel his time among them was drawing to a close.</s>
 <s id="37">As the fleece gleamed in his mind, he knew he would have to retrieve it alone.</s>
 <s id="38">But he could not guess that this final task would have the most horrible price of all.</s>
</text>
