<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">We do not choose where to be born.</s>
 <s id="2">We do not choose who our parents are.</s>
 <s id="3">But we do choose how we are going to live our lives.</s>
 <s id="4">I did not choose to be born in South Sudan, a country rife with conflict.</s>
 <s id="5">I did not choose my name -- Nyiriak, which means "war."</s>
 <s id="6">I've always rejected it and all the legacy it was born into.</s>
 <s id="7">I choose to be called Mary.</s>
 <s id="8">As a teacher, I've stood in front of 120 students, so this stage does not intimidate me.</s>
 <s id="9">My students come from war-torn countries.</s>
 <s id="10">They're so different from each other, but they have one thing in common: they fled their homes in order to stay alive.</s>
 <s id="11">Some of them belong to parents back home in South Sudan who are killing each other because they belong to a different tribe or they have a different belief.</s>
 <s id="12">Others come from other African countries devastated by war.</s>
 <s id="13">But when they enter my class, they make friends, they walk home together, they do their homework together.</s>
 <s id="14">There is no hatred allowed in my class.</s>
 <s id="15">My story is like that of so many other refugees.</s>
 <s id="16">The war came when I was still a baby.</s>
 <s id="17">And my father, who had been absent in most of my early childhood, was doing what other men were doing: fighting for the country.</s>
 <s id="18">He had two wives and many children.</s>
 <s id="19">My mother was his second wife, married to him at the age of 16.</s>
 <s id="20">This is simply because my mother came from a poor background, and she had no choice.</s>
 <s id="21">My father, on the other hand, was rich.</s>
 <s id="22">He had many cows.</s>
 <s id="23">Gunshots were the order of the day.</s>
 <s id="24">My community was constantly under attack.</s>
 <s id="25">Communities would fight each other as they took water along the Nile.</s>
 <s id="26">But that was not all.</s>
 <s id="27">Planes would drop the spinning and terrifying bombs that chopped off people's limbs.</s>
 <s id="28">But the most terrifying thing for every single parent was to see their children being abducted and turned into young soldiers.</s>
 <s id="29">My mother dug a trench that soon became our home.</s>
 <s id="30">But yet, we did not feel protected.</s>
 <s id="31">She had to flee in search of a safe place for us.</s>
 <s id="32">I was four years old, and my younger sister was two.</s>
 <s id="33">We joined a huge mass of people, and together we walked for many agonizing days in search of a secure place.</s>
 <s id="34">But we could barely rest before we were attacked again.</s>
 <s id="35">I remember my mother was pregnant, when she would take turns to carry me and my younger sister.</s>
 <s id="36">We finally made it across the Kenyan border, yes.</s>
 <s id="37">But that was the longest journey that I have ever had in my whole life.</s>
 <s id="38">My feet were raw with blisters.</s>
 <s id="39">To our surprise, we found other family members who had fled into the camp earlier on, where you all are today, the Kakuma camp.</s>
 <s id="40">Now, I want you all to be very quiet just for a moment.</s>
 <s id="41">Do you hear that?</s>
 <s id="42">The sound of silence.</s>
 <s id="43">No gunshots.</s>
 <s id="44">Peace, at last.</s>
 <s id="45">That was my first memory of this camp.</s>
 <s id="46">When you move from a war zone and come to a secure place like Kakuma, you've really gone far.</s>
 <s id="47">I only stayed in the camp for three years, though.</s>
 <s id="48">My father, who had been absent in most of my early childhood, came back into my life.</s>
 <s id="49">And he organized for me to move with my uncle to our family in Nakuru.</s>
 <s id="50">There, I found my father's first wife, my half sisters and my half brothers.</s>
 <s id="51">I got enrolled in school.</s>
 <s id="52">I remember my first day in school -- I could sing and laugh again -- and my first set of school uniforms, you bet.</s>
 <s id="53">It was amazing.</s>
 <s id="54">But then I came to realize that my uncle did not find it fit for me to go to school, simply because I was a girl.</s>
 <s id="55">My half brothers were his first priority.</s>
 <s id="56">He would say, "Educating a girl is a waste of time."</s>
 <s id="57">And for that reason, I missed many days of school, because the fees were not paid.</s>
 <s id="58">My father stepped in and organized for me to go to boarding school.</s>
 <s id="59">I remember the faith that he put in me over the couple of years to come.</s>
 <s id="60">He would say, "Education is an animal that you have to overcome.</s>
 <s id="61">With an education, you can survive.</s>
 <s id="62">Education shall be your first husband."</s>
 <s id="63">And with these words came in his first big investment.</s>
 <s id="64">I felt lucky!</s>
 <s id="65">But I was missing something: my mother.</s>
 <s id="66">My mother had been left behind in the camp, and I had not seen her since I left it.</s>
 <s id="67">Six years without seeing her was really long.</s>
 <s id="68">I was alone, in school, when I heard of her death.</s>
 <s id="69">I've seen many people back in South Sudan lose their lives.</s>
 <s id="70">I've heard from neighbors lose their sons, their husbands, their children.</s>
 <s id="71">But I never thought that that would ever come into my life.</s>
 <s id="72">A month earlier, my stepmother, who had been so good to me back in Nakuru, died first.</s>
 <s id="73">Then I came to realize that after giving birth to four girls, my mother had finally given birth to something that could have made her be accepted into the community -- a baby boy, my baby brother.</s>
 <s id="74">But he, too, joined the list of the dead.</s>
 <s id="75">The most hurting part for me was the fact that I wasn't able to attend my mother's burial.</s>
 <s id="76">I wasn't allowed.</s>
 <s id="77">They said her family did not find it fit for her children, who are all girls, to attend her burial, simply because we were girls.</s>
 <s id="78">They would lament to me and say, "We are sorry, Mary, for your loss.</s>
 <s id="79">We are sorry that your parents never left behind any children."</s>
 <s id="80">And I would wonder: What are we?</s>
 <s id="81">Are we not children?</s>
 <s id="82">In the mentality of my community, only the boy child counted.</s>
 <s id="83">And for that reason, I knew this was the end of me.</s>
 <s id="84">But I was the eldest girl.</s>
 <s id="85">I had to take care of my siblings.</s>
 <s id="86">I had to ensure they went to school.</s>
 <s id="87">I was 13 years old.</s>
 <s id="88">How could I have made that happen?</s>
 <s id="89">I came back to the camp to take care of my siblings.</s>
 <s id="90">I've never felt so stuck.</s>
 <s id="91">But then, one of my aunts, Auntie Okoi, decided to take my sisters.</s>
 <s id="92">My father sent me money from Juba for me to go back to school.</s>
 <s id="93">Boarding school was heaven, but it was also so hard.</s>
 <s id="94">I remember during the visiting days when parents would come to school, and my father would miss.</s>
 <s id="95">But when he did come, he repeated the same faith in me.</s>
 <s id="96">This time he would say, "Mary, you cannot go astray, because you are the future of your siblings."</s>
 <s id="97">But then, in 2012, life took away the only thing that I was clinging on.</s>
 <s id="98">My father died.</s>
 <s id="99">My grades in school started to collapse, and when I sat for my final high school exams in 2015, I was devastated to receive a C grade.</s>
 <s id="100">OK, I keep telling students in my class, "It's not about the A's; it's about doing your best."</s>
 <s id="101">That was not my best.</s>
 <s id="102">I was determined.</s>
 <s id="103">I wanted to go back and try again.</s>
 <s id="104">But my parents were gone.</s>
 <s id="105">I had no one to take care of me, and I had no one to pay that fee.</s>
 <s id="106">I felt so hopeless.</s>
 <s id="107">But then, one of my best friends, a beautiful Kenyan lady, Esther Kaecha, called me during this devastating moment, and she was like, "Mary, you have a strong will.</s>
 <s id="108">And I have a plan, and it's going to work."</s>
 <s id="109">OK, when you're in those devastating moments, you accept anything, right?</s>
 <s id="110">So the plan was, she organized some travel money for us to travel to Anester Victory Girls High School.</s>
 <s id="111">I remember that day so well.</s>
 <s id="112">It was raining when we entered the principal's office.</s>
 <s id="113">We were shaking like two chickens that had been rained on, and we looked at him.</s>
 <s id="114">He was asking, "What do you want?"</s>
 <s id="115">And we looked at him with the cat face.</s>
 <s id="116">"We just want to go back to school."</s>
 <s id="117">Well, believe it or not, he not only paid our school fees but also our uniform and pocket money for food.</s>
 <s id="118">Clap for him.</s>
 <s id="119">(Applause) When I finished my high school career, I became the head girl.</s>
 <p id="p120">
  <s id="120.1">And when I sat for the KCSE for a second time, I was able to receive a B minus.</s>
  <s id="120.2">Clap.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="121">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="122">So I really want to say thank you to Anester Victory, Mr. Gatimu and the whole Anester fraternity for giving me that chance.</s>
 <s id="123">From time to time, members of my family will insist that my sister and I should get married so that somebody will take care of us.</s>
 <s id="124">They will say, "We have a man for you."</s>
 <s id="125">I really hate the fact that people took us as property rather than children.</s>
 <s id="126">Sometimes they will jokingly say, "You are going to lose your market value the more educated you become."</s>
 <s id="127">But the truth is, an educated woman is feared in my community.</s>
 <s id="128">But I told them, this is not what I want.</s>
 <s id="129">I don't want to get kids at 16 like my mother did.</s>
 <s id="130">This is not my life.</s>
 <s id="131">Even though my sisters and I are suffering, there's no way we are heading in that direction.</s>
 <s id="132">I refuse to repeat history.</s>
 <s id="133">Educating a girl will create equal and stable societies.</s>
 <s id="134">And educated refugees will be the hope of rebuilding their countries someday.</s>
 <s id="135">Girls and women have a part to play in this just as much as men.</s>
 <s id="136">Well, we have men in my family that encourage me to move on: my half brothers and also my half sisters.</s>
 <s id="137">When I finished my high school career, I moved my sisters to Nairobi, where they live with my stepsister.</s>
 <s id="138">They live 17 people in a house.</s>
 <s id="139">But don't pity us.</s>
 <s id="140">The most important thing is that they all get a decent education.</s>
 <s id="141">The winners of today are the losers of yesterday, but who never gave up.</s>
 <s id="142">And that is who we are, my sisters and I.</s>
 <s id="143">And I'm so proud of that.</s>
 <s id="144">My biggest investment in life -- (Applause) is the education of my sisters.</s>
 <s id="145">Education creates an equal and fair chance for everyone to make it.</s>
 <s id="146">I personally believe education is not all about the syllabus.</s>
 <s id="147">It's about friendship.</s>
 <s id="148">It's about discovering our talents.</s>
 <s id="149">It's about discovering our destiny.</s>
 <s id="150">I will, for example, not forget the joy that I had when I first had singing lessons in school, which is still a passion of mine.</s>
 <s id="151">But I wouldn't have gotten that anywhere else.</s>
 <s id="152">As a teacher, I see my classroom as a laboratory that not only generates skills and knowledge but also understanding and hope.</s>
 <s id="153">Let's take a tree.</s>
 <s id="154">A tree may have its branches cut, but give it water, and it will grow new branches.</s>
 <s id="155">For the child of war, an education can turn their tears of loss into a passion for peace.</s>
 <s id="156">And for that reason, I refuse to give up on a single student in my class.</s>
 <s id="157">(Applause) Education heals.</s>
 <s id="158">The school environment gives you a focus to focus ahead.</s>
 <s id="159">Let's take it this way: when you're busy solving mathematical equations, and you are memorizing poetry, you forget the violence that you witnessed back home.</s>
 <s id="160">And that is the power of education.</s>
 <s id="161">It creates this place for peace.</s>
 <s id="162">Kakuma is teeming with learners.</s>
 <s id="163">Over 85,000 students are enrolled in schools here, which makes up 40 percent of the refugee population.</s>
 <s id="164">It includes children who lost years of education because of the war back home.</s>
 <s id="165">And I want to ask you a question: If education is about building a generation of hope, why are there 120 students packed in my classroom?</s>
 <s id="166">Why is it that only six percent of the primary school students are making it to high school, simply because we do not have enough places for them?</s>
 <s id="167">And why is it that only one percent of the secondary school graduates are making it to university?</s>
 <s id="168">I began by saying that I am a teacher.</s>
 <s id="169">But once again, I have become a student.</s>
 <s id="170">In March, I moved to Rwanda on a scholarship program called "Bridge2Rwanda."</s>
 <s id="171">It prepares scholars for universities.</s>
 <s id="172">They are able to get a chance to compete for universities abroad.</s>
 <s id="173">I am now having teachers telling me what to do, instead of the other way round.</s>
 <s id="174">People are once again investing in me.</s>
 <s id="175">So I want to ask you all to invest in young refugees.</s>
 <s id="176">Think of the tree that we mentioned earlier.</s>
 <s id="177">We are the generation to plant it, so that the next generation can water it, and the one that follows will enjoy the shade.</s>
 <s id="178">They will reap the benefits.</s>
 <s id="179">And the greatest benefit of them all is an education that will last.</s>
 <s id="180">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="181">(Applause)</s>
</text>
