<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Way before the first selfie, the ancient Greeks and Romans had a myth about someone a little too obsessed with his own image.</s>
 <s id="2">In one telling, Narcissus was a handsome guy wandering the world in search of someone to love.</s>
 <s id="3">After rejecting a nymph named Echo, he caught a glimpse of his own reflection in a river, and fell in love with it.</s>
 <s id="4">Unable to tear himself away, Narcissus drowned.</s>
 <s id="5">A flower marked the spot of where he died, and we call that flower the Narcissus.</s>
 <s id="6">The myth captures the basic idea of narcissism, elevated and sometimes detrimental self-involvement.</s>
 <s id="7">But it's not just a personality type that shows up in advice columns.</s>
 <s id="8">It's actually a set of traits classified and studied by psychologists.</s>
 <s id="9">The psychological definition of narcissism is an inflated, grandiose self-image.</s>
 <s id="10">To varying degrees, narcissists think they're better looking, smarter, and more important than other people, and that they deserve special treatment.</s>
 <s id="11">Psychologists recognize two forms of narcissism as a personality trait: grandiose and vulnerable narcissism.</s>
 <s id="12">There's also narcissistic personality disorder, a more extreme form, which we'll return to shortly.</s>
 <s id="13">Grandiose narcissism is the most familiar kind, characterized by extroversion, dominance, and attention seeking.</s>
 <s id="14">Grandiose narcissists pursue attention and power, sometimes as politicians, celebrities, or cultural leaders.</s>
 <s id="15">Of course, not everyone who pursues these positions of power is narcissistic.</s>
 <s id="16">Many do it for very positive reasons, like reaching their full potential, or helping make people's lives better.</s>
 <s id="17">But narcissistic individuals seek power for the status and attention that goes with it.</s>
 <s id="18">Meanwhile, vulnerable narcissists can be quiet and reserved.</s>
 <s id="19">They have a strong sense of entitlement, but are easily threatened or slighted.</s>
 <s id="20">In either case, the dark side of narcissism shows up over the long term.</s>
 <s id="21">Narcissists tend to act selfishly, so narcissistic leaders may make risky or unethical decisions, and narcissistic partners may be dishonest or unfaithful.</s>
 <s id="22">When their rosy view of themselves is challenged, they can become resentful and aggressive.</s>
 <s id="23">It's like a disease where the sufferers feel pretty good, but the people around them suffer.</s>
 <s id="24">Taken to the extreme, this behavior is classified as a psychological disorder called narcissistic personality disorder.</s>
 <s id="25">It affects one to two percent of the population, more commonly men.</s>
 <s id="26">It is also a diagnosis reserved for adults.</s>
 <s id="27">Young people, especially children, can be very self-centered, but this might just be a normal part of development.</s>
 <s id="28">The fifth edition of the American Psychiatric Association's Diagnostic and Statistical Manual describes several traits associated with narcissistic personality disorder.</s>
 <s id="29">They include a grandiose view of oneself, problems with empathy, a sense of entitlement, and a need for admiration or attention.</s>
 <s id="30">What makes these trait a true personality disorder is that they take over people's lives and cause significant problems.</s>
 <s id="31">Imagine that instead of caring for your spouse or children, you used them as a source of attention or admiration.</s>
 <s id="32">Or imagine that instead of seeking constructive feedback about your performance, you instead told everyone who tried to help you that they were wrong.</s>
 <s id="33">So what causes narcissism?</s>
 <s id="34">Twin studies show a strong genetic component, although we don't know which genes are involved.</s>
 <s id="35">But environment matters, too.</s>
 <s id="36">Parents who put their child on a pedestal can foster grandiose narcissism.</s>
 <s id="37">And cold, controlling parents can contribute to vulnerable narcissism.</s>
 <s id="38">Narcissism also seems to be higher in cultures that value individuality and self-promotion.</s>
 <s id="39">In the United States, for example, narcissism as a personality trait has been rising since the 1970s, when the communal focus of the 60s gave way to the self-esteem movement and a rise in materialism.</s>
 <s id="40">More recently, social media has multiplied the possibilities for self-promotion, though it's worth noting that there's no clear evidence that social media causes narcissism.</s>
 <s id="41">Rather, it provides narcissists a means to seek social status and attention.</s>
 <s id="42">So can narcissists improve on those negative traits?</s>
 <s id="43">Yes!</s>
 <s id="44">Anything that promotes honest reflection on their own behavior and caring for others, like psychotherapy or practicing compassion towards others, can be helpful.</s>
 <s id="45">The difficulty is it can be challenging for people with narcissistic personality disorder to keep working at self-betterment.</s>
 <s id="46">For a narcissist, self-reflection is hard from an unflattering angle.</s>
</text>
