<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Sarah Parcak: A hundred years ago, archaeology was for the rich, fifty years ago it was for men.</s>
 <s id="2">But we are expanding it to the world.</s>
 <s id="3">I wish for us to discover the millions of unknown archaeological sites around the world.</s>
 <s id="4">By creating a 21st-century army of global explorers, we'll find and protect the world's hidden heritage.</s>
 <s id="5">So how are we going to do this?</s>
 <s id="6">[Great Big Story in partnership with TED] Narrator: They had a big idea to change the world.</s>
 <s id="7">But they couldn't do it alone.</s>
 <p id="p8">
  <s id="8.1">(Voices overlapping) So, my wish ...</s>
  <s id="8.2">My wish ...</s>
  <s id="8.3">I wish ...</s>
 </p>
 <s id="9">And now, here's my wish ...</s>
 <s id="10">[Torchbearers] [Ideas in action] SP: I am an archaeologist, and I specialize in using satellite imagery to map ancient landscapes.</s>
 <s id="11">The really fun title is space archaeology.</s>
 <s id="12">You of course want to record maybe how thick something is, which you can't measure from space, whether that's soil or snow.</s>
 <s id="13">When I won the prize, I had to present this completely crazy wish.</s>
 <s id="14">I had to present the case for archaeology to the world.</s>
 <s id="15">Why does it matter, so what?</s>
 <s id="16">The reality is, there aren't enough of us scientists, we've got to give more people opportunities to become explorers.</s>
 <s id="17">GlobalXplorer is an online crowdsourcing platform that allows anyone in the world to help map ancient sites by looking at satellite imagery.</s>
 <s id="18">And it's this idea that everyone in the world can make a contribution to science.</s>
 <s id="19">It can be anyone.</s>
 <s id="20">(Music) Doris Jones: I'm Doris Jones, I'm 90 years old, I live alone except for my two kitties.</s>
 <s id="21">And I need something to do.</s>
 <s id="22">I play games, I like sudoku.</s>
 <s id="23">And I play mahjong with friends on Friday.</s>
 <s id="24">(Music) And I'm an armchair archaeologist.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">Why don't you want to work?</s>
  <s id="25.2">Down.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">Down, let's work.</s>
 <s id="27">SP: Doris is one of our top contributors; she's a space archaeologist.</s>
 <s id="28">She's looked at many, many thousands of tiles.</s>
 <s id="29">People like her are just a gift to GlobalXplorer.</s>
 <s id="30">DJ: Right now, I'm looking at a tile, but ...</s>
 <s id="31">Well, it has a wall, probably for animals.</s>
 <s id="32">But it has a number of what look more like trails and roads.</s>
 <s id="33">I'll go to the next one.</s>
 <s id="34">SP: All you have to do is look at an image and look carefully, and you see that there could potentially be a new site there.</s>
 <s id="35">Doris just has this passion and energy, an excitement for exploration.</s>
 <s id="36">She's able to give back and really contribute in a meaningful way.</s>
 <s id="37">(Skype dial tone) SP: Doris!</s>
 <s id="38">DJ: Hi.</s>
 <s id="39">SP: I'm actually crying right now, because I'm overwhelmed with emotion.</s>
 <s id="40">DJ: Well, thank you.</s>
 <s id="41">SP: I just had to see your face and say, "Thank you."</s>
 <s id="42">DJ: I really admire what you're doing.</s>
 <s id="43">And I really enjoy the program.</s>
 <s id="44">SP: When did your love for archaeology and paleontology and science start?</s>
 <s id="45">DJ: Well, in the middle 50s my husband and I were in the backyard digging a garden.</s>
 <s id="46">It was late fall, and we were getting ready for next spring.</s>
 <s id="47">And I saw a strange-looking white rock on the ground.</s>
 <s id="48">I picked it up and he said, "Let me see that."</s>
 <s id="49">I showed it to him and he said, "You know what this is?"</s>
 <s id="50">I told him I didn't.</s>
 <s id="51">He said, "This is a fossil."</s>
 <s id="52">And we took out to the creek and started looking for fossils.</s>
 <s id="53">From then on, there was no turning back.</s>
 <s id="54">SP: That's wonderful.</s>
 <s id="55">DJ: So then I collected for years.</s>
 <s id="56">And after all those years, of course I've got all those memories.</s>
 <s id="57">But that's a type of thing ...</s>
 <s id="58">It's not just hunting the fossils but the experiences.</s>
 <s id="59">And you just learn and really live and enjoy.</s>
 <s id="60">And I think the fun is in the hunt.</s>
 <s id="61">You know, it's like ...</s>
 <s id="62">Well, like the rainbow -- at the end of the rainbow is a pot of gold.</s>
 <s id="63">So GlobalXplorer was kind of my rainbow.</s>
 <s id="64">And even at my age I can continue to hunt for lost civilizations.</s>
 <s id="65">SP: I want to tell you about some of the incredible things that happened as a result of your discoveries.</s>
 <s id="66">We're now beginning to take thousands of features that people like you have found and we're sharing them with archaeologists who work in Peru.</s>
 <s id="67">They're beginning to confirm the things the crowd has found.</s>
 <s id="68">So, in other words, the platform works.</s>
 <s id="69">Ultimately, this technology is helping us to rewrite our history.</s>
 <s id="70">DJ: We need to know our history.</s>
 <s id="71">We're all one peoples.</s>
 <s id="72">It's all our history, we're all here on this little ball of dirt.</s>
 <s id="73">SP: I believe we have barely scratched the surface in terms of what's left to discover.</s>
 <s id="74">And the greatest story ever told is the story of our shared human journey.</s>
 <s id="75">But the only way that we're going to be able to write it is if we do it together.</s>
 <s id="76">[Become a GlobalXplorer GlobalXplorer.org]</s>
</text>
