<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">This is a kindergarten we designed in 2007.</s>
 <s id="2">We made this kindergarten to be a circle.</s>
 <s id="3">It's a kind of endless circulation on top of the roof.</s>
 <s id="4">If you are a parent, you know that kids love to keep making circles.</s>
 <s id="5">This is how the rooftop looks.</s>
 <s id="6">And why did we design this?</s>
 <s id="7">The principal of this kindergarten said, "No, I don't want a handrail."</s>
 <s id="8">I said, "It's impossible."</s>
 <s id="9">But he insisted: "How about having a net sticking out from the edge of the roof?</s>
 <s id="10">So that it can catch the children falling off?"</s>
 <s id="11">(Laughter) I said, "It's impossible."</s>
 <s id="12">And of course, the government official said, "Of course you have to have a handrail."</s>
 <s id="13">But we could keep that idea around the trees.</s>
 <s id="14">There are three trees popping through.</s>
 <s id="15">And we were allowed to call this rope as a handrail.</s>
 <s id="16">But of course, rope has nothing to do with them.</s>
 <s id="17">They fall into the net.</s>
 <s id="18">And you get more, and more, more.</s>
 <s id="19">(Laughter) Sometimes 40 children are around a tree.</s>
 <s id="20">The boy on the branch, he loves the tree so he is eating the tree.</s>
 <s id="21">(Laughter) And at the time of an event, they sit on the edge.</s>
 <s id="22">It looks so nice from underneath.</s>
 <s id="23">Monkeys in the zoo.</s>
 <s id="24">(Laughter) Feeding time.</s>
 <s id="25">(Laughter) (Applause) And we made the roof as low as possible, because we wanted to see children on top of the roof, not only underneath the roof.</s>
 <s id="26">And if the roof is too high, you see only the ceiling.</s>
 <s id="27">And the leg washing place -- there are many kinds of water taps.</s>
 <s id="28">You see with the flexible tubes, you want to spray water to your friends, and the shower, and the one in front is quite normal.</s>
 <s id="29">But if you look at this, the boy is not washing his boots, he's putting water into his boots.</s>
 <s id="30">(Laughter) This kindergarten is completely open, most of the year.</s>
 <s id="31">And there is no boundary between inside and outside.</s>
 <s id="32">So it means basically this architecture is a roof.</s>
 <s id="33">And also there is no boundary between classrooms.</s>
 <s id="34">So there is no acoustic barrier at all.</s>
 <s id="35">When you put many children in a quiet box, some of them get really nervous.</s>
 <s id="36">But in this kindergarten, there is no reason they get nervous.</s>
 <s id="37">Because there is no boundary.</s>
 <s id="38">And the principal says if the boy in the corner doesn't want to stay in the room, we let him go.</s>
 <s id="39">He will come back eventually, because it's a circle, it comes back.</s>
 <s id="40">(Laughter) But the point is, in that kind of occasion, usually children try to hide somewhere.</s>
 <s id="41">But here, just they leave and come back.</s>
 <s id="42">It's a natural process.</s>
 <s id="43">And secondly, we consider noise very important.</s>
 <s id="44">You know that children sleep better in noise.</s>
 <s id="45">They don't sleep in a quiet space.</s>
 <s id="46">And in this kindergarten, these children show amazing concentration in class.</s>
 <s id="47">And you know, our kind grew up in the jungle with noise.</s>
 <s id="48">They need noise.</s>
 <s id="49">And you know, you can talk to your friends in a noisy bar.</s>
 <s id="50">You are not supposed to be in silence.</s>
 <s id="51">And you know, these days we are trying to make everything under control.</s>
 <s id="52">You know, it's completely open.</s>
 <s id="53">And you should know that we can go skiing in -20 degrees in winter.</s>
 <s id="54">In summer you go swimming.</s>
 <s id="55">The sand is 50 degrees.</s>
 <s id="56">And also, you should know that you are waterproof.</s>
 <s id="57">You never melt in rain.</s>
 <s id="58">So, children are supposed to be outside.</s>
 <s id="59">So that is how we should treat them.</s>
 <s id="60">This is how they divide classrooms.</s>
 <s id="61">They are supposed to help teachers.</s>
 <s id="62">They don't.</s>
 <s id="63">(Laughter) I didn't put him in.</s>
 <s id="64">A classroom.</s>
 <s id="65">And a washbasin.</s>
 <s id="66">They talk to each other around the well.</s>
 <s id="67">And there are always some trees in the classroom.</s>
 <s id="68">A monkey trying to fish another monkey from above.</s>
 <s id="69">(Laughter) Monkeys.</s>
 <s id="70">(Laughter) And each classroom has at least one skylight.</s>
 <s id="71">And this is where Santa Claus comes down at the time of Christmas.</s>
 <s id="72">This is the annex building, right next to that oval-shaped kindergarten.</s>
 <s id="73">The building is only five meters tall with seven floors.</s>
 <s id="74">And of course, the ceiling height is very low.</s>
 <s id="75">So you have to consider safety.</s>
 <s id="76">So, we put our children, a daughter and a son.</s>
 <s id="77">They tried to go in.</s>
 <s id="78">He hit his head.</s>
 <p id="p79">
  <s id="79.1">He's okay.</s>
  <s id="79.2">His skull is quite strong.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p80">
  <s id="80.1">He is resilient.</s>
  <s id="80.2">It's my son.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="81">(Laughter) And he is trying to see if it is safe to jump off.</s>
 <s id="82">And then we put other children.</s>
 <s id="83">The traffic jam is awful in Tokyo, as you know.</s>
 <s id="84">(Laughter) The driver in front, she needs to learn how to drive.</s>
 <s id="85">Now these days, kids need a small dosage of danger.</s>
 <s id="86">And in this kind of occasion, they learn to help each other.</s>
 <p id="p87">
  <s id="87.1">This is society.</s>
  <s id="87.2">This is the kind of opportunity we are losing these days.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="88">Now, this drawing is showing the movement of a boy between 9:10 and 9:30.</s>
 <s id="89">And the circumference of this building is 183 meters.</s>
 <s id="90">So it's not exactly small at all.</s>
 <s id="91">And this boy did 6,000 meters in the morning.</s>
 <s id="92">But the surprise is yet to come.</s>
 <s id="93">The children in this kindergarten do 4,000 meters on average.</s>
 <s id="94">And these children have the highest athletic abilities among many kindergartens.</s>
 <p id="p95">
  <s id="95.1">The principal says, "I don't train them.</s>
  <s id="95.2">We leave them on top of the roof.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="96">Just like sheep."</s>
 <s id="97">(Laughter) They keep running.</s>
 <s id="98">(Laughter) My point is don't control them, don't protect them too much, and they need to tumble sometimes.</s>
 <s id="99">They need to get some injury.</s>
 <s id="100">And that makes them learn how to live in this world.</s>
 <s id="101">I think architecture is capable of changing this world, and people's lives.</s>
 <s id="102">And this is one of the attempts to change the lives of children.</s>
 <s id="103">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="104">(Applause)</s>
</text>
