<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'll just take you to Bangladesh for a minute.</s>
 <s id="2">Before I tell that story, we should ask ourselves the question: Why does poverty exist?</s>
 <s id="3">I mean, there is plenty of knowledge and scientific breakthroughs.</s>
 <s id="4">We all live in the same planet, but there's still a great deal of poverty in the world.</s>
 <s id="5">And I think -- so I want to throw a perspective that I have, so that we can assess this project, or any other project, for that matter, to see whether it's contributing or -- contributing to poverty or trying to alleviate it.</s>
 <s id="6">Rich countries have been sending aid to poor countries for the last 60 years.</s>
 <s id="7">And by and large, this has failed.</s>
 <s id="8">And you can see this book, written by someone who worked in the World Bank for 20 years, and he finds economic growth in this country to be elusive.</s>
 <s id="9">By and large, it did not work.</s>
 <s id="10">So the question is, why is that?</s>
 <s id="11">In my mind, there is something to learn from the history of Europe.</s>
 <s id="12">I mean, even here, yesterday I was walking across the street, and they showed three bishops were executed 500 years ago, right across the street from here.</s>
 <s id="13">So my point is, there's a lot of struggle has gone in Europe, where citizens were empowered by technologies.</s>
 <s id="14">And they demanded authorities from -- to come down from their high horses.</s>
 <s id="15">And in the end, there's better bargaining between the authorities and citizens, and democracies, capitalism -- everything else flourished.</s>
 <s id="16">And so you can see, the real process of -- and this is backed up by this 500-page book -- that the authorities came down and citizens got up.</s>
 <s id="17">But if you look, if you have that perspective, then you can see what happened in the last 60 years.</s>
 <s id="18">Aid actually did the opposite.</s>
 <s id="19">It empowered authorities, and, as a result, marginalized citizens.</s>
 <s id="20">The authorities did not have the reason to make economic growth happen so that they could tax people and make more money for to run their business.</s>
 <s id="21">Because they were getting it from abroad.</s>
 <s id="22">And in fact, if you see oil-rich countries, where citizens are not yet empowered, the same thing goes -- Nigeria, Saudi Arabia, all sorts of countries.</s>
 <s id="23">Because the aid and oil or mineral money acts the same way.</s>
 <s id="24">It empowers authorities, without activating the citizens -- their hands, legs, brains, what have you.</s>
 <s id="25">And if you agree with that, then I think the best way to improve these countries is to recognize that economic development is of the people, by the people, for the people.</s>
 <s id="26">And that is the real network effect.</s>
 <s id="27">If citizens can network and make themselves more organized and productive, so that their voices are heard, so then things would improve.</s>
 <s id="28">And to contrast that, you can see the most important institution in the world, the World Bank, is an organization of the government, by the government, for the governments.</s>
 <s id="29">Just see the contrast.</s>
 <s id="30">And that is the perspective I have, and then I can start my story.</s>
 <s id="31">Of course, how would you empower citizens?</s>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">There could be all sorts of technologies.</s>
  <s id="32.2">And one is cell phones.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="33">Recently "The Economist" recognized this, but I stumbled upon the idea 12 years ago, and that's what I've been working on.</s>
 <s id="34">So 12 years ago, I was trying to be an investment banker in New York.</s>
 <s id="35">We had -- quite a few our colleagues were connected by a computer network.</s>
 <s id="36">And we got more productive because we didn't have to exchange floppy disks; we could update each other more often.</s>
 <s id="37">But one time it broke down.</s>
 <s id="38">And it reminded me of a day in 1971.</s>
 <s id="39">There was a war going on in my country.</s>
 <s id="40">And my family moved out of an urban place, where we used to live, to a remote rural area where it was safer.</s>
 <s id="41">And one time my mother asked me to get some medicine for a younger sibling.</s>
 <s id="42">And I walked 10 miles or so, all morning, to get there, to the medicine man.</s>
 <s id="43">And he wasn't there, so I walked all afternoon back.</s>
 <s id="44">So I had another unproductive day.</s>
 <s id="45">So while I was sitting in a tall building in New York, I put those two experiences together side by side, and basically concluded that connectivity is productivity -- whether it's in a modern office or an underdeveloped village.</s>
 <s id="46">So naturally, I -- the implication of that is that the telephone is a weapon against poverty.</s>
 <s id="47">And if that's the case, then the question is how many telephones did we have at that time?</s>
 <s id="48">And it turns out, that there was one telephone in Bangladesh for every 500 people.</s>
 <s id="49">And all those phones were in the few urban places.</s>
 <s id="50">The vast rural areas, where 100 million people lived, there were no telephones.</s>
 <s id="51">So just imagine how many man-months or man-years are wasted, just like I wasted a day.</s>
 <s id="52">If you just multiply by 100 million people, let's say losing one day a month, whatever, and you see a vast amount of resource wasted.</s>
 <s id="53">And after all, poor countries, like rich countries, one thing we've got equal, is their days are the same length: 24 hours.</s>
 <s id="54">So if you lose that precious resource, where you are somewhat equal to the richer countries, that's a huge waste.</s>
 <s id="55">So I started looking for any evidence that -- does connectivity really increase productivity?</s>
 <s id="56">And I couldn't find much, really, but I found this graph produced by the ITU, which is the International Telecommunication Union, based in Geneva.</s>
 <s id="57">They show an interesting thing.</s>
 <s id="58">That you see, the horizontal axis is where you place your country.</s>
 <s id="59">So the United States or the UK would be here, outside.</s>
 <s id="60">And so the impact of one new telephone, which is on the vertical axis, is very little.</s>
 <p id="p61">
  <s id="61.1">But if you come back to a poorer country, where the GNP per capita is, let's say, 500 dollars, or 300 dollars, then the impact is huge: 6,000 dollars.</s>
  <s id="61.2">Or 5,000 dollars.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="62">The question was, how much did it cost to install a new telephone in Bangladesh?</s>
 <s id="63">It turns out: 2,000 dollars.</s>
 <s id="64">So if you spend 2,000 dollars, and let's say the telephone lasts 10 years, and if 5,000 dollars every year -- so that's 50,000 dollars.</s>
 <s id="65">So obviously this was a gadget to have.</s>
 <s id="66">And of course, if the cost of installing a telephone is going down, because there's a digital revolution going on, then it would be even more dramatic.</s>
 <s id="67">And I knew a little economics by then -- it says Adam Smith taught us that specialization leads to productivity.</s>
 <s id="68">But how would you specialize?</s>
 <s id="69">Let's say I'm a fisherman and a farmer.</s>
 <p id="p70">
  <s id="70.1">And Chris is a fisherman farmer.</s>
  <s id="70.2">Both are generalists.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="71">So the point is that we could only -- the only way we could depend on each other, is if we can connect with each other.</s>
 <s id="72">And if we are neighbors, I could just walk over to his house.</s>
 <s id="73">But then we are limiting our economic sphere to something very small area.</s>
 <s id="74">But in order to expand that, you need a river, or you need a highway, or you need telephone lines.</s>
 <s id="75">But in any event, it's connectivity that leads to dependability.</s>
 <s id="76">And that leads to specialization.</s>
 <s id="77">That leads to productivity.</s>
 <s id="78">So the question was, I started looking at this issue, and going back and forth between Bangladesh and New York.</s>
 <s id="79">There were a lot of reasons people told me why we don't have enough telephones.</s>
 <s id="80">And one of them is the lacking buying power.</s>
 <s id="81">Poor people apparently don't have the power to buy.</s>
 <s id="82">But the point is, if it's a production tool, why do we have to worry about that?</s>
 <s id="83">I mean, in America, people buy cars, and they put very little money down.</s>
 <s id="84">They get a car, and they go to work.</s>
 <s id="85">The work pays them a salary; the salary allows them to pay for the car over time.</s>
 <s id="86">The car pays for itself.</s>
 <s id="87">So if the telephone is a production tool, then we don't quite have to worry about the purchasing power.</s>
 <s id="88">And of course, even if that's true, then what about initial buying power?</s>
 <s id="89">So then the question is, why can't we have some kind of shared access?</s>
 <s id="90">In the United States, we have -- everybody needs a banking service, but very few of us are trying to buy a bank.</s>
 <s id="91">So it's -- a bank tends to serve a whole community.</s>
 <s id="92">So we could do that for telephones.</s>
 <s id="93">And also people told me that we have a lot of important primary needs to meet: food, clothing, shelter, whatever.</s>
 <s id="94">But again, it's very paternalistic.</s>
 <s id="95">You should be raising income and let people decide what they want to do with their money.</s>
 <s id="96">But the real problem is the lack of other infrastructures.</s>
 <s id="97">See, you need some kind of infrastructure to bring a new thing.</s>
 <s id="98">For instance, the Internet was booming in the U.S.</s>
 <s id="99">because there were -- there were people who had computers.</s>
 <s id="100">They had modems.</s>
 <s id="101">They had telephone lines, so it's very easy to bring in a new idea, like the Internet.</s>
 <s id="102">But that's what's lacking in a poor country.</s>
 <s id="103">So for example, we didn't have ways to have credit checks, few banks to collect bills, etc.</s>
 <s id="104">But that's why I noticed Grameen Bank, which is a bank for poor people, and had 1,100 branches, 12,000 employees, 2.3 million borrowers.</s>
 <s id="105">And they had these branches.</s>
 <s id="106">I thought I could put cell towers and create a network.</s>
 <s id="107">And anyway, to cut the time short -- so I started -- I first went to them and said, "You know, perhaps I could connect all your branches and make you more efficient."</s>
 <p id="p108">
  <s id="108.1">But you know, they have, after all, evolved in a country without telephones, so they are decentralized.</s>
  <s id="108.2">I mean, of course there might be other good reasons, but this was one of the reasons -- they had to be.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="109">And so they were not that interested to connect all their branches, and then to be -- and rock the boat.</s>
 <p id="p110">
  <s id="110.1">So I started focusing.</s>
  <s id="110.2">What is it that they really do?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="111">So what happens is that somebody borrows money from the bank.</s>
 <p id="p112">
  <s id="112.1">She typically buys a cow.</s>
  <s id="112.2">The cow gives milk.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="113">And she sells the milk to the villagers, and pays off the loan.</s>
 <s id="114">And this is a business for her, but it's milk for everybody else.</s>
 <s id="115">And suddenly I realized that a cell phone could be a cow.</s>
 <s id="116">Because some way she could borrow 200 dollars from the bank, get a phone and have the phone for everybody.</s>
 <s id="117">And it's a business for her.</s>
 <s id="118">So I wrote to the bank, and they thought for a while, and they said, "It's a little crazy, but logical.</s>
 <s id="119">If you think it can be done, come and make it happen."</s>
 <s id="120">So I quit my job; I went back to Bangladesh.</s>
 <s id="121">I created a company in America called Gonofone, which in Bengali means "people's phone."</s>
 <s id="122">And angel investors in America put in money into that.</s>
 <s id="123">I flew around the world.</s>
 <s id="124">After about a million -- I mean, I got rejected from lots of places, because I was not only trying to go to a poor country, I was trying to go to the poor of the poor country.</s>
 <s id="125">After about a million miles, and a meaningful -- a substantial loss of hair, I eventually put together a consortium, and -- which involved the Norwegian telephone company, which provided the know-how, and the Grameen Bank provided the infrastructure to spread the service.</s>
 <s id="126">To make the story short, here is the coverage of the country.</s>
 <s id="127">You can see it's pretty much covered.</s>
 <s id="128">Even in Bangladesh, there are some empty places.</s>
 <s id="129">But we are also investing around another 300 million dollars this year to extend that coverage.</s>
 <s id="130">Now, about that cow model I talked about.</s>
 <s id="131">There are about 115,000 people who are retailing telephone services in their neighborhoods.</s>
 <s id="132">And it's serving 52,000 villages, which represent about 80 million people.</s>
 <s id="133">And these phones are generating about 100 million dollars for the company.</s>
 <s id="134">And two dollars profit per entrepreneur per day, which is like 700 dollars per year.</s>
 <s id="135">And of course, it's very beneficial in a lot of ways.</s>
 <s id="136">It increases income, improves welfare, etc.</s>
 <s id="137">And the result is, right now, this company is the largest telephone company, with 3.5 million subscribers, 115,000 of these phones I talked about -- that produces about a third of the traffic in the network.</s>
 <s id="138">And 2004, the net profit, after taxes -- very serious taxes -- was 120 million dollars.</s>
 <s id="139">And the company contributed about 190 million dollars to the government coffers.</s>
 <s id="140">And again, here are some of the lessons.</s>
 <s id="141">"The government needs to provide economically viable services."</s>
 <s id="142">Actually, this is an instance where private companies can provide that.</s>
 <s id="143">"Governments need to subsidize private companies."</s>
 <s id="144">This is what some people think.</s>
 <s id="145">And actually, private companies help governments with taxes.</s>
 <s id="146">"Poor people are recipients."</s>
 <s id="147">Poor people are a resource.</s>
 <s id="148">"Services cost too much for the poor."</s>
 <s id="149">Their involvement reduces the cost.</s>
 <s id="150">"The poor are uneducated and cannot do much."</s>
 <s id="151">They are very eager learners and very capable survivors.</s>
 <s id="152">I've been very surprised.</s>
 <s id="153">Most of them learn how to operate a telephone within a day.</s>
 <s id="154">"Poor countries need aid."</s>
 <s id="155">Businesses -- this one company has raised the -- if the ideal figures are even five percent true, this one company is raising the GNP of the country much more than the aid the country receives.</s>
 <s id="156">And as I was trying to show you, as far as I'm concerned, aid does damages because it removes the government from its citizens.</s>
 <s id="157">And this is a new project I have with Dean Kamen, the famous inventor in America.</s>
 <s id="158">He has produced some power generators, which we are now doing an experiment in Bangladesh, in two villages where cow manure is producing biogas, which is running these generators.</s>
 <s id="159">And each of these generators is selling electricity to 20 houses each.</s>
 <s id="160">It's just an experiment.</s>
 <s id="161">We don't know how far it will go, but it's going on.</s>
 <s id="162">Thank you.</s>
</text>
