<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">When we're young, we're innocently brave, and we fearlessly dream about what our lives might be like.</s>
 <s id="2">Maybe you wanted to be an astronaut or a rocket scientist.</s>
 <s id="3">Maybe you dreamed of traveling to every continent.</s>
 <s id="4">Since I was very young, I dreamed of working for the United Nations in some of the most difficult countries in the world.</s>
 <s id="5">And thanks to a lot of courage that dream came true.</s>
 <s id="6">But here's the thing about courage: it doesn't just appear whenever we need it.</s>
 <s id="7">It's the result of tough reflection and real work, involving the balance between fear and bravery.</s>
 <s id="8">Without fear, we'll do foolish things.</s>
 <s id="9">And without courage, we'll never step into the unknown.</s>
 <s id="10">The balance of the two is where the magic lies, and it's a balance we all deal with every day.</s>
 <s id="11">First, a word about my fancy wheels.</s>
 <s id="12">I haven't always used a wheelchair.</s>
 <s id="13">I grew up like many of you, running, jumping and dancing.</s>
 <s id="14">I love to dance.</s>
 <s id="15">However, in my mid-twenties, I began to experience a series of inexplicable falls.</s>
 <s id="16">And a few years later, I was diagnosed with a recessive genetic condition called hereditary inclusion body myopathy, or HIBM.</s>
 <s id="17">It's a progressive muscle wasting disease that affects all of my muscles from head to toe.</s>
 <s id="18">HIBM is very rare.</s>
 <s id="19">In the United States there are less than 200 people diagnosed.</s>
 <s id="20">To date, there is no proved treatment or cure, and within 10 to 15 years of its onset, HIBM typically leads to quadriplegia, which is why I now use a wheelchair.</s>
 <s id="21">When I was first diagnosed, everything changed.</s>
 <s id="22">It was frightening news because I had no experience with chronic illness or disabilities.</s>
 <s id="23">And I had no idea how the disease might progress.</s>
 <s id="24">But what was most disheartening was to listen to other people advise me to limit my ambitions and dreams, and to change my expectations of what to expect from life.</s>
 <s id="25">"You should quit your international career."</s>
 <s id="26">"No one will marry you this way."</s>
 <s id="27">"You would be selfish to have children."</s>
 <s id="28">The fact that someone who wasn't me was putting limitations on my dreams and ambitions was preposterous.</s>
 <s id="29">And unacceptable.</s>
 <s id="30">So I ignored them.</s>
 <s id="31">(Cheers and applause) I did get married.</s>
 <s id="32">And I decided for myself not to have children.</s>
 <s id="33">And I continued my career with the United Nations after my diagnosis, going to work for two years in Angola, a country recovering from 27 years of brutal civil war.</s>
 <s id="34">However, it would be another five years until I officially declared my diagnosis to my employer.</s>
 <s id="35">Because I was afraid that they would question my capacity to manage and I'd lose my job.</s>
 <s id="36">I was working in countries where polio had been common, so when I overheard someone say that they thought I might have survived polio, I thought my secret was safe.</s>
 <s id="37">No one asked why I was limping.</s>
 <s id="38">So I didn't say anything.</s>
 <s id="39">It took me over a decade to internalize the severity of HIBM, even as basic tasks and functions became increasingly difficult.</s>
 <s id="40">Yet, I continued to pursue my dream of working all over the world, and was even appointed as a disability focal point for UNICEF in Haiti, where I served for two years after the devastating 2010 earthquake.</s>
 <s id="41">And then my work brought me to the United States.</s>
 <s id="42">And even as the disease progressed significantly and I needed leg braces and a walker to get around, I still longed for adventure.</s>
 <s id="43">And this time, I started dreaming of a grand outdoor adventure.</s>
 <s id="44">And what's more grand than the Grand Canyon?</s>
 <s id="45">Did you know that for every five million people who visit the Rim only one percent go down to the canyon's base?</s>
 <s id="46">I wanted to be a part of that one percent.</s>
 <s id="47">The only thing is -- (Applause) The only thing is that the Grand Canyon isn't exactly accessible.</s>
 <s id="48">I was going to need some assistance to get down the 5,000-foot descent of vertical loose terrain.</s>
 <s id="49">Now, when I face obstacles, fear doesn't necessarily immediately set in because I assume that one way or another, I'll figure it out.</s>
 <s id="50">And in this case, my thought was, well, if I can't walk down, I could learn to ride a horse.</s>
 <s id="51">So that's what I did.</s>
 <s id="52">And with that fateful decision began a four-year commitment, tossing back and forth between fear and courage to undertake a 12-day expedition.</s>
 <s id="53">Four days on horseback to cross Grand Canyon rim to rim, and eight days rafting 150 miles of the Colorado River, all with a film crew in tow.</s>
 <s id="54">Spoiler alert -- we made it.</s>
 <s id="55">But not without showing me how my deepest fear can somehow manifest a mirror response of equal courage.</s>
 <s id="56">On April 13, 2018, sitting eight feet above the ground, riding a mustang horse named Sheriff, my first impression of Grand Canyon was one of shock and terror.</s>
 <s id="57">Who knew I had a fear of heights.</s>
 <s id="58">(Laughter) But there was no giving up now.</s>
 <s id="59">I mustered up every ounce of courage inside me to not let my fear get the best of me.</s>
 <s id="60">Embarking on the South Rim, all I could do to keep myself composed was to breathe deeply, stare up into the clouds and focus on my team's voices.</s>
 <s id="61">But then, in the first hour, disaster struck.</s>
 <s id="62">Unable to hold myself upright in the saddle, going down an oversized step, I flung forward and smacked my face on the back of the horse's head.</s>
 <s id="63">There was panic, my head hurt fiercely, but the path was too narrow for us to dismount.</s>
 <s id="64">Only at the halfway point at 2,300 feet, at least another two hours down, could we stop and remove my helmet and see the egg-sized bump protruding from my forehead.</s>
 <s id="65">For all of that planning and gear, how is it that we didn't even have an ice pack?</s>
 <s id="66">(Laughter) Luckily for all of us, the swelling came outwards, and would drain into my face as two fantastic black eyes which is an amazing way to look in a documentary film.</s>
 <s id="67">(Laughter) (Applause and cheers) This was not an easy, peaceful journey, and yet, that was exactly the point.</s>
 <s id="68">Even though I was afraid to get back into the saddle, I got back in.</s>
 <s id="69">The descent alone to the canyon floor took a total of 10 hours and that was just day one of four riding.</s>
 <s id="70">Next came the mighty rapids.</s>
 <s id="71">The Colorado River in the Grand Canyon has some of the highest white water in the country.</s>
 <s id="72">And just to be prepared in case we should capsize, we'd practice having me swim through a smaller rapid.</s>
 <s id="73">And it's safe to say it wasn't glamorous.</s>
 <s id="74">(Laughter) I took my breath in the wrong part of the wave, choked on river water and was unable to steer myself.</s>
 <s id="75">Yes, it was scary, but it was also fantastic.</s>
 <s id="76">Waterfalls, slick canyons and a couple billion years of bedrock that seemed to change color throughout the day.</s>
 <s id="77">The Grand Canyon is true wilderness and worthy of all of its accolades.</s>
 <s id="78">(Applause) The expedition, all that planning and the trip itself, showed me a level of fear I had never experienced before.</s>
 <s id="79">But more importantly, it showed me how boldly courageous I can be.</s>
 <s id="80">My Grand Canyon journey was not easy.</s>
 <s id="81">This was not a vision of an Amazonian woman effortlessly making her way through epic scenery.</s>
 <s id="82">This was me crying, exhausted and beat up with two black eyes.</s>
 <s id="83">It was scary, it was stressful, it was exhilarating.</s>
 <s id="84">Now that the trip is over, it's easy to be blasé about what we achieved.</s>
 <s id="85">I know I want to raft the river again.</s>
 <s id="86">This time, all 277 miles of it.</s>
 <s id="87">(Applause) But I also know that I would never do the horseback-riding part again.</s>
 <s id="88">(Laughter) It's just too dangerous.</s>
 <s id="89">And that's my real point.</s>
 <s id="90">I'm not just here to show you my film footage.</s>
 <s id="91">I'm here to remind us all that life is really just a lesson in finding the balance between fear and courage.</s>
 <s id="92">And understanding what is and what isn't a good idea.</s>
 <s id="93">(Laughter) Life is already scary, so for our dreams to come true, we need to be brave.</s>
 <s id="94">In facing my fears and finding the courage to push through them, I swear my life has been extraordinary.</s>
 <s id="95">So live big and try to let your courage outweigh your fear.</s>
 <s id="96">You never know where it might take you.</s>
 <s id="97">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="98">(Applause and cheers)</s>
</text>
