<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Some years ago, I was visiting Paris and walking along the Seine River during a beautiful summer afternoon.</s>
 <s id="2">I saw giant bubbles floating on the riverbank, like this one.</s>
 <s id="3">The next moment, it popped and was gone.</s>
 <s id="4">Making them were two street performers surrounded by a crowd.</s>
 <s id="5">They visibly make a living by asking for donations and by selling pairs of sticks tied with two strings.</s>
 <s id="6">When I was there, a man bought a pair of sticks for 10 euros, which surprised me.</s>
 <s id="7">I am a scientist who is passionate about bubbles.</s>
 <s id="8">I know the right trick to make the giant bubbles is the right soapy water mixture itself -- not the sticks, which may be needed, but you can easily make them at home.</s>
 <s id="9">Focusing on the sticks makes us not see that the real tool is the bubble itself.</s>
 <s id="10">Bubbles might seem like something just children make while playing, but sometimes it can be really stunning.</s>
 <s id="11">However, there are more fascinating science to bubbles, such as problem-solving tools.</s>
 <s id="12">So I would like to share with you a few stories about the science of creating bubbles and the science of eliminating the microscopic ones.</s>
 <s id="13">Since it's up on the screen, let's start with the soap bubble.</s>
 <s id="14">It is made from very common substances: air, water, soap, in the right mixture.</s>
 <s id="15">You can see soap bubbles constantly changing their colors.</s>
 <s id="16">This is due to the interaction with light at various directions and the changes of their thickness.</s>
 <s id="17">One of the common substances, water molecules, are formed by two atoms of hydrogen and one atom of oxygen -- H2O.</s>
 <s id="18">On most surfaces, water droplets tend to curve inwards, forming a semihemisphere shape.</s>
 <s id="19">This is because the water droplet's surface is like an elastic sheet.</s>
 <s id="20">The water molecule on the surface is constantly being pulled inwards by the molecule at the center.</s>
 <s id="21">And the quality of the elasticity is what we call "surface tension."</s>
 <s id="22">Now by adding soap, what happens is the soap molecule reduces the surface tension of water, making it more elastic and easier to form bubbles.</s>
 <s id="23">You can think of a bubble as a mathematical problem-solver.</s>
 <s id="24">You see it relentlessly trying to achieve geometry perfection.</s>
 <s id="25">For instance, a sphere is the shape with the least surface area for a given volume.</s>
 <s id="26">That's why a single bubble is always in the shape of a sphere.</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">Let me show you.</s>
  <s id="27.2">Check it out.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="28">This is a single bubble.</s>
 <s id="29">When two bubbles touch each other, they can save materials by sharing a common wall.</s>
 <s id="30">When more and more bubbles are added together, their geometry changes.</s>
 <s id="31">These four bubbles are added together.</s>
 <s id="32">They meet at one point at the center.</s>
 <s id="33">When six bubbles are added together, a magical cube appears at the center.</s>
 <s id="34">(Applause) That is surface tension at work, trying to find the most effective geometry arrangement.</s>
 <s id="35">Now, let me give you another example.</s>
 <s id="36">This is a very simple prop.</s>
 <s id="37">This is made from two layers of plastic with four pins connected to each other.</s>
 <s id="38">Imagine these four pins represent four cities that are equally apart, and we would like to make roads to connect these four cities.</s>
 <s id="39">My question is: What is the shortest length to connect these four cities?</s>
 <s id="40">Let's find out the answer by dipping it into the soapy water.</s>
 <s id="41">Remember, the soap bubble forms will always try to minimize their surface area with a perfect geometry arrangement.</s>
 <s id="42">So the solution might not be something you expected.</s>
 <s id="43">The shortest length to connect these four cities is 2.73 times the distance between these two cities.</s>
 <s id="44">(Applause) Now you've got the idea.</s>
 <s id="45">The soap bubble forms will always try to minimize their surface area with a perfect geometry arrangement.</s>
 <s id="46">Now, let us look at bubbles in another perspective.</s>
 <s id="47">My daughter, Zoe, loves visiting zoos.</s>
 <s id="48">Her favorite spot is Penguin Cove at Marwell Zoo in Southern England, where she could see penguins swim at speed under the water.</s>
 <s id="49">One day, she noticed that the body of penguins leaves a trail of bubbles when they swim and asked why.</s>
 <s id="50">Animals and birds like penguins that spend a lot of their time under the water have evolved an ingenious way of utilizing the capability of bubbles to reduce the density of water.</s>
 <s id="51">Emperor penguins are thought to be able to dive a few hundred meters below the sea surface.</s>
 <s id="52">They are thought to store the air under their feathers before they dive and then progressively release it as a cloud of bubbles.</s>
 <s id="53">This reduces the density of water surrounding them, making it easier to swim through and speed up their swimming speed at least 40 percent.</s>
 <s id="54">This feature has been noticed by the ship manufacturers.</s>
 <s id="55">I am talking about the big ships here, the ones that are used to transport thousands of containers across the ocean.</s>
 <s id="56">Recently, they developed a system called "air lubricating system," inspired by the penguins.</s>
 <s id="57">In this system, they produce a lot of air bubbles and redistribute them across the whole of the ship, like an air carpet that reduces the water resistance when a ship is moving.</s>
 <s id="58">This feature cuts off the energy consumption for the ship up to 15 percent.</s>
 <s id="59">Bubbles can also be used for medicines.</s>
 <s id="60">It can also play a role in medicines, for instance, as a method for noninvasive delivery systems for drugs and genes to a specific part of the body.</s>
 <s id="61">Imagine a microbubble filled with a mixture of drugs and magnetic agents being injected into our bloodstream.</s>
 <s id="62">The bubbles will move to the target areas.</s>
 <s id="63">But how do they know where to go?</s>
 <s id="64">Because we placed a magnet there.</s>
 <s id="65">For instance, this part of my hand.</s>
 <s id="66">When the microbubbles move to this part of my hand, we can pop it via ultrasound and release the drug exactly where it's needed.</s>
 <s id="67">Now, I mentioned about the science of creating bubbles.</s>
 <s id="68">But sometimes we also need to remove them.</s>
 <s id="69">That's actually part of my job.</s>
 <s id="70">My exact job title is "ink formulation scientist."</s>
 <s id="71">But I don't work on the ink that you use for your writing pens.</s>
 <s id="72">I'm working on some cool applications such as organic photovoltaics, OPVs, and organic light-emitting diodes, OLEDs.</s>
 <s id="73">Part of my job is to figure out how and why we want to remove the bubbles from the ink that my company produces.</s>
 <s id="74">During the formulation-mixing process, or preparation process, we mix active ingredients, solvents and additives in order to achieve the formulations with the properties we want when the ink is being used.</s>
 <s id="75">But just like you would make drinks or bake cakes, it is unavoidable that some air bubbles will be trapped inside that ink.</s>
 <s id="76">Here, we are talking about a different space from the bubbles I'd seen in Paris.</s>
 <s id="77">The bubbles that are trapped inside those inks vary between a few millimeters, a few microns or even a few nanometers in size.</s>
 <s id="78">And what we are concerned about is the oxygen and the moisture that is trapped inside.</s>
 <s id="79">At this size scale, removing them is not easy.</s>
 <s id="80">But it matters, for instance, for organic light-emitting diodes inks that we can use to produce display for your smartphone, for example.</s>
 <s id="81">It's supposed to last for many years, but if the ink that we use has been absorbed with oxygen and moisture [which] are not being removed, then we can quickly see dark spots appear in the pixels.</s>
 <s id="82">Now, one challenge we face in removing the microbubbles is that they are not very cooperative.</s>
 <s id="83">They like to sit there, bathing in the ink without moving much.</s>
 <s id="84">But how do we kick them out?</s>
 <s id="85">One technology we use is to force the ink going through a thin, long and tiny tube with a porous wall, and we place the tubes inside the vacuum chamber, so that the bubbles can be squeezed out from the ink and be removed.</s>
 <s id="86">Once we manage to remove the bubbles from the ink that we produce, it is time for celebration.</s>
 <s id="87">Let's open a bubbling champagne.</s>
 <s id="88">Ooh, this is going to be fun!</s>
 <s id="89">(Laughter) Woooo!</s>
 <s id="90">(Applause) You could see a lot of bubbles rushing out from the champagne bottle.</s>
 <s id="91">These are the bubbles filled with carbon dioxide, a gas that's been produced during the fermentation process of the wine.</s>
 <s id="92">Let me pour some out.</s>
 <s id="93">I can't miss the chance.</s>
 <s id="94">I guess it's enough.</s>
 <s id="95">(Laughter) Here, I can see a lot of microbubbles moving from the bottom of the glass to the top of the champagne.</s>
 <s id="96">Before it pops, it will jet tiny droplets of aroma molecules and intensify the flavor of champagne, making us enjoy much more the flavor of champagne.</s>
 <s id="97">As a scientist who is passionate about bubbles, I love to see them, I love to play with them, and I love to study them.</s>
 <s id="98">And also, I love to drink them.</s>
 <s id="99">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="100">(Applause)</s>
</text>
