<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In 1956, during a diplomatic reception in Moscow, Soviet leader Nikita Khrushchev told Western Bloc ambassadors, "My vas pokhoronim!"</s>
 <s id="2">His interpreter rendered that into English as, "We will bury you!"</s>
 <s id="3">This statement sent shockwaves through the Western world, heightening the tension between the Soviet Union and the US who were in the thick of the Cold War.</s>
 <s id="4">Some believe this incident alone set East/West relations back a decade.</s>
 <s id="5">As it turns out, Khrushchev's remark was translated a bit too literally.</s>
 <s id="6">Given the context, his words should have been rendered as, "We will live to see you buried," meaning that Communism would outlast Capitalism, a less threatening comment.</s>
 <s id="7">Though the intended meaning was eventually clarified, the initial impact of Khrushchev's apparent words put the world on a path that could have led to nuclear armageddon.</s>
 <s id="8">So now, given the complexities of language and cultural exchange, how does this sort of thing not happen all the time?</s>
 <s id="9">Much of the answer lies with the skill and training of interpreters to overcome language barriers.</s>
 <s id="10">For most of history, interpretation was mainly done consecutively, with speakers and interpreters making pauses to allow each other to speak.</s>
 <s id="11">But after the advent of radio technology, a new simultaneous interpretations system was developed in the wake of World War II.</s>
 <s id="12">In the simultaneous mode interpreters instantaneously translate a speaker's words into a microphone while he speaks.</s>
 <s id="13">Without pauses, those in the audience can choose the language in which they want to follow.</s>
 <s id="14">On the surface, it all looks seamless, but behind the scenes, human interpreters work incessantly to ensure every idea gets across as intended.</s>
 <s id="15">And that is no easy task.</s>
 <s id="16">It takes about two years of training for already fluent bilingual professionals to expand their vocabulary and master the skills necessary to become a conference interpreter.</s>
 <s id="17">To get used to the unnatural task of speaking while they listen, students shadow speakers and repeat their every word exactly as heard in the same language.</s>
 <s id="18">In time, they begin to paraphrase what is said, making stylistic adjustments as they go.</s>
 <s id="19">At some point, a second language is introduced.</s>
 <s id="20">Practicing in this way creates new neural pathways in the interpreter's brain, and the constant effort of reformulation gradually becomes second nature.</s>
 <s id="21">Over time and through much hard work, the interpreter masters a vast array of tricks to keep up with speed, deal with challenging terminology, and handle a multitude of foreign accents.</s>
 <s id="22">They may resort to acronyms to shorten long names, choose generic terms over specific, or refer to slides and other visual aides.</s>
 <s id="23">They can even leave a term in the original language, while they search for the most accurate equivalent.</s>
 <s id="24">Interpreters are also skilled at keeping aplomb in the face of chaos.</s>
 <s id="25">Remember, they have no control over who is going to say what, or how articulate the speaker will sound.</s>
 <s id="26">A curveball can be thrown at any time.</s>
 <s id="27">Also, they often perform to thousands of people and in very intimidating settings, like the UN General Assembly.</s>
 <s id="28">To keep their emotions in check, they carefully prepare for an assignment, building glossaries in advance, reading voraciously about the subject matter, and reviewing previous talks on the topic.</s>
 <s id="29">Finally, interpreters work in pairs.</s>
 <s id="30">While one colleague is busy translating incoming speeches in real time, the other gives support by locating documents, looking up words, and tracking down pertinent information.</s>
 <s id="31">Because simultaneous interpretation requires intense concentration, every 30 minutes, the pair switches roles.</s>
 <s id="32">Success is heavily dependent on skillful collaboration.</s>
 <s id="33">Language is complex, and when abstract or nuanced concepts get lost in translation, the consequences may be catastrophic.</s>
 <s id="34">As Margaret Atwood famously noted, "War is what happens when language fails."</s>
 <s id="35">Conference interpreters of all people are aware of that and work diligently behind the scenes to make sure it never does.</s>
</text>
