<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I want to talk to you about something kind of big.</s>
 <s id="2">We'll start here.</s>
 <s id="3">Sixty-five million years ago -- (Laughter) the dinosaurs had a bad day.</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) A chunk of rock six miles across, moving something like 50 times the speed of a rifle bullet, slammed into the Earth.</s>
 <s id="5">It released its energy all at once, and it was an explosion that was mind-numbing.</s>
 <s id="6">If you took every nuclear weapon ever built at the height of the Cold War, lumped them together, and blew them up at the same time, that would be one one-millionth of the energy released at that moment.</s>
 <s id="7">The dinosaurs had a really bad day.</s>
 <s id="8">OK?</s>
 <s id="9">Now, a six-mile-wide rock is very large.</s>
 <s id="10">We all live here in Boulder.</s>
 <s id="11">If you look out your window and see Longs Peak -- you're probably familiar with it -- now, scoop up Longs Peak and put it out in space.</s>
 <p id="p12">
  <s id="12.1">Take ...</s>
  <s id="12.2">Meeker, Mt.</s>
  <s id="12.3">Meeker.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="13">Lump that in there, and put that in space as well.</s>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">And Mt.</s>
  <s id="14.2">Everest.</s>
  <s id="14.3">And K2.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="15">And the Indian peaks.</s>
 <s id="16">Then you're starting to get an idea of how much rock we're talking about, OK?</s>
 <s id="17">We know it was that big because of the impact it had and the crater it left.</s>
 <s id="18">It hit in what we now know as Yucatan, the Gulf of Mexico.</s>
 <s id="19">You can see here, there's the Yucatan Peninsula, if you recognize Cozumel off the east coast there.</s>
 <s id="20">Here is how big of a crater was left.</s>
 <s id="21">It was huge.</s>
 <s id="22">To give you a sense of the scale ... there you go.</s>
 <s id="23">The scale here is 50 miles on top, a hundred kilometers on the bottom.</s>
 <s id="24">This thing was 300 kilometers across -- 200 miles -- an enormous crater that excavated out vast amounts of earth that splashed around the globe and set fires all over the planet, threw up enough dust to block out the sun.</s>
 <s id="25">It wiped out 75 percent of all species on Earth.</s>
 <s id="26">Now, not all asteroids are that big.</s>
 <s id="27">Some of them are smaller.</s>
 <s id="28">Here is one that came in over the United States in October of 1992.</s>
 <s id="29">It came in on a Friday night.</s>
 <s id="30">Why is that important?</s>
 <s id="31">Because back then, video cameras were just starting to become popular, and parents would bring them to their kids' football games to film their kids playing football.</s>
 <s id="32">And since this came in on a Friday, they were able to get this great footage of this thing breaking up as it came in over West Virginia, Maryland, Pennsylvania and New Jersey until it did that to a car in New York.</s>
 <s id="33">(Laughter) Now, this is not a 200-mile-wide crater, but then again, you can see the rock, which is sitting right here, about the size of a football, that hit that car and did that damage.</s>
 <s id="34">Now, this thing was probably about the size of a school bus when it first came in.</s>
 <s id="35">It broke up through atmospheric pressure, it crumbled, and then the pieces fell apart and did some damage.</s>
 <s id="36">Now, you wouldn't want that falling on your foot or your head, because it would do that to it.</s>
 <s id="37">That would be bad.</s>
 <s id="38">But it won't wipe out, you know, all life on Earth, so that's fine.</s>
 <s id="39">But it turns out, you don't need something six miles across to do a lot of damage.</s>
 <s id="40">There is a median point between tiny rock and gigantic rock, and in fact, if any of you have ever been to near Winslow, Arizona, there is a crater in the desert there that is so iconic that it is actually called "Meteor Crater."</s>
 <s id="41">To give you a sense of scale, this is about a mile wide.</s>
 <s id="42">If you look up at the top, that's a parking lot, and those are recreational vehicles right there.</s>
 <s id="43">So it's about a mile across, 600 feet deep.</s>
 <s id="44">The object that formed this was probably about 30 to 50 yards across, so roughly the size of Macky Auditorium here.</s>
 <s id="45">It came in at speeds that were tremendous, slammed into the ground, blew up, and exploded with the energy of roughly a 20-megaton nuclear bomb -- a very hefty bomb.</s>
 <s id="46">This was 50,000 years ago, so it may have wiped out a few buffalo or antelope, or something like that out in the desert, but it probably would not have caused global devastation.</s>
 <s id="47">It turns out that these things don't have to hit the ground to do a lot of damage.</s>
 <s id="48">Now, in 1908, over Siberia, near the Tunguska region -- for those of you who are Dan Aykroyd fans and saw "Ghostbusters," when he talked about the greatest cross-dimensional rift since the Siberia blast of 1909, where he got the date wrong, but that's OK.</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">(Laughter) It was 1908.</s>
  <s id="49.2">That's fine.</s>
  <s id="49.3">I can live with that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">(Laughter) Another rock came into the Earth's atmosphere and this one blew up above the ground, several miles up above the surface of the Earth.</s>
 <s id="51">The heat from the explosion set fire to the forest below it, and then the shock wave came down and knocked down trees for hundreds of square miles.</s>
 <s id="52">This did a huge amount of damage.</s>
 <s id="53">And again, this was a rock probably roughly the size of this auditorium that we're sitting in.</s>
 <s id="54">In Meteor Crater, it was made of metal, and metal is much tougher, so it made it to the ground.</s>
 <s id="55">The one over Tunguska was probably made of rock, and that's much more crumbly, so it blew up in the air.</s>
 <s id="56">Either way, these are tremendous explosions -- 20 megatons.</s>
 <s id="57">Now, when these things blow up, they're not going to do global ecological damage.</s>
 <s id="58">They're not going to do something like the dinosaur killer did.</s>
 <s id="59">They're just not big enough.</s>
 <s id="60">But they will do global economic damage, because they don't have to hit, necessarily, to do this kind of damage.</s>
 <s id="61">They don't have to do global devastation.</s>
 <s id="62">If one of these things were to hit pretty much anywhere, it would cause a panic.</s>
 <s id="63">But if it came over a city, an important city -- not that any city is more important than others, but some of them we depend on more on the global economic basis -- that could do a huge amount of damage to us as a civilization.</s>
 <s id="64">So, now that I've scared the crap out of you -- (Laughter) what can we do about this?</s>
 <s id="65">This is a potential threat.</s>
 <s id="66">Let me note that we have not had a giant impact like the dinosaur killer for 65 million years.</s>
 <s id="67">They're very rare.</s>
 <s id="68">The smaller ones happen more often, but probably on the order of a millennium, every few centuries or every few thousand years.</s>
 <s id="69">But it's still something to be aware of.</s>
 <s id="70">Well, what do we do about them?</s>
 <s id="71">The first thing we have to do is find them.</s>
 <s id="72">This is an image of an asteroid that passed us in 2009.</s>
 <s id="73">It's right here.</s>
 <s id="74">But you can see that it's extremely faint.</s>
 <s id="75">I don't know if you can see that in the back row.</s>
 <s id="76">These are just stars.</s>
 <s id="77">This is a rock that was about 30 yards across, so roughly the size of the ones that blew up over Tunguska and hit Arizona 50,000 years ago.</s>
 <s id="78">These things are faint.</s>
 <s id="79">They're hard to see, and the sky is really big.</s>
 <s id="80">We have to find these things first.</s>
 <s id="81">Well, the good news is, we're looking for them.</s>
 <s id="82">NASA has devoted money to this; the National Science Foundation and other countries are interested in doing this.</s>
 <s id="83">We're building telescopes that are looking for the threat.</s>
 <p id="p84">
  <s id="84.1">That's a great first step.</s>
  <s id="84.2">But what's the second step?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="85">The second step is if we see one heading toward us, we have to stop it.</s>
 <s id="86">What do we do?</s>
 <s id="87">You've probably heard about the asteroid Apophis.</s>
 <s id="88">If you haven't yet, you will.</s>
 <s id="89">If you've heard about the Mayan 2012 apocalypse, you're going to hear about Apophis, because you're keyed in to all the doomsday networks, anyway.</s>
 <s id="90">(Laughter) Apophis is an asteroid that was discovered in 2004.</s>
 <s id="91">It's roughly 250 [meters] across, so it's pretty big -- bigger than a football stadium.</s>
 <s id="92">And it's going to pass by the Earth in April of 2029.</s>
 <s id="93">And it's going to pass us so close that it's actually going to come underneath our weather satellites.</s>
 <s id="94">The Earth's gravity is going to bend the orbit of this thing so much that if it's just right, if it passes through this region of space, this kidney-bean-shaped region called the keyhole, the Earth's gravity will bend it just enough that seven years later, on April 13 -- which is a Friday, I'll note -- in the year 2036 -- (Laughter) you can't plan that kind of stuff -- (Laughter) Apophis is going to hit us.</s>
 <s id="95">And it's 250 meters across, so it would do unbelievable damage.</s>
 <s id="96">The good news is that the odds of it actually passing through this keyhole and hitting us next go-around are one in a million, roughly -- very, very low odds.</s>
 <s id="97">So I personally am not lying awake at night worrying about this at all.</s>
 <s id="98">I don't think Apophis is a problem.</s>
 <s id="99">In fact, Apophis is a blessing in disguise, because it woke us up to the dangers of these things.</s>
 <s id="100">This thing was discovered just a few years ago and could hit us a few years from now.</s>
 <s id="101">It won't, but it gives us a chance to study these kinds of asteroids.</s>
 <s id="102">We didn't really necessarily understand these keyholes, and now we do, and it turns out that's really important, because how do you stop an asteroid like this?</s>
 <s id="103">Well, let me ask you: What happens if you're standing in the road and a car's headed for you?</s>
 <s id="104">What do you do?</s>
 <p id="p105">
  <s id="105.1">You do this.</s>
  <s id="105.2">Right?</s>
  <s id="105.3">Move, and the car goes past you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="106">But we can't move the Earth, at least not easily, but we can move a small asteroid.</s>
 <s id="107">And it turns out, we've even done it.</s>
 <s id="108">In the year 2005, NASA launched a probe called Deep Impact, which slammed a piece of itself into the nucleus of a comet.</s>
 <s id="109">Comets are very much like asteroids.</s>
 <s id="110">The purpose wasn't to push it out of the way; the purpose was to make a crater to excavate the material and see what was underneath the surface of this comet, which we learned quite a bit about.</s>
 <s id="111">We did move the comet a little tiny bit -- not very much, but that wasn't the point.</s>
 <s id="112">However, think about this: This thing is orbiting the Sun at 10, 20 miles per second.</s>
 <s id="113">We shot a space probe at it and hit it, OK?</s>
 <s id="114">Imagine how hard that must be, and we did it.</s>
 <s id="115">That means we can do it again.</s>
 <s id="116">If we see an asteroid that's coming toward us, headed right for us, and we have two years to go?</s>
 <p id="p117">
  <s id="117.1">Boom!</s>
  <s id="117.2">We hit it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="118">You know, if you watch the movies -- (Laughter) you might think: Why don't we use a nuclear weapon?</s>
 <s id="119">Well, you can try that, but the problem is timing.</s>
 <s id="120">Shoot a nuclear weapon at this thing, you have to blow it up within a few milliseconds of tolerance, or else you'll miss it.</s>
 <s id="121">And there are a lot of other problems with that; it's very hard to do.</s>
 <p id="p122">
  <s id="122.1">But just hitting something?</s>
  <s id="122.2">That's pretty easy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="123">I think even NASA can do that, and proved that they can.</s>
 <s id="124">(Laughter) The problem is, if you hit this asteroid, you've changed the orbit, you measure the orbit, then you find out, oh yeah, we just pushed it into a keyhole, and now it's going to hit us in three years.</s>
 <s id="125">Well, my opinion is: fine!</s>
 <s id="126">It's not hitting us in six months -- that's good.</s>
 <s id="127">Now we have three years to do something else.</s>
 <s id="128">And you can hit it again.</s>
 <s id="129">That's kind of ham-fisted; you might just push it into a third keyhole or whatever, so you don't do that.</s>
 <s id="130">And this is the part -- it's the part I just love.</s>
 <p id="p131">
  <s id="131.1">(Laughter) After the big macho "Grr ... bam!</s>
  <s id="131.2">We're gonna hit this thing in the face," then we bring in the velvet gloves.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="132">(Laughter) There's a group of scientists and engineers and astronauts, and they call themselves The B612 Foundation.</s>
 <s id="133">For those of you who've read "The Little Prince," you understand that reference, I hope -- the little prince lived on an asteroid called B612.</s>
 <s id="134">These are smart guys -- men and women -- astronauts, like I said, engineers.</s>
 <s id="135">Rusty Schweickart, who was an Apollo 9 astronaut, is on this.</s>
 <s id="136">Dan Durda, my friend who made this image, works here at Southwest Research Institute in Boulder, on Walnut Street.</s>
 <s id="137">He created this image for this.</s>
 <s id="138">He's actually one of the astronomers who works for them.</s>
 <s id="139">If we see an asteroid that's going to hit the Earth and we have enough time, we can hit it to move it into a better orbit.</s>
 <s id="140">But then what we do is launch a probe that has to weigh a ton or two.</s>
 <s id="141">It doesn't have to be huge -- a couple of tons, not that big -- and you park it near the asteroid.</s>
 <s id="142">You don't land on it, because these things are tumbling end over end.</s>
 <s id="143">It's very hard to land on them.</s>
 <s id="144">Instead you get near it.</s>
 <s id="145">The gravity of the asteroid pulls on the probe, and the probe has a couple of tons of mass.</s>
 <s id="146">It has a little tiny bit of gravity, but it's enough that it can pull the asteroid, and you have your rocket set up -- you can barely see it here, but there's rocket plumes -- and these guys are connected by their own gravity, and if you move the probe very slowly -- very, very gently, you can very easily finesse that rock into a safe orbit.</s>
 <s id="147">You can even put in orbit around the Earth where we could mine it, although that's a whole other thing; I won't go into that.</s>
 <s id="148">(Laughter) But we'd be rich!</s>
 <s id="149">(Laughter) So think about this, right?</s>
 <s id="150">There are these giant rocks flying out there, and they're hitting us, and they're doing damage to us.</s>
 <s id="151">But we've figured out how to do this, and all the pieces are in place to do this.</s>
 <s id="152">We have astronomers with telescopes, looking for them.</s>
 <s id="153">We have very, very smart people, who are concerned about this and figuring out how to fix the problem, and we have the technology to do this.</s>
 <s id="154">This probe actually can't use chemical rockets.</s>
 <s id="155">Chemical rockets provide too much thrust, too much push.</s>
 <s id="156">The probe would just shoot away.</s>
 <s id="157">We invented something called an ion drive, which is a very, very, very low-thrust engine.</s>
 <s id="158">It generates the force a piece of paper would have on your hand -- incredibly light, but it can run for months and years, providing that very gentle push.</s>
 <s id="159">If anybody here is a fan of the original "Star Trek," they ran across an alien ship that had an ion drive, and Spock said, "They're very technically sophisticated.</s>
 <s id="160">They're a hundred years ahead of us with this drive."</s>
 <s id="161">Yeah, we have an ion drive now.</s>
 <s id="162">We don't have the Enterprise, but we've got an ion drive now.</s>
 <s id="163">(Laughter) (Applause) Spock.</s>
 <s id="164">(Laughter) So ...</s>
 <s id="165">That's the difference -- that's the difference between us and the dinosaurs.</s>
 <s id="166">This happened to them.</s>
 <s id="167">It doesn't have to happen to us.</s>
 <s id="168">The difference between the dinosaurs and us is that we have a space program and we can vote, and so we can change our future.</s>
 <s id="169">(Laughter) We have the ability to change our future.</s>
 <s id="170">Sixty-five million years from now, we don't have to have our bones collecting dust in a museum.</s>
 <s id="171">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="172">(Applause)</s>
</text>
