<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In 2008, something incredible happened: a man was cured of HIV.</s>
 <s id="2">In over 70 million HIV cases, that was a first and, so far, a last.</s>
 <s id="3">We don't yet understand exactly how he was cured.</s>
 <s id="4">We can cure people of various diseases, such as malaria and hepatitis C, so why can't we cure HIV?</s>
 <s id="5">Well, first let's examine how HIV infects people and progresses into AIDS.</s>
 <s id="6">HIV spreads through exchanges of bodily fluids.</s>
 <s id="7">Unprotected sex and contaminated needles are the leading cause of transmission.</s>
 <s id="8">It, fortunately, cannot spread through air, water, or casual contact.</s>
 <s id="9">Individuals of any age, sexual orientation, gender and race can contract HIV.</s>
 <s id="10">Once inside the body, HIV infects cells that are part of the immune system.</s>
 <s id="11">It particularly targets helper T cells, which help defend the body against bacterial and fungal infections.</s>
 <s id="12">HIV is a retrovirus, which means it can write its genetic code into the genome of infected cells, co-opting them into making more copies of itself.</s>
 <s id="13">During the first stage of HIV infection, the virus replicates within helper T cells, destroying many of them in the process.</s>
 <s id="14">During this stage, patients often experience flu-like symptoms, but are typically not yet in mortal danger.</s>
 <s id="15">However, for a period ranging from a few months to several years, during which time the patient may look and feel completely healthy, the virus continues to replicate and destroy T cells.</s>
 <s id="16">When T cell counts drop too low, patients are in serious danger of contracting deadly infections that healthy immune systems can normally handle.</s>
 <s id="17">This stage of HIV infection is known as AIDS.</s>
 <s id="18">The good news is there are drugs that are highly effective at managing levels of HIV and preventing T cell counts from getting low enough for the disease to progress to AIDS.</s>
 <s id="19">With antiretroviral therapy, most HIV-positive people can expect to live long and healthy lives, and are much less likely to infect others.</s>
 <s id="20">However, there are two major catches.</s>
 <s id="21">One is that HIV-positive patients must keep taking their drugs for the rest of their lives.</s>
 <s id="22">Without them, the virus can make a deadly comeback.</s>
 <s id="23">So, how do these drugs work?</s>
 <s id="24">The most commonly prescribed ones prevent the viral genome from being copied and incorporated into a host cell's DNA.</s>
 <s id="25">Other drugs prevent the virus from maturing or assembling, causing HIV to be unable to infect new cells in the body.</s>
 <s id="26">But HIV hides out somewhere our current drugs cannot reach it: inside the DNA of healthy T cells.</s>
 <s id="27">Most T cells die shortly after being infected with HIV.</s>
 <s id="28">But in a tiny percentage, the instructions for building more HIV viruses lies dormant, sometimes for years.</s>
 <s id="29">So even if we could wipe out every HIV virus from an infected person's body, one of those T cells could activate and start spreading the virus again.</s>
 <s id="30">The other major catch is that not everyone in the world has access to the therapies that could save their lives.</s>
 <s id="31">In Sub-Saharan Africa, which accounts for over 70% of HIV patients worldwide, antiretrovirals reached only about one in three HIV-positive patients in 2012.</s>
 <s id="32">There is no easy answer to this problem.</s>
 <s id="33">A mix of political, economic and cultural barriers makes effective prevention and treatment difficult.</s>
 <s id="34">And even in the U.S., HIV still claims more than 10,000 lives per year.</s>
 <s id="35">However, there is ample cause for hope.</s>
 <s id="36">Researchers may be closer than ever to developing a true cure.</s>
 <s id="37">One research approach involves using a drug to activate all cells harboring the HIV genetic information.</s>
 <s id="38">This would both destroy those cells and flush the virus out into the open, where our current drugs are effective.</s>
 <s id="39">Another is looking to use genetic tools to cut the HIV DNA out of cells genomes altogether.</s>
 <s id="40">And while one cure out of 70 million cases may seem like terrible odds, one is immeasurably better than zero.</s>
 <s id="41">We now know that a cure is possible, and that may give us what we need to beat HIV for good.</s>
</text>
