<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Like many of you here, I am trying to contribute towards a renaissance in Africa.</s>
 <s id="2">The question of transformation in Africa really is a question of leadership.</s>
 <s id="3">Africa can only be transformed by enlightened leaders.</s>
 <s id="4">And it is my contention that the manner in which we educate our leaders is fundamental to progress on this continent.</s>
 <s id="5">I want to tell you some stories that explain my view.</s>
 <s id="6">We all heard about the importance of stories yesterday.</s>
 <s id="7">An American friend of mine this year volunteered as a nurse in Ghana, and in a period of three months she came to a conclusion about the state of leadership in Africa that had taken me over a decade to reach.</s>
 <s id="8">Twice she was involved in surgeries where they lost power at the hospital.</s>
 <s id="9">The emergency generators did not start.</s>
 <s id="10">There was not a flashlight, not a lantern, not a candle -- pitch black.</s>
 <s id="11">The patient's cut open, twice.</s>
 <s id="12">The first time it was a C-section.</s>
 <s id="13">Thankfully, baby was out -- mother and child survived.</s>
 <s id="14">The second time was a procedure that involved local anesthesia.</s>
 <p id="p15">
  <s id="15.1">Anesthetic wears off.</s>
  <s id="15.2">The patient feels pain.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">He's crying.</s>
  <s id="16.2">He's screaming.</s>
  <s id="16.3">He's praying.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">Pitch black.</s>
  <s id="17.2">Not a candle, not a flashlight.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="18">And that hospital could have afforded flashlights.</s>
 <s id="19">They could have afforded to purchase these things, but they didn't.</s>
 <s id="20">And it happened twice.</s>
 <s id="21">Another time, she watched in horror as nurses watched a patient die because they refused to give her oxygen that they had.</s>
 <s id="22">And so three months later, just before she returned to the United States, nurses in Accra go on strike.</s>
 <s id="23">And her recommendation is take this opportunity to fire everyone, start all over again.</s>
 <s id="24">Start all over again.</s>
 <s id="25">Now what does this have to do with leadership?</s>
 <s id="26">You see, the folks at the ministry of health, the hospital administrators, the doctors, the nurses -- they are among just five percent of their peers who get an education after secondary school.</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">They are the elite.</s>
  <s id="27.2">They are our leaders.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="28">Their decisions, their actions matter.</s>
 <s id="29">And when they fail, a nation literally suffers.</s>
 <s id="30">So when I speak of leadership, I'm not talking about just political leaders.</s>
 <s id="31">We've heard a lot about that.</s>
 <s id="32">I'm talking about the elite.</s>
 <s id="33">Those who've been trained, whose job it is to be the guardians of their society.</s>
 <s id="34">The lawyers, the judges, the policemen, the doctors, the engineers, the civil servants -- those are the leaders.</s>
 <s id="35">And we need to train them right.</s>
 <s id="36">Now, my first pointed and memorable experience with leadership in Ghana occurred when I was 16 years old.</s>
 <s id="37">We had just had a military coup, and soldiers were pervasive in our society.</s>
 <s id="38">They were a pervasive presence.</s>
 <s id="39">And one day I go to the airport to meet my father, and as I walk up this grassy slope from the car park to the terminal building, I'm stopped by two soldiers wielding AK-47 assault weapons.</s>
 <s id="40">And they asked me to join a crowd of people that were running up and down this embankment.</s>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">Why?</s>
  <s id="41.2">Because the path I had taken was considered out of bounds.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">No sign to this effect.</s>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">Now, I was 16.</s>
  <s id="43.2">I was very worried about what my peers at school might think if they saw me running up and down this hill.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">I was especially concerned of what the girls might think.</s>
 <s id="45">And so I started to argue with these men.</s>
 <s id="46">It was a little reckless, but you know, I was 16.</s>
 <s id="47">I got lucky.</s>
 <s id="48">A Ghana Airways pilot falls into the same predicament.</s>
 <s id="49">Because of his uniform they speak to him differently, and they explain to him that they're just following orders.</s>
 <s id="50">So he takes their radio, talks to their boss, and gets us all released.</s>
 <s id="51">What lessons would you take from an experience like this?</s>
 <s id="52">Several, for me.</s>
 <p id="p53">
  <s id="53.1">Leadership matters.</s>
  <s id="53.2">Those men are following the orders of a superior officer.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="54">I learned something about courage.</s>
 <s id="55">It was important not to look at those guns.</s>
 <s id="56">And I also learned that it can be helpful to think about girls.</s>
 <s id="57">(Laughter) So a few years after this event, I leave Ghana on a scholarship to go to Swarthmore College for my education.</s>
 <s id="58">It was a breath of fresh air.</s>
 <s id="59">You know, the faculty there didn't want us to memorize information and repeat back to them as I was used to back in Ghana.</s>
 <s id="60">They wanted us to think critically.</s>
 <s id="61">They wanted us to be analytical.</s>
 <s id="62">They wanted us to be concerned about social issues.</s>
 <s id="63">In my economics classes I got high marks for my understanding of basic economics.</s>
 <s id="64">But I learned something more profound than that, which is that the leaders -- the managers of Ghana's economy -- were making breathtakingly bad decisions that had brought our economy to the brink of collapse.</s>
 <s id="65">And so here was this lesson again -- leadership matters.</s>
 <s id="66">It matters a great deal.</s>
 <s id="67">But I didn't really fully understand what had happened to me at Swarthmore.</s>
 <s id="68">I had an inkling, but I didn't fully realize it until I went out into the workplace and I went to work at Microsoft Corporation.</s>
 <s id="69">And I was part of this team -- this thinking, learning team whose job it was to design and implement new software that created value in the world.</s>
 <s id="70">And it was brilliant to be part of this team.</s>
 <s id="71">It was brilliant.</s>
 <s id="72">And I realized just what had happened to me at Swarthmore, this transformation -- the ability to confront problems, complex problems, and to design solutions to those problems.</s>
 <s id="73">The ability to create is the most empowering thing that can happen to an individual.</s>
 <s id="74">And I was part of that.</s>
 <s id="75">Now, while I was at Microsoft, the annual revenues of that company grew larger than the GDP of the Republic of Ghana.</s>
 <s id="76">And by the way, it's continued to.</s>
 <s id="77">The gap has widened since I left.</s>
 <s id="78">Now, I've already spoken about one of the reasons why this has occurred.</s>
 <s id="79">I mean, it's the people there who are so hardworking, persistent, creative, empowered.</s>
 <s id="80">But there were also some external factors: free markets, the rule of law, infrastructure.</s>
 <s id="81">These things were provided by institutions run by the people that I call leaders.</s>
 <s id="82">And those leaders did not emerge spontaneously.</s>
 <s id="83">Somebody trained them to do the work that they do.</s>
 <s id="84">Now, while I was at Microsoft, this funny thing happened.</s>
 <s id="85">I became a parent.</s>
 <s id="86">And for the first time, Africa mattered more to me than ever before.</s>
 <s id="87">Because I realized that the state of the African continent would matter to my children and their children.</s>
 <s id="88">That the state of the world -- the state of the world depends on what's happening to Africa, as far as my kids would be concerned.</s>
 <s id="89">And at this time, when I was going through what I call my "pre-mid-life crisis," Africa was a mess.</s>
 <s id="90">Somalia had disintegrated into anarchy.</s>
 <s id="91">Rwanda was in the throes of this genocidal war.</s>
 <s id="92">And it seemed to me that that was the wrong direction, and I needed to be back helping.</s>
 <s id="93">I couldn't just stay in Seattle and raise my kids in an upper-middle class neighborhood and feel good about it.</s>
 <s id="94">This was not the world that I'd want my children to grow up in.</s>
 <s id="95">So I decided to get engaged, and the first thing that I did was to come back to Ghana and talk with a lot of people and really try to understand what the real issues were.</s>
 <s id="96">And three things kept coming up for every problem: corruption, weak institutions and the people who run them -- the leaders.</s>
 <s id="97">Now, I was a little scared because when you see those three problems, they seem really hard to deal with.</s>
 <s id="98">And they might say, "Look, don't even try."</s>
 <s id="99">But, for me, I asked the question, "Well, where are these leaders coming from?</s>
 <s id="100">What is it about Ghana that produces leaders that are unethical or unable to solve problems?"</s>
 <s id="101">So I went to look at what was happening in our educational system.</s>
 <s id="102">And it was the same -- learning by rote -- from primary school through graduate school.</s>
 <s id="103">Very little emphasis on ethics, and the typical graduate from a university in Ghana has a stronger sense of entitlement than a sense of responsibility.</s>
 <s id="104">This is wrong.</s>
 <s id="105">So I decided to engage this particular problem.</s>
 <s id="106">Because it seems to me that every society, every society, must be very intentional about how it trains its leaders.</s>
 <s id="107">And Ghana was not paying enough attention.</s>
 <s id="108">And this is true across sub-Saharan Africa, actually.</s>
 <s id="109">So this is what I'm doing now.</s>
 <s id="110">I'm trying to bring the experience that I had at Swarthmore to Africa.</s>
 <s id="111">I wish there was a liberal arts college in every African country.</s>
 <s id="112">I think it would make a huge difference.</s>
 <s id="113">And what Ashesi University is trying to do is to train a new generation of ethical, entrepreneurial leaders.</s>
 <s id="114">We're trying to train leaders of exceptional integrity, who have the ability to confront the complex problems, ask the right questions, and come up with workable solutions.</s>
 <s id="115">I'll admit that there are times when it seems like "Mission: Impossible," but we must believe that these kids are smart.</s>
 <s id="116">That if we involve them in their education, if we have them discuss the real issues that they confront -- that our whole society confronts -- and if we give them skills that enable them to engage the real world, that magic will happen.</s>
 <s id="117">Now, a month into this project, we'd just started classes.</s>
 <s id="118">And a month into it, I come to the office, and I have this email from one of our students.</s>
 <s id="119">And it said, very simply, "I am thinking now."</s>
 <s id="120">And he signs off, "Thank you."</s>
 <s id="121">It's such a simple statement.</s>
 <s id="122">But I was moved almost to tears because I understood what was happening to this young man.</s>
 <s id="123">And it is an awesome thing to be a part of empowering someone in this way.</s>
 <s id="124">I am thinking now.</s>
 <s id="125">This year we challenged our students to craft an honor code themselves.</s>
 <s id="126">There's a very vibrant debate going on on campus now over whether they should have an honor code, and if so, what it should look like.</s>
 <s id="127">One of the students asked a question that just warmed my heart.</s>
 <s id="128">Can we create a perfect society?</s>
 <s id="129">Her understanding that a student-crafted honor code constitutes a reach towards perfection is incredible.</s>
 <s id="130">Now, we cannot achieve perfection, but if we reach for it, then we can achieve excellence.</s>
 <s id="131">I don't know ultimately what they will do.</s>
 <s id="132">I don't know whether they will decide to have this honor code.</s>
 <s id="133">But the conversation they're having now -- about what their good society should look like, what their excellent society should look like, is a really good thing.</s>
 <p id="p134">
  <s id="134.1">Am I out of time?</s>
  <s id="134.2">OK.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="135">Now, I just wanted to leave that slide up because it's important that we think about it.</s>
 <s id="136">I'm very excited about the fact that every student at Ashesi University does community service before they graduate.</s>
 <s id="137">That for many of them, it has been a life-altering experience.</s>
 <s id="138">These young future leaders are beginning to understand the real business of leadership, the real privilege of leadership, which is after all to serve humanity.</s>
 <s id="139">I am even more thrilled by the fact that least year our student body elected a woman to be the head of Student Government.</s>
 <s id="140">It's the first time in the history of Ghana that a woman has been elected head of Student Government at any university.</s>
 <s id="141">It says a lot about her.</s>
 <s id="142">It says a lot about the culture that's forming on campus.</s>
 <s id="143">It says a lot about her peers who elected her.</s>
 <s id="144">She won with 75 percent of the vote.</s>
 <s id="145">And it gives me a lot of hope.</s>
 <s id="146">It turns out that corporate West Africa also appreciates what's happening with our students.</s>
 <s id="147">We've graduated two classes of students to date.</s>
 <s id="148">And every single one of them has been placed.</s>
 <s id="149">And we're getting great reports back from corporate Ghana, corporate West Africa, and the things that they're most impressed about is work ethic.</s>
 <s id="150">You know, that passion for what they're doing.</s>
 <s id="151">The persistence, their ability to deal with ambiguity, their ability to tackle problems that they haven't seen before.</s>
 <s id="152">This is good because over the past five years, there have been times when I've felt this is "Mission: Impossible."</s>
 <s id="153">And it's just wonderful to see these glimmers of the promise of what can happen if we train our kids right.</s>
 <s id="154">I think that the current and future leaders of Africa have an incredible opportunity to drive a major renaissance on the continent.</s>
 <s id="155">It's an incredible opportunity.</s>
 <s id="156">There aren't very many more opportunities like this in the world.</s>
 <s id="157">I believe that Africa has reached an inflection point with a march of democracy and free markets across the continent.</s>
 <s id="158">We have reached a moment from which can emerge a great society within one generation.</s>
 <s id="159">It will depend on inspired leadership.</s>
 <s id="160">And it is my contention that the manner in which we train our leaders will make all the difference.</s>
 <s id="161">Thank you, and God bless.</s>
 <s id="162">(Applause)</s>
</text>
