<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">All buildings today have something in common.</s>
 <s id="2">They're made using Victorian technologies.</s>
 <s id="3">This involves blueprints, industrial manufacturing and construction using teams of workers.</s>
 <s id="4">All of this effort results in an inert object.</s>
 <s id="5">And that means that there is a one-way transfer of energy from our environment into our homes and cities.</s>
 <s id="6">This is not sustainable.</s>
 <s id="7">I believe that the only way that it is possible for us to construct genuinely sustainable homes and cities is by connecting them to nature, not insulating them from it.</s>
 <s id="8">Now, in order to do this, we need the right kind of language.</s>
 <s id="9">Living systems are in constant conversation with the natural world, through sets of chemical reactions called metabolism.</s>
 <s id="10">And this is the conversion of one group of substances into another, either through the production or the absorption of energy.</s>
 <s id="11">And this is the way in which living materials make the most of their local resources in a sustainable way.</s>
 <s id="12">So, I'm interested in the use of metabolic materials for the practice of architecture.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">But they don't exist.</s>
  <s id="13.2">So I'm having to make them.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">I'm working with architect Neil Spiller at the Bartlett School of Architecture, and we're collaborating with international scientists in order to generate these new materials from a bottom up approach.</s>
 <s id="15">That means we're generating them from scratch.</s>
 <s id="16">One of our collaborators is chemist Martin Hanczyc, and he's really interested in the transition from inert to living matter.</s>
 <s id="17">Now, that's exactly the kind of process that I'm interested in, when we're thinking about sustainable materials.</s>
 <s id="18">So, Martin, he works with a system called the protocell.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">Now all this is -- and it's magic -- is a little fatty bag.</s>
  <s id="19.2">And it's got a chemical battery in it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">And it has no DNA.</s>
 <s id="21">This little bag is able to conduct itself in a way that can only be described as living.</s>
 <s id="22">It is able to move around its environment.</s>
 <s id="23">It can follow chemical gradients.</s>
 <s id="24">It can undergo complex reactions, some of which are happily architectural.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">So here we are.</s>
  <s id="25.2">These are protocells, patterning their environment.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">We don't know how they do that yet.</s>
 <s id="27">Here, this is a protocell, and it's vigorously shedding this skin.</s>
 <s id="28">Now, this looks like a chemical kind of birth.</s>
 <s id="29">This is a violent process.</s>
 <s id="30">Here, we've got a protocell to extract carbon dioxide out of the atmosphere and turn it into carbonate.</s>
 <s id="31">And that's the shell around that globular fat.</s>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">They are quite brittle.</s>
  <s id="32.2">So you've only got a part of one there.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="33">So what we're trying to do is, we're trying to push these technologies towards creating bottom-up construction approaches for architecture, which contrast the current, Victorian, top-down methods which impose structure upon matter.</s>
 <s id="34">That can't be energetically sensible.</s>
 <s id="35">So, bottom-up materials actually exist today.</s>
 <s id="36">They've been in use, in architecture, since ancient times.</s>
 <s id="37">If you walk around the city of Oxford, where we are today, and have a look at the brickwork, which I've enjoyed doing in the last couple of days, you'll actually see that a lot of it is made of limestone.</s>
 <s id="38">And if you look even closer, you'll see, in that limestone, there are little shells and little skeletons that are piled upon each other.</s>
 <s id="39">And then they are fossilized over millions of years.</s>
 <s id="40">Now a block of limestone, in itself, isn't particularly that interesting.</s>
 <s id="41">It looks beautiful.</s>
 <s id="42">But imagine what the properties of this limestone block might be if the surfaces were actually in conversation with the atmosphere.</s>
 <s id="43">Maybe they could extract carbon dioxide.</s>
 <s id="44">Would it give this block of limestone new properties?</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">Well, most likely it would.</s>
  <s id="45.2">It might be able to grow.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="46">It might be able to self-repair, and even respond to dramatic changes in the immediate environment.</s>
 <s id="47">So, architects are never happy with just one block of an interesting material.</s>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">They think big.</s>
  <s id="48.2">Okay?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="49">So when we think about scaling up metabolic materials, we can start thinking about ecological interventions like repair of atolls, or reclamation of parts of a city that are damaged by water.</s>
 <s id="50">So, one of these examples would of course be the historic city of Venice.</s>
 <s id="51">Now, Venice, as you know, has a tempestuous relationship with the sea, and is built upon wooden piles.</s>
 <s id="52">So we've devised a way by which it may be possible for the protocell technology that we're working with to sustainably reclaim Venice.</s>
 <s id="53">And architect Christian Kerrigan has come up with a series of designs that show us how it may be possible to actually grow a limestone reef underneath the city.</s>
 <s id="54">So, here is the technology we have today.</s>
 <s id="55">This is our protocell technology, effectively making a shell, like its limestone forefathers, and depositing it in a very complex environment, against natural materials.</s>
 <s id="56">We're looking at crystal lattices to see the bonding process in this.</s>
 <s id="57">Now, this is the very interesting part.</s>
 <s id="58">We don't just want limestone dumped everywhere in all the pretty canals.</s>
 <s id="59">What we need it to do is to be creatively crafted around the wooden piles.</s>
 <s id="60">So, you can see from these diagrams that the protocell is actually moving away from the light, toward the dark foundations.</s>
 <s id="61">We've observed this in the laboratory.</s>
 <s id="62">The protocells can actually move away from the light.</s>
 <p id="p63">
  <s id="63.1">They can actually also move towards the light.</s>
  <s id="63.2">You have to just choose your species.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="64">So that these don't just exist as one entity, we kind of chemically engineer them.</s>
 <s id="65">And so here the protocells are depositing their limestone very specifically, around the foundations of Venice, effectively petrifying it.</s>
 <p id="p66">
  <s id="66.1">Now, this isn't going to happen tomorrow.</s>
  <s id="66.2">It's going to take a while.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="67">It's going to take years of tuning and monitoring this technology in order for us to become ready to test it out in a case-by-case basis on the most damaged and stressed buildings within the city of Venice.</s>
 <s id="68">But gradually, as the buildings are repaired, we will see the accretion of a limestone reef beneath the city.</s>
 <s id="69">An accretion itself is a huge sink of carbon dioxide.</s>
 <s id="70">Also it will attract the local marine ecology, who will find their own ecological niches within this architecture.</s>
 <p id="p71">
  <s id="71.1">So, this is really interesting.</s>
  <s id="71.2">Now we have an architecture that connects a city to the natural world in a very direct and immediate way.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="72">But perhaps the most exciting thing about it is that the driver of this technology is available everywhere.</s>
 <p id="p73">
  <s id="73.1">This is terrestrial chemistry.</s>
  <s id="73.2">We've all got it, which means that this technology is just as appropriate for developing countries as it is for First World countries.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="74">So, in summary, I'm generating metabolic materials as a counterpoise to Victorian technologies, and building architectures from a bottom-up approach.</s>
 <s id="75">Secondly, these metabolic materials have some of the properties of living systems, which means they can perform in similar ways.</s>
 <s id="76">They can expect to have a lot of forms and functions within the practice of architecture.</s>
 <s id="77">And finally, an observer in the future marveling at a beautiful structure in the environment may find it almost impossible to tell whether this structure has been created by a natural process or an artificial one.</s>
 <s id="78">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="79">(Applause)</s>
</text>
