<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm here to tell you how change is happening at a local level in Pakistan, because women are finding their place in the political process.</s>
 <s id="2">I want to take you all on a journey to the place I was raised, northwest Pakistan, called Dir.</s>
 <s id="3">Dir was founded in the 17th century.</s>
 <s id="4">It was a princely state until its merger with Pakistan in 1969.</s>
 <s id="5">Our prince, Nawab Shah Jahan, reserved the right to wear white, the color of honor, but only for himself.</s>
 <s id="6">He didn't believe in educating his people.</s>
 <s id="7">And at the time of my birth in 1979, only five percent of boys and one percent of girls received any schooling at all.</s>
 <s id="8">I was one among that one percent.</s>
 <s id="9">Growing up, I was very close to my father.</s>
 <s id="10">He is a pharmacy doctor, and he sent me to school.</s>
 <s id="11">Every day, I would go to his clinic when my lessons finished.</s>
 <s id="12">He's a wonderful man and a well-respected community leader.</s>
 <s id="13">He was leading a welfare organization, and I would go with him to the social and political gatherings to listen and talk to the local men about our social and economic problems.</s>
 <s id="14">However, when I was 16, my father asked me to stop coming with him to the public gatherings.</s>
 <s id="15">Now, I was a young woman, and my place was in the home.</s>
 <s id="16">I was very upset.</s>
 <s id="17">But most of my family members, they were happy with this decision.</s>
 <s id="18">It was very difficult for me to sit back in the home and not be involved.</s>
 <s id="19">It took two years that finally my family agreed that my father could reconnect me with women and girls, so they could share their problems and together we could resolve them.</s>
 <s id="20">So, with his blessings, I started to reconnect with women and girls so we could resolve their problems together.</s>
 <s id="21">When women show up, they bring their realities and views with them.</s>
 <s id="22">And yet, I have found all too often, women underestimate their own strength, their potential and their self-respect.</s>
 <s id="23">However, while connecting with these women and girls, it became very clear to me that if there was to be any hope to create a better life for these women and girls and their families, we must stand up for our own rights -- and not wait for someone else to come and help us.</s>
 <s id="24">So I took a huge leap of faith and founded my own organization in '94 to create our very own platform for women empowerment.</s>
 <s id="25">I engaged many women and girls to work with me.</s>
 <s id="26">It was hard.</s>
 <s id="27">Many of the women working with me had to leave once they got married, because their husbands wouldn't let them work.</s>
 <s id="28">One colleague of mine was given away by her family to make amends for a crime her brother had committed.</s>
 <s id="29">I couldn't help her.</s>
 <s id="30">And I felt so helpless at that time.</s>
 <s id="31">But it made me more determined to continue my struggle.</s>
 <s id="32">I saw many practices like these, where these women suffered silently, bearing this brutality.</s>
 <s id="33">But when I see a woman struggling to change her situation instead of giving up, it motivates me.</s>
 <s id="34">So I ran for a public office as an independent candidate in Lower Dir in the local elections in 2001.</s>
 <s id="35">Despite all the challenges and hurdles I faced throughout this process, I won.</s>
 <s id="36">(Applause) And I served in the public office for six years.</s>
 <s id="37">But unfortunately, we women, elected women, we were not allowed to sit in the council together with all the members and to take part in the proceedings.</s>
 <s id="38">We had to sit in a separate, ladies-only room, not even aware what was happening in the council.</s>
 <s id="39">Men told me that, "You women, elected women members, should buy sewing machines for women."</s>
 <s id="40">When I knew what they needed the most was access to clean drinking water.</s>
 <s id="41">So I did everything I could do to prioritize the real challenges these women faced.</s>
 <s id="42">I set up five hand pumps in the two dried up wells in my locality.</s>
 <s id="43">Well, we got them working again.</s>
 <s id="44">Before long, we made water accessible for over 5,000 families.</s>
 <s id="45">We proved that anything the men could do, so could we women.</s>
 <s id="46">I built alliances with other elected women members, and last year, we women were allowed to sit together with all the members in the council.</s>
 <s id="47">(Applause) And to take part in the legislation and planning and budgeting, in all the decisions.</s>
 <s id="48">I saw there is strength in numbers.</s>
 <s id="49">You know yourselves.</s>
 <s id="50">Lack of representation means no one is fighting for you.</s>
 <s id="51">Pakistan is -- We're 8,000 miles away from where I'm here with you today.</s>
 <s id="52">But I hope what I'm about to tell you will resonate with you, though we have this big distance in miles and in our cultures.</s>
 <s id="53">When women show up, they bring the realities and hopes of half a population with them.</s>
 <s id="54">In 2007, we saw the rise of the Taliban in Swat, Dir and nearby districts.</s>
 <s id="55">It was horrifying.</s>
 <s id="56">The Taliban killed innocent people.</s>
 <s id="57">Almost every day, people collected the dead bodies of their loved ones from the streets.</s>
 <s id="58">Most of the social and political leaders struggling and working for the betterment of their communities were threatened and targeted.</s>
 <s id="59">Even I had to leave, leaving my children behind with my in-laws.</s>
 <s id="60">I closed my office in Dir and relocated to Peshawar, the capital of my province.</s>
 <s id="61">I was in trauma, kept thinking what to do next.</s>
 <s id="62">And most of the family members and friends were suggesting, "Shad, stop working.</s>
 <s id="63">The threat is very serious."</s>
 <s id="64">But I persisted.</s>
 <s id="65">In 2009, we experienced a historic influx of internally displaced persons, from Swat, Dir and other nearby districts.</s>
 <s id="66">I started visiting the camps almost every day, until the internally displaced persons started to go back to their place of origin.</s>
 <s id="67">I established four mother-child health care units, especially to take care of over 10,000 women and children nearby the camps.</s>
 <s id="68">But you know, during all these visits, I observed that there was very little attention towards women's needs.</s>
 <s id="69">And I was looking for what is the reason behind it.</s>
 <s id="70">And I found it was because of the underrepresentation of women in both social and political platforms, in our society as a whole.</s>
 <s id="71">And that was the time when I realized that I need to narrow down my focus on building and strengthening women's political leadership to increase their political representation, so they would have their own voice in their future.</s>
 <s id="72">So we started training around 300 potential women and youth for the upcoming local elections in 2015.</s>
 <s id="73">And you know what?</s>
 <s id="74">Fifty percent of them won.</s>
 <s id="75">(Applause) And they are now sitting in the councils, taking part actively in the legislation, planning and budgeting.</s>
 <s id="76">Most of them are now investing their funds on women's health, education, skill development and safe drinking water.</s>
 <s id="77">All these elected women now share, discuss and resolve their problems together.</s>
 <s id="78">Let me tell you about two of the women I have been working with: Saira Shams.</s>
 <s id="79">You can see, this young lady, age 26, she ran for a public office in 2015 in Lower Dir, and she won.</s>
 <s id="80">She completed two of the community infrastructure schemes.</s>
 <s id="81">You know, women, community infrastructure schemes ...</s>
 <s id="82">Some people think this is men's job.</s>
 <s id="83">But no, this is women's job, too, we can do it.</s>
 <s id="84">And she also fixed two of the roads leading towards girls schools, knowing that without access to these schools, they are useless to the girls of Dir.</s>
 <s id="85">And another young woman is Asma Gul.</s>
 <s id="86">She is a very active member of the young leaders forum we established.</s>
 <s id="87">She was unable to run for the public office, so she has become the first female journalist of our region.</s>
 <s id="88">She speaks and writes for women's and girls' issues and their rights.</s>
 <s id="89">Saira and Asma, they are the living examples of the importance of inclusion and representation.</s>
 <s id="90">Let me tell you this, too.</s>
 <s id="91">In the 2013 general elections in Pakistan and the local elections in 2015, there were less than 100 women voters in Dir.</s>
 <s id="92">But you know what?</s>
 <s id="93">I'm proud to tell you that this year, during the general elections, there were 93,000 women voters in Dir.</s>
 <s id="94">(Applause) So our struggle is far from over.</s>
 <s id="95">But this shift is historic.</s>
 <s id="96">And a sign that women are standing up, showing up and making it absolutely clear that we all must invest in building women's leadership.</s>
 <s id="97">In Pakistan and here in the United States, and everywhere in the world, this means women in politics, women in business and women in positions of power making important decisions.</s>
 <s id="98">It took me 23 years to get here.</s>
 <s id="99">But I don't want any girl or any woman to take 23 years of her life to make herself heard.</s>
 <s id="100">I have had some dark days.</s>
 <s id="101">But I have spent every waking moment of my life working for the right of every woman to live her full potential.</s>
 <s id="102">Imagine with me a world where thousands of us stand up and they support other young women together, creating opportunities and choices that benefit all.</s>
 <s id="103">And that, my friends, can change the world.</s>
 <s id="104">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="105">(Applause)</s>
</text>
