<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">For most jobs, it's understood that you can be fired, whether for crime, incompetence, or just poor performance.</s>
 <s id="2">But what if your job happens to be the most powerful position in the country, or the world?</s>
 <s id="3">That's where impeachment comes in.</s>
 <s id="4">Impeachment isn't the same as actually removing someone from office.</s>
 <s id="5">Like an indictment in criminal court, it's only the formal accusation that launches a trial, which could end in conviction or acquittal.</s>
 <s id="6">Originating in the United Kingdom, impeachment allowed Parliament to vote for removing a government official from office even without the king's consent.</s>
 <s id="7">Although this was an important check on royal power, the king couldn't be impeached because the monarch was considered the source of all government power.</s>
 <s id="8">But for the founders of the American Republic, there was no higher authority beyond the people themselves.</s>
 <s id="9">And so impeachment was adopted in the United States as a power of Congress applying to any civil officers, up to and including the president.</s>
 <s id="10">Although demands for impeachment can come from any members of the public, only the House of Representatives has the power to actually initiate the process.</s>
 <s id="11">It begins by referring the matter to a committee, usually the House Committee on Rules and the House Committee on the Judiciary.</s>
 <s id="12">These committees review the accusations, examine the evidence, and issue a recommendation.</s>
 <s id="13">If they find sufficient grounds to proceed, the House holds a separate vote on each of the specific charges, known as Articles of Impeachment.</s>
 <s id="14">If one or more passes by a simple majority, the official is impeached and the stage is set for trial.</s>
 <s id="15">The actual trial that follows impeachment is held in the Senate.</s>
 <s id="16">Selected members of the House, known as managers, act as the prosecution, while the impeached official and their lawyers present their defense.</s>
 <s id="17">The Senate acts as both judge and jury, conducting the trial and deliberating after hearing all the arguments.</s>
 <s id="18">If it's the president or vice president being impeached, the chief justice of the Supreme Court presides.</s>
 <s id="19">A conviction requires a supermajority of two-thirds and results in automatic removal from power.</s>
 <s id="20">Depending on the original charges, it can also disqualify them from holding office in the future and open them to standard criminal prosecution.</s>
 <s id="21">So what exactly can get someone impeached?</s>
 <s id="22">That's a bit more complicated.</s>
 <s id="23">Unlike in the United Kingdom, impeachment in the U.S. pits an elected legislature against other democratically elected members of government.</s>
 <s id="24">Therefore, to prevent the process from being used as a political weapon, the Constitution specifies that an official can only be impeached for treason, bribery, or other high crimes and misdemeanors.</s>
 <s id="25">That still leaves a lot of room for interpretation, not to mention politics, and many impeachment trials have split along partisan lines.</s>
 <s id="26">But the process is generally understood to be reserved for serious abuses of power.</s>
 <s id="27">The first official to be impeached was Tennesse Senator William Blount in 1797 for conspiring with Britain to cease the Spanish colony of Louisiana.</s>
 <s id="28">Since then, the House has launched impeachment investigations about 60 times, but only 19 have led to actual impeachment proceedings.</s>
 <s id="29">The eight cases that ended in a conviction and removal from office were all federal judges.</s>
 <s id="30">And impeachment of a sitting president is even more rare.</s>
 <s id="31">Andrew Johnson was impeached in 1868 for attempting to replace Secretary of War Edwin Stanton without consulting the Senate.</s>
 <s id="32">Over a century later, Bill Clinton was impeached for making false statements under oath during a sexual harassment trial.</s>
 <s id="33">Both were ultimately acquitted when the Senate's votes to convict fell short of the required two-thirds majority.</s>
 <s id="34">And contrary to popular belief, Richard Nixon was never actually impeached for the Watergate scandal.</s>
 <s id="35">He resigned before it could happen knowing he would almost certainly be convicted.</s>
 <s id="36">Theoretically, the U.S. government is already designed to prevent abuses of power, limiting different branches through a system of checks and balances, term limits, and free elections.</s>
 <s id="37">But impeachment can be seen as an emergency brake for when these safeguards fail.</s>
</text>
