<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I have a daughter, Mulan.</s>
 <s id="2">And when she was eight, last year, she was doing a report for school or she had some homework about frogs.</s>
 <s id="3">And we were at this restaurant, and she said, "So, basically, frogs lay eggs and the eggs turn into tadpoles, and tadpoles turn into frogs."</s>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">And I said, "Yeah.</s>
  <s id="4.2">You know, I'm not really up on my frog reproduction that much.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="5">It's the females, I think, that lay the eggs, and then the males fertilize them.</s>
 <s id="6">And then they become tadpoles and frogs."</s>
 <p id="p7">
  <s id="7.1">And she says, "What?</s>
  <s id="7.2">Only the females have eggs?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="8">And I said, "Yeah."</s>
 <s id="9">And she goes, "And what's this fertilizing?"</s>
 <p id="p10">
  <s id="10.1">So I kind of said, "Oh, it's this extra ingredient, you know, that you need to create a new frog from the mom and dad frog."</s>
  <s id="10.2">(Laughter) And she said, "Oh, so is that true for humans too?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="11">And I thought, "Okay, here we go."</s>
 <s id="12">I didn't know it would happen so quick, at eight.</s>
 <s id="13">I was trying to remember all the guidebooks, and all I could remember was, "Only answer the question they're asking.</s>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">Don't give any more information."</s>
  <s id="14.2">(Laughter) So I said, "Yes."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="15">And she said, "And where do, um, where do human women, like, where do women lay their eggs?"</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">And I said, "Well, funny you should ask.</s>
  <s id="16.2">(Laughter) We have evolved to have our own pond.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="17">We have our very own pond inside our bodies.</s>
 <s id="18">And we lay our eggs there, we don't have to worry about other eggs or anything like that.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">It's our own pond.</s>
  <s id="19.2">And that's how it happens."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">And she goes, "Then how do they get fertilized?"</s>
 <s id="21">And I said, "Well, Men, through their penis, they fertilize the eggs by the sperm coming out.</s>
 <s id="22">And you go through the woman's vagina."</s>
 <s id="23">And so we're just eating, and her jaw just drops, and she goes, "Mom!</s>
 <s id="24">Like, where you go to the bathroom?"</s>
 <s id="25">And I said, "I know.</s>
 <s id="26">I know."</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">(Laughter) That's how we evolved.</s>
  <s id="27.2">It does seem odd.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="28">It is a little bit like having a waste treatment plant right next to an amusement park ...</s>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">Bad zoning, but ..."</s>
  <s id="29.2">(Laughter) She's like, "What?"</s>
  <s id="29.3">And she goes, "But Mom, but men and women can't ever see each other naked, Mom.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">So how could that ever happen?"</s>
 <s id="31">And then I go, "Well," and then I put my Margaret Mead hat on.</s>
 <s id="32">"Human males and females develop a special bond, and when they're much older, much, much older than you, and they have a very special feeling, then they can be naked together."</s>
 <s id="33">And she said, "Mom, have you done this before?"</s>
 <s id="34">And I said, "Yes."</s>
 <s id="35">And she said, "But Mom, you can't have kids."</s>
 <s id="36">Because she knows that I adopted her and that I can't have kids.</s>
 <s id="37">And I said, "Yes."</s>
 <s id="38">And she said, "Well, you don't have to do that again."</s>
 <s id="39">And I said, "..."</s>
 <s id="40">And then she said, "But how does it happen when a man and woman are together?</s>
 <s id="41">Like, how do they know that's the time?</s>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">Mom, does the man just say, 'Is now the time to take off my pants?'"</s>
  <s id="42.2">(Laughter) And I said, "Yes."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="43">(Laughter) "That is exactly right.</s>
 <s id="44">That's exactly how it happens."</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">So we're driving home and she's looking out the window, and she goes, "Mom.</s>
  <s id="45.2">What if two just people saw each other on the street, like a man and a woman, they just started doing it.</s>
  <s id="45.3">Would that ever happen?"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p46">
  <s id="46.1">And I said, "Oh, no.</s>
  <s id="46.2">Humans are so private.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="47">Oh ..."</s>
 <s id="48">And then she goes, "What if there was like a party, and there was just like a whole bunch of girls and a whole bunch of boys, and there was a bunch of men and women and they just started doing it, Mom?</s>
 <s id="49">Would that ever happen?"</s>
 <s id="50">And I said, "Oh, no, no.</s>
 <s id="51">That's not how we do it."</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">Then we got home and we see the cat.</s>
  <s id="52.2">And she goes, "Mom, how do cats do it?"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p53">
  <s id="53.1">And I go, "Oh, it's the same.</s>
  <s id="53.2">It's basically the same."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">And then she got all caught up in the legs.</s>
  <s id="54.2">"But how would the legs go, Mom?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">I don't understand the legs."</s>
 <s id="56">She goes, "Mom, everyone can't do the splits."</s>
 <s id="57">And I go, "I know, but the legs ..."</s>
 <s id="58">and I'm probably like, "The legs get worked out."</s>
 <s id="59">And she goes, "But I just can't understand it."</s>
 <p id="p60">
  <s id="60.1">So I go, "You know, why don't we go on the Internet, and maybe we can see ... like on Wikipedia."</s>
  <s id="60.2">(Laughter) So we go online, and we put in "cats mating."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="61">And, unfortunately, on YouTube, there's many cats mating videos.</s>
 <p id="p62">
  <s id="62.1">And we watched them and I'm so thankful, because she's just like, "Wow!</s>
  <s id="62.2">This is so amazing."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="63">She goes, "What about dogs?"</s>
 <s id="64">So we put in dogs mating, and, you know, we're watching it, and she's totally absorbed.</s>
 <s id="65">And then she goes, "Mom, do you think they would have, on the Internet, any humans mating?"</s>
 <p id="p66">
  <s id="66.1">(Laughter) And then I realized that I had taken my little eight year old's hand, and taken her right into Internet porn.</s>
  <s id="66.2">(Laughter) And I looked into this trusting, loving face, and I said, "Oh, no.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="67">That would never happen."</s>
 <s id="68">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="69">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <p id="p70">
  <s id="70.1">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="70.2">I'm so happy to be here.</s>
 </p>
</text>
