<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Meet our chemist, Harriet.</s>
 <s id="2">She has a chemical reaction that needs to occur more quickly.</s>
 <s id="3">A chemist has some processes at her disposal that can help her speed up her reaction, and she knows of five ways.</s>
 <s id="4">And to remember them, she thinks back to her days as a high school student, and the day she got a date for the dance.</s>
 <s id="5">Harriet was in high school, studying between classes.</s>
 <s id="6">She had lost track of time and was going to be late to class.</s>
 <s id="7">Unbeknownst to her, Harold, who was just around the corner, was running late, too.</s>
 <s id="8">They both sprinted to class and, as it happened, sprinted directly into one another.</s>
 <s id="9">Now, this was no small collision.</s>
 <s id="10">They ran squarely into one another in such a way that he knocked the books right out of her hand.</s>
 <p id="p11">
  <s id="11.1">"I'm sorry," he said.</s>
  <s id="11.2">"Let me help you with your books."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="12">He kindly helped her re-collect her belongings, and politely offered to walk her to class.</s>
 <s id="13">And you'll never guess who went together to the dance later that year.</s>
 <s id="14">Yup, those two.</s>
 <s id="15">So as we can see from this example, the key to getting a date for the dance is to collide with someone and knock the books out of their hands.</s>
 <s id="16">Now, you're probably already aware that not all collisions lead to dates for the dance, thankfully.</s>
 <s id="17">The collisions must have two important characteristics: One, correct orientation that allows books to be knocked from one's hands; and two, enough energy to knock the books out.</s>
 <s id="18">Shortly after this incident, Harriet decided to tell me, her chemistry teacher, all about it.</s>
 <s id="19">I noticed some interesting parallels between her story and chemical reaction rates, which happened to be what she was studying in the hallway the day of the collision.</s>
 <s id="20">Together, we decided to set out on two missions.</s>
 <s id="21">Harriet wanted to help all chemistry students and chemists remember how to speed up the rate of chemical reactions and I, being the nice guy that I am, decided to make it my mission to help create educational environments in which more book-dropping collisions can take place to increase future chemists' chances of getting a date for the dance.</s>
 <s id="22">In order to facilitate this improved dance-date-getting process, I propose five changes to all schools that parallel Harriet's five ways to increase chemical reaction rates.</s>
 <s id="23">First, I propose that we shrink the size of the hallways.</s>
 <s id="24">This will make it more difficult to safely navigate the hallways and will cause more collisions than in larger hallways.</s>
 <s id="25">And by increasing the number of collisions, we increase the likelihood that some of those collisions will have the correct alignment and enough energy to create a date to the dance.</s>
 <s id="26">Now, chemically speaking, this is equivalent to lowering the volume of a reaction vessel or a reaction mixture.</s>
 <s id="27">In doing so, the individual particles are closer together, and more collisions will occur.</s>
 <s id="28">More collisions means a greater likelihood that collisions with the appropriate energy and configuration will happen.</s>
 <s id="29">Second, I propose increasing the overall population of the school.</s>
 <s id="30">More students equals more collisions.</s>
 <s id="31">By increasing the number of particles available for collision, we create an environment where more collisions can take place.</s>
 <s id="32">Third, we must reduce the time allowed between classes -- heck, let's just cut it in half.</s>
 <s id="33">In doing so, students will need to move more quickly to get from one class to the next.</s>
 <s id="34">This increase in velocity will help make sure collisions have the appropriate amount of energy necessary to ensure book-dropping.</s>
 <s id="35">This is analogous to increasing the temperature of the reaction mixture.</s>
 <s id="36">Higher temperature means particles are moving faster.</s>
 <s id="37">Faster-moving particles means more energy, and a greater likelihood of the reaction-causing collision.</s>
 <s id="38">Fourth, students must stop traveling in packs.</s>
 <s id="39">By traveling in packs, the students on the outside of the pack insulate those in the middle from undergoing any collisions.</s>
 <s id="40">By splitting up, each student has more area exposed that is available for a collision from a passing student.</s>
 <s id="41">When particles travel in packs, the surface area is very small, and only the outside particles can collide.</s>
 <s id="42">However, by breaking up the clumps into individual particles, the total surface area is increased, and each particle has an exposed surface that can react.</s>
 <s id="43">Fifth and finally, we hire a matchmaker.</s>
 <s id="44">Is this colliding and book-dropping too violent?</s>
 <s id="45">Is there an easier way to get a date that requires less initial energy?</s>
 <s id="46">Then a matchmaker will help with this.</s>
 <s id="47">The matchmaker makes it easier for a couple to get together, by coordinating the match.</s>
 <s id="48">Our matchmaker is like a catalyst.</s>
 <s id="49">Chemical catalysts function by lowering the activation energy -- in other words, by lowering the energy required to start a reaction.</s>
 <s id="50">They do this by bringing two particles together and orienting them correctly in space so that the two can meet at the correct configuration and allow a reaction to take place.</s>
 <s id="51">So, to sum up: if a future chemist wants a date for the dance, he must collide with another person and knock the books out of their hands.</s>
 <s id="52">And if a chemist wants to make a chemical reaction occur, the particles must collide in the correct orientation with an appropriate amount of energy.</s>
 <s id="53">And both of these processes can be accelerated, using the five methods I've described.</s>
</text>
