<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">When Homer’s Iliad was first written down in the 8th century BCE, the story of the Trojan war was already an old one.</s>
 <s id="2">From existing oral tradition, audiences knew the tales of the long siege, the epic duels outside the city walls, and the cunning trick that finally won the war.</s>
 <s id="3">In the end, the magnificent city was burned to the ground, never to rise again.</s>
 <s id="4">But had it ever existed?</s>
 <s id="5">By the time the field of archaeology began to take shape in the 19th century, many were skeptical, considering the epic to be pure fiction, a founding myth imagining a bygone heroic era.</s>
 <s id="6">But some scholars believed that behind the superhuman feats and divine miracles there must have been a grain of historical truth - a war that was really fought, and a place where it happened.</s>
 <s id="7">Frank Calvert was one such believer.</s>
 <s id="8">He had spent his youth traveling and learning about ancient civilizations before accompanying his brother Frederick on a diplomatic mission to the northwest Anatolian region of Çanakkale.</s>
 <s id="9">It was here that Homer described the Greek encampment at the mouth of the Scamander river.</s>
 <s id="10">And it was here that fate brought Frank into contact with a journalist and geologist named Charles Maclaren.</s>
 <s id="11">Locals and travelers had long speculated that Troy might’ve stood on one of the surrounding hilltops.</s>
 <s id="12">But Maclaren had been one of the first to publish a detailed topographical study of the area.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">He believed he had found the site – a 32-meter mound known by the name Hisarlık, derived from the Turkish word for “fortress.”</s>
  <s id="13.2">Soon after meeting with him in 1847, the Calverts bought 2,000 acres of farmland that included part of the hill.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">Before they could explore any further, the Crimean War broke out and forestalled their archaeological ambitions for several years.</s>
 <s id="15">After the war’s end, Frank Calvert began to survey the site, but lacked the funds for a full excavation.</s>
 <s id="16">This was where the wealthy German businessman and amateur archaeologist Heinrich Schliemann came in.</s>
 <s id="17">At Calvert’s invitation, Schliemann visited the grounds in 1868, and decided to excavate.</s>
 <s id="18">Eager to find the ancient city, Schliemann tore massive trenches all the way to the base of the hill.</s>
 <s id="19">There, he uncovered a hoard of precious artifacts, jewelry, and metalwork, including two diadems and a copper shield.</s>
 <s id="20">Schliemann took full credit for the discovery, announcing that he had found Troy and the treasure of its king Priam.</s>
 <s id="21">But the real treasure was elsewhere.</s>
 <s id="22">When later archaeologists studied the site, they realized that the mound consisted of no less than nine cities, each built atop the ruins of the last.</s>
 <s id="23">The layer Schliemann had uncovered dated back to the Mycenaean Age, more than 1,000 years too early for Homer.</s>
 <s id="24">But inside the mound was indeed evidence for a city that had thrived during the Bronze Age, with charred stone, broken arrowheads, and damaged human skeletons suggesting a violent end.</s>
 <s id="25">It was Troy VII, contained in the middle layers and now ravaged for a second time by Schliemann’s careless excavation.</s>
 <s id="26">The settlement, spanning some 200,000 square meters and home to as many as 10,000 people, thrived until around 1180 BCE.</s>
 <s id="27">Its position at the southern entrance of the Dardanelles strait would’ve made a formidable strategic location for both defense and trade.</s>
 <s id="28">Most importantly, there are the remains of a massive fortification wall – perhaps the very same one from which Priam and Hector once watched the Greeks approach.</s>
 <s id="29">Of course, it’s difficult to be certain that these ruins are the true remains of ancient Troy, and scholars still dispute whether the Trojan War as described by Homer ever happened.</s>
 <s id="30">Yet the evidence is strong enough that UNESCO has labelled Hisarlık the archeological site of Troy.</s>
 <s id="31">Regardless of its identity, thanks to persistence, a bit of faith, and a lot of research, archaeologists are bringing the long-buried secrets of an ancient, lost city to light.</s>
</text>
