<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Here's what has to happen for pregnancy to occur after sexual intercourse.</s>
 <s id="2">Sperm must swim up the vagina, through the cervical opening, upwards through the uterus, and into one of the two fallopian tubes.</s>
 <s id="3">If an egg, released during that month's ovulation, is in the tube, one sperm has a chance to fertilize it.</s>
 <s id="4">Contraceptives are designed to prevent this process, and they work in three basic ways.</s>
 <s id="5">They block the sperm, disable sperm before they reach the uterus, or suppress ovulation.</s>
 <s id="6">Block is the simplest.</s>
 <s id="7">Male and female condoms prevent sperm from coming into contact with the vaginal space.</s>
 <s id="8">That barrier is also why they, unlike other contraceptive methods, are able to prevent transmission of certain sexually transmitted diseases.</s>
 <s id="9">Meanwhile, the diaphragm, cervical cap, and sponge work by being placed over the cervix, barricading the entrance to the uterus.</s>
 <s id="10">These contraceptives are sometimes called barrier methods and can be used with spermicides, an example of the second category, disable.</s>
 <s id="11">A spermicide is a chemical that immobilizes and destroys sperm.</s>
 <s id="12">Today's spermicides come as foam, cream, jelly, suppositories, and even a thin piece of translucent film that dissolves in the vagina.</s>
 <s id="13">These products can be inserted directly into the vagina before intercourse, or can be combined with block methods, like a diaphragm or condom, for added proection.</s>
 <s id="14">The third category for preventing pregnancy works by suppressing the action of an egg maturing in the ovary.</s>
 <s id="15">If there isn't an egg available in the fallopian tube, there's nothing for sperm to fertilize.</s>
 <s id="16">Hormonal contraceptives, including the pill, the patch, the Depo shot, and the vaginal ring all release synthetic versions of various combinations of progesterone and estrogen.</s>
 <s id="17">This hormone cocktail suppresses ovulation, keeping the immature egg safely sequestered in the ovary.</s>
 <s id="18">Synthetic progesterone also has a block trick up its sleeve.</s>
 <s id="19">It makes cervical mucus too thick and sticky for sperm to swim through easily.</s>
 <s id="20">There are other contraceptives that use multiple approaches at the same time.</s>
 <s id="21">For example, many IUDs, or intrauterine devices, contain synthetic hormones which suppress ovulation.</s>
 <s id="22">Some also contain copper, which disable sperm while also making egg implantation in the uterus difficult.</s>
 <s id="23">Block, disable, or suppress: is one strategy better than the other?</s>
 <s id="24">There are differences, but a lot of it has to do with how convenient and easy it is to use each contraceptive correctly.</s>
 <s id="25">For example, male condoms would be about 98% effective if everyone used them perfectly.</s>
 <s id="26">That 98% means if 100 couples correctly used condoms for a year, two women would get pregnant.</s>
 <s id="27">But not everyone uses them correctly, so they're only 82% effective in practice.</s>
 <s id="28">Other methods, like the patch and pill, are 99% effective when they're used perfectly.</s>
 <s id="29">But in practice, that's 91%.</s>
 <s id="30">Spermicide is only 85% effective, even with perfect usage, and just 71% effective with typical usage.</s>
 <s id="31">Another important consideration in the choice of contraceptives are side effects, which almost exclusively affect women rather than men.</s>
 <s id="32">Hormonal methods in particular can cause symptoms like headaches, nausea, and high blood pressure, but they vary from woman to woman.</s>
 <s id="33">That's why these methods require a prescription from a doctor.</s>
 <s id="34">The choice of contraceptive method is a personal one, and what works best for you now may change later.</s>
 <s id="35">Scientists also continue to research new methods, such as a male pill that would prevent sperm production.</s>
 <s id="36">In the meantime, there are quite a few options to block sperm, disable them, or suppress eggs and keep them out of reach.</s>
</text>
