<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In 479 BC, when Persian soldiers besieged the Greek city of Potidaea, the tide retreated much farther than usual, leaving a convenient invasion route.</s>
 <s id="2">But this wasn't a stroke of luck.</s>
 <s id="3">Before they had crossed halfway, the water returned in a wave higher than anyone had ever seen, drowning the attackers.</s>
 <s id="4">The Potiidaeans believed they had been saved by the wrath of Poseidon.</s>
 <s id="5">But what really saved them was likely the same phenomenon that has destroyed countless others: a tsunami.</s>
 <s id="6">Although tsunamis are commonly known as tidal waves, they're actually unrelated to the tidal activity caused by the gravitational forces of the Sun and Moon.</s>
 <s id="7">In many ways, tsunamis are just larger versions of regular waves.</s>
 <s id="8">They have a trough and a crest, and consist not of moving water, but the movement of energy through water.</s>
 <s id="9">The difference is in where this energy comes from.</s>
 <s id="10">For normal ocean waves, it comes from wind.</s>
 <s id="11">Because this only affects the surface, the waves are limited in size and speed.</s>
 <s id="12">But tsunamis are caused by energy originating underwater, from a volcanic eruption, a submarine landslide, or most commonly, an earthquake on the ocean floor caused when the tectonic plates of the Earth's surface slip, releasing a massive amount of energy into the water.</s>
 <s id="13">This energy travels up to the surface, displacing water and raising it above the normal sea level, but gravity pulls it back down, which makes the energy ripple outwards horizontally.</s>
 <s id="14">Thus, the tsunami is born, moving at over 500 miles per hour.</s>
 <s id="15">When it's far from shore, a tsunami can be barely detectable since it moves through the entire depth of the water.</s>
 <s id="16">But when it reaches shallow water, something called wave shoaling occurs.</s>
 <s id="17">Because there is less water to move through, this still massive amount of energy is compressed.</s>
 <s id="18">The wave's speed slows down, while its height rises to as much as 100 feet.</s>
 <s id="19">The word tsunami, Japanese for "harbor wave," comes from the fact that it only seems to appear near the coast.</s>
 <s id="20">If the trough of a tsunami reaches shore first, the water will withdraw farther than normal before the wave hits, which can be misleadingly dangerous.</s>
 <s id="21">A tsunami will not only drown people near the coast, but level buildings and trees for a mile inland or more, especially in low-lying areas.</s>
 <s id="22">As if that weren't enough, the water then retreats, dragging with it the newly created debris, and anything, or anyone, unfortunate enough to be caught in its path.</s>
 <s id="23">The 2004 Indian Ocean tsunami was one of the deadliest natural disasters in history, killing over 200,000 people throughout South Asia.</s>
 <s id="24">So how can we protect ourselves against this destructive force of nature?</s>
 <s id="25">People in some areas have attempted to stop tsunamis with sea walls, flood gates, and channels to divert the water.</s>
 <s id="26">But these are not always effective.</s>
 <s id="27">In 2011, a tsunami surpassed the flood wall protecting Japan's Fukushima Power Plant, causing a nuclear disaster in addition to claiming over 18,000 lives.</s>
 <s id="28">Many scientists and policy makers are instead focusing on early detection, monitoring underwater pressure and seismic activity, and establishing global communication networks for quickly distributing alerts.</s>
 <s id="29">When nature is too powerful to stop, the safest course is to get out of its way.</s>
</text>
