<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">If you can't imagine life without chocolate, you're lucky you weren't born before the 16th century.</s>
 <s id="2">Until then, chocolate only existed in Mesoamerica in a form quite different from what we know.</s>
 <s id="3">As far back as 1900 BCE, the people of that region had learned to prepare the beans of the native cacao tree.</s>
 <s id="4">The earliest records tell us the beans were ground and mixed with cornmeal and chili peppers to create a drink - not a relaxing cup of hot cocoa, but a bitter, invigorating concoction frothing with foam.</s>
 <s id="5">And if you thought we make a big deal about chocolate today, the Mesoamericans had us beat.</s>
 <s id="6">They believed that cacao was a heavenly food gifted to humans by a feathered serpent god, known to the Maya as Kukulkan and to the Aztecs as Quetzalcoatl.</s>
 <s id="7">Aztecs used cacao beans as currency and drank chocolate at royal feasts, gave it to soldiers as a reward for success in battle, and used it in rituals.</s>
 <s id="8">The first transatlantic chocolate encounter occurred in 1519 when Hernán Cortés visited the court of Moctezuma at Tenochtitlan.</s>
 <s id="9">As recorded by Cortés's lieutenant, the king had 50 jugs of the drink brought out and poured into golden cups.</s>
 <s id="10">When the colonists returned with shipments of the strange new bean, missionaries' salacious accounts of native customs gave it a reputation as an aphrodisiac.</s>
 <s id="11">At first, its bitter taste made it suitable as a medicine for ailments, like upset stomachs, but sweetening it with honey, sugar, or vanilla quickly made chocolate a popular delicacy in the Spanish court.</s>
 <s id="12">And soon, no aristocratic home was complete without dedicated chocolate ware.</s>
 <s id="13">The fashionable drink was difficult and time consuming to produce on a large scale.</s>
 <s id="14">That involved using plantations and imported slave labor in the Caribbean and on islands off the coast of Africa.</s>
 <s id="15">The world of chocolate would change forever in 1828 with the introduction of the cocoa press by Coenraad van Houten of Amsterdam.</s>
 <s id="16">Van Houten's invention could separate the cocoa's natural fat, or cocoa butter.</s>
 <s id="17">This left a powder that could be mixed into a drinkable solution or recombined with the cocoa butter to create the solid chocolate we know today.</s>
 <s id="18">Not long after, a Swiss chocolatier named Daniel Peter added powdered milk to the mix, thus inventing milk chocolate.</s>
 <s id="19">By the 20th century, chocolate was no longer an elite luxury but had become a treat for the public.</s>
 <s id="20">Meeting the massive demand required more cultivation of cocoa, which can only grow near the equator.</s>
 <s id="21">Now, instead of African slaves being shipped to South American cocoa plantations, cocoa production itself would shift to West Africa with Cote d'Ivoire providing two-fifths of the world's cocoa as of 2015.</s>
 <s id="22">Yet along with the growth of the industry, there have been horrific abuses of human rights.</s>
 <s id="23">Many of the plantations throughout West Africa, which supply Western companies, use slave and child labor, with an estimation of more than 2 million children affected.</s>
 <s id="24">This is a complex problem that persists despite efforts from major chocolate companies to partner with African nations to reduce child and indentured labor practices.</s>
 <s id="25">Today, chocolate has established itself in the rituals of our modern culture.</s>
 <s id="26">Due to its colonial association with native cultures, combined with the power of advertising, chocolate retains an aura of something sensual, decadent, and forbidden.</s>
 <s id="27">Yet knowing more about its fascinating and often cruel history, as well as its production today, tells us where these associations originate and what they hide.</s>
 <s id="28">So as you unwrap your next bar of chocolate, take a moment to consider that not everything about chocolate is sweet.</s>
</text>
