<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Allow me to start this talk with a question to everyone.</s>
 <s id="2">You know that all over the world, people fight for their freedom, fight for their rights.</s>
 <s id="3">Some battle oppressive governments.</s>
 <s id="4">Others battle oppressive societies.</s>
 <s id="5">Which battle do you think is harder?</s>
 <s id="6">Allow me to try to answer this question in the few coming minutes.</s>
 <s id="7">Let me take you back two years ago in my life.</s>
 <s id="8">It was the bedtime of my son, Aboody.</s>
 <s id="9">He was five at the time.</s>
 <s id="10">After finishing his bedtime rituals, he looked at me and he asked a question: "Mommy, are we bad people?"</s>
 <s id="11">I was shocked.</s>
 <s id="12">"Why do you say such things, Aboody?"</s>
 <s id="13">Earlier that day, I noticed some bruises on his face when he came from school.</s>
 <s id="14">He wouldn't tell me what happened.</s>
 <s id="15">[But now] he was ready to tell.</s>
 <s id="16">"Two boys hit me today in school.</s>
 <s id="17">They told me, 'We saw your mom on Facebook.</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">You and your mom should be put in jail.'"</s>
  <s id="18.2">I've never been afraid to tell Aboody anything.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="19">I've been always a proud woman of my achievements.</s>
 <s id="20">But those questioning eyes of my son were my moment of truth, when it all came together.</s>
 <s id="21">You see, I'm a Saudi woman who had been put in jail for driving a car in a country where women are not supposed to drive cars.</s>
 <s id="22">Just for giving me his car keys, my own brother was detained twice, and he was harassed to the point he had to quit his job as a geologist, leave the country with his wife and two-year-old son.</s>
 <s id="23">My father had to sit in a Friday sermon listening to the imam condemning women drivers and calling them prostitutes amongst tons of worshippers, some of them our friends and family of my own father.</s>
 <s id="24">I was faced with an organized defamation campaign in the local media combined with false rumors shared in family gatherings, in the streets and in schools.</s>
 <s id="25">It all hit me.</s>
 <s id="26">It came into focus that those kids did not mean to be rude to my son.</s>
 <s id="27">They were just influenced by the adults around them.</s>
 <s id="28">And it wasn't about me, and it wasn't a punishment for taking the wheel and driving a few miles.</s>
 <s id="29">It was a punishment for daring to challenge the society's rules.</s>
 <s id="30">But my story goes beyond this moment of truth of mine.</s>
 <s id="31">Allow me to give you a briefing about my story.</s>
 <s id="32">It was May, 2011, and I was complaining to a work colleague about the harassments I had to face trying to find a ride back home, although I have a car and an international driver's license.</s>
 <s id="33">As long as I've known, women in Saudi Arabia have been always complaining about the ban, but it's been 20 years since anyone tried to do anything about it, a whole generation ago.</s>
 <s id="34">He broke the good/bad news in my face.</s>
 <s id="35">"But there is no law banning you from driving."</s>
 <s id="36">I looked it up, and he was right.</s>
 <s id="37">There wasn't an actual law in Saudi Arabia.</s>
 <s id="38">It was just a custom and traditions that are enshrined in rigid religious fatwas and imposed on women.</s>
 <s id="39">That realization ignited the idea of June 17, where we encouraged women to take the wheel and go drive.</s>
 <s id="40">It was a few weeks later, we started receiving all these "Man wolves will rape you if you go and drive."</s>
 <s id="41">A courageous woman, her name is Najla Hariri, she's a Saudi woman in the city of Jeddah, she drove a car and she announced but she didn't record a video.</s>
 <s id="42">We needed proof.</s>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">So I drove.</s>
  <s id="43.2">I posted a video on YouTube.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">And to my surprise, it got hundreds of thousands of views the first day.</s>
 <s id="45">What happened next, of course?</s>
 <s id="46">I started receiving threats to be killed, raped, just to stop this campaign.</s>
 <s id="47">The Saudi authorities remained very quiet.</s>
 <s id="48">That really creeped us out.</s>
 <s id="49">I was in the campaign with other Saudi women and even men activists.</s>
 <s id="50">We wanted to know how the authorities would respond on the actual day, June 17, when women go out and drive.</s>
 <s id="51">So this time I asked my brother to come with me and drive by a police car.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">It went fast.</s>
  <s id="52.2">We were arrested, signed a pledge not to drive again, released.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="53">Arrested again, he was sent to detention for one day, and I was sent to jail.</s>
 <s id="54">I wasn't sure why I was sent there, because I didn't face any charges in the interrogation.</s>
 <s id="55">But what I was sure of was my innocence.</s>
 <s id="56">I didn't break a law, and I kept my abaya — it's a black cloak we wear in Saudi Arabia before we leave the house — and my fellow prisoners kept asking me to take it off, but I was so sure of my innocence, I kept saying, "No, I'm leaving today."</s>
 <s id="57">Outside the jail, the whole country went into a frenzy, some attacking me badly, and others supportive and even collecting signatures in a petition to be sent to the king to release me.</s>
 <s id="58">I was released after nine days.</s>
 <s id="59">June 17 comes.</s>
 <s id="60">The streets were packed with police cars and religious police cars, but some hundred brave Saudi women broke the ban and drove that day.</s>
 <p id="p61">
  <s id="61.1">None were arrested.</s>
  <s id="61.2">We broke the taboo.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="62">(Applause) So I think by now, everyone knows that we can't drive, or women are not allowed to drive, in Saudi Arabia, but maybe few know why.</s>
 <s id="63">Allow me to help you answer this question.</s>
 <s id="64">There was this official study that was presented to the Shura Council -- it's the consultative council appointed by the king in Saudi Arabia — and it was done by a local professor, a university professor.</s>
 <s id="65">He claims it's done based on a UNESCO study.</s>
 <s id="66">And the study states, the percentage of rape, adultery, illegitimate children, even drug abuse, prostitution in countries where women drive is higher than countries where women don't drive.</s>
 <s id="67">(Laughter) I know, I was like this, I was shocked.</s>
 <s id="68">I was like, "We are the last country in the world where women don't drive."</s>
 <s id="69">So if you look at the map of the world, that only leaves two countries: Saudi Arabia, and the other society is the rest of the world.</s>
 <s id="70">We started a hashtag on Twitter mocking the study, and it made headlines around the world.</s>
 <s id="71">[BBC News: 'End of virginity' if women drive, Saudi cleric warns] (Laughter) And only then we realized it's so empowering to mock your oppressor.</s>
 <s id="72">It strips it away of its strongest weapon: fear.</s>
 <s id="73">This system is based on ultra-conservative traditions and customs that deal with women as if they are inferior and they need a guardian to protect them, so they need to take permission from this guardian, whether verbal or written, all their lives.</s>
 <s id="74">We are minors until the day we die.</s>
 <s id="75">And it becomes worse when it's enshrined in religious fatwas based on wrong interpretation of the sharia law, or the religious laws.</s>
 <s id="76">What's worst, when they become codified as laws in the system, and when women themselves believe in their inferiority, and they even fight those who try to question these rules.</s>
 <s id="77">So for me, it wasn't only about these attacks I had to face.</s>
 <s id="78">It was about living two totally different perceptions of my personality, of my person -- the villain back in my home country, and the hero outside.</s>
 <s id="79">Just to tell you, two stories happened in the last two years.</s>
 <s id="80">One of them is when I was in jail.</s>
 <s id="81">I'm pretty sure when I was in jail, everyone saw titles in the international media something like this during these nine days I was in jail.</s>
 <s id="82">But in my home country, it was a totally different picture.</s>
 <s id="83">It was more like this: "Manal al-Sharif faces charges of disturbing public order and inciting women to drive."</s>
 <s id="84">I know.</s>
 <s id="85">"Manal al-Sharif withdraws from the campaign."</s>
 <p id="p86">
  <s id="86.1">Ah, it's okay.</s>
  <s id="86.2">This is my favorite.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p87">
  <s id="87.1">"Manal al-Sharif breaks down and confesses: 'Foreign forces incited me.'"</s>
  <s id="87.2">(Laughter) And it goes on, even trial and flogging me in public.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="88">So it's a totally different picture.</s>
 <s id="89">I was asked last year to give a speech at the Oslo Freedom Forum.</s>
 <s id="90">I was surrounded by this love and the support of people around me, and they looked at me as an inspiration.</s>
 <s id="91">At the same time, I flew back to my home country, they hated that speech so much.</s>
 <s id="92">The way they called it: a betrayal to the Saudi country and the Saudi people, and they even started a hashtag called #OsloTraitor on Twitter.</s>
 <s id="93">Some 10,000 tweets were written in that hashtag, while the opposite hashtag, #OsloHero, there was like a handful of tweets written.</s>
 <s id="94">They even started a poll.</s>
 <s id="95">More than 13,000 voters answered this poll: whether they considered me a traitor or not after that speech.</s>
 <s id="96">Ninety percent said yes, she's a traitor.</s>
 <s id="97">So it's these two totally different perceptions of my personality.</s>
 <s id="98">For me, I'm a proud Saudi woman, and I do love my country, and because I love my country, I'm doing this.</s>
 <s id="99">Because I believe a society will not be free if the women of that society are not free.</s>
 <s id="100">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="101">(Applause) Thank you, thank you, thank you, thank you.</s>
 <s id="102">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="103">But you learn lessons from these things that happen to you.</s>
 <s id="104">I learned to be always there.</s>
 <s id="105">The first thing, I got out of jail, of course after I took a shower, I went online, I opened my Twitter account and my Facebook page, and I've been always very respectful to those people who are opining to me.</s>
 <s id="106">I would listen to what they say, and I would never defend myself with words only.</s>
 <p id="p107">
  <s id="107.1">I would use actions.</s>
  <s id="107.2">When they said I should withdraw from the campaign, I filed the first lawsuit against the general directorate of traffic police for not issuing me a driver's license.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="108">There are a lot of people also -- very big support, like those 3,000 people who signed the petition to release me.</s>
 <s id="109">We sent a petition to the Shura Council in favor of lifting the ban on Saudi women, and there were, like, 3,500 citizens who believed in that and they signed that petition.</s>
 <s id="110">There were people like that, I just showed some examples, who are amazing, who are believing in women's rights in Saudi Arabia, and trying, and they are also facing a lot of hate because of speaking up and voicing their views.</s>
 <s id="111">Saudi Arabia today is taking small steps toward enhancing women's rights.</s>
 <s id="112">The Shura Council that's appointed by the king, by royal decree of King Abdullah, last year there were 30 women assigned to that Council, like 20 percent.</s>
 <p id="p113">
  <s id="113.1">20 percent of the Council.</s>
  <s id="113.2">(Applause) The same time, finally, that Council, after rejecting our petition four times for women driving, they finally accepted it last February.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="114">(Applause) After being sent to jail or sentenced lashing, or sent to a trial, the spokesperson of the traffic police said, we will only issue traffic violation for women drivers.</s>
 <s id="115">The Grand Mufti, who is the head of the religious establishment in Saudi Arabia, he said, it's not recommended for women to drive.</s>
 <s id="116">It used to be haram, forbidden, by the previous Grand Mufti.</s>
 <s id="117">So for me, it's not about only these small steps.</s>
 <s id="118">It's about women themselves.</s>
 <s id="119">A friend once asked me, she said, "So when do you think this women driving will happen?"</s>
 <s id="120">I told her, "Only if women stop asking 'When?' and take action to make it now."</s>
 <s id="121">So it's not only about the system, it's also about us women to drive our own life, I'd say.</s>
 <s id="122">So I have no clue, really, how I became an activist.</s>
 <s id="123">And I don't know how I became one now.</s>
 <s id="124">But all I know, and all I'm sure of, in the future when someone asks me my story, I will say, "I'm proud to be amongst those women who lifted the ban, fought the ban, and celebrated everyone's freedom."</s>
 <s id="125">So the question I started my talk with, who do you think is more difficult to face, oppressive governments or oppressive societies?</s>
 <s id="126">I hope you find clues to answer that from my speech.</s>
 <s id="127">Thank you, everyone.</s>
 <s id="128">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <p id="p129">
  <s id="129.1">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="129.2">(Applause)</s>
 </p>
</text>
