<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I normally teach courses on how to rebuild states after war.</s>
 <s id="2">But today I've got a personal story to share with you.</s>
 <s id="3">This is a picture of my family, my four siblings -- my mom and I -- taken in 1977.</s>
 <s id="4">And we're actually Cambodians.</s>
 <s id="5">And this picture is taken in Vietnam.</s>
 <s id="6">So how did a Cambodian family end up in Vietnam in 1977?</s>
 <s id="7">Well to explain that, I've got a short video clip to explain the Khmer Rouge regime during 1975 and 1979.</s>
 <s id="8">Video: April 17th, 1975.</s>
 <s id="9">The communist Khmer Rouge enters Phnom Penh to liberate their people from the encroaching conflict in Vietnam, and American bombing campaigns.</s>
 <s id="10">Led by peasant-born Pol Pot, the Khmer Rouge evacuates people to the countryside in order to create a rural communist utopia, much like Mao Tse-tung's Cultural Revolution in China.</s>
 <s id="11">The Khmer Rouge closes the doors to the outside world.</s>
 <s id="12">But after four years the grim truth seeps out.</s>
 <s id="13">In a country of only seven million people, one and a half million were murdered by their own leaders, their bodies piled in the mass graves of the killing fields.</s>
 <s id="14">Sophal Ear: So, notwithstanding the 1970s narration, on April 17th 1975 we lived in Phnom Penh.</s>
 <s id="15">And my parents were told by the Khmer Rouge to evacuate the city because of impending American bombing for three days.</s>
 <s id="16">And here is a picture of the Khmer Rouge.</s>
 <s id="17">They were young soldiers, typically child soldiers.</s>
 <s id="18">And this is very normal now, of modern day conflict, because they're easy to bring into wars.</s>
 <s id="19">The reason that they gave about American bombing wasn't all that far off.</s>
 <s id="20">I mean, from 1965 to 1973 there were more munitions that fell on Cambodia than in all of World War II Japan, including the two nuclear bombs of August 1945.</s>
 <s id="21">The Khmer Rouge didn't believe in money.</s>
 <s id="22">So the equivalent of the Federal Reserve Bank in Cambodia was bombed.</s>
 <s id="23">But not just that, they actually banned money.</s>
 <s id="24">I think it's the only precedent in which money has ever been stopped from being used.</s>
 <s id="25">And we know money is the root of all evil, but it didn't actually stop evil from happening in Cambodia, in fact.</s>
 <s id="26">My family was moved from Phnom Penh to Pursat province.</s>
 <s id="27">This is a picture of what Pursat looks like.</s>
 <s id="28">It's actually a very pretty area of Cambodia, where rice growing takes place.</s>
 <s id="29">And in fact they were forced to work the fields.</s>
 <s id="30">So my father and mother ended up in a sort of concentration camp, labor camp.</s>
 <s id="31">And it was at that time that my mother got word from the commune chief that the Vietnamese were actually asking for their citizens to go back to Vietnam.</s>
 <s id="32">And she spoke some Vietnamese, as a child having grown up with Vietnamese friends.</s>
 <s id="33">And she decided, despite the advice of her neighbors, that she would take the chance and claim to be Vietnamese so that we could have a chance to survive, because at this point they're forcing everybody to work.</s>
 <s id="34">And they're giving about -- in a modern-day, caloric-restriction diet, I guess -- they're giving porridge, with a few grains of rice.</s>
 <s id="35">And at about this time actually my father got very sick.</s>
 <s id="36">And he didn't speak Vietnamese.</s>
 <s id="37">So he died actually, in January 1976.</s>
 <s id="38">And it made it possible, in fact, for us to take on this plan.</s>
 <s id="39">So the Khmer Rouge took us from a place called Pursat to Kaoh Tiev, which is across from the border from Vietnam.</s>
 <s id="40">And there they had a detention camp where alleged Vietnamese would be tested, language tested.</s>
 <s id="41">And my mother's Vietnamese was so bad that to make our story more credible, she'd given all the boys and girls new Vietnamese names.</s>
 <s id="42">But she'd given the boys girls' names, and the girls boys' names.</s>
 <s id="43">And it wasn't until she met a Vietnamese lady who told her this, and then tutored her for two days intensively, that she was able to go into her exam and -- you know, this was a moment of truth.</s>
 <s id="44">If she fails, we're all headed to the gallows; if she passes, we can leave to Vietnam.</s>
 <s id="45">And she actually, of course -- I'm here, she passes.</s>
 <s id="46">And we end up in Hong Ngu on the Vietnamese side.</s>
 <s id="47">And then onwards to Chau Doc.</s>
 <s id="48">And this is a picture of Hong Ngu, Vietnam today.</s>
 <s id="49">A pretty idyllic place on the Mekong Delta.</s>
 <s id="50">But for us it meant freedom.</s>
 <s id="51">And freedom from persecution from the Khmer Rouge.</s>
 <s id="52">Last year, the Khmer Rouge Tribunal, which the U.N. is helping Cambodia take on, started, and I decided that as a matter of record I should file a Civil Complaint with the Tribunal about my father's passing away.</s>
 <s id="53">And I got word last month that the complaint was officially accepted by the Khmer Rouge Tribunal.</s>
 <s id="54">And it's for me a matter of justice for history, and accountability for the future, because Cambodia remains a pretty lawless place, at times.</s>
 <s id="55">Five years ago my mother and I went back to Chau Doc.</s>
 <s id="56">And she was able to return to a place that for her meant freedom, but also fear, because we had just come out of Cambodia.</s>
 <s id="57">I'm happy, actually, today, to present her.</s>
 <s id="58">She's here today with us in the audience.</s>
 <s id="59">Thank you mother.</s>
 <s id="60">(Applause)</s>
</text>
