<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">At the age of 21, Simone de Beauvoir became the youngest person to take the philosophy exams at France’s most esteemed university.</s>
 <s id="2">She passed with flying colors.</s>
 <s id="3">But as soon as she mastered the rules of philosophy, she wanted to break them.</s>
 <s id="4">She’d been schooled on Plato’s Theory of Forms, which dismissed the physical world as a flawed reflection of higher truths and unchanging ideals.</s>
 <s id="5">But for de Beauvoir, earthly life was enthralling, sensual, and anything but static.</s>
 <s id="6">Her desire to explore the physical world to its fullest would shape her life, and eventually, inspire a radical new philosophy.</s>
 <s id="7">Endlessly debating with her romantic and intellectual partner Jean Paul Sartre, de Beauvoir explored free will, desire, rights and responsibilities, and the value of personal experience.</s>
 <s id="8">In the years following WWII, these ideas would converge into the school of thought most closely associated with their work: existentialism.</s>
 <s id="9">Where Judeo-Christian traditions taught that humans are born with preordained purpose, de Beauvoir and Sartre proposed a revolutionary alternative.</s>
 <s id="10">They argued that humans are born free, and thrown into existence without a divine plan.</s>
 <s id="11">As de Beauvoir acknowledged, this freedom is both a blessing and a burden.</s>
 <s id="12">In "The Ethics of Ambiguity" she argued that our greatest ethical imperative is to create our own life’s meaning, while protecting the freedom of others to do the same.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">As de Beauvoir wrote, “A freedom which is interested only in denying freedom must be denied.”</s>
  <s id="13.2">This philosophy challenged its students to navigate the ambiguities and conflicts our desires produce, both internally and externally.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">And as de Beauvoir sought to find her own purpose, she began to question: if everyone deserves to freely pursue meaning, why was she restricted by society’s ideals of womanhood?</s>
 <s id="15">Despite her prolific writing, teaching and activism, de Beauvoir struggled to be taken seriously by her male peers.</s>
 <s id="16">She’d rejected her Catholic upbringing and marital expectations to study at university, and write memoirs, fiction and philosophy.</s>
 <s id="17">But the risks she was taking by embracing this lifestyle were lost on many of her male counterparts, who took these freedoms for granted.</s>
 <s id="18">They had no intellectual interest in de Beauvoir’s work, which explored women’s inner lives, as well the author’s open relationship and bisexuality.</s>
 <s id="19">To convey the importance of her perspective, de Beauvoir embarked on her most challenging book yet.</s>
 <s id="20">Just as she’d created the foundations of existentialism, she’d now redefine the limits of gender.</s>
 <s id="21">Published in 1949, "The Second Sex" argues that, like our life’s meaning, gender is not predestined.</s>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">As de Beauvoir famously wrote, “one is not born, but rather becomes, woman.”</s>
  <s id="22.2">And to “become” a woman, she argued, was to become the Other.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">De Beauvoir defined Othering as the process of labeling women as less than the men who’d historically defined, and been defined as, the ideal human subjects.</s>
 <s id="24">As the Other, she argued that women were considered second to men, and therefore systematically restricted from pursuing freedom.</s>
 <s id="25">"The Second Sex" became an essential feminist treatise, offering a detailed history of women’s oppression and a wealth of anecdotal testimony.</s>
 <s id="26">"The Second Sex"’s combination of personal experience and philosophical intervention provided a new language to discuss feminist theory.</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">Today, those conversations are still informed by de Beauvoir’s insistence that in the pursuit of equality, “there is no divorce between philosophy and life.”</s>
  <s id="27.2">Of course, like any foundational work, the ideas in "The Second Sex" have been expanded upon since its publication.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="28">Many modern thinkers have explored additional ways people are Othered that de Beauvoir doesn’t acknowledge.</s>
 <s id="29">These include racial and economic identities, as well as the broader spectrum of gender and sexual identities we understand today.</s>
 <s id="30">De Beauvoir’s legacy is further complicated by accusations of sexual misconduct by two of her university students.</s>
 <s id="31">In the face of these accusations, she had her teaching license revoked for abusing her position.</s>
 <s id="32">In this aspect and others, de Beauvoir’s life remains controversial— and her work represents a contentious moment in the emergence of early feminism.</s>
 <s id="33">She participated in those conversations for the rest of her life; writing fiction, philosophy, and memoirs until her death in 1986.</s>
 <s id="34">Today, her work offers a philosophical language to be reimagined, revisited and rebelled against— a response this revolutionary thinker might have welcomed.</s>
</text>
