<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">This is the tale of two ancient cities and the trees that determined their destinies.</s>
 <s id="2">In 3,000 BC Uruk was more densely populated than modern day New York City.</s>
 <s id="3">This crowded capital had to continually expand their irrigation system to feed its growing population.</s>
 <s id="4">2,500 years later in Sri Lanka, the city of Anuradhapura had a similar problem.</s>
 <s id="5">They were also growing constantly, and like Uruk, their city relied heavily on an elaborate irrigation system.</s>
 <s id="6">As Uruk grew, its farmers began chopping down trees to make space for more crops.</s>
 <s id="7">In Anuradhapura, however, trees were sacred.</s>
 <s id="8">Their city housed an offshoot of the Bodhi tree under which Buddha himself was said to have attained enlightenment.</s>
 <s id="9">Religious reverence slowed farmer’s axes and even led the city to plant additional trees in urban parks.</s>
 <s id="10">Initially, Uruk’s expansion worked well.</s>
 <s id="11">But without trees to filter their water supply, Uruk’s irrigation system became contaminated.</s>
 <s id="12">Evaporating water left mineral deposits, which rendered the soil too salty for agriculture.</s>
 <s id="13">Conversely, Anuradhapura’s irrigation system was designed to work in concert with the surrounding forest.</s>
 <s id="14">Their city eventually grew to more than twice Uruk’s population, and today, Anuradhapura still cares for a tree planted over 2,000 years ago.</s>
 <s id="15">We may think of nature as being unconnected to our urban spaces, but trees have always been an essential part of successful cities.</s>
 <s id="16">Trees act like a natural sponge, absorbing storm water runoff before releasing it back into the atmosphere.</s>
 <s id="17">The webs of their roots protect against mudslides while allowing soil to retain water and filter out toxins.</s>
 <s id="18">Roots help prevent floods, while reducing the need for storm drains and water treatment plants.</s>
 <s id="19">Their porous leaves purify the air by trapping carbon and other pollutants, making them essential in the fight against climate change.</s>
 <s id="20">Humanity has been uncovering these arboreal benefits for centuries.</s>
 <s id="21">But trees aren’t just crucial to the health of a city’s infrastructure; they play a vital role in the health of its citizens as well.</s>
 <s id="22">In the 1870’s, Manhattan had few trees outside the island’s parks.</s>
 <s id="23">Without trees to provide shade, buildings absorbed up to nine times more solar radiation during deadly summer heat waves.</s>
 <s id="24">Combined with the period’s poor sanitation standards, the oppressive heat made the city a breeding ground for bacteria like cholera.</s>
 <s id="25">In modern day Hong Kong, tall skyscrapers and underground infrastructure make it difficult for trees to grow.</s>
 <s id="26">This contributes to the city’s dangerously poor air quality, which can cause bronchitis and diminished lung function.</s>
 <s id="27">Trees affect our mental health as well.</s>
 <s id="28">Research indicates that the presence of green foliage increases attention spans and decreases stress levels.</s>
 <s id="29">It’s even been shown that hospital patients with views of brick walls recover more slowly than those with views of trees.</s>
 <s id="30">Fortunately, many cities are full of views like this— and that’s no accident.</s>
 <s id="31">As early as the 18th century, city planners began to embrace the importance of urban trees.</s>
 <s id="32">In 1733, Colonel James Oglethorpe planned the city of Savannah, Georgia to ensure that no neighborhood was more than a 2-minute walk from a park.</s>
 <s id="33">After World War II, Copenhagen directed all new development along five arteries— each sandwiched between a park.</s>
 <s id="34">This layout increased the city’s resilience to pollution and natural disasters.</s>
 <s id="35">And urban trees don’t just benefit people.</s>
 <s id="36">Portland’s Forest Park preserves the region’s natural biodiversity, making the city home to various local plants, 112 bird species, and 62 species of mammals.</s>
 <s id="37">No city is more committed to trees than Singapore.</s>
 <s id="38">Since 1967, Singapore’s government has planted over 1.2 million trees, including those within 50-meter tall vertical gardens called supertrees.</s>
 <s id="39">These structures sustain themselves and nearby conservatories with solar energy and collected rainwater.</s>
 <s id="40">Trees and vegetation currently cover over 50% of Singapore’s landmass, reducing the need for air conditioning and encouraging low-pollution transportation.</s>
 <s id="41">By 2050, it’s estimated that over 65% of the world will be living in cities.</s>
 <s id="42">City planners can lay an eco-friendly foundation, but it’s up to the people who live in these urban forests to make them homes for more than humans.</s>
</text>
