<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Your internship in Professor Ramsey’s physics lab has been amazing.</s>
 <s id="2">Until, that is, the professor accidentally stepped through a time portal.</s>
 <s id="3">You’ve got just a minute to jump through the portal to save him before it closes and leaves him stranded in history.</s>
 <s id="4">Once you’re through it, the portal will close, and your only way back will be to create a new one using the chrono-nodules from your lab.</s>
 <s id="5">Activated nodules connect to each other via red or blue tachyon entanglement.</s>
 <s id="6">Activate more nodules and they’ll connect to all other nodules in the area.</s>
 <s id="7">As soon as a red or blue triangle is created with a nodule at each point, it opens a doorway through time that will take you back to the present.</s>
 <s id="8">But the color of each individual connection manifests at random, and there’s no way to choose or change its color.</s>
 <s id="9">And there’s one more problem: each individual nodule creates a temporal instability that raises the chances the portal might collapse as you go through it.</s>
 <s id="10">So the fewer you bring, the better.</s>
 <s id="11">The portal’s about to close.</s>
 <s id="12">What’s the minimum number of nodules you need to bring to be certain you’ll create a red or blue triangle and get back to the present?</s>
 <s id="13">Pause here if you want to figure it out for yourself!</s>
 <s id="14">Answer in: 3 Answer in: 2 Answer in: 1 This question is so rich that an entire branch of mathematics known as Ramsey Theory developed from it.</s>
 <s id="15">Ramsey Theory is home to some famously difficult problems.</s>
 <s id="16">This one isn’t easy, but it can be handled if you approach it systematically.</s>
 <s id="17">Imagine you brought just three nodules.</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">Would that be enough?</s>
  <s id="18.2">No - for example, you might have two blue and one red connection, and be stuck in the past forever.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">Would four nodules be enough?</s>
  <s id="19.2">No - there are many arrangements here that don’t give a blue or red triangle.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">What about five?</s>
 <s id="21">It turns out there is an arrangement of connections that avoids creating a blue or red triangle.</s>
 <s id="22">These smaller triangles don’t count because they don’t have a nodule at each corner.</s>
 <s id="23">However, six nodules will always create a blue triangle or a red triangle.</s>
 <s id="24">Here’s how we can prove that without sorting through every possible case.</s>
 <s id="25">Imagine activating the sixth nodule, and consider how it might connect to the other five.</s>
 <s id="26">It could do so in one of six ways: with five red connections, five blue connections, or some mix of red and blue.</s>
 <s id="27">Notice that every possibility has at least three connections of the same color coming from this nodule.</s>
 <s id="28">Let’s look at just the nodules on the other end of those same three color connections.</s>
 <s id="29">If the connections were blue, then any additional blue connection between those three would give us a blue triangle.</s>
 <s id="30">So the only way we could get in trouble is if all the connections between them were red.</s>
 <s id="31">But those three red connections would give us a red triangle.</s>
 <s id="32">No matter what happens, we’ll get a red or a blue triangle, and open our doorway.</s>
 <s id="33">On the other hand, if the original three connections were all red instead of blue, the same argument still works, with all the colors flipped.</s>
 <s id="34">In other words, no matter how the connections are colored, six nodules will always create a red or blue triangle and a doorway leading home.</s>
 <s id="35">So you grab six nodules and jump through the portal.</s>
 <s id="36">You were hoping your internship would give you valuable life experience.</s>
 <s id="37">Turns out, that didn’t take much time.</s>
</text>
