<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So, 120 years ago, Dr. Röntgen X-rayed his wife's hand.</s>
 <p id="p2">
  <s id="2.1">Quite why he had to pin her fingers to the floor with her brooch, I'm not sure.</s>
  <s id="2.2">It seems a bit extreme to me.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="3">That image was the start of the X-ray technology.</s>
 <s id="4">And I'm still fundamentally using the same principles today.</s>
 <s id="5">I'm interpreting it in a more contemporary manner.</s>
 <s id="6">The first shot I ever did was of a soda can, which was to promote a brand that we all know, so I'm not going to do them any favors by showing you it.</s>
 <s id="7">But the second shot I did was my shoes I was wearing on the day.</s>
 <s id="8">And I do really like this shot, because it shows all the detritus that's sort of embedded in the sole of the sneakers.</s>
 <s id="9">It was just one of those pot-luck things where you get it right first time.</s>
 <s id="10">Moving on to something a bit larger, this is an X-ray of a bus.</s>
 <s id="11">And the bus is full of people.</s>
 <p id="p12">
  <s id="12.1">It's actually the same person.</s>
  <s id="12.2">It's just one skeleton.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="13">And back in the '60s, they used to teach student radiographers to take X-rays, thankfully not on you and I, but on dead people.</s>
 <s id="14">So, I've still got access to one of these dead people called Frieda; she's falling apart, I'm afraid, because she's very old and fragile.</s>
 <s id="15">But everyone on that bus is Frieda.</s>
 <s id="16">And the bus is taken with a cargo-scanning X-ray, which is the sort of machine you have on borders, which checks for contraband and drugs and bombs and things.</s>
 <s id="17">Fairly obvious what that is.</s>
 <s id="18">So, using large-scale objects does sort of create drama because you just don't see X-rays of big things that often.</s>
 <s id="19">Technology is moving ahead, and these large cargo scanner X-rays that work with the digital system are getting better and better and better.</s>
 <s id="20">Again though, to make it come alive you need, somehow, to add the human element.</s>
 <s id="21">And I think the reason this image works, again, is because Frieda is driving the bulldozer.</s>
 <s id="22">(Laughter) Quite a difficult brief, make a pair of men's pants look beautiful.</s>
 <s id="23">But I think the process, in itself, shows how exquisite they are.</s>
 <s id="24">Fashion -- now, I'm sort of anti-fashion because I don't show the surface, I show what's within.</s>
 <s id="25">So, the fashionistas don't really like me because it doesn't matter if Kate Moss is wearing it or if I'm wearing it, it looks the same.</s>
 <s id="26">(Laughter) We all look the same inside, believe me.</s>
 <s id="27">The creases in the material and the sort of nuances.</s>
 <s id="28">And I show things for really what they are, what they're made of.</s>
 <s id="29">I peel back the layers and expose it.</s>
 <s id="30">And if it's well made I show it, if it's badly made I show it.</s>
 <s id="31">And I'm sure Ross can associate that with design.</s>
 <s id="32">The design comes from within.</s>
 <s id="33">It's not just Topshop, I get some strange looks when I go out getting my props.</s>
 <s id="34">Here I was fumbling around in the ladies' underwear department of a department store, almost got escorted from the premises.</s>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">I live opposite a farm.</s>
  <s id="35.2">And this was the runt of the litter, a piglet that died.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="36">And what's really interesting is, if you look at the legs, you'll notice that the bones haven't fused.</s>
 <s id="37">And should that pig have grown, unfortunately it was dead, it would have certainly been dead after I X-rayed it, with the amount of radiation I used anyway.</s>
 <s id="38">(Laughter) But once the bones had fused together it would have been healthy.</s>
 <s id="39">So, that's an empty parka jacket.</s>
 <s id="40">But I quite love the way it's posed.</s>
 <s id="41">Nature is my greatest inspiration.</s>
 <s id="42">And to carry on with a theme that we've already touched with is how nature is related to architecture.</s>
 <s id="43">If you look at the roof of the Eden Project, or the British library, it's all this honeycomb structure.</s>
 <s id="44">And I'm sure those architects are inspired, as I am, by what surrounds us, by nature.</s>
 <s id="45">This, in fact, is a Victoria water lily leaf that floats on the top of a pond.</s>
 <s id="46">An amaryllis flower looking really three-dimensional.</s>
 <s id="47">Seaweed, ebbing in the tide.</s>
 <s id="48">Now, how do I do this, and where do I do this, and all of that sort of thing.</s>
 <s id="49">This is my new, purpose-built, X-ray shed.</s>
 <s id="50">And the door to my X-ray room is made of lead and steel.</s>
 <s id="51">It weighs 1,250 kilograms and the only exercise I get is opening and closing it.</s>
 <s id="52">(Laughter) The walls are 700 millimeters thick of solid dense concrete.</s>
 <s id="53">So, I'm using quite a lot of radiation.</s>
 <s id="54">A lot more than you'd get in a hospital or a vet's.</s>
 <p id="p55">
  <s id="55.1">And there I am.</s>
  <s id="55.2">This is a quite high-powered X-ray machine.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="56">What's interesting really about X-ray really is, if you think about it, is that that technology is used for looking for cancer or looking for drugs, or looking for contraband or whatever.</s>
 <s id="57">And I use that sort of technology to create things that are quite beautiful.</s>
 <s id="58">So, still working with film, I'm afraid.</s>
 <s id="59">Technology in X-ray where it's life-size processed, apart from these large cargo-scanning machines, hasn't moved on enough for the quality of the image and the resolution to be good enough for what I want to do with it, which is show my pictures big.</s>
 <s id="60">So, I have to use a 1980s drum scanner, which was designed in the days when everyone shot photographs on film.</s>
 <s id="61">They scan each individual X-ray.</s>
 <s id="62">And this shows how I do my process of same-size X-rays.</s>
 <s id="63">So, this is, again, my daughter's dress.</s>
 <s id="64">Still has the tag in it from me buying it, so I can take it back to the shop if she didn't like it.</s>
 <s id="65">But there are four X-ray plates.</s>
 <s id="66">You can see them overlapping.</s>
 <s id="67">So, when you move forward from something fairly small, a dress which is this size, onto something like that which is done in exactly the same process, you can see that that is a lot of work.</s>
 <s id="68">In fact, that is three months solid X-raying.</s>
 <s id="69">There is over 500 separate components.</s>
 <s id="70">Boeing sent me a 747 in containers.</s>
 <s id="71">And I sent them back an X-ray.</s>
 <s id="72">(Laughter) I kid you not.</s>
 <s id="73">Okay, so Frieda is my dead skeleton.</s>
 <s id="74">This, unfortunately, is basically two pictures.</s>
 <s id="75">One on the extreme right is a photograph of an American footballer.</s>
 <s id="76">The one on the left is an x-ray.</s>
 <s id="77">But this time I had to use a real body.</s>
 <s id="78">Because I needed all the skin tissue to make it look real, to make it look like it was a real athlete.</s>
 <s id="79">So, here I had to use a recently deceased body.</s>
 <s id="80">And getting a hold of that was extremely difficult and laborious.</s>
 <s id="81">But people do donate their bodies to art and science.</s>
 <s id="82">And when they do, I'm in the queue.</s>
 <s id="83">So, I like to use them.</s>
 <s id="84">(Laughter) The coloring, so coloring adds another level to the X-rays.</s>
 <s id="85">It makes it more organic, more natural.</s>
 <s id="86">It's whatever takes my fancy, really.</s>
 <s id="87">It's not accurately colored to how it is in real life.</s>
 <s id="88">That flower doesn't come in bright orange, I don't think.</s>
 <s id="89">But I just like it in bright orange.</s>
 <s id="90">And also with something technical, like these are DJ decks, it sort of adds another level.</s>
 <s id="91">It makes a two dimensional image look more three dimensional.</s>
 <s id="92">The most difficult things to X-ray, the most technically challenging things to X-ray are the lightest things, the most delicate things.</s>
 <s id="93">To get the detail in a feather, believe me, if there is anyone out here who knows anything about X-rays, that's quite a challenge.</s>
 <s id="94">I'm now going to show you a short film, I'll step to the side.</s>
 <s id="95">Video: (Music) The thing in there is very dangerous.</s>
 <s id="96">If you touch that, you could possibly die through radiation poisoning.</s>
 <s id="97">In my career I've had two exposures to radiation, which is two too many, because it stays with you for life.</s>
 <s id="98">It's cumulative.</s>
 <s id="99">(Music) It has human connotations.</s>
 <s id="100">The fact that it's a child's toy that we all recognize, but also it looks like it's a robot, and it comes from a sci-fi genus.</s>
 <s id="101">It's a surprise that it has humanity, but also man-made, future, alien associations.</s>
 <s id="102">And it's just a bit spooky.</s>
 <s id="103">(Music) The bus was done with a cargo-scanning X-ray machine, which is used on the borders between countries, looking for contraband and illegal immigrants.</s>
 <p id="p104">
  <s id="104.1">The lorry goes in front of it.</s>
  <s id="104.2">And it takes slices of X-rays through the lorry.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p105">
  <s id="105.1">And that's how this was done.</s>
  <s id="105.2">It's actually slice, slice.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p106">
  <s id="106.1">It's a bit like a CT scanner in a hospital.</s>
  <s id="106.2">Slices.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="107">And then if you look carefully, there is all little things.</s>
 <s id="108">He's got headphones on, reading the newspaper, got a hat on, glasses, got a bag.</s>
 <s id="109">So, these little details help to make it work, make it real.</s>
 <s id="110">(Music) The problem with using living people is that to take an X-ray, if I X-ray you, you get exposed to radiation.</s>
 <s id="111">So, to avoid that -- I have to avoid it somehow -- is I use dead people.</s>
 <s id="112">Now, that's a variety of things, from recently deceased bodies, to a skeleton that was used by student radiographers to train in taking X-rays of the human body, at different densities.</s>
 <s id="113">(Music) I have very high-tech equipment of gloves, scissors and a bucket.</s>
 <s id="114">(Music) I will show how the capillary action works, how it feeds, I'll be able to get all the cells inside that stem.</s>
 <s id="115">Because it transfers food from its roots to its leaves.</s>
 <s id="116">Look at this monster.</s>
 <p id="p117">
  <s id="117.1">(Music) It's so basic.</s>
  <s id="117.2">It just grows wild.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="118">That's what I really like about it, the fact that I haven't got to go and buy it, and it hasn't been genetically modified at all.</s>
 <s id="119">It's just happening.</s>
 <s id="120">And the X-ray shows how beautiful nature can be.</s>
 <p id="p121">
  <s id="121.1">Not that that is particularly beautiful when you look at it with the human eye, the way the leaves form.</s>
  <s id="121.2">They're curling back on each other.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="122">So the X-ray will show the overlaps in these little corners.</s>
 <s id="123">The thicker the object, the more radiation it needs, and the more time it needs.</s>
 <s id="124">The lighter the object, the less radiation.</s>
 <s id="125">Sometimes you keep the time up, because the time gives you detail.</s>
 <s id="126">The longer the exposure goes on for, the more detail you get.</s>
 <s id="127">(Music) If you look at this, just the tube, it is quite bright.</s>
 <s id="128">But I could get a bit darker in the tube, but everything else would suffer.</s>
 <s id="129">So, these leaves at the edge would start to disappear.</s>
 <s id="130">What I like is how hard the edges are, how sharp.</s>
 <s id="131">Yeah, I'm quite pleased with it.</s>
 <s id="132">(Music) I travel beyond the surface and show something for what it's worth, for what it's really made of, how it really works.</s>
 <s id="133">But also I find that I've got the benefit of taking away all the surface, which is things that people are used to seeing.</s>
 <s id="134">And that's the sort of thing I've been doing.</s>
 <s id="135">I've got the opportunity now to show you what I'm going to be doing in the future.</s>
 <s id="136">This is a commercial application of my most recent work.</s>
 <s id="137">And what's good about this, I think, is that it's like a moment in time, like you've turned around, you've got X-ray vision and you've taken a picture with the X-ray camera.</s>
 <s id="138">Unfortunately I haven't got X-ray vision.</s>
 <p id="p139">
  <s id="139.1">I do dream in X-ray.</s>
  <s id="139.2">I see my projects in my sleep.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="140">And I know what they're going to look like in X-ray and I'm not far off.</s>
 <s id="141">So, what am I doing in the future?</s>
 <s id="142">Well, this year is the 50th anniversary of Issigonis's Mini, which is one of my favorite cars.</s>
 <s id="143">So, I've taken it apart, component by component, months and months and months of work.</s>
 <s id="144">And with this image, I'm going to be displaying it in the Victoria and Albert Museum as a light box, which is actually attached to the car.</s>
 <s id="145">So, I've got to saw the car in half, down the middle, not an easy task, in itself.</s>
 <s id="146">And then, so you can get in the driver's side, sit down, and up against you is a wall.</s>
 <s id="147">And if you get out and walk around to the other side of the car, you see a life-sized light box of the car showing you how it works.</s>
 <s id="148">And I'm going to take that idea and apply it to other sort of iconic things from my life.</s>
 <s id="149">Like, my first computer was a big movement in my life.</s>
 <p id="p150">
  <s id="150.1">And I had a Mac Classic.</s>
  <s id="150.2">And it's a little box.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="151">And I think that would look quite neat as an X-ray.</s>
 <s id="152">I'm also looking to take my work from the two-dimensional form to a more three-dimensional form.</s>
 <s id="153">And this is quite a good way of doing it.</s>
 <s id="154">I'm also working now with X-ray video.</s>
 <s id="155">So, if you can imagine, some of these flowers, and they're actually moving and growing and you can film that in X-ray, should be quite stunning.</s>
 <p id="p156">
  <s id="156.1">But that's it.</s>
  <s id="156.2">I'm done.</s>
  <s id="156.3">Thank you very much.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="157">(Applause)</s>
</text>
