<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Do you think the things we build today will be considered wonders in the future?</s>
 <s id="2">Think of Stonehenge, the Pyramids, Machu Picchu and Easter Island.</s>
 <s id="3">Now, they're all pretty different from what we're doing today, with those massive stones, assembled in complex but seemingly illogical ways, and all traces of their construction erased, shrouding them in mystery.</s>
 <s id="4">It seems like people could not have possibly built these things, because people didn't.</s>
 <s id="5">They were carefully crafted by a primordial race of giants known as Cyclops.</s>
 <s id="6">(Laughter) And I've been collaborating with these monsters to learn their secrets for moving those massive stones.</s>
 <s id="7">And as it turns out, Cyclops aren't even that strong.</s>
 <s id="8">They're just really smart about getting material to work for them.</s>
 <s id="9">Now, the videos you see behind me of large, stone-like, wobbly creatures are the results of this collaboration.</s>
 <s id="10">OK, so Cyclops might be a mythical creature, but those wonders are still real.</s>
 <s id="11">People made them.</s>
 <s id="12">But they also made the myths that surround them, and when it comes to wonders, there's this thick connective tissue between mythology and reality.</s>
 <s id="13">Take Easter Island, for example.</s>
 <s id="14">When the Dutch explorers first encountered the island, they asked the people of Rapa Nui how their ancestors could have possibly moved those massive statues.</s>
 <s id="15">And the Rapa Nui said, "Our ancestors didn't move the statues, because the statues walked themselves."</s>
 <s id="16">For centuries, this was dismissed, but actually it's true.</s>
 <s id="17">The statues, known as moai, were transported standing, pivoting from side to side.</s>
 <s id="18">OK?</s>
 <s id="19">As spectacular as the moai are for visitors today, you have to imagine being there then, with colossal moai marching around the island.</s>
 <s id="20">Because the real memorial was not the objects themselves, it was the cultural ritual of bringing a stone to life.</s>
 <s id="21">So as an architect, I've been chasing that dream.</s>
 <s id="22">How can we shift our idea of construction to accommodate that mythical side?</s>
 <s id="23">So what I've been doing is challenging myself with putting on a series of performances of the ancient but pretty straightforward task of just moving and standing big heavy objects, like this 16-foot-tall megalith designed to walk across land and stand vertically; or this 4,000-pound behemoth that springs itself to life to dance onstage.</s>
 <s id="24">And what I've found is that by thinking of architecture not as an end product but as a performance from conception to completion, we end up rediscovering some really smart ways to build things today.</s>
 <s id="25">You know, so much of the discussion surrounding our future focuses on technology, efficiency and speed.</s>
 <s id="26">But if I've learned anything from Cyclops, it's that wonders can be smart, spectacular and sustainable -- because of their mass and their mystery.</s>
 <s id="27">And while people still want to know how those ancient wonders were built, I've been asking Cyclops how to create the mystery that compels people to ask that very question.</s>
 <s id="28">Because in an era where we design buildings to last 30, maybe 60 years, I would love to learn how to create something that could entertain for an eternity.</s>
 <s id="29">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="30">(Applause)</s>
</text>
