<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">At 7:45 a.m., I open the doors to a building dedicated to building, yet only breaks me down.</s>
 <s id="2">I march down hallways cleaned up after me every day by regular janitors, but I never have the decency to honor their names.</s>
 <s id="3">Lockers left open like teenage boys' mouths when teenage girls wear clothes that covers their insecurities but exposes everything else.</s>
 <s id="4">Masculinity mimicked by men who grew up with no fathers, camouflage worn by bullies who are dangerously armed but need hugs.</s>
 <s id="5">Teachers paid less than what it costs them to be here.</s>
 <s id="6">Oceans of adolescents come here to receive lessons but never learn to swim, part like the Red Sea when the bell rings.</s>
 <s id="7">This is a training ground.</s>
 <s id="8">My high school is Chicago, diverse and segregated on purpose.</s>
 <s id="9">Social lines are barbed wire.</s>
 <s id="10">Labels like "Regulars" and "Honors" resonate.</s>
 <s id="11">I am an Honors but go home with Regular students who are soldiers in territory that owns them.</s>
 <s id="12">This is a training ground to sort out the Regulars from the Honors, a reoccurring cycle built to recycle the trash of this system.</s>
 <s id="13">Trained at a young age to capitalize, letters taught now that capitalism raises you but you have to step on someone else to get there.</s>
 <s id="14">This is a training ground where one group is taught to lead and the other is made to follow.</s>
 <s id="15">No wonder so many of my people spit bars, because the truth is hard to swallow.</s>
 <s id="16">The need for degrees has left so many people frozen.</s>
 <s id="17">Homework is stressful, but when you go home every day and your home is work, you don't want to pick up any assignments.</s>
 <s id="18">Reading textbooks is stressful, but reading does not matter when you feel your story is already written, either dead or getting booked.</s>
 <s id="19">Taking tests is stressful, but bubbling in a Scantron does not stop bullets from bursting.</s>
 <s id="20">I hear education systems are failing, but I believe they're succeeding at what they're built to do -- to train you, to keep you on track, to track down an American dream that has failed so many of us all.</s>
 <s id="21">(Applause)</s>
</text>
