<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">There is a curse that has plagued humanity since ancient times.</s>
 <s id="2">The Greeks fought it by chewing aromatic resins, while the Chinese resorted to egg shells.</s>
 <s id="3">In the ancient Jewish Talmud, it's even considered legal grounds for divorce.</s>
 <s id="4">This horrible scourge is halitosis, otherwise known as bad breath.</s>
 <s id="5">But what causes it, and why is it so universally terrifying?</s>
 <s id="6">Well, think of some of the worst odors you can imagine, like garbage, feces or rotting meat.</s>
 <s id="7">All of these smells come from the activity of microorganisms, particularly bacteria, and, as disgusting as it may sound, similar bacteria live in the moisture-rich environment of your mouth.</s>
 <s id="8">Don't panic.</s>
 <s id="9">The presence of bacteria in your body is not only normal, it's actually vital for all sorts of things, like digestion and disease prevention.</s>
 <s id="10">But like all living things, bacteria need to eat.</s>
 <s id="11">The bacteria in your mouth feed off of mucus, food remnants, and dead tissue cells.</s>
 <s id="12">In order to absorb nutrients through their cell membranes, they must break down the organic matter into much smaller molecules.</s>
 <s id="13">For example, they'll break proteins into their component amino acids and then break those down even further into various compounds.</s>
 <s id="14">Some of the foul-smelling byproducts of these reactions, such as hydrogen sulfide and cadaverine, escape into the air and waft their way towards unsuspecting noses.</s>
 <s id="15">Our sensitivity to these odors and interpretation of them as bad smells may be an evolutionary mechanism warning us of rotten food and the presence of disease.</s>
 <s id="16">Smell is one of our most intimate and primal senses, playing a huge role in our attraction to potential mates.</s>
 <s id="17">In one poll, 59% of men and 70% of women said they wouldn't go on a date with someone who has bad breath, which may be why Americans alone spend $1 billion a year on various breath products.</s>
 <s id="18">Fortunately, most bad breath is easily treated.</s>
 <s id="19">The worst smelling byproducts come from gram-negative bacteria that live in the spaces between gums and teeth and on the back of the tongue.</s>
 <s id="20">By brushing and flossing our teeth, using antibacterial mouthwash at bedtime, gently cleaning the back of the tongue with a plastic scraper and even just eating a healthy breakfast, we can remove many of these bacteria and their food sources.</s>
 <s id="21">In some cases, these measures may not be enough due to dental problems, nasal conditions, or rarer ailments, such as liver disease and uncontrolled diabetes.</s>
 <s id="22">Behaviors like smoking and excessive alcohol consumption also have a very recognizable odor.</s>
 <s id="23">Regardless of cause, the bad smell almost always originates in the mouth and not the stomach or elsewhere in the body.</s>
 <s id="24">But one of the biggest challenges lies in actually determining how our breath smells in the first place, and it's unclear why.</s>
 <s id="25">It may be that we're too acclimatized to the smell inside our own mouths to judge it.</s>
 <s id="26">And methods like cupping your hands over your mouth, or licking and smelling your wrist don't work perfectly either.</s>
 <s id="27">One study showed that even when people do this, they tend to rate the smell subjectively according to how bad they thought it was going to be.</s>
 <s id="28">But there's one simple, if socially difficult, way of finding out how your breath smells: just take a deep breath and ask a friend.</s>
</text>
