<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">What's up, people?</s>
 <s id="2">First of all, I cannot believe I'm on TED Talk.</s>
 <s id="3">This is a big deal.</s>
 <s id="4">Because right now, everybody in my village is watching this.</s>
 <s id="5">And so, of course, my bride price just went up.</s>
 <s id="6">My name is Adeola Fayehun.</s>
 <s id="7">I'm from Nigeria.</s>
 <s id="8">I live in the US, I'm a journalist, or a comedian, or a satirist, anything you want me to be, really.</s>
 <s id="9">I'm every woman, it's all in me.</s>
 <s id="10">I host a YouTube show called "Keeping It Real with Adeola."</s>
 <s id="11">Now this show is a gentle, respectful and very blunt way of calling out corrupt African leaders.</s>
 <s id="12">(Video) President Buhari: I don't know which party my wife belongs to, but she belongs to my kitchen.</s>
 <s id="13">Adeola Fayehun: Oh, my God!</s>
 <s id="14">I need some water -- I said I need some water!</s>
 <s id="15">See?</s>
 <s id="16">I basically keep it real with them, ha!</s>
 <s id="17">Especially when they mess up, which is a lot of times.</s>
 <s id="18">If any African official is watching me, by the way, I'm not talking about you, sir.</s>
 <s id="19">I'm talking about your colleagues, yes.</s>
 <s id="20">I do this because Africa has everything in it to be great.</s>
 <s id="21">You know, I grew up believing that Africa as a continent is a giant.</s>
 <s id="22">We've got skills, intellectuals, natural resources more than any other continent.</s>
 <s id="23">Africa supplies 31 percent of the world's gold, manganese and uranium, 57 percent of the world's diamonds and 13 percent of the world's oil.</s>
 <s id="24">We have no reason to depend on aid or borrowing money from China or the World Bank.</s>
 <s id="25">But without good leaders, we're like an eagle that has no idea it could fly, let alone soar.</s>
 <s id="26">Africa is a like a sleeping giant.</s>
 <s id="27">Now the truth is, I'm trying to wake up this giant, and that's why I air the dirty laundry of those in charge of the giant.</s>
 <s id="28">Our politicians, our religious leaders, with huge respect, of course, because more than anything else, African leaders love to be respected.</s>
 <s id="29">So I give it to them in doses.</s>
 <s id="30">On my show, I kneel for them -- ha! -- I call them my uncles, my aunties, my fathers in the lord, and then -- I insult them for insulting our intelligence.</s>
 <s id="31">And it's because we are tired of the hypocrisy and false promises.</s>
 <s id="32">For example, the Nigerian president vowed to end medical tourism by fixing our dilapidated hospitals and building us new ones.</s>
 <s id="33">But what did he do?</s>
 <s id="34">He spends three months receiving treatment in London in 2017.</s>
 <s id="35">We were without a president for three months.</s>
 <s id="36">We were president-less for three months.</s>
 <s id="37">So then it becomes my job to call out the President, with respect, of course.</s>
 <s id="38">I said, "Ha, Mr. President, it's your girl, Adeola.</s>
 <s id="39">You know how I do, how you doing?</s>
 <s id="40">You have no shame."</s>
 <s id="41">I forgot to add "sir."</s>
 <s id="42">"Sir, you have no shame.</s>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">(In Yoruba: You have no fear of God.)</s>
  <s id="43.2">You have no fear of God."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">Thirty-five thousand Nigerian doctors are presently working in the US, the UK and Canada, doing amazing things, because in Nigeria, they are not well-paid, neither do they have the necessary equipment to do the job of being a doctor.</s>
 <s id="45">And this is happening in many African countries.</s>
 <s id="46">We have the capacity to fly.</s>
 <s id="47">But sadly, a lot of African talent is flying straight out of Africa to other continents.</s>
 <s id="48">For example, this Nigerian doctor operated on an unborn baby in Texas.</s>
 <s id="49">Also, this Nigerian doctor discovered the neurological effects of concussion on athletes.</s>
 <s id="50">And many countries have African athletes winning the gold medal for them.</s>
 <s id="51">The interesting thing is, we're waiting for God to fix Africa.</s>
 <s id="52">Like, for real, it's not a joke, we are, we're waiting for God.</s>
 <s id="53">I mean, just look at the president of Burundi.</s>
 <s id="54">He's jailing journalists and opposition members, but he declared national day of prayer so that people could pray for God to fix the country.</s>
 <s id="55">And I'm like, shouldn't he be fixing the country?</s>
 <s id="56">Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no.</s>
 <s id="57">We want God to fix it.</s>
 <s id="58">Do you see what I have to deal with?</s>
 <s id="59">I'm telling you, thunder is getting ready to hit these politicians some day.</s>
 <s id="60">We are better than this.</s>
 <s id="61">I want our leaders to start taking responsibility and stop putting everything on God.</s>
 <s id="62">God has given us everything we need.</s>
 <s id="63">It's right here, let's use it.</s>
 <s id="64">But here's the thing, my favorite part of what I do is featuring Africans doing amazing work, ordinary people touching lives.</s>
 <s id="65">Like this Kenyan woman, Wangari Maathai, the first African woman to receive the Nobel Peace prize, for standing up for human rights and planting a million trees.</s>
 <s id="66">Also this Zimbabwean woman, Dr. Tererai Trent, who was married off at the age of 14 in exchange for a cow.</s>
 <s id="67">Yet, this woman taught herself to read and write, and she ended up on Oprah's show.</s>
 <s id="68">Oh, Father, I want to be on Oprah some day.</s>
 <s id="69">Today, this woman has built schools for thousands of children in Zimbabwe.</s>
 <s id="70">Also, popular British architect David Adjaye has designed spectacular buildings around the world.</s>
 <s id="71">And he's both Ghanian and Tanzanian, so we know that it has to be the Ghanian Jollof rice, which he ate, that gave him the inspiration to design.</s>
 <s id="72">Ah, maybe it's the Nigerian Jollof rice, because Nigerian one is better.</s>
 <s id="73">Anyway, but that is what gave him the inspiration to become the great man that he is today.</s>
 <s id="74">And while I have your attention, I have one more thing to say, so please move closer.</s>
 <s id="75">OK, that's good, don't get too close, that's good.</s>
 <s id="76">I don't like the way some of you portray Africa.</s>
 <s id="77">Not all of you, just some of you.</s>
 <s id="78">You especially.</s>
 <s id="79">First of all, it's not a country, it's a continent.</s>
 <s id="80">I do not know Paul from Uganda, I don't know Rebecca from Zimbabwe.</s>
 <s id="81">Nigeria is as far from Zimbabwe as New York is from France.</s>
 <s id="82">And it's not a bunch of naked people in need of Western charity.</s>
 <s id="83">You have it all wrong.</s>
 <s id="84">Lions are not roaming our streets, OK?</s>
 <s id="85">And I could go on, but you already know what I'm talking about.</s>
 <s id="86">So while I try to do my job, trying to wake up the sleeping giant, Africa, so she could take her rightful place on the world's arena, you can your bit, too.</s>
 <s id="87">Please listen more.</s>
 <s id="88">Listen to your African friends without a preconceived notion of what you think that they're going to say.</s>
 <s id="89">Read African books.</s>
 <s id="90">Oh, my God, watch African movies.</s>
 <s id="91">Or at the very least, learn some of the names of our 54 beautiful countries.</s>
 <s id="92">That's right, 54, baby, five-four.</s>
 <s id="93">Alright, y'all, it's been real, and I'm keeping it real right up in here.</s>
 <s id="94">Until next time, I'm going to see you all later.</s>
 <s id="95">Peace out.</s>
</text>
