<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Hercules, son of Zeus and champion of humankind, gazed in horror as he realized he had just committed the most unspeakable crime imaginable.</s>
 <s id="2">The goddess Hera, who hated Hercules for being born of her husband’s adultery, had stricken him with a temporary curse of madness.</s>
 <s id="3">And his own family were the casualties.</s>
 <s id="4">Consumed by grief, Hercules sought out the Oracle of Delphi, who told him the path to atonement lay with his cousin, King Eurystheus of Tiryns, a favorite of Hera’s.</s>
 <s id="5">Eurystheus hoped to humiliate Hercules with ten impossible tasks that pitted him against invincible monsters and unfathomable forces.</s>
 <s id="6">Instead, the king set the stage for an epic series of adventures that would come to be known as the Labors of Hercules.</s>
 <s id="7">The first labor was to slay the Nemean Lion, who kidnapped women and devoured warriors.</s>
 <s id="8">Its golden fur was impervious to arrows, but Hercules cornered the lion in its dark cave, stunned it with a club, and strangled it with his bare hands.</s>
 <s id="9">He found no tool sharp enough to skin the beast, until the goddess Athena suggested using one of its own claws.</s>
 <s id="10">Hercules returned to Tiryns wearing the lion’s hide, frightening King Eurystheus so much that he hid in a wine jar.</s>
 <s id="11">From then on, Hercules was ordered to present his trophies at a safe distance.</s>
 <s id="12">The second target was the Lernaean Hydra, a giant serpent with many heads.</s>
 <s id="13">Hercules fought fiercely, but every time he cut one head off, two more grew in its place.</s>
 <s id="14">The battle was hopeless until his nephew Iolaus thought to cauterize the necks with fire, keeping the heads from regrowing.</s>
 <s id="15">The dead serpent’s remains became the Hydra constellation.</s>
 <s id="16">Instead of slaying a beast, Hercules next had to catch one, alive.</s>
 <s id="17">The Ceryneian Hind was a female deer so fast it could outrun an arrow.</s>
 <s id="18">Hercules tracked it for a year, finally trapping it in the northern land of Hyperborea.</s>
 <s id="19">The animal turned out to be sacred to Artemis, goddess of the hunt, and Hercules swore to return it.</s>
 <s id="20">When Eurystheus saw the hind, he demanded to keep it instead, but as soon as Hercules let go, the animal ran to its mistress.</s>
 <s id="21">Thus, Hercules completed his task without breaking his promise.</s>
 <s id="22">The fourth mission was to capture the Erymanthian boar, which had ravaged many fields.</s>
 <s id="23">Advised by the wise centaur Chiron, Hercules trapped it by chasing it into thick snow.</s>
 <s id="24">For the fifth task, there were no animals, just their leftovers.</s>
 <s id="25">The stables where King Augeas kept his hundreds of divine cattle had not been maintained in ages.</s>
 <s id="26">Hercules promised to clean them in one day if he could keep one-tenth of the livestock.</s>
 <s id="27">Augeas expected the hero to fail.</s>
 <s id="28">Instead, Hercules dug massive trenches, rerouting two nearby rivers to flow through the stables until they were spotless.</s>
 <s id="29">Next came three more beastly foes, each requiring a clever strategy to defeat.</s>
 <s id="30">The carnivorous Stymphalian birds nested in an impenetrable swamp, but Hercules used Athena’s special rattle to frighten them into the air, at which point he shot them down.</s>
 <s id="31">No mortal could stand before the Cretan bull’s mad rampage, but a chokehold from behind did the trick.</s>
 <s id="32">And the mad King Diomedes, who had trained his horses to devour his guests, got a taste of his own medicine when Hercules wrestled him into his own stables.</s>
 <s id="33">The ensuing feast calmed the beasts enough for Hercules to bind their mouths.</s>
 <s id="34">But the ninth labor involved someone more dangerous than any beast, Hippolyta, Queen of the Amazons.</s>
 <s id="35">Hercules was to retrieve the belt given to her by her father Ares, the god of war.</s>
 <s id="36">He sailed to the Amazon land of Themyscira prepared for battle, but the queen was so impressed with the hero and his exploits that she gave the belt willingly.</s>
 <s id="37">For his tenth labor, Hercules had to steal a herd of magical red cattle from Geryon, a giant with three heads and three bodies.</s>
 <s id="38">On his way, Hercules was so annoyed by the Libyan desert heat that he shot an arrow at the Sun.</s>
 <s id="39">The sun god Helios admired the hero’s strength and lent his chariot for the journey to the island of Erytheia.</s>
 <s id="40">There, Hercules fought off Geryon’s herdsman and his two-headed dog, before killing the giant himself.</s>
 <s id="41">That should have been the end.</s>
 <s id="42">But Eurystheus announced that two labors hadn’t counted: the Hydra, because Iolaus had helped Hercules kill it, and the stables, because he’d accepted payment.</s>
 <s id="43">And so, the hero set about his eleventh task, obtaining golden apples from the garden of the Hesperides nymphs.</s>
 <s id="44">Hercules began by catching the Old Man of the Sea and holding the shape-shifting water-god until he revealed the garden’s location.</s>
 <s id="45">Once there, the hero found the titan Atlas holding up the heavens.</s>
 <s id="46">Hercules offered to take his place if Atlas would retrieve the apples.</s>
 <s id="47">Atlas eagerly complied, but Hercules then tricked him into trading places again, escaping with apples in hand.</s>
 <s id="48">The twelfth and final task was to bring back Cerberus, the three-headed hound guarding the underworld.</s>
 <s id="49">Helped by Hermes and Athena, Hercules descended and met Hades himself.</s>
 <s id="50">The lord of the dead allowed Hercules to take the beast if he could do it without weapons, which he achieved by grabbing all three of its heads at once.</s>
 <s id="51">When he presented the hound to a horrified Eurystheus, the king finally declared the hero’s service complete.</s>
 <s id="52">After 12 years of toil, Hercules had redeemed the tragic deaths of his family and earned a place in the divine pantheon.</s>
 <s id="53">But his victory held an even deeper importance.</s>
 <s id="54">In overcoming the chaotic and monstrous forces of the world, the hero swept away what remained of the Titans’ primordial order, reshaping it into one where humanity could thrive.</s>
 <s id="55">Through his labors, Hercules tamed the world’s madness by atoning for his own.</s>
</text>
