<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The periodic table is instantly recognizable.</s>
 <s id="2">It's not just in every chemistry lab worldwide, it's found on t-shirts, coffee mugs, and shower curtains.</s>
 <s id="3">But the periodic table isn't just another trendy icon.</s>
 <s id="4">It's a massive slab of human genius, up there with the Taj Mahal, the Mona Lisa, and the ice cream sandwich -- and the table's creator, Dmitri Mendeleev, is a bonafide science hall-of-famer.</s>
 <p id="p5">
  <s id="5.1">But why?</s>
  <s id="5.2">What's so great about him and his table?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="6">Is it because he made a comprehensive list of the known elements?</s>
 <s id="7">Nah, you don't earn a spot in science Valhalla just for making a list.</s>
 <s id="8">Besides, Mendeleev was far from the first person to do that.</s>
 <s id="9">Is it because Mendeleev arranged elements with similar properties together?</s>
 <s id="10">Not really, that had already been done too.</s>
 <s id="11">So what was Mendeleev's genius?</s>
 <s id="12">Let's look at one of the first versions of the periodic table from around 1870.</s>
 <s id="13">Here we see elements designated by their two-letter symbols arranged in a table.</s>
 <s id="14">Check out the entry of the third column, fifth row.</s>
 <s id="15">There's a dash there.</s>
 <s id="16">From that unassuming placeholder springs the raw brilliance of Mendeleev.</s>
 <s id="17">That dash is science.</s>
 <s id="18">By putting that dash there, Dmitri was making a bold statement.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">He said -- and I'm paraphrasing here -- Y'all haven't discovered this element yet.</s>
  <s id="19.2">In the meantime, I'm going to give it a name.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">It's one step away from aluminum, so we'll call it eka-aluminum, "eka" being Sanskrit for one.</s>
 <s id="21">Nobody's found eka-aluminum yet, so we don't know anything about it, right?</s>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">Wrong!</s>
  <s id="22.2">Based on where it's located, I can tell you all about it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">First of all, an atom of eka-aluminum has an atomic weight of 68, about 68 times heavier than a hydrogen atom.</s>
 <s id="24">When eka-aluminum is isolated, you'll see it's a solid metal at room temperature.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">It's shiny, it conducts heat really well, it can be flattened into a sheet, stretched into a wire, but its melting point is low.</s>
  <s id="25.2">Like, freakishly low.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">Oh, and a cubic centimeter of it will weigh six grams.</s>
 <s id="27">Mendeleev could predict all of these things simply from where the blank spot was, and his understanding of how the elements surrounding it behave.</s>
 <s id="28">A few years after this prediction, a French guy named Paul Emile Lecoq de Boisbaudran discovered a new element in ore samples and named it gallium after Gaul, the historical name for France.</s>
 <s id="29">Gallium is one step away from aluminum on the periodic table.</s>
 <p id="p30">
  <s id="30.1">It's eka-aluminum.</s>
  <s id="30.2">So were Mendeleev's predictions right?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="31">Gallium's atomic weight is 69.72.</s>
 <s id="32">A cubic centimeter of it weighs 5.9 grams.</s>
 <s id="33">it's a solid metal at room temperature, but it melts at a paltry 30 degrees Celcius, 85 degrees Fahrenheit.</s>
 <s id="34">It melts in your mouth and in your hand.</s>
 <s id="35">Not only did Mendeleev completely nail gallium, he predicted other elements that were unknown at the time: scandium, germanium, rhenium.</s>
 <s id="36">The element he called eka-manganese is now called technetium.</s>
 <s id="37">Technetium is so rare it couldn't be isolated until it was synthesized in a cyclotron in 1937, almost 70 years after Dmitri predicted its existence, 30 years after he died.</s>
 <s id="38">Dmitri died without a Nobel Prize in 1907, but he wound up receiving a much more exclusive honor.</s>
 <s id="39">In 1955, scientists at UC Berkeley successfully created 17 atoms of a previously undiscovered element.</s>
 <s id="40">This element filled an empty spot in the perodic table at number 101, and was officially named Mendelevium in 1963.</s>
 <s id="41">There have been well over 800 Nobel Prize winners, but only 15 scientists have an element named after them.</s>
 <s id="42">So the next time you stare at a periodic table, whether it's on the wall of a university classroom or on a five-dollar coffee mug, Dmitri Mendeleev, the architect of the periodic table, will be staring back.</s>
</text>
