<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">A few years ago, I got a call from the highest ranking legal official in the state of Georgia: the attorney general.</s>
 <s id="2">That moment was a wake-up call.</s>
 <s id="3">It was 2013, and the city of Atlanta was hosting the Final Four basketball tournament.</s>
 <s id="4">The AG called to ask if the company that I worked for could help sponsor billboards that would be put up around the city as part of an anti-human trafficking campaign.</s>
 <s id="5">He said this was important because sex trafficking spikes with big sporting events and with conventions.</s>
 <s id="6">And the billboards would help to raise awareness.</s>
 <s id="7">Now, if I'm being honest with you, my first inclination was to politely decline.</s>
 <s id="8">(Laughter) Let's face it -- there are thousands of things that corporate America could get involved in.</s>
 <s id="9">Sex trafficking seemed a little messy.</s>
 <s id="10">Little bit too difficult, something that is better left for someone else.</s>
 <s id="11">But then I started to understand and learn how big the problem really is.</s>
 <s id="12">And that it's rampant in my company's home town.</s>
 <s id="13">I lived and worked in Atlanta for years.</s>
 <s id="14">I practice law here.</s>
 <s id="15">And yet, I had no idea that the birthplace of my children is among the most prevalent cities for sex trafficking in the US.</s>
 <s id="16">At last report, Atlanta's illegal sex trade has generated up to 290 million dollars a year.</s>
 <s id="17">That's more money that the city's illegal gun and drug trade combined.</s>
 <s id="18">So we stepped up and we helped with the billboards.</s>
 <s id="19">But I couldn't help feeling like it wasn't enough.</s>
 <s id="20">The parent in me, the mother in me needed to do more.</s>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">I started talking to people about this and inevitably, I was surprised, because the conversation would turn from curiosity: "Really?</s>
  <s id="21.2">This happens here?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="22">to empathy: "Wow, we've got to do something about that."</s>
 <s id="23">To blame: "You're not telling me that every prostitute is a victim, are you?</s>
 <s id="24">I mean, don't they know what they're getting into?"</s>
 <s id="25">I get it, I understand why people are confused.</s>
 <s id="26">So, to be clear, the people that I'm talking about do not choose this life.</s>
 <s id="27">They're forced, defrauded or coerced.</s>
 <s id="28">That's actually the legal definition for human trafficking under federal law, for adults.</s>
 <s id="29">Now, when it comes to kids, any minor under 18 that's transported, facilitated or used for commercial sex, is automatically a victim.</s>
 <s id="30">Regardless of whether force, fraud or coercion is used.</s>
 <s id="31">This crime knows no age, gender or socioeconomic barrier.</s>
 <s id="32">I'm talking about the 16-year-old girl that I met in Washington, DC.</s>
 <s id="33">She had been trafficked from the time she was 14 until she was 16.</s>
 <s id="34">She was a victim of the foster care system.</s>
 <s id="35">And she told me she'd been sold up to five times a day.</s>
 <s id="36">She didn't even know the term "human trafficking;" she thought that it was just a part of her life as a foster care kid.</s>
 <s id="37">Sex trafficking also shows up in affluent areas and gated communities.</s>
 <s id="38">And men lure young girls into sex trafficking situations with promises of modeling contracts, cell phones.</s>
 <s id="39">Sometimes they're just kidnapped right off the street.</s>
 <s id="40">In the US, an estimated 200,000 to 300,000 girls and boys are anticipated to be used for commercial sex trafficking every year.</s>
 <s id="41">You heard that right -- girls and boys.</s>
 <s id="42">Worldwide, the International Labor Organization estimates that up to one million children a year are vulnerable for sex trafficking.</s>
 <s id="43">Those numbers are huge.</s>
 <s id="44">And so while the billboards are great for raising awareness generally, they're just not enough to put an end to this problem.</s>
 <s id="45">I believe that if we're going to be serious about sex trafficking, we can't legislate or arrest our way out of modern-day slavery.</s>
 <s id="46">If we really want to end sex trafficking in the US, we have to systematically educate and target demand.</s>
 <s id="47">And I think the business community is in the perfect position to do just that.</s>
 <s id="48">So, sex trafficking is big business.</s>
 <s id="49">And I'm proposing a business plan that starts with the customer.</s>
 <s id="50">And in the sex trade, the customer is referred to as a John.</s>
 <s id="51">He is the man that fuels the demand for sex trafficking.</s>
 <s id="52">Johns do not fit into neat stereotypes.</s>
 <s id="53">But there is one universal truth: no John, no buyer, no victim.</s>
 <s id="54">So if we want to start to put a dent in sex trafficking, we have to get to John.</s>
 <s id="55">And businesses can do that while he's at work.</s>
 <s id="56">There's an organization called Businesses Ending Slavery and Trafficking, or BEST for short.</s>
 <s id="57">And when they launched in 2012, they did a study of Seattle-based Johns.</s>
 <s id="58">And you know what they found out?</s>
 <s id="59">Johns are everyday guys, employed at local businesses.</s>
 <s id="60">They range in age from 18 to 84.</s>
 <s id="61">Johns are dads.</s>
 <s id="62">Johns have admitted that they buy sex when they are traveling for business, when they're going to sporting events or when they're in the military.</s>
 <s id="63">But here's the kicker.</s>
 <s id="64">BEST study determined that web-based sex buying spikes at 2pm in the afternoon.</s>
 <s id="65">Which means that these Johns are likely buying sex in the middle of the workday.</s>
 <s id="66">I believe that there is a way to stop Johns in the middle of the workday from buying sex.</s>
 <s id="67">And businesses can do it in three simple ways.</s>
 <s id="68">The first is with a policy.</s>
 <s id="69">A policy that clearly says, the company prohibits sex-buying during work, with company resources or on company time.</s>
 <s id="70">That's right.</s>
 <s id="71">I'm saying that your handbook has to specifically give an example that says no sex-buying while you're traveling, at the international trade show, because that's where it's happening.</s>
 <s id="72">Now, a policy is only as good as its enforcement and its communication.</s>
 <s id="73">Several studies have indicated from Johns that the best way to deter them is public humiliation and embarrassment.</s>
 <s id="74">So, businesses who catch Johns buying sex, using company-based equipment or company resources, but cut them a break or sweep it under the rug and don't fire them, are complicit in fueling demand.</s>
 <s id="75">Now, a policy is one of the best ways to start.</s>
 <s id="76">The second way is educating the workforce.</s>
 <s id="77">Businesses can go a long way in simply training their workforce about the signs and the red flags of human trafficking.</s>
 <s id="78">This was my "aha!" moment for how our company could make a big difference.</s>
 <s id="79">Our nation's highways, airports and truck stops are literally used as modern-day slave routes.</s>
 <s id="80">Our company has more than 100,000 drivers all over the country, all over the world.</s>
 <s id="81">And so it made perfect sense to train them to see the red flags.</s>
 <s id="82">We don't want them jumping out there and doing things on their own, so we want them to call a phone number, the hotline, and let law enforcement intervene.</s>
 <s id="83">So to do this, we teamed up with an organization called Truckers Against Trafficking.</s>
 <s id="84">This Colorado-based organization had web-based support and materials that we gave to our truck drivers that gave them exactly what they needed to spot the red flags.</s>
 <s id="85">Like, hearing CB chatter on their radios about girls at nearby exits.</s>
 <s id="86">Or, seeing underaged women emerging from vehicles in the truck stop parking lots.</s>
 <s id="87">When we rolled out this training, a few brave drivers admitted they had seen these women, knocking on the cabs in the truck stops, looking for customers.</s>
 <s id="88">Now, they said that they weren't buying.</s>
 <s id="89">But they also didn't know enough to make a call.</s>
 <s id="90">And that's what we want them to do.</s>
 <s id="91">TAT's organization -- Truckers Against Trafficking -- also emphasizes the need for men to talk to other men about web-based sex buying and not buying commercial sex.</s>
 <s id="92">They feature men in uniform, proudly proclaiming why they don't buy.</s>
 <s id="93">If we're going to see a cultural shift in this atrocity, we need men talking to other men about the underlying issues fueling demand.</s>
 <s id="94">Because sometimes, Johns don't even know that they're purchasing girls who are enslaved.</s>
 <s id="95">Which brings me to my final way that businesses can help.</s>
 <s id="96">Every business has a special resource or a secret sauce or resource that they can bring to fight human trafficking.</s>
 <s id="97">For example, Visa, Master Card and American Express refuse to process transactions from backpage.com, an online sex site that sold commercial sex to the tune of nine million dollars a month.</s>
 <s id="98">In April of 2018, backpage.com and affiliated websites were shut down, and the FBI seized all their assets.</s>
 <s id="99">Hiring survivors is another way that any company can help.</s>
 <s id="100">Randstad, an organization that works with companies to find survivors who need good jobs, has an excellent program, called Hire Hope.</s>
 <s id="101">We've used this program; we know that it works.</s>
 <s id="102">In addition to training their flight attendants and their airline crew, Delta Air Lines also offers SkyMiles, through a program called SkyWish, to survivors to help them escape their traffickers and reunite with their families.</s>
 <s id="103">There are thousands of things that businesses can do.</s>
 <s id="104">They just have to decide what to do to join the fight.</s>
 <s id="105">No one can justify slavery today.</s>
 <s id="106">But I believe it remains one of the greatest civil rights atrocities of our time.</s>
 <s id="107">Fortunately, the business community is uniquely positioned to help train their employees, to enforce policies and to help use their special resources to fight human trafficking.</s>
 <s id="108">And what about you?</s>
 <s id="109">What if you decided to learn the red flags?</s>
 <s id="110">What if you decided to look at the signs that are all around you and make a call?</s>
 <s id="111">There is no penalty for calling law enforcement when you see something that doesn't sit right.</s>
 <s id="112">Together, we can all protect our children, we can educate the workforces around us and improve society, where we all live and work with John.</s>
 <s id="113">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="114">(Applause)</s>
</text>
