<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">This is really a two-hour presentation I give to high school students, cut down to three minutes.</s>
 <s id="2">And it all started one day on a plane, on my way to TED, seven years ago.</s>
 <s id="3">And in the seat next to me was a high school student, a teenager, and she came from a really poor family.</s>
 <s id="4">And she wanted to make something of her life, and she asked me a simple little question.</s>
 <s id="5">She said, "What leads to success?"</s>
 <s id="6">And I felt really badly, because I couldn't give her a good answer.</s>
 <s id="7">So I get off the plane, and I come to TED.</s>
 <s id="8">And I think, jeez, I'm in the middle of a room of successful people!</s>
 <s id="9">So why don't I ask them what helped them succeed, and pass it on to kids?</s>
 <s id="10">So here we are, seven years, 500 interviews later, and I'm going to tell you what really leads to success and makes TEDsters tick.</s>
 <s id="11">And the first thing is passion.</s>
 <s id="12">Freeman Thomas says, "I'm driven by my passion."</s>
 <s id="13">TEDsters do it for love; they don't do it for money.</s>
 <s id="14">Carol Coletta says, "I would pay someone to do what I do."</s>
 <s id="15">And the interesting thing is: if you do it for love, the money comes anyway.</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">Work!</s>
  <s id="16.2">Rupert Murdoch said to me, "It's all hard work.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">Nothing comes easily.</s>
  <s id="17.2">But I have a lot of fun."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">Did he say fun?</s>
  <s id="18.2">Rupert?</s>
  <s id="18.3">Yes!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">(Laughter) TEDsters do have fun working.</s>
  <s id="19.2">And they work hard.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">I figured, they're not workaholics.</s>
  <s id="20.2">They're workafrolics.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="21">(Laughter) Good!</s>
 <s id="22">(Applause) Alex Garden says, "To be successful, put your nose down in something and get damn good at it."</s>
 <s id="23">There's no magic; it's practice, practice, practice.</s>
 <s id="24">And it's focus.</s>
 <s id="25">Norman Jewison said to me, "I think it all has to do with focusing yourself on one thing."</s>
 <s id="26">And push!</s>
 <s id="27">David Gallo says, "Push yourself.</s>
 <s id="28">Physically, mentally, you've got to push, push, push."</s>
 <s id="29">You've got to push through shyness and self-doubt.</s>
 <s id="30">Goldie Hawn says, "I always had self-doubts.</s>
 <s id="31">I wasn't good enough; I wasn't smart enough.</s>
 <s id="32">I didn't think I'd make it."</s>
 <s id="33">Now it's not always easy to push yourself, and that's why they invented mothers.</s>
 <s id="34">(Laughter) (Applause) Frank Gehry said to me, "My mother pushed me."</s>
 <s id="35">(Laughter) Serve!</s>
 <s id="36">Sherwin Nuland says, "It was a privilege to serve as a doctor."</s>
 <s id="37">A lot of kids want to be millionaires.</s>
 <s id="38">The first thing I say is: "OK, well you can't serve yourself; you've got to serve others something of value.</s>
 <s id="39">Because that's the way people really get rich."</s>
 <s id="40">Ideas!</s>
 <s id="41">TEDster Bill Gates says, "I had an idea: founding the first micro-computer software company."</s>
 <s id="42">I'd say it was a pretty good idea.</s>
 <s id="43">And there's no magic to creativity in coming up with ideas -- it's just doing some very simple things.</s>
 <s id="44">And I give lots of evidence.</s>
 <s id="45">Persist!</s>
 <s id="46">Joe Kraus says, "Persistence is the number one reason for our success."</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">You've got to persist through failure.</s>
  <s id="47.2">You've got to persist through crap!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="48">Which of course means "Criticism, Rejection, Assholes and Pressure."</s>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) So, the answer to this question is simple: Pay 4,000 bucks and come to TED.</s>
 <s id="50">(Laughter) Or failing that, do the eight things -- and trust me, these are the big eight things that lead to success.</s>
 <s id="51">Thank you TEDsters for all your interviews!</s>
 <s id="52">(Applause)</s>
</text>
