<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm a meteorologist by degree, I have a bachelor's, master's and PhD in physical meteorology, so I'm a meteorologist, card carrying.</s>
 <s id="2">And so with that comes four questions, always.</s>
 <s id="3">This is one prediction I will always get right.</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) And those questions are, "Marshall, what channel are you on?"</s>
 <s id="5">(Laughter) "Dr. Shepherd, what's the weather going to be tomorrow?"</s>
 <s id="6">(Laughter) And oh, I love this one: "My daughter is getting married next September, it's an outdoor wedding.</s>
 <s id="7">Is it going to rain?"</s>
 <s id="8">(Laughter) Not kidding, I get those, and I don't know the answer to that, the science isn't there.</s>
 <s id="9">But the one I get a lot these days is, "Dr. Shepherd, do you believe in climate change?"</s>
 <s id="10">"Do you believe in global warming?"</s>
 <s id="11">Now, I have to gather myself every time I get that question.</s>
 <s id="12">Because it's an ill-posed question -- science isn't a belief system.</s>
 <s id="13">My son, he's 10 -- he believes in the tooth fairy.</s>
 <s id="14">And he needs to get over that, because I'm losing dollars, fast.</s>
 <s id="15">(Laughter) But he believes in the tooth fairy.</s>
 <s id="16">But consider this.</s>
 <s id="17">Bank of America building, there, in Atlanta.</s>
 <s id="18">You never hear anyone say, "Do you believe, if you go to the top of that building and throw a ball off, it's going to fall?"</s>
 <s id="19">You never hear that, because gravity is a thing.</s>
 <s id="20">So why don't we hear the question, "Do you believe in gravity?"</s>
 <s id="21">But of course, we hear the question, "Do you believe in global warming?"</s>
 <s id="22">Well, consider these facts.</s>
 <s id="23">The American Association for the Advancement of Science, AAAS, one of the leading organizations in science, queried scientists and the public on different science topics.</s>
 <s id="24">Here are some of them: genetically modified food, animal research, human evolution.</s>
 <s id="25">And look at what the scientists say about those, the people that actually study those topics, in red, versus the gray, what the public thinks.</s>
 <s id="26">How did we get there?</s>
 <s id="27">How did we get there?</s>
 <s id="28">That scientists and the public are so far apart on these science issues.</s>
 <s id="29">Well, I'll come a little bit closer to home for me, climate change.</s>
 <s id="30">Eighty-seven percent of scientists believe that humans are contributing to climate change.</s>
 <s id="31">But only 50 percent of the public?</s>
 <s id="32">How did we get there?</s>
 <s id="33">So it begs the question, what shapes perceptions about science?</s>
 <s id="34">It's an interesting question and one that I've been thinking about quite a bit.</s>
 <s id="35">I think that one thing that shapes perceptions in the public, about science, is belief systems and biases.</s>
 <s id="36">Belief systems and biases.</s>
 <s id="37">Go with me for a moment.</s>
 <s id="38">Because I want to talk about three elements of that: confirmation bias, Dunning-Kruger effect and cognitive dissonance.</s>
 <s id="39">Now, these sound like big, fancy, academic terms, and they are.</s>
 <s id="40">But when I describe them, you're going to be like, "Oh!</s>
 <s id="41">I recognize that; I even know somebody that does that."</s>
 <s id="42">Confirmation bias.</s>
 <s id="43">Finding evidence that supports what we already believe.</s>
 <s id="44">Now, we're probably all a little bit guilty of that at times.</s>
 <s id="45">Take a look at this.</s>
 <s id="46">I'm on Twitter.</s>
 <s id="47">And often, when it snows, I'll get this tweet back to me.</s>
 <s id="48">(Laughter) "Hey, Dr. Shepherd, I have 20 inches of global warming in my yard, what are you guys talking about, climate change?"</s>
 <s id="49">I get that tweet a lot, actually.</s>
 <s id="50">It's a cute tweet, it makes me chuckle as well.</s>
 <s id="51">But it's oh, so fundamentally scientifically flawed.</s>
 <s id="52">Because it illustrates that the person tweeting doesn't understand the difference between weather and climate.</s>
 <s id="53">I often say, weather is your mood and climate is your personality.</s>
 <s id="54">Think about that.</s>
 <s id="55">Weather is your mood, climate is your personality.</s>
 <s id="56">Your mood today doesn't necessarily tell me anything about your personality, nor does a cold day tell me anything about climate change, or a hot day, for that matter.</s>
 <s id="57">Dunning-Kruger.</s>
 <s id="58">Two scholars from Cornell came up with the Dunning-Kruger effect.</s>
 <s id="59">If you go look up the peer-reviewed paper for this, you will see all kinds of fancy terminology: it's an illusory superiority complex, thinking we know things.</s>
 <s id="60">In other words, people think they know more than they do.</s>
 <s id="61">Or they underestimate what they don't know.</s>
 <s id="62">And then, there's cognitive dissonance.</s>
 <s id="63">Cognitive dissonance is interesting.</s>
 <s id="64">We just recently had Groundhog Day, right?</s>
 <s id="65">Now, there's no better definition of cognitive dissonance than intelligent people asking me if a rodent's forecast is accurate.</s>
 <s id="66">(Laughter) But I get that, all of the time.</s>
 <s id="67">(Laughter) But I also hear about the Farmer's Almanac.</s>
 <s id="68">We grew up on the Farmer's Almanac, people are familiar with it.</s>
 <s id="69">The problem is, it's only about 37 percent accurate, according to studies at Penn State University.</s>
 <s id="70">But we're in an era of science where we actually can forecast the weather.</s>
 <s id="71">And believe it or not, and I know some of you are like, "Yeah, right," we're about 90 percent accurate, or more, with weather forecast.</s>
 <s id="72">You just tend to remember the occasional miss, you do.</s>
 <s id="73">(Laughter) So confirmation bias, Dunning-Kruger and cognitive dissonance.</s>
 <s id="74">I think those shape biases and perceptions that people have about science.</s>
 <s id="75">But then, there's literacy and misinformation that keep us boxed in, as well.</s>
 <s id="76">During the hurricane season of 2017, media outlets had to actually assign reporters to dismiss fake information about the weather forecast.</s>
 <s id="77">That's the era that we're in.</s>
 <s id="78">I deal with this all the time in social media.</s>
 <s id="79">Someone will tweet a forecast -- that's a forecast for Hurricane Irma, but here's the problem: it didn't come from the Hurricane Center.</s>
 <s id="80">But people were tweeting and sharing this; it went viral.</s>
 <s id="81">It didn't come from the National Hurricane Center at all.</s>
 <s id="82">So I spent 12 years of my career at NASA before coming to the University of Georgia, and I chair their Earth Science Advisory Committee, I was just up there last week in DC.</s>
 <s id="83">And I saw some really interesting things.</s>
 <s id="84">Here's a NASA model and science data from satellite showing the 2017 hurricane season.</s>
 <s id="85">You see Hurricane Harvey there?</s>
 <s id="86">Look at all the dust coming off of Africa.</s>
 <s id="87">Look at the wildfires up in northwest US and in western Canada.</s>
 <s id="88">There comes Hurricane Irma.</s>
 <s id="89">This is fascinating to me.</s>
 <s id="90">But admittedly, I'm a weather geek.</s>
 <s id="91">But more importantly, it illustrates that we have the technology to not only observe the weather and climate system, but predict it.</s>
 <s id="92">There's scientific understanding, so there's no need for some of those perceptions and biases that we've been talking about.</s>
 <s id="93">We have knowledge.</s>
 <s id="94">But think about this ...</s>
 <s id="95">This is Houston, Texas, after Hurricane Harvey.</s>
 <s id="96">Now, I write a contribution for "Forbes" magazine periodically, and I wrote an article a week before Hurricane Harvey made landfall, saying, "There's probably going to be 40 to 50 inches of rainfall."</s>
 <s id="97">I wrote that a week before it happened.</s>
 <s id="98">But yet, when you talk to people in Houston, people are saying, "We had no idea it was going to be this bad."</s>
 <s id="99">I'm just...</s>
 <s id="100">(Sigh) (Laughter) A week before.</s>
 <s id="101">But -- I know, it's amusing, but the reality is, we all struggle with perceiving something outside of our experience level.</s>
 <s id="102">People in Houston get rain all of the time, they flood all of the time.</s>
 <s id="103">But they've never experienced that.</s>
 <s id="104">Houston gets about 34 inches of rainfall for the entire year.</s>
 <s id="105">They got 50 inches in three days.</s>
 <s id="106">That's an anomaly event, that's outside of the normal.</s>
 <s id="107">So belief systems and biases, literacy and misinformation.</s>
 <s id="108">How do we step out of the boxes that are cornering our perceptions?</s>
 <s id="109">Well we don't even have to go to Houston, we can come very close to home.</s>
 <s id="110">(Laughter) Remember "Snowpocalypse?"</s>
 <s id="111">(Laughter) Snowmageddon?</s>
 <s id="112">Snowzilla?</s>
 <s id="113">Whatever you want to call it.</s>
 <s id="114">All two inches of it.</s>
 <s id="115">(Laughter) Two inches of snow shut the city of Atlanta down.</s>
 <s id="116">(Laughter) But the reality is, we were in a winter storm watch, we went to a winter weather advisory, and a lot of people perceived that as being a downgrade, "Oh, it's not going to be as bad."</s>
 <s id="117">When in fact, the perception was that it was not going to be as bad, but it was actually an upgrade.</s>
 <s id="118">Things were getting worse as the models were coming in.</s>
 <s id="119">So that's an example of how we get boxed in by our perceptions.</s>
 <s id="120">So, the question becomes, how do we expand our radius?</s>
 <s id="121">The area of a circle is "pi r squared".</s>
 <s id="122">We increase the radius, we increase the area.</s>
 <s id="123">How do we expand our radius of understanding about science?</s>
 <s id="124">Here are my thoughts.</s>
 <s id="125">You take inventory of your own biases.</s>
 <s id="126">And I'm challenging you all to do that.</s>
 <s id="127">Take an inventory of your own biases.</s>
 <s id="128">Where do they come from?</s>
 <s id="129">Your upbringing, your political perspective, your faith -- what shapes your own biases?</s>
 <s id="130">Then, evaluate your sources -- where do you get your information on science?</s>
 <s id="131">What do you read, what do you listen to, to consume your information on science?</s>
 <s id="132">And then, it's important to speak out.</s>
 <s id="133">Talk about how you evaluated your biases and evaluated your sources.</s>
 <s id="134">I want you to listen to this little 40-second clip from one of the top TV meteorologists in the US, Greg Fishel, in the Raleigh, Durham area.</s>
 <s id="135">He's revered in that region.</s>
 <s id="136">But he was a climate skeptic.</s>
 <s id="137">But listen to what he says about speaking out.</s>
 <s id="138">Greg Fishel: The mistake I was making and didn't realize until very recently, was that I was only looking for information to support what I already thought, and was not interested in listening to anything contrary.</s>
 <s id="139">And so I woke up one morning, and there was this question in my mind, "Greg, are you engaging in confirmation bias?</s>
 <s id="140">Are you only looking for information to support what you already think?"</s>
 <s id="141">And if I was honest with myself, and I tried to be, I admitted that was going on.</s>
 <s id="142">And so the more I talked to scientists and read peer-reviewed literature and tried to conduct myself the way I'd been taught to conduct myself at Penn State when I was a student, it became very difficult for me to make the argument that we weren't at least having some effect.</s>
 <s id="143">Maybe there was still a doubt as to how much, but to say "nothing" was not a responsible thing for me to do as a scientist or a person.</s>
 <s id="144">JMS: Greg Fishel just talked about expanding his radius of understanding of science.</s>
 <s id="145">And when we expand our radius, it's not about making a better future, but it's about preserving life as we know it.</s>
 <s id="146">So as we think about expanding our own radius in understanding science, it's critical for Athens, Georgia, for Atlanta, Georgia, for the state of Georgia, and for the world.</s>
 <s id="147">So expand your radius.</s>
 <s id="148">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="149">(Applause)</s>
</text>
