<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm here because I have a very important message: I think we have found the most important factor for success.</s>
 <s id="2">And it was found close to here, Stanford.</s>
 <s id="3">Psychology professor took kids that were four years old and put them in a room all by themselves.</s>
 <s id="4">And he would tell the child, a four-year-old kid, "Johnny, I am going to leave you here with a marshmallow for 15 minutes.</s>
 <p id="p5">
  <s id="5.1">If, after I come back, this marshmallow is here, you will get another one.</s>
  <s id="5.2">So you will have two."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="6">To tell a four-year-old kid to wait 15 minutes for something that they like, is equivalent to telling us, "We'll bring you coffee in two hours."</s>
 <s id="7">(Laughter) Exact equivalent.</s>
 <s id="8">So what happened when the professor left the room?</s>
 <s id="9">As soon as the door closed...</s>
 <s id="10">two out of three ate the marshmallow.</s>
 <s id="11">Five seconds, 10 seconds, 40 seconds, 50 seconds, two minutes, four minutes, eight minutes.</s>
 <s id="12">Some lasted 14-and-a-half minutes.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">(Laughter) Couldn't do it.</s>
  <s id="13.2">Could not wait.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">What's interesting is that one out of three would look at the marshmallow and go like this ...</s>
 <s id="15">Would look at it.</s>
 <s id="16">Put it back.</s>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">They would walk around.</s>
  <s id="17.2">They would play with their skirts and pants.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="18">That child already, at four, understood the most important principle for success, which is the ability to delay gratification.</s>
 <s id="19">Self-discipline: the most important factor for success.</s>
 <s id="20">15 years later, 14 or 15 years later, follow-up study.</s>
 <s id="21">What did they find?</s>
 <s id="22">They went to look for these kids who were now 18 and 19.</s>
 <s id="23">And they found that 100 percent of the children that had not eaten the marshmallow were successful.</s>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">They had good grades.</s>
  <s id="24.2">They were doing wonderful.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">They were happy.</s>
  <s id="25.2">They had their plans.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">They had good relationships with the teachers, students.</s>
 <s id="27">They were doing fine.</s>
 <s id="28">A great percentage of the kids that ate the marshmallow, they were in trouble.</s>
 <s id="29">They did not make it to university.</s>
 <p id="p30">
  <s id="30.1">They had bad grades.</s>
  <s id="30.2">Some of them dropped out.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="31">A few were still there with bad grades.</s>
 <s id="32">A few had good grades.</s>
 <s id="33">I had a question in my mind: Would Hispanic kids react the same way as the American kids?</s>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">So I went to Colombia.</s>
  <s id="34.2">And I reproduced the experiment.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">And it was very funny.</s>
  <s id="35.2">I used four, five and six years old kids.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="36">And let me show you what happened.</s>
 <s id="37">(Spanish) (Laughter) So what happened in Colombia?</s>
 <s id="38">Hispanic kids, two out of three ate the marshmallow; one out of three did not.</s>
 <s id="39">This little girl was interesting; she ate the inside of the marshmallow.</s>
 <s id="40">(Laughter) In other words, she wanted us to think that she had not eaten it, so she would get two.</s>
 <s id="41">But she ate it.</s>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">So we know she'll be successful.</s>
  <s id="42.2">But we have to watch her.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="43">(Laughter) She should not go into banking, for example, or work at a cash register.</s>
 <s id="44">But she will be successful.</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">And this applies for everything.</s>
  <s id="45.2">Even in sales.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p46">
  <s id="46.1">The sales person that -- the customer says, "I want that."</s>
  <s id="46.2">And the person says, "Okay, here you are."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="47">That person ate the marshmallow.</s>
 <s id="48">If the sales person says, "Wait a second.</s>
 <s id="49">Let me ask you a few questions to see if this is a good choice."</s>
 <s id="50">Then you sell a lot more.</s>
 <s id="51">So this has applications in all walks of life.</s>
 <s id="52">I end with -- the Koreans did this.</s>
 <p id="p53">
  <s id="53.1">You know what?</s>
  <s id="53.2">This is so good that we want a marshmallow book for children.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">We did one for children.</s>
  <s id="54.2">And now it is all over Korea.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">They are teaching these kids exactly this principle.</s>
 <s id="56">And we need to learn that principle here in the States, because we have a big debt.</s>
 <s id="57">We are eating more marshmallows than we are producing.</s>
 <s id="58">Thank you so much.</s>
</text>
