<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Something happened while I was studying in the seminary and training to be a priest.</s>
 <s id="2">I came in contact with a different idea of life.</s>
 <s id="3">An idea of life that contradicted the main teachings of religion -- humanism.</s>
 <s id="4">Some of you may be wondering, what on earth is humanism?</s>
 <s id="5">Humanism is a way of thinking and living that emphasizes the agency of human beings.</s>
 <s id="6">Humanism stresses the fact that we, human beings, are capable of changing the world.</s>
 <s id="7">That we have the power to make a difference in our lives, both individually and collectively, without recourse to some outside force.</s>
 <s id="8">It may interest you to know that the best humanist lessons I learned were not from reading philosophy books or from poring over humanist manifestos and declarations.</s>
 <s id="9">No, not at all.</s>
 <s id="10">The best humanist lesson I learned was from the life of my own parents.</s>
 <s id="11">My parents come from a poor family background in Mbaise, in southeastern Nigeria.</s>
 <s id="12">They had limited opportunities.</s>
 <s id="13">But my parents did not allow the circumstances of their bad upbringing to determine the ambition and dreams for themselves and for their children.</s>
 <s id="14">My father worked part-time, trained as a teacher, and rose to become a headmaster at a local primary school.</s>
 <s id="15">My mother dropped out of school quite early, because her mother, my grandmother, could not afford her education.</s>
 <s id="16">As a parent, my mother worked very hard, combining farming, petty trading and taking care of my siblings and me.</s>
 <s id="17">By the time I was born -- that was shortly after the Nigerian civil war -- life was very difficult, a struggle day by day.</s>
 <s id="18">My family was living in a hut.</s>
 <s id="19">With the eye of a child, I can still see water dripping from the thatched roof of our house when it rained.</s>
 <s id="20">My father reared goats to supplement the family income.</s>
 <s id="21">And part of my duty after school hours or during vacation was to feed these goats.</s>
 <s id="22">There was no electricity, no pipe with water.</s>
 <s id="23">We trekked to fetch water from the nearby streams.</s>
 <s id="24">That was an easy work in the wet season, but kilometers when it was hot and dry.</s>
 <s id="25">Through hard work and perseverance, my parents were able to erect a block apartment and send my siblings and me to school.</s>
 <s id="26">They made it possible for us to enjoy a standard of living which they never did and to attain educational levels which they only imagined when they were growing up.</s>
 <s id="27">My parents' life, their story, is my best lesson in humanism.</s>
 <s id="28">So as a humanist, I believe that human beings are challengers, not prisoners of faith.</s>
 <s id="29">Our destinies are in our hands, not predetermined.</s>
 <s id="30">And it's left for us to shape our lives and destinies to reflect our best hopes and aspirations.</s>
 <s id="31">I believe that human beings have the power to turn situations of poverty into those of wealth and prosperity.</s>
 <s id="32">We have the capacity to alleviate suffering, extend life, prevent diseases, cure debilitating ailments, reduce infant mortality and preserve our planet.</s>
 <s id="33">But we cannot accomplish all these goals by wishful thinking with our eyes closed or by armchair speculation or by expecting salvation from empty sky.</s>
 <s id="34">In contrast, millions of Africans imagine that their religious faith will help their dream come true, and they spend so much time praying for miracles and for divine intervention in their lives.</s>
 <s id="35">In 2009, a Gallup survey in 114 countries revealed that religiosity was highest in the world's poorest nations.</s>
 <s id="36">In fact, six of the 10 countries where 95 percent of the population said that religion was an important part of their daily lives, were African.</s>
 <s id="37">In some cases, religion drives many Africans to extraordinary length: to attack other human beings, to commit ritual killing, targeting those living with albinism, those with a humpback, and as I recently learned, those with a bald head.</s>
 <s id="38">In Africa, superstition is widespread, with so many people believing in witchcraft, something that has no basis in reason or in science.</s>
 <s id="39">Yet alleged witches, usually women, children and elderly persons are still routinely attacked, banished and killed.</s>
 <s id="40">And I've made it part of my life's mission to end witchcraft accusation and witch persecution in Africa.</s>
 <s id="41">So as a humanist, I believe in a proactive approach to life.</s>
 <s id="42">The changes that we want cannot be achieved only by dreaming but require doing as well.</s>
 <s id="43">The challenges that we face cannot go away if we recoil and retreat into our shells, wishing and imagining that those problems will somehow magically disappear.</s>
 <s id="44">The good life that we desire will not fall like manna from heaven.</s>
 <s id="45">My parents did not erect a block apartment by wishing and dreaming.</s>
 <s id="46">They worked hard, they failed, they tried again.</s>
 <s id="47">They toiled with rolled-up sleeves, with their hands deep in debt, they plowed ahead, growing their dreams into reality.</s>
 <s id="48">So as a humanist, I believe we must be adventurous and even daring.</s>
 <s id="49">The path of success is paved with risk and uncertainties.</s>
 <s id="50">We have to muster the will and courage to do what people have never done.</s>
 <s id="51">To think what people have never thought.</s>
 <s id="52">Envisage what people have never imagined.</s>
 <s id="53">Go to places human beings have not been to.</s>
 <s id="54">And succeed where people have tried but failed.</s>
 <s id="55">We must be ready to explore new frontiers of knowledge and understanding and attempt doing not just what is possible but also what is seemingly impossible.</s>
 <s id="56">But I realize that at the end of the day, our efforts do not always yield our desires.</s>
 <s id="57">We fail, we suffer disappointments and setbacks.</s>
 <s id="58">Some problems, such as wars and conflict, poverty and diseases and other natural and human-made disasters seem as if they may never go away.</s>
 <s id="59">Solutions to old problems have led to new dangers, new cures to diseases have resulted in new health risks.</s>
 <s id="60">But the fact that these problems persist and that solutions sometimes create their own problems is not a reason for us to give up or to resign.</s>
 <s id="61">It's not a reason for us to think that our efforts are of no consequence.</s>
 <s id="62">In fact, there is fulfillment in striving, and trying to provide answers and solutions to the problem humanity faces even when the likely outcome is failure.</s>
 <s id="63">So as a humanist, I believe we must not despair for humanity.</s>
 <s id="64">Even in the face of overwhelming difficulties and in the bleakest of circumstances.</s>
 <s id="65">Human beings are creative beings.</s>
 <s id="66">We have the power to generate new ideas, new solutions and new cures.</s>
 <s id="67">So why despair when the unexpected knocks on the horizon?</s>
 <s id="68">It is in our nature to create anew, to be inventive and innovative, so why languish in idle expectation of a savior from above?</s>
 <s id="69">So it is time for us Africans to take our destiny in our hands and realize we have agency in the scheme of life.</s>
 <s id="70">We need to put an end to this game of blame that has prevented us from taking full responsibility for our own lives.</s>
 <s id="71">For too long, we have been prisoners of our past.</s>
 <s id="72">We have allowed despair and pessimism to drain us, drain our energies, limit our imaginations and dim our vision for a better and brighter future.</s>
 <s id="73">We have let this continent flounder.</s>
 <s id="74">Why passing the buck like a Frisbee?</s>
 <s id="75">We've blamed slavery, colonialism and the new colonialism for the woes we experience, including our own self-inflicted wounds.</s>
 <s id="76">We have conducted ourselves in ways that seem as if Africa is damned and doomed.</s>
 <s id="77">And that all these experiences in history have irreversibly, irreparably foreclosed the chances and possibility for Africa to emerge, thrive and flourish.</s>
 <s id="78">We must realize that there is no part of the world that has not been colonized or enslaved in the past.</s>
 <s id="79">And if other parts of the world have moved on, why can't we, now?</s>
 <s id="80">So as a humanist, I believe that the past is gone; we cannot change it, we cannot alter it.</s>
 <s id="81">But the future beckons us on with limitless possibilities to recreate, reshape and remake our destinies.</s>
 <s id="82">So let's all of us seize this opportunity.</s>
 <s id="83">And as my parents did, begin the urgent task of rebuilding Africa, brick by brick.</s>
 <s id="84">Let's give free reign to our ideas and imaginations, as demonstrated at this TEDGlobal 2017.</s>
 <s id="85">Let's open our hearts and minds.</s>
 <s id="86">And exert our energy, intelligence and ingenuity and begin the urgent task of rebuilding Africa and of transforming this continent into a citadel of unrivaled prosperity and civilization.</s>
 <s id="87">This is what I believe as a humanist, as an African humanist.</s>
 <s id="88">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="89">(Applause)</s>
</text>
