<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Your hands, up close, are anything but smooth.</s>
 <s id="2">With peaks and valleys, folds and rifts, there are plenty of hiding places for a virus to stick.</s>
 <s id="3">If you then touch your face, the virus can infect you.</s>
 <s id="4">But there are two extraordinarily simple ways you can keep that from happening: soap and water, and hand sanitizer.</s>
 <s id="5">So which is better?</s>
 <s id="6">The coronavirus that causes COVID-19 is one of many viruses whose protective outer surface is made of a lipid bilayer.</s>
 <s id="7">These lipids are pin shaped molecules whose heads are attracted to water, and tails are repulsed by it.</s>
 <s id="8">So in water-rich environments, lipids naturally form a shell like this, with the heads outside and the tails inside.</s>
 <s id="9">Their shared reaction to water makes the lipids stick loosely together— this is called the hydrophobic effect.</s>
 <s id="10">This outer structure helps the molecular machinery of the virus break through cellular membranes and hijack our cells.</s>
 <s id="11">But it has thousands upon thousands of weak points where the right molecules could pry it apart.</s>
 <s id="12">And this is where soap comes in.</s>
 <s id="13">A single drop of any brand of soap contains quadrillions of molecules called amphiphiles, which resemble biological lipids.</s>
 <s id="14">Their tails, which are similarly repulsed by water, compete for space with the lipids that make up the virus’s shell.</s>
 <s id="15">But they’re just different enough to break up the regularity of the virus’s membrane, making the whole thing come crashing down.</s>
 <s id="16">Those amphiphiles then form bubbles of their own around particles including the virus’s RNA and proteins.</s>
 <s id="17">Apply water, and you’ll wash that whole bubble away.</s>
 <s id="18">Hand sanitizers work less like a crowbar, and more like an earthquake.</s>
 <s id="19">When you surround a coronavirus with water, the hydrophobic effect gives the bonds within the membrane their strength.</s>
 <s id="20">That same effect also holds the big proteins that form coronavirus’s spikes in place and in the shape that enables them to infect your cells.</s>
 <s id="21">If you dry the virus out in air, it keeps its stability.</s>
 <s id="22">But now surround it with a high concentration of an alcohol, like the ethanol or isopropanol found in most hand-sanitizers.</s>
 <s id="23">This makes the hydrophobic effect disappear, and gives the molecules room to move around.</s>
 <s id="24">The overall effect is like removing all of the nails and mortar from a house and then hitting it with an earthquake.</s>
 <s id="25">The cell’s membrane collapses and those spike proteins crumble.</s>
 <s id="26">In either method, the actual process of destroying the virus happens in just a second or two.</s>
 <s id="27">But doctors recommend at least 20 seconds of hand-washing because of the intricate landscape that is your hand.</s>
 <s id="28">Soap and sanitizer need to get everywhere, including your palms, fingertips, the outsides of your hands, and between your fingers, to protect you properly.</s>
 <s id="29">And when it comes to a coronavirus outbreak, doctors recommend washing your hands with soap and water whenever possible.</s>
 <s id="30">Even though both approaches are similarly effective at killing the virus, soap and water has two benefits: first it washes away any dirt which could otherwise hide virus particles.</s>
 <s id="31">But more importantly, it’s simply easier to fully cover your hands with soap and water for 20 seconds.</s>
 <s id="32">Of course, hand sanitizer is more convenient to use on the go.</s>
 <s id="33">In the absence of a sink, use the sanitizer as thoroughly as possible and rub your hands together until they’re dry.</s>
 <s id="34">Unfortunately, there are billions of people who don’t have access to clean drinking water, which is a huge problem at any time but especially during an outbreak.</s>
 <s id="35">Researchers and aid groups are working to provide solutions for these communities.</s>
 <s id="36">One example is a device that uses salt, water, and a car battery to make chlorinated water that kills harmful pathogens and is safe for hand-washing.</s>
 <s id="37">So wherever possible, soap and water are recommended for a coronavirus, but does that mean it's best for every viral outbreak?</s>
 <s id="38">Not necessarily.</s>
 <s id="39">Many common colds are caused by rhinoviruses that have a geometric protein structure called a capsid instead of a lipid membrane.</s>
 <s id="40">The capsid doesn't have nearly as many weak points where soap amphiphiles can pry it apart, so it takes longer for soap to be effective.</s>
 <s id="41">However some of its surface proteins are still vulnerable to the destabilizing effect of hand sanitizer.</s>
 <s id="42">In this and similar cases, hand sanitizer may be more effective, especially if you then wash your hands to remove residual particles.</s>
 <s id="43">The best way to know which to use for any given outbreak is to do what's best for all things illness-related: follow the advice of accredited medical professionals.</s>
</text>
