<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So what does it mean to be a woman?</s>
 <s id="2">We all have XX chromosomes, right?</s>
 <s id="3">Actually, that's not true.</s>
 <s id="4">Some women are mosaics.</s>
 <s id="5">They have a mix of chromosome types with X, with XY or with XXX.</s>
 <s id="6">If it's not just about our chromosomes, then what is being a woman about?</s>
 <s id="7">Being feminine?</s>
 <s id="8">Getting married?</s>
 <s id="9">Having kids?</s>
 <s id="10">You don't have to look far to find fantastic exceptions to these rules, but we all share something that makes us women.</s>
 <s id="11">Maybe that something is in our brains.</s>
 <s id="12">You might have heard theories from last century about how men are better at math than women because they have bigger brains.</s>
 <s id="13">These theories have been debunked.</s>
 <s id="14">The average man has a brain about three times smaller than the average elephant, but that doesn't mean the average man is three times dumber than an elephant ...</s>
 <s id="15">or does it?</s>
 <s id="16">(Laughter) There's a new wave of female neuroscientists that are finding important differences between female and male brains in neuron connectivity, in brain structure, in brain activity.</s>
 <s id="17">They're finding that the brain is like a patchwork mosaic -- a mixture.</s>
 <s id="18">Women have mostly female patches and a few male patches.</s>
 <s id="19">With all this new data, what does it mean to be a woman?</s>
 <s id="20">This is something that I've been thinking about almost my entire life.</s>
 <s id="21">When people learn that I'm a woman who happens to be transgender, they always ask, "How do you know you're a woman?"</s>
 <s id="22">As a scientist, I'm searching for a biological basis of gender.</s>
 <s id="23">I want to understand what makes me me.</s>
 <s id="24">New discoveries at the front edge of science are shedding light on the biomarkers that define gender.</s>
 <s id="25">My colleagues and I in genetics, neuroscience, physiology and psychology, we're trying to figure out exactly how gender works.</s>
 <s id="26">These vastly different fields share a common connection -- epigenetics.</s>
 <s id="27">In epigenetics, we're studying how DNA activity can actually radically and permanently change, even though the sequence stays the same.</s>
 <s id="28">DNA is the long, string-like molecule that winds up inside our cells.</s>
 <s id="29">There's so much DNA that it actually gets tangled into these knot-like things -- we'll just call them knots.</s>
 <s id="30">So external factors change how those DNA knots are formed.</s>
 <s id="31">You can think of it like this: inside our cells, there's different contraptions building things, connecting circuits, doing all the things they need to make life happen.</s>
 <s id="32">Here's one that's sort of reading the DNA and making RNA.</s>
 <s id="33">And then this one is carrying a huge sac of neurotransmitters from one end of the brain cell to the other.</s>
 <s id="34">Don't they get hazard pay for this kind of work?</s>
 <s id="35">(Laughter) This one is an entire molecular factory -- some say it's the secret to life.</s>
 <s id="36">It's call the ribosome.</s>
 <s id="37">I've been studying this since 2001.</s>
 <s id="38">One of the stunning things about our cells is that the components inside them are actually biodegradable.</s>
 <s id="39">They dissolve, and then they're rebuilt each day, kind of like a traveling carnival where the rides are taken down and then rebuilt every single day.</s>
 <s id="40">A big difference between our cells and the traveling carnival is that in the carnival, there are skilled craftsmen that rebuild the rides each day.</s>
 <s id="41">In our cells, there are no such skilled craftsmen, only dumb builder machines that build whatever's written in the plans, no matter what those plans say.</s>
 <s id="42">Those plans are the DNA.</s>
 <s id="43">The instructions for every nook and cranny inside our cells.</s>
 <s id="44">If everything in, say, our brain cells dissolves almost every day, then how can the brain remember anything past one day?</s>
 <s id="45">That's where DNA comes in.</s>
 <s id="46">DNA is one of the those things that does not dissolve.</s>
 <s id="47">But for DNA to remember that something happened, it has to change somehow.</s>
 <s id="48">We know the change can't be in the sequence; if it changed sequence all the time, then we might be growing like, a new ear or a new eyeball every single day.</s>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) So, instead it changes shape, and that's where those DNA knots come in.</s>
 <s id="50">You can think of them like DNA memory.</s>
 <s id="51">When something big in our life happens, like a traumatic childhood event, stress hormones flood our brain.</s>
 <s id="52">The stress hormones don't affect the sequence of DNA, but they do change the shape.</s>
 <s id="53">They affect that part of DNA with the instructions for molecular machines that reduce stress.</s>
 <s id="54">That piece of DNA gets wound up into a knot, and now the dumb builder machines can't read the plans they need to build the machines that reduce stress.</s>
 <s id="55">That's a mouthful, but it's what's happening on the microscale.</s>
 <s id="56">On the macroscale, you practically lose the ability to deal with stress, and that's bad.</s>
 <s id="57">And that's how DNA can remember what happens in the past.</s>
 <s id="58">This is what I think was happening to me when I first started my gender transition.</s>
 <s id="59">I knew I was a woman on the inside, and I wore women's clothes on the outside, but everyone saw me as a man in a dress.</s>
 <s id="60">I felt like no matter how many things I try, no one would ever really see me as a woman.</s>
 <s id="61">In science, your credibility is everything, and people were snickering in the hallways, giving me stares, looks of disgust -- afraid to be near me.</s>
 <s id="62">I remember my first big talk after transition.</s>
 <s id="63">It was in Italy.</s>
 <s id="64">I'd given prestigious talks before, but this one, I was terrified.</s>
 <s id="65">I looked out into the audience, and the whispers started -- the stares, the smirks, the chuckles.</s>
 <s id="66">To this day, I still have social anxiety around my experience eight years ago.</s>
 <s id="67">I lost hope.</s>
 <s id="68">Don't worry, I've had therapy so I'm OK -- I'm OK now.</s>
 <s id="69">(Laughter) (Cheers) (Applause) But I felt enough is enough: I'm a scientist, I have a doctorate in astrophysics, I've published in the top journals, in wave-particle interactions, space physics, nucleic acid biochemistry.</s>
 <s id="70">I've actually been trained to get to the bottom of things, so -- (Laughter) I went online -- (Applause) So I went online, and I found fascinating research papers.</s>
 <s id="71">I learned that these DNA knot things are not always bad.</s>
 <s id="72">Actually, the knotting and unknotting -- it's like a complicated computer language.</s>
 <s id="73">It programs our bodies with exquisite precision.</s>
 <s id="74">So when we get pregnant, our fertilized eggs grow into newborn babies.</s>
 <s id="75">This process requires thousands of DNA decisions to happen.</s>
 <s id="76">Should an embryo cell become a blood cell?</s>
 <p id="p77">
  <s id="77.1">A heart cell?</s>
  <s id="77.2">A brain cell?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="78">And the decisions happen at different times during pregnancy.</s>
 <s id="79">Some in the first trimester, some in the second trimester and some in the third trimester.</s>
 <s id="80">To truly understand DNA decision-making, we need to see the process of knot formation in atomic detail.</s>
 <s id="81">Even the most powerful microscopes can't see this.</s>
 <s id="82">What if we tried to simulate these on a computer?</s>
 <s id="83">For that we'd need a million computers to do that.</s>
 <s id="84">That's exactly what we have at Los Alamos Labs -- a million computers connected in a giant warehouse.</s>
 <s id="85">So here we're showing the DNA making up an entire gene folded into very specific shapes of knots.</s>
 <s id="86">For the first time, my team has simulated an entire gene of DNA -- the largest biomolecular simulation performed to date.</s>
 <s id="87">For the first time, we're beginning to understand the unsolved problem of how hormones trigger the formation of these knots.</s>
 <s id="88">DNA knot formation can be seen beautifully in calico cats.</s>
 <s id="89">The decision between orange and black happens early on in the womb, so that orange-and-black patchy pattern, it's an exact readout of what happened when that cat was just a tiny little kitten embryo inside her mom's womb.</s>
 <s id="90">And the patchy pattern actually happens in our brains and in cancer.</s>
 <s id="91">It's directly related to intellectual disability and breast cancer.</s>
 <s id="92">These DNA decisions also happen in other parts of the body.</s>
 <s id="93">It turns out that the precursor genitals transform into either female or male during the first trimester of pregnancy.</s>
 <s id="94">The precursor brains, on the other hand, transform into female or male during the second trimester of pregnancy.</s>
 <s id="95">So the current working model is that a unique mix in my mom's womb caused the precursor genitals to transform one way, but the precursor brain to transform the other way.</s>
 <s id="96">Most of epigenetic research has really focused on stress, anxiety, depression -- kind of a downer, kind of bad things.</s>
 <s id="97">(Laughter) But nowadays -- the latest stuff -- people are looking at relaxation.</s>
 <s id="98">Can that have a positive effect on your DNA?</s>
 <s id="99">Right now we're missing key data from mice models.</s>
 <s id="100">We know that mice relax, but could they meditate like the Dalai Lama?</s>
 <s id="101">Achieve enlightenment?</s>
 <s id="102">Could they move stones with their mind like Jedi Master Yoda?</s>
 <s id="103">(Yoda voice): Hm, a Jedi mouse must feel the force flow, hm.</s>
 <s id="104">(Laughter) (Applause) I wonder if the support I've had since that talk back in Italy has tried to unwind my DNA.</s>
 <s id="105">Having a great circle of friends, supportive parents and being in a loving relationship has actually given me strength and hope to help others.</s>
 <s id="106">At work I wear a rainbow bracelet.</s>
 <s id="107">Sometimes it raises eyebrows, but it also raises awareness.</s>
 <s id="108">There's so many transgender people -- especially women of color -- that are just one demeaning comment away from taking their own lives.</s>
 <s id="109">Forty percent of us attempt suicide.</s>
 <s id="110">If you're listening and you feel like you have no other option, try to call a friend, go online or try to get in a support group.</s>
 <s id="111">If you're a woman who's not transgender but you know pain of isolation, of sexual assault -- reach out.</s>
 <s id="112">So what does it mean to be a woman?</s>
 <s id="113">The latest research is showing that female and male brains do develop differently in the womb, possibly giving us females this innate sense of being a woman.</s>
 <s id="114">On the other hand, maybe it's our shared sense of commonality that makes us women.</s>
 <s id="115">We come in so many different shapes and sizes that asking what it means to be a woman may not be the right question.</s>
 <s id="116">It's like asking a calico cat what it means to be a calico cat.</s>
 <s id="117">Maybe becoming a woman means accepting ourselves for who we really are and acknowledging the same in each other.</s>
 <s id="118">I see you.</s>
 <s id="119">And you've just seen me.</s>
 <s id="120">(Applause and cheers)</s>
</text>
