<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">My topic is economic growth in China and India.</s>
 <s id="2">And the question I want to explore with you is whether or not democracy has helped or has hindered economic growth.</s>
 <s id="3">You may say this is not fair, because I'm selecting two countries to make a case against democracy.</s>
 <s id="4">Actually, exactly the opposite is what I'm going to do.</s>
 <s id="5">I'm going to use these two countries to make an economic argument for democracy, rather than against democracy.</s>
 <s id="6">The first question there is why China has grown so much faster than India.</s>
 <s id="7">Over the last 30 years, in terms of the GDP growth rates, China has grown at twice the rate of India.</s>
 <s id="8">In the last five years, the two countries have begun to converge somewhat in economic growth.</s>
 <s id="9">But over the last 30 years, China undoubtedly has done much better than India.</s>
 <s id="10">One simple answer is China has Shanghai and India has Mumbai.</s>
 <s id="11">Look at the skyline of Shanghai.</s>
 <s id="12">This is the Pudong area.</s>
 <s id="13">The picture on India is the Dharavi slum of Mumbai in India.</s>
 <s id="14">The idea there behind these two pictures is that the Chinese government can act above rule of law.</s>
 <s id="15">It can plan for the long-term benefits of the country and in the process, evict millions of people -- that's just a small technical issue.</s>
 <s id="16">Whereas in India, you cannot do that, because you have to listen to the public.</s>
 <s id="17">You're being constrained by the public's opinion.</s>
 <s id="18">Even Prime Minister Manmohan Singh agrees with that view.</s>
 <s id="19">In an interview printed in the financial press of India, He said that he wants to make Mumbai another Shanghai.</s>
 <s id="20">This is an Oxford-trained economist steeped in humanistic values, and yet he agrees with the high-pressure tactics of Shanghai.</s>
 <s id="21">So let me call it the Shanghai model of economic growth, that emphasizes the following features for promoting economic development: infrastructures, airports, highways, bridges, things like that.</s>
 <s id="22">And you need a strong government to do that, because you cannot respect private property rights.</s>
 <s id="23">You cannot be constrained by the public's opinion.</s>
 <s id="24">You need also state ownership, especially of land assets, in order to build and roll out infrastructures very quickly.</s>
 <s id="25">The implication of that model is that democracy is a hindrance for economic growth, rather than a facilitator of economic growth.</s>
 <s id="26">Here's the key question.</s>
 <s id="27">Just how important are infrastructures for economic growth?</s>
 <s id="28">This is a key issue.</s>
 <s id="29">If you believe that infrastructures are very important for economic growth, then you would argue a strong government is necessary to promote growth.</s>
 <s id="30">If you believe that infrastructures are not as important as many people believe, then you will put less emphasis on strong government.</s>
 <s id="31">So to illustrate that question, let me give you two countries.</s>
 <s id="32">And for the sake of brevity, I'll call one country Country 1 and the other country Country 2.</s>
 <s id="33">Country 1 has a systematic advantage over Country 2 in infrastructures.</s>
 <s id="34">Country 1 has more telephones, and Country 1 has a longer system of railways.</s>
 <s id="35">So if I were to ask you, "Which is China and which is India, and which country has grown faster?"</s>
 <s id="36">if you believe in the infrastructure view, then you will say, "Country 1 must be China.</s>
 <s id="37">They must have done better, in terms of economic growth.</s>
 <s id="38">And Country 2 is possibly India."</s>
 <s id="39">Actually the country with more telephones is the Soviet Union, and the data referred to 1989.</s>
 <s id="40">After the country reported very impressive statistics on telephones, the country collapsed.</s>
 <s id="41">That's not too good.</s>
 <s id="42">The picture there is Khrushchev.</s>
 <s id="43">I know that in 1989 he no longer ruled the Soviet Union, but that's the best picture that I can find.</s>
 <s id="44">(Laughter) Telephones, infrastructures do not guarantee you economic growth.</s>
 <s id="45">Country 2, that has fewer telephones, is China.</s>
 <s id="46">Since 1989, the country has performed at a double-digit rate every year for the last 20 years.</s>
 <s id="47">If you know nothing about China and the Soviet Union other than the fact about their telephones, you would have made a poor prediction about their economic growth in the next two decades.</s>
 <s id="48">Country 1, that has a longer system of railways, is actually India.</s>
 <s id="49">And Country 2 is China.</s>
 <s id="50">This is a very little known fact about the two countries.</s>
 <s id="51">Yes, today China has a huge infrastructure advantage over India.</s>
 <s id="52">But for many years, until the late 1990s, China had an infrastructure disadvantage vis-a-vis India.</s>
 <s id="53">In developing countries, the most common mode of transportation is the railways, and the British built a lot of railways in India.</s>
 <s id="54">India is the smaller of the two countries, and yet it had a longer system of railways until the late 1990s.</s>
 <s id="55">So clearly, infrastructure doesn't explain why China did better before the late 1990s, as compared with India.</s>
 <s id="56">In fact, if you look at the evidence worldwide, the evidence is more supportive of the view that the infrastructure are actually the result of economic growth.</s>
 <s id="57">The economy grows, government accumulates more resources, and the government can invest in infrastructure -- rather than infrastructure being a cause for economic growth.</s>
 <s id="58">And this is clearly the story of the Chinese economic growth.</s>
 <s id="59">Let me look at this question more directly.</s>
 <s id="60">Is democracy bad for economic growth?</s>
 <s id="61">Now let's turn to two countries, Country A and Country B.</s>
 <s id="62">Country A, in 1990, had about $300 per capita GDP as compared with Country B, which had $460 in per capita GDP.</s>
 <s id="63">By 2008, Country A has surpassed Country B with $700 per capita GDP as compared with $650 per capita GDP.</s>
 <s id="64">Both countries are in Asia.</s>
 <s id="65">If I were to ask you, "Which are the two Asian countries?</s>
 <s id="66">And which one is a democracy?"</s>
 <s id="67">you may argue, "Well, maybe Country A is China and Country B is India."</s>
 <s id="68">In fact, Country A is democratic India, and Country B is Pakistan -- the country that has a long period of military rule.</s>
 <s id="69">And it's very common that we compare India with China.</s>
 <s id="70">That's because the two countries have about the same population size.</s>
 <s id="71">But the more natural comparison is actually between India and Pakistan.</s>
 <s id="72">Those two countries are geographically similar.</s>
 <s id="73">They have a complicated, but shared common history.</s>
 <s id="74">By that comparison, democracy looks very, very good in terms of economic growth.</s>
 <s id="75">So why do economists fall in love with authoritarian governments?</s>
 <s id="76">One reason is the East Asian Model.</s>
 <s id="77">In East Asia, we have had successful economic growth stories such as Korea, Taiwan, Hong Kong and Singapore.</s>
 <s id="78">Some of these economies were ruled by authoritarian governments in the 60s and 70s and 1980s.</s>
 <s id="79">The problem with that view is like asking all the winners of lotteries, "Have you won the lottery?"</s>
 <s id="80">And they all tell you, "Yes, we have won the lottery."</s>
 <s id="81">And then you draw the conclusion the odds of winning the lottery are 100 percent.</s>
 <s id="82">The reason is you never go and bother to ask the losers who also purchased lottery tickets and didn't end up winning the prize.</s>
 <s id="83">For each of these successful authoritarian governments in East Asia, there's a matched failure.</s>
 <s id="84">Korea succeeded, North Korea didn't.</s>
 <s id="85">Taiwan succeeded, China under Mao Zedong didn't.</s>
 <s id="86">Burma didn't succeed.</s>
 <s id="87">The Philippines didn't succeed.</s>
 <s id="88">If you look at the statistical evidence worldwide, there's really no support for the idea that authoritarian governments hold a systematic edge over democracies in terms of economic growth.</s>
 <s id="89">So the East Asian model has this massive selection bias -- it is known as selecting on a dependent variable, something we always tell our students to avoid.</s>
 <s id="90">So exactly why did China grow so much faster?</s>
 <s id="91">I will take you to the Cultural Revolution, when China went mad, and compare that country's performance with India under Indira Gandhi.</s>
 <s id="92">The question there is: Which country did better, China or India?</s>
 <s id="93">China was during the Cultural Revolution.</s>
 <s id="94">It turns out even during the Cultural Revolution, China out-perfomed India in terms of GDP growth by an average of about 2.2 percent every year in terms of per capita GDP.</s>
 <s id="95">So that's when China was mad.</s>
 <s id="96">The whole country went mad.</s>
 <s id="97">It must mean that the country had something so advantageous to itself in terms of economic growth to overcome the negative effects of the Cultural Revolution.</s>
 <s id="98">The advantage the country had was human capital -- nothing else but human capital.</s>
 <s id="99">This is the world development index indicator data in the early 1990s.</s>
 <s id="100">And this is the earliest data that I can find.</s>
 <s id="101">The adult literacy rate in China is 77 percent as compared with 48 percent in India.</s>
 <s id="102">The contrast in literacy rates is especially sharp between Chinese women and Indian women.</s>
 <s id="103">I haven't told you about the definition of literacy.</s>
 <s id="104">In China, the definition of literacy is the ability to read and write 1,500 Chinese characters.</s>
 <s id="105">In India, the definition of literacy, operating definition of literacy, is the ability, the grand ability, to write your own name in whatever language you happen to speak.</s>
 <s id="106">The gap between the two countries in terms of literacy is much more substantial than the data here indicated.</s>
 <s id="107">If you go to other sources of data such as Human Development Index, that data series, go back to the early 1970s, you see exactly the same contrast.</s>
 <s id="108">China held a huge advantage in terms of human capital vis-a-vis India.</s>
 <s id="109">Life expectancies: as early as 1965, China had a huge advantage in life expectancy.</s>
 <s id="110">On average, as a Chinese in 1965, you lived 10 years more than an average Indian.</s>
 <s id="111">So if you have a choice between being a Chinese and being an Indian, you would want to become a Chinese in order to live 10 years longer.</s>
 <s id="112">If you made that decision in 1965, the down side of that is the next year we have the Cultural Revolution.</s>
 <s id="113">So you have to always think carefully about these decisions.</s>
 <s id="114">If you cannot chose your nationality, then you will want to become an Indian man.</s>
 <s id="115">Because, as an Indian man, you have about two years of life expectancy advantage vis-a-vis Indian women.</s>
 <s id="116">This is an extremely strange fact.</s>
 <s id="117">It's very rare among countries to have this kind of pattern.</s>
 <s id="118">It shows the systematic discrimination and biases in the Indian society against women.</s>
 <s id="119">The good news is, by 2006, India has closed the gap between men and women in terms of life expectancy.</s>
 <s id="120">Today, Indian women have a sizable life expectancy edge over Indian men.</s>
 <s id="121">So India is reverting to the normal.</s>
 <s id="122">But India still has a lot of work to do in terms of gender equality.</s>
 <s id="123">These are the two pictures taken of garment factories in Guangdong Province and garment factories in India.</s>
 <s id="124">In China, it's all women.</s>
 <s id="125">60 to 80 percent of the workforce in China is women in the coastal part of the country, whereas in India, it's all men.</s>
 <s id="126">Financial Times printed this picture of an Indian textile factory with the title, "India Poised to Overtake China in Textile."</s>
 <s id="127">By looking at these two pictures, I say no, it won't overtake China for a while.</s>
 <s id="128">If you look at other East Asian countries, women there play a hugely important role in terms of economic take-off -- in terms of creating the manufacturing miracle associated with East Asia.</s>
 <s id="129">India still has a long way to go to catch up with China.</s>
 <s id="130">Then the issue is, what about the Chinese political system?</s>
 <s id="131">You talk about human capital, you talk about education and public health.</s>
 <s id="132">What about the political system?</s>
 <s id="133">Isn't it true that the one-party political system has facilitated economic growth in China?</s>
 <s id="134">Actually, the answer is more nuanced and subtle than that.</s>
 <s id="135">It depends on a distinction that you draw between statics of the political system and the dynamics of the political system.</s>
 <s id="136">Statically, China is a one-party system, authoritarian -- there's no question about it.</s>
 <s id="137">Dynamically, it has changed over time to become less authoritarian and more democratic.</s>
 <s id="138">When you explain change -- for example, economic growth; economic growth is about change -- when you explain change, you use other things that have changed to explain change, rather than using the constant to explain change.</s>
 <s id="139">Sometimes a fixed effect can explain change, but a fixed effect only explains changes in interaction with the things that change.</s>
 <s id="140">In terms of the political changes, they have introduced village elections.</s>
 <s id="141">They have increased the security of proprietors.</s>
 <s id="142">And they have increased the security with long-term land leases.</s>
 <s id="143">There are also financial reforms in rural China.</s>
 <s id="144">There is also a rural entrepreneurial revolution in China.</s>
 <s id="145">To me, the pace of political changes is too slow, too gradual.</s>
 <s id="146">And my own view is the country is going to face some substantial challenges, because they have not moved further and faster on political reforms.</s>
 <s id="147">But nevertheless, the system has moved in a more liberal direction, moved in a more democratic direction.</s>
 <s id="148">You can apply exactly the same dynamic perspective on India.</s>
 <s id="149">In fact, when India was growing at a Hindu rate of growth -- about one percent, two percent a year -- that was when India was least democratic.</s>
 <s id="150">Indira Gandhi declared emergency rule in 1975.</s>
 <s id="151">The Indian government owned and operated all the TV stations.</s>
 <s id="152">A little-known fact about India in the 1990s is that the country not only has undertaken economic reforms, the country has also undertaken political reforms by introducing village self-rule, privatization of media and introducing freedom of information acts.</s>
 <s id="153">So the dynamic perspective fits both with China and in India in terms of the direction.</s>
 <s id="154">Why do many people believe that India is still a growth disaster?</s>
 <s id="155">One reason is they are always comparing India with China.</s>
 <s id="156">But China is a superstar in terms of economic growth.</s>
 <s id="157">If you are a NBA player and you are always being compared to Michael Jordan, you're going to look not so impressive.</s>
 <s id="158">But that doesn't mean that you're a bad basketball player.</s>
 <s id="159">Comparing with a superstar is the wrong benchmark.</s>
 <s id="160">In fact, if you compare India with the average developing country, even before the more recent period of acceleration of Indian growth -- now India is growing between eight and nine percent -- even before this period, India was ranked fourth in terms of economic growth among emerging economies.</s>
 <s id="161">This is a very impressive record indeed.</s>
 <s id="162">Let's think about the future: the dragon vis-a-vis the elephant.</s>
 <s id="163">Which country has the growth momentum?</s>
 <s id="164">China, I believe, still has some of the excellent raw fundamentals -- mostly the social capital, the public health, the sense of egalitarianism that you don't find in India.</s>
 <s id="165">But I believe that India has the momentum.</s>
 <s id="166">It has the improving fundamentals.</s>
 <s id="167">The government has invested in basic education, has invested in basic health.</s>
 <s id="168">I believe the government should do more, but nevertheless, the direction it is moving in is the right direction.</s>
 <s id="169">India has the right institutional conditions for economic growth, whereas China is still struggling with political reforms.</s>
 <s id="170">I believe that the political reforms are a must for China to maintain its growth.</s>
 <s id="171">And it's very important to have political reforms, to have widely shared benefits of economic growth.</s>
 <s id="172">I don't know whether that's going to happen or not, but I'm an optimist.</s>
 <s id="173">Hopefully, five years from now, I'm going to report to TEDGlobal that political reforms will happen in China.</s>
 <s id="174">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="175">(Applause)</s>
</text>
