<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">When I was 14 years old, I had low self-esteem.</s>
 <s id="2">I felt I was not talented at anything.</s>
 <s id="3">One day, I bought a yo-yo.</s>
 <s id="4">When I tried my first trick, it looked like this: (Laughter) I couldn't even do the simplest trick, but it was very natural for me, because I was not dextrous, and hated all sports.</s>
 <s id="5">But after one week of practicing, my throws became more like this: A bit better.</s>
 <s id="6">I thought, the yo-yo is something for me to be good at.</s>
 <s id="7">For the first time in my life, I found my passion.</s>
 <s id="8">I was spending all my time practicing.</s>
 <s id="9">It took me hours and hours a day to build my skills up to the next level.</s>
 <s id="10">And then, four years later, when I was 18 years old, I was standing onstage at the World YoYo Contest.</s>
 <s id="11">And I won.</s>
 <s id="12">I was so excited.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">"Yes, I did it!</s>
  <s id="13.2">I became a hero.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">I may get many sponsors, a lot of money, tons of interviews, and be on TV!"</s>
  <s id="14.2">I thought.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="15">(Laughter) But after coming back to Japan, totally nothing changed in my life.</s>
 <s id="16">(Laughter) I realized society didn't value my passion.</s>
 <s id="17">So I went back to my college and became a typical Japanese worker as a systems engineer.</s>
 <s id="18">I felt my passion, heart and soul, had left my body.</s>
 <s id="19">I felt I was not alive anymore.</s>
 <s id="20">So I started to consider what I should do, and I thought, I wanted to make my performance better, and to show onstage how spectacular the yo-yo could be to change the public's image of the yo-yo.</s>
 <s id="21">So I quit my company and started a career as a professional performer.</s>
 <s id="22">I started to learn classic ballet, jazz dance, acrobatics and other things to make my performance better.</s>
 <s id="23">As a result of these efforts, and the help of many others, it happened.</s>
 <s id="24">I won the World YoYo Contest again in the artistic performance division.</s>
 <s id="25">I passed an audition for Cirque Du Soleil.</s>
 <s id="26">Today, I am standing on the TED stage with the yo-yo in front of you.</s>
 <s id="27">(Applause) What I learned from the yo-yo is, if I make enough effort with huge passion, there is no impossible.</s>
 <s id="28">Could you let me share my passion with you through my performance?</s>
 <s id="29">(Applause) (Water sound) (Music) (Music ends) (Applause) (Music) (Music ends) (Applause) (Applause ends) (Music) (Applause)</s>
</text>
