<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Riding a wave is like suddenly gaining speed and gliding at the same time.</s>
 <s id="2">Like walking on water, like flying.</s>
 <s id="3">I think it's really about being one with a natural phenomenon.</s>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">[Small thing.</s>
  <s id="4.2">Big idea.]</s>
  <s id="4.3">The surfboard requires a lot of ergonomic thinking.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p5">
  <s id="5.1">How do I stand on it?</s>
  <s id="5.2">How do I not slip off?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="6">But at the same time, it really has to work in that fluid environment.</s>
 <s id="7">It's really considered for the rider in some areas and for water and physics in others.</s>
 <s id="8">A surfboard is made out of a core element which tends to be foam, which makes the board float, and the skin of the board is some kind of resin, epoxy, sometimes fiberglass.</s>
 <s id="9">There often is also a stringer, a wood piece down the middle, which makes it stronger.</s>
 <s id="10">The rocker is the curvature of the board in the front.</s>
 <s id="11">That is important because that determines what kind of wave you will be able to take, how steep the wave is.</s>
 <s id="12">The tail affects performance.</s>
 <s id="13">Different tails will make the board react differently, so it's a lot about personal preference.</s>
 <s id="14">Our understanding of surfing comes from when the Tahitians in 1200 AD brought it to Hawaii.</s>
 <s id="15">So when James Cook arrived around 1780, he was mesmerized by hundreds of people in the water, children, women, men, surfing naked.</s>
 <s id="16">Calvinist missionaries arrive and they're scandalized by it.</s>
 <s id="17">It becomes an illegal activity.</s>
 <s id="18">It becomes counterculture.</s>
 <s id="19">The father of modern surfing is a Hawaiian named Duke Kahanamoku.</s>
 <s id="20">He is an extraordinary swimmer, wins gold at the Olympics in 1912.</s>
 <s id="21">Goes around the world to show his swimming but brings surfboards and demonstrates surfing.</s>
 <s id="22">Imagine, people had never seen surfing before.</s>
 <s id="23">Suddenly, some person from a faraway place is standing on water, riding on water.</s>
 <s id="24">He comes back to Hawaii, and they start to make more boards.</s>
 <s id="25">Pre-Second World War, you're still looking at big, heavy wood boards.</s>
 <s id="26">Post-Second World War, new materials and new technologies become available, and those make the board lighter, more accessible, cheaper, but it continues to be a custom object, something that is made specifically for a person or for a certain spot.</s>
 <s id="27">It's a very symbiotic relationship between surfer and shaper.</s>
 <s id="28">There's so many different criteria that affect the physics of how that surfboard is moving in water.</s>
 <s id="29">A longboard is typically used on smaller waves.</s>
 <s id="30">The riding has a lot of style.</s>
 <s id="31">You can walk the board, put your toes over it, do a hang ten.</s>
 <s id="32">A shortboard will be faster.</s>
 <s id="33">They're harder to ride, they sink under the body.</s>
 <s id="34">Board design comes at the intersection between those physical factors, and really, how I want to put myself in the water.</s>
 <s id="35">It's an expression as much as it is a physical activity.</s>
 <s id="36">The draw may be because water is so elusive.</s>
 <s id="37">You can't fight it, you can't change it.</s>
 <s id="38">The best I can do is recognize what it does.</s>
 <s id="39">The surf may be big and getting bigger and surging while you're in the water.</s>
 <s id="40">The elements are changing.</s>
 <s id="41">The wind is coming up.</s>
 <s id="42">You have to be in symbiosis with the environment.</s>
 <s id="43">You need to look and feel for everything that's happening around you.</s>
 <s id="44">And yet, it's so short.</s>
 <s id="45">Five, eight, 15 seconds.</s>
 <s id="46">It's fleeting, but you have to go back to it.</s>
</text>
