<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Currently, most refugees live in the cities rather than in the refugee camps.</s>
 <s id="2">We represent over 60 percent of the number of refugees globally.</s>
 <s id="3">With the majority of refugees living in urban areas, there is a strong need for a paradigm shift and new thinking.</s>
 <s id="4">Rather than wasting money on building walls, it would be better to spend on programs to help refugees to help themselves.</s>
 <s id="5">(Applause) We always have to leave behind all our possessions.</s>
 <s id="6">But not our skills and knowledge.</s>
 <s id="7">If allowed to live a productive life, refugees can help themselves and contribute to the development of their host country.</s>
 <s id="8">I was born in the city called Bukavu, South Kivu, in the Democratic Republic of Congo.</s>
 <s id="9">I am the fifth-born in a family of 12 children.</s>
 <s id="10">My father, a mechanic by profession, worked very hard to send me to school.</s>
 <s id="11">Just like other young people, I had a lot of plans and dreams.</s>
 <s id="12">I wanted to complete my studies, get a nice job, marry and have my own children and support my family.</s>
 <s id="13">But this didn't happen.</s>
 <s id="14">War in my homeland forced me to flee to Uganda in 2008, nine years ago.</s>
 <s id="15">My family joined a steady exodus of refugees who settled in Uganda's capital, Kampala.</s>
 <s id="16">In my country, I lived already in the city, and we felt Kampala was much better than a refugee camp.</s>
 <s id="17">Refugees in the cities have always been denied international assistance, even after their recognition by UNHCR in 1997.</s>
 <s id="18">In addition to the poverty problem we were confronted with as the local urban poor, we were facing challenges due to our refugee status, such as a language barrier.</s>
 <s id="19">In Congo, the official language is French.</s>
 <s id="20">But in Uganda, it is English.</s>
 <s id="21">We didn't have access to education and health.</s>
 <s id="22">We were exposed to harassment, exploitation, intimidation and discrimination.</s>
 <s id="23">Humanitarian organizations mostly focused on the formal settlement in rural areas, and there was nothing in place for us.</s>
 <s id="24">But we didn't want handouts.</s>
 <s id="25">We wanted to work and support ourselves.</s>
 <s id="26">I joined my other two colleagues in exile and set up an organization to support other refugees.</s>
 <s id="27">YARID -- Young African Refugees for Integral Development -- began as a conversation within the Congolese community.</s>
 <s id="28">We asked the community how they could organize themselves to solve these challenges.</s>
 <s id="29">The YARID programs for support evolve in stages, progressing from soccer community, to English language to sewing livelihoods.</s>
 <s id="30">The soccer changed the energy of unemployed youth and connected people from different communities.</s>
 <s id="31">The free English classes help empower people to engage with the Ugandan community, allowing them to get to know their neighbors and sell wares.</s>
 <s id="32">The vocational training program offers livelihood skills, and with them, important opportunities for economic self-reliance.</s>
 <s id="33">We've seen so many families become self-sustaining.</s>
 <s id="34">We've seen who no longer needs our help.</s>
 <s id="35">As YARID's programs have expanded, it has included an increasing range of nationalities -- Congolese, Rwandan, Burundian, Somalis, Ethiopian, South Sudanese.</s>
 <s id="36">Today, YARID has supported over 3,000 refugees across Kampala and continues supporting more.</s>
 <s id="37">(Applause) Refugees want empowerment, not handouts.</s>
 <s id="38">We know our community better than anyone.</s>
 <s id="39">We understand the challenges and opportunities we face to become self-reliant.</s>
 <s id="40">I know better than anyone that initiatives created by refugees work.</s>
 <s id="41">They need to be internationally recognized and supported.</s>
 <s id="42">Give us the support we deserve, and we will pay you back with interest.</s>
 <s id="43">Thank you so much.</s>
 <s id="44">(Applause)</s>
</text>
