<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">From space, our planet appears to be more ocean than Earth.</s>
 <s id="2">But despite the water covering 71% of the planet’s surface, more than half the world’s population endures extreme water scarcity for at least one month a year.</s>
 <s id="3">And current estimates predict that by 2040, up to 20 more countries could be experiencing water shortages.</s>
 <s id="4">Taken together, these bleak statistics raise a startling question: are we running out of clean water?</s>
 <s id="5">Well yes, and no.</s>
 <s id="6">At a planetary scale, Earth can’t run out of freshwater thanks to the water cycle, a system that continuously produces and recycles water, morphing it from vapour, to liquid, to ice as it circulates around the globe.</s>
 <s id="7">So this isn’t really a question of how much water there is, but of how much of it is accessible to us.</s>
 <s id="8">97% of earth’s liquid is saltwater, too loaded with minerals for humans to drink or use in agriculture.</s>
 <s id="9">Of the remaining 3% of potentially usable freshwater, more than two-thirds is frozen in ice caps and glaciers.</s>
 <s id="10">That leaves less than 1% available for sustaining all life on Earth, spread across our planet in rivers, lakes, underground aquifers, ground ice and permafrost.</s>
 <s id="11">It’s these sources of water that are being rapidly depleted by humans, but slowly replenished by rain and snowfall.</s>
 <s id="12">And this limited supply isn’t distributed evenly around the globe.</s>
 <s id="13">Diverse climates and geography provide some regions with more rainfall and natural water sources, while other areas have geographic features that make transporting water much more difficult.</s>
 <s id="14">And supplying the infrastructure and energy it would take to move water across these regions is extremely expensive.</s>
 <s id="15">In many of these water-poor areas, as well as some with greater access to water, humanity is guzzling up the local water supply faster than it can be replenished.</s>
 <s id="16">And when more quickly renewed sources can’t meet the demand, we start pumping it out of our finite underground reserves.</s>
 <s id="17">Of Earth’s 37 major underground reservoirs, 21 are on track to be irreversibly emptied.</s>
 <s id="18">So while it’s true that our planet isn’t actually losing water, we are depleting the water sources we rely on at an unsustainable pace.</s>
 <s id="19">This might seem surprising – after all, on average, people only drink about two liters of water a day.</s>
 <s id="20">But water plays a hidden role in our daily lives, and in that same 24 hours, most people will actually consume an estimated 3000 liters of water.</s>
 <s id="21">In fact, household water – which we use to drink, cook, and clean – accounts for only 3.6% of humanity’s water consumption.</s>
 <s id="22">Another 4.4% goes to the wide range of factories which make the products we buy each day.</s>
 <s id="23">But the remaining 92% of our water consumption is all spent on a single industry: agriculture.</s>
 <s id="24">Our farms drain the equivalent of 3.3 billion Olympic-sized swimming pools every year, all of it swallowed up by crops and livestock to feed Earth’s growing population.</s>
 <s id="25">Agriculture currently covers 37% of Earth’s land area, posing the biggest threat to our regional water supplies.</s>
 <s id="26">And yet, it’s also a necessity.</s>
 <s id="27">So how do we limit agriculture’s thirst while still feeding those who rely on it?</s>
 <s id="28">Farmers are already finding ingenious ways to reduce their impact, like using special irrigation techniques to grow “more crop per drop”, and breeding new crops that are less thirsty.</s>
 <s id="29">Other industries are following suit, adopting production processes that reuse and recycle water.</s>
 <s id="30">On a personal level, reducing food waste is the first step to reducing water use, since one-third of the food that leaves farms is currently wasted or thrown away.</s>
 <s id="31">You might also want to consider eating less water-intensive foods like shelled nuts and red meat.</s>
 <s id="32">Adopting a vegetarian lifestyle could reduce up to one third of your water footprint.</s>
 <s id="33">Our planet may never run out of water, but it doesn’t have to for individuals to go thirsty.</s>
 <s id="34">Solving this local problem requires a global solution, and small day-to-day decisions can affect reservoirs around the world.</s>
</text>
