<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I was born in Switzerland and raised in Ghana, West Africa.</s>
 <s id="2">Ghana felt safe to me as a child.</s>
 <s id="3">I was free, I was happy.</s>
 <s id="4">The early 70s marked a time of musical and artistic excellence in Ghana.</s>
 <s id="5">But then by the end of the decade, the country had fallen back into political instability and mismanagement.</s>
 <s id="6">In 1979, I witnessed my first military coup.</s>
 <s id="7">We the children had gathered at a friend's house.</s>
 <s id="8">It was a dimly lit shack.</s>
 <s id="9">There was a beaten up black and white television flickering in the background, and a former head of state and general was being blindfolded and tied to the pole.</s>
 <s id="10">The firing squad aimed, fired -- the general was dead.</s>
 <s id="11">Now this was being broadcast live.</s>
 <s id="12">And shortly after, we left the country, and we returned to Switzerland.</s>
 <s id="13">Now Europe came as a shock to me, and I think I started feeling the need to shed my skin in order to fit in.</s>
 <s id="14">I wanted to blend in like a chameleon.</s>
 <s id="15">I think it was a tactic of survival.</s>
 <s id="16">And it worked, or so I believed.</s>
 <s id="17">So here I was in 2008 wondering where I was in my life.</s>
 <s id="18">And I felt I was being typecast as an actor.</s>
 <s id="19">I was always playing the exotic African.</s>
 <s id="20">I was playing the violent African, the African terrorist.</s>
 <s id="21">And I was thinking, how many terrorists could I possibly play before turning into one myself?</s>
 <s id="22">And I had become ashamed of the other, the African in me.</s>
 <s id="23">And fortunately I decided in 2008 to return to Ghana, after 28 years of absence.</s>
 <s id="24">I wanted to document on film the 2008 presidential elections.</s>
 <s id="25">And there, I started by searching for the footprints in my childhood.</s>
 <s id="26">And before I even knew it, I was suddenly on a stage surrounded by thousands of cheering people during a political rally.</s>
 <s id="27">And I realized that, when I'd left the country, free and fair elections in a democratic environment were a dream.</s>
 <s id="28">And now that I'd returned, that dream had become reality, though a fragile reality.</s>
 <s id="29">And I was thinking, was Ghana searching for its identity like I was looking for my identity?</s>
 <s id="30">Was what was happening in Ghana a metaphor for what was happening in me?</s>
 <s id="31">And it was as if through the standards of my Western life, I hadn't lived up to my full potential.</s>
 <s id="32">I mean, nor had Ghana, even though we had been trying very hard.</s>
 <s id="33">Now in 1957, Ghana was the first sub-Saharan country to gain its independence.</s>
 <s id="34">In the late 50s, Ghana and Singapore had the same GDP.</s>
 <s id="35">I mean, today, Singapore is a First World country and Ghana is not.</s>
 <s id="36">But maybe it was time to prove to myself, yes, it's important to understand the past, it is important to look at it in a different light, but maybe we should look at the strengths in our own culture and build on those foundations in the present.</s>
 <s id="37">So here I was, December 7th, 2008.</s>
 <s id="38">The polling stations opened to the voters at 7:00 AM, but voters, eager to take their own political fate into their hands, were starting to line up at 4:00 AM in the morning.</s>
 <s id="39">And they had traveled from near, they had traveled from far, because they wanted to make their voices heard.</s>
 <s id="40">And I asked one of the voters, I said, "Whom are you going to vote for?"</s>
 <s id="41">And he said, "I'm sorry, I can't tell you."</s>
 <s id="42">He said that his vote was in his heart.</s>
 <s id="43">And I understood, this was their election, and they weren't going to let anyone take it away from them.</s>
 <s id="44">Now the first round of the voting didn't bring forth a clear winner -- so nobody had achieved the absolute majority -- so voting went into a second round three weeks later.</s>
 <s id="45">The candidates were back on the road; they were campaigning.</s>
 <s id="46">The rhetoric of the candidates, of course, changed.</s>
 <s id="47">The heat was on.</s>
 <s id="48">And then the cliche came to haunt us.</s>
 <s id="49">There were claims of intimidation at the polling stations, of ballot boxes being stolen.</s>
 <s id="50">Inflated results started coming in and the mob was starting to get out of control.</s>
 <s id="51">We witnessed the eruption of violence in the streets.</s>
 <s id="52">People were being beaten brutally.</s>
 <p id="p53">
  <s id="53.1">The army started firing their guns.</s>
  <s id="53.2">People were scrambling.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="54">It was complete chaos.</s>
 <s id="55">And my heart sank, because I thought, here we are again.</s>
 <s id="56">Here is another proof that the African is not capable of governing himself.</s>
 <s id="57">And not only that, I am documenting it -- documenting my own cultural shortcomings.</s>
 <s id="58">So when the echo of the gunshots had lingered, it was soon drowned by the chanting of the mob, and I didn't believe what I was hearing.</s>
 <s id="59">They were chanting, "We want peace.</s>
 <s id="60">We want peace."</s>
 <s id="61">And I realized it had to come from the people.</s>
 <s id="62">After all, they decide, and they did.</s>
 <s id="63">So the sounds that were before distorted and loud, were suddenly a melody.</s>
 <s id="64">The sounds of the voices were harmonious.</s>
 <s id="65">So it could happen.</s>
 <s id="66">A democracy could be upheld peacefully.</s>
 <s id="67">It could be, by the will of the masses who were now urgently pressing with all their heart and all their will for peace.</s>
 <s id="68">Now here's an interesting comparison.</s>
 <s id="69">We in the West, we preach the values, the golden light of democracy, that we are the shining example of how it's done.</s>
 <s id="70">But when it comes down to it, Ghana found itself in the same place in which the U.S. election stalled in the 2000 presidential elections -- Bush versus Gore.</s>
 <s id="71">But instead of the unwillingness of the candidates to allow the system to proceed and the people to decide, Ghana honored democracy and its people.</s>
 <s id="72">It didn't leave it up to the Supreme Court to decide; the people did.</s>
 <s id="73">Now the second round of voting did not bring forth a clear winner either.</s>
 <s id="74">I mean, it was so incredibly close.</s>
 <s id="75">The electoral commissioner declared, with the consent of the parties, to run an unprecedented second re-run.</s>
 <s id="76">So the people went back to the polls to determine their own president, not the legal system.</s>
 <s id="77">And guess what, it worked.</s>
 <s id="78">The defeated candidate gave up power and made way for Ghana to move into a new democratic cycle.</s>
 <s id="79">I mean, at the absolute time for the absolute need of democracy, they did not abuse their power.</s>
 <s id="80">The belief in true democracy and in the people runs deep, proving that the African is capable of governing himself.</s>
 <s id="81">Now the uphill battle for Ghana and for Africa is not over, but I have proof that the other side of democracy exists, and that we must not take it for granted.</s>
 <s id="82">Now I have learned that my place is not just in the West or in Africa, and I'm still searching for my identity, but I saw Ghana create democracy better.</s>
 <s id="83">Ghana taught me to look at people differently and to look at myself differently.</s>
 <s id="84">And yes, we Africans can.</s>
 <s id="85">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="86">(Applause)</s>
</text>
