<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'd like to tell you a story.</s>
 <s id="2">When I was 24, I found myself living in a small beach town by the name of Naples, Florida.</s>
 <s id="3">I was looking for something new.</s>
 <s id="4">I was 24.</s>
 <s id="5">I'm 29 now.</s>
 <s id="6">And in that small coastal town, I was the only Deaf resident.</s>
 <s id="7">In fact, the closest deaf person was a few hours away by car.</s>
 <s id="8">And all of the friends and acquaintances that I had made could hear.</s>
 <s id="9">I didn't mind though; I wanted something new.</s>
 <s id="10">Lucky for me, Naples, Florida is home to some of the U.S. Olympics volleyball team, where they reside and train through the year.</s>
 <s id="11">So I had a fantastic opportunity to play with them every day I could.</s>
 <s id="12">And we'd hit the court all the time, either indoors or out at the beach; it was great.</s>
 <s id="13">Lucky for them, I happen to be very good at volleyball.</s>
 <s id="14">So one night after a great game, a friend and I pull up some chairs by the water to watch the sun go down and chat.</s>
 <s id="15">And he looks over at me and he asks me a question that completely blew me away.</s>
 <s id="16">To be honest, in 24 years of my life, nobody had ever asked me.</s>
 <s id="17">And his question was simple: "Have you ever wished you could hear?"</s>
 <s id="18">I looked at him for a second and thought, Where did that come from?</s>
 <s id="19">Then I took a moment and I realized while we had been sitting there, I could see waves coming in and crashing on the beach.</s>
 <s id="20">He could hear that.</s>
 <s id="21">Obviously, I couldn't.</s>
 <s id="22">My entire world is completely silent.</s>
 <s id="23">To our left, people had taken over the court and were playing volleyball, cheering each other on.</s>
 <s id="24">To our right, a mother was playing and laughing with her baby.</s>
 <s id="25">And behind us, cars and ATVs had passed by all day without me even noticing.</s>
 <s id="26">So, I was quick to answer: "No, of course not.</s>
 <s id="27">I've never wished I could hear.</s>
 <s id="28">I've never wished that because I love who I am."</s>
 <s id="29">And you may be wondering, How do I love myself as a Deaf man?</s>
 <s id="30">Well, first, I was born deaf.</s>
 <s id="31">My deafness shaped my childhood, and it's all I've ever known.</s>
 <s id="32">So my perspective on life and my experience of the world is very different.</s>
 <s id="33">My outlook and my life has involved experiences that many of you have never had to encounter as hearing people.</s>
 <s id="34">My culture, something I embody and cherish, has always been Deaf.</s>
 <s id="35">My perspective on life is completely different.</s>
 <s id="36">The experiences I've had, something I hold most dear, have taught me to love myself as a Deaf man.</s>
 <s id="37">To illustrate that point, if I were to walk into a job interview with a panel of hearing peers, and if I were to approach that meeting wishing that I could hear, wishing that I could speak like them, and focusing on that imbalance, do you think that I would do very well?</s>
 <s id="38">Obviously not, right?</s>
 <s id="39">Because in the back of my mind I'm focusing on the negative, therefore creating a negative outcome, and I'm certain I wouldn't get that job.</s>
 <s id="40">But, if instead, I use my difference as an advantage and an asset, I know that as a Deaf man I have so much to offer their company.</s>
 <s id="41">My experiences growing up are much different from theirs.</s>
 <s id="42">And knowing that allows me to approach the interview positive.</s>
 <s id="43">I can go into that meeting and confidently tell them how they will benefit from hiring a Deaf man for a multitude of reasons.</s>
 <s id="44">And I can walk out with that job because it's all about mindset.</s>
 <s id="45">So I say first and foremost to love yourself.</s>
 <s id="46">So as I mentioned, the first reason I love myself is my upbringing.</s>
 <s id="47">But many of you may not know that I come from a rather large family.</s>
 <s id="48">I have two brothers who are also Deaf along with my parents, my grandparents, and yes, even my great-grandparents as well.</s>
 <s id="49">I'm the fourth generation in a beautiful family with over 25 Deaf members.</s>
 <s id="50">Born to Deaf parents who understood the Deaf experience, they knew exactly how to raise me.</s>
 <s id="51">They knew how to provide me with the best opportunities and to support me.</s>
 <s id="52">From day one of my existence, my parents gave me language, access to education, and love.</s>
 <s id="53">Growing up, my life was perfect.</s>
 <s id="54">Imagine, like many of you born to hearing parents, I never noticed barriers that simply weren't there.</s>
 <s id="55">I'm sure many of you felt your life was normal, the same way that I did.</s>
 <s id="56">Coming from a Deaf family, my world, in every way, was a utopia.</s>
 <s id="57">When it came time for my parents to enroll me in school, they already knew that I would go to the Deaf school.</s>
 <s id="58">I would learn in an environment that was designed for me.</s>
 <s id="59">At that time, all of my peers, and teachers, and even the superintendent was Deaf.</s>
 <s id="60">So, I was still in my perfect world.</s>
 <s id="61">I was in an environment where I could grow and where I could thrive.</s>
 <s id="62">And I had no problems; it was perfect for me.</s>
 <s id="63">And many people don't believe that, but it's true.</s>
 <s id="64">For me, the Deaf community, our world, was the perfect world for me.</s>
 <s id="65">And I remember in the summer before fifth grade, I was ready to go back to school, and I asked my mom to go to a public school.</s>
 <s id="66">She thought I was crazy.</s>
 <p id="p67">
  <s id="67.1">She said, "What?!</s>
  <s id="67.2">No!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="68">Public school, it's all hearing kids.</s>
 <s id="69">The Deaf school is a perfect fit."</s>
 <s id="70">And I said, "No, I want to learn what those students are learning.</s>
 <s id="71">I want to see what their classrooms are like.</s>
 <s id="72">What are public school teachers like?"</s>
 <s id="73">So upon my insistence she enrolled me.</s>
 <s id="74">And after two weeks of frustration, I came home pleading to go back to the Deaf school.</s>
 <s id="75">She listened very sympathetically and told me, "Nope, too bad."</s>
 <s id="76">I was floored.</s>
 <s id="77">She told me I needed to stick it out for a year because I needed to learn how to interact with my hearing peers, and that if I gave it a little patience, I would learn so much about the world around me.</s>
 <s id="78">Because the reality is the world is hearing.</s>
 <s id="79">I was the only Deaf kid in the entire school.</s>
 <s id="80">Of course, I always had hearing friends, but they could sign like me.</s>
 <s id="81">So that year I gained a lot of insight.</s>
 <s id="82">I couldn't be involved in any of the school organizations.</s>
 <s id="83">My friends never learned enough sign to communicate.</s>
 <s id="84">And every time I tried to play a sport, I'd get benched.</s>
 <s id="85">The basketball coach told me a Deaf kid could never help the team win a game.</s>
 <s id="86">And I was athletic.</s>
 <s id="87">So after a year, I went back to the Deaf school where I realized that's my home.</s>
 <s id="88">That's my community.</s>
 <s id="89">And my community is where I can thrive.</s>
 <s id="90">I got involved in the classroom again, joined a bunch of school organizations, and got back on the basketball team, where I helped win many games.</s>
 <s id="91">So it's without hesitation that I can say the Deaf community is in fact my home.</s>
 <s id="92">After graduating high school, I was accepted into the only Deaf university in the world: Gallaudet University in Washington, D.C.</s>
 <s id="93">It was there I gained my degree in mathematics with the intention of becoming a better teacher than the ones I had growing up.</s>
 <s id="94">Like many of you, I sat through some math teachers who seriously sucked.</s>
 <s id="95">(Laughter) I wanted to be a good math teacher.</s>
 <s id="96">But I also wanted to be a good role model for those students.</s>
 <s id="97">So as time got closer to graduation, of course I was nervous.</s>
 <s id="98">I started questioning if I had made the right decision.</s>
 <s id="99">And I decided to get out - to get out of my comfort zone and to travel the world.</s>
 <s id="100">Since then, I've been to over 43 countries.</s>
 <p id="p101">
  <s id="101.1">And the funny thing about when I travel is that I'm constantly meeting hearing people who say, "Nyle, you are so brave.</s>
  <s id="101.2">How do you travel like this?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="102">Isn't it hard to be Deaf and travel?</s>
 <s id="103">It looks impossible."</s>
 <s id="104">And let me tell you, traveling as a Deaf person, I think, is actually much easier than traveling for hearing people.</s>
 <s id="105">Because sign language is something that gives me access to a much larger world.</s>
 <s id="106">I'll tell you one of my favorite stories.</s>
 <s id="107">A few years ago, I was in south Sicily perusing a flea market, when I walked into a butcher shop, and standing there is an American tourist trying to ask the butcher where the meat he was slicing is sourced from.</s>
 <s id="108">So the Sicilian man, speaking no English, is gesturing, right?</s>
 <s id="109">And you know Italians gesture.</s>
 <s id="110">He's trying to explain where the meat comes from, and it's going right over the head of the tourist.</s>
 <s id="111">So watching this very comical breakdown in conversation, I'm understanding everything perfectly, so I pull out a paper and a pen, and I translate what the butcher is saying, and I hand it over to the tourist and explain, "This is what he's trying to tell you."</s>
 <s id="112">So there I am, the Deaf person translating for two hearing people.</s>
 <s id="113">And in that situation, they're the ones disabled, not me.</s>
 <s id="114">(Laughter) While that story is ironic, it happens so many times when I meet people in other countries.</s>
 <s id="115">I'm always amazed to meet locals in other countries, and their ability to gesticulate and communicate with me, often quite easily.</s>
 <s id="116">And I would always tell myself to visit the local Deaf schools and to make time to meet Deaf locals.</s>
 <s id="117">But with every new Deaf school that I saw, I was sad to see that their schools were in terrible condition, and their education was greatly lacking.</s>
 <s id="118">Often, I just couldn't believe my eyes.</s>
 <s id="119">When I would meet Deaf adults, I realized a common thread very quickly.</s>
 <s id="120">They either didn't have the same level of education I did or their language was incomplete, making it hard to communicate.</s>
 <s id="121">They'd often complain to me that the system had failed them, and now they struggled to find work.</s>
 <s id="122">And I kept asking myself, why is this happening, and why is this happening so often?</s>
 <s id="123">Why am I somehow more fortunate?</s>
 <s id="124">Growing up, I thought every deaf person in the world was like me and had the same opportunities that I did.</s>
 <s id="125">So in returning to the United States, I decided to do some research on the topic.</s>
 <s id="126">And what I found shocked me.</s>
 <s id="127">There are currently more than 70 million deaf people in the world with only two percent of them having access to education in sign languages.</s>
 <s id="128">Which means millions upon millions of deaf children not receiving the education they need, also known as education deprivation.</s>
 <s id="129">I also learned that over 75 percent of hearing parents don't sign to communicate with their deaf children.</s>
 <s id="130">Which is astonishing.</s>
 <s id="131">Again, imagine millions and millions of deaf children without an education, without a language.</s>
 <s id="132">Those children without language and access to education exhibit signs of brain damage.</s>
 <s id="133">In my research, I also found that I'm a part of an even smaller group.</s>
 <s id="134">Ten percent of Deaf children come from Deaf parents like mine.</s>
 <s id="135">Only 10 percent.</s>
 <s id="136">I'm incredibly lucky.</s>
 <s id="137">I had access to language, an education, and I had parents who loved me and put me on a path to success.</s>
 <s id="138">I wouldn't be who I am today without any of those things.</s>
 <s id="139">So it was clear to me that something needed to be done.</s>
 <s id="140">I got to work in setting up my own foundation - the Nyle DiMarco Foundation - with the goal of improving the lives of millions of deaf people around the world.</s>
 <s id="141">We've since partnered with another Deaf organization in the United States to introduce legislation - a bill that requires all deaf children have access to language between the ages of zero and five, setting up benchmarks for their success.</s>
 <s id="142">Because before the age of five, children have the ability to acquire a foundation in language, readying them for the classroom and for a successful life.</s>
 <s id="143">After the age of five, that critical language acquisition window closes.</s>
 <s id="144">I'm working to give every deaf child in the world a future filled with a rich language and the opportunities I was lucky enough to receive.</s>
 <s id="145">But the Deaf community cannot do it alone; we need you to become our allies and join us in making the world more knowledgeable.</s>
 <s id="146">We need you to join us, to fight with us and for us in the ongoing battle of affording children what they need to thrive.</s>
 <s id="147">So before I go, I want to teach you two very simple but important signs.</s>
 <s id="148">The first is "love."</s>
 <s id="149">The second, "yourself."</s>
 <s id="150">Follow me: Love yourself.</s>
 <s id="151">Brilliant!</s>
 <s id="152">A-plusses all around!</s>
 <s id="153">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="154">(Laughter)</s>
</text>
