<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Well, that's kind of an obvious statement up there.</s>
 <s id="2">I started with that sentence about 12 years ago, and I started in the context of developing countries, but you're sitting here from every corner of the world.</s>
 <s id="3">So if you think of a map of your country, I think you'll realize that for every country on Earth, you could draw little circles to say, "These are places where good teachers won't go."</s>
 <s id="4">On top of that, those are the places from where trouble comes.</s>
 <s id="5">So we have an ironic problem -- good teachers don't want to go to just those places where they're needed the most.</s>
 <s id="6">I started in 1999 to try and address this problem with an experiment, which was a very simple experiment in New Delhi.</s>
 <s id="7">I basically embedded a computer into a wall of a slum in New Delhi.</s>
 <s id="8">The children barely went to school, they didn't know any English -- they'd never seen a computer before, and they didn't know what the internet was.</s>
 <s id="9">I connected high speed internet to it -- it's about three feet off the ground -- turned it on and left it there.</s>
 <s id="10">After this, we noticed a couple of interesting things, which you'll see.</s>
 <s id="11">But I repeated this all over India and then through a large part of the world and noticed that children will learn to do what they want to learn to do.</s>
 <s id="12">This is the first experiment that we did -- eight year-old boy on your right teaching his student, a six year-old girl, and he was teaching her how to browse.</s>
 <s id="13">This boy here in the middle of central India -- this is in a Rajasthan village, where the children recorded their own music and then played it back to each other and in the process, they've enjoyed themselves thoroughly.</s>
 <s id="14">They did all of this in four hours after seeing the computer for the first time.</s>
 <s id="15">In another South Indian village, these boys here had assembled a video camera and were trying to take the photograph of a bumble bee.</s>
 <s id="16">They downloaded it from Disney.com, or one of these websites, 14 days after putting the computer in their village.</s>
 <s id="17">So at the end of it, we concluded that groups of children can learn to use computers and the internet on their own, irrespective of who or where they were.</s>
 <s id="18">At that point, I became a little more ambitious and decided to see what else could children do with a computer.</s>
 <s id="19">We started off with an experiment in Hyderabad, India, where I gave a group of children -- they spoke English with a very strong Telugu accent.</s>
 <s id="20">I gave them a computer with a speech-to-text interface, which you now get free with Windows, and asked them to speak into it.</s>
 <s id="21">So when they spoke into it, the computer typed out gibberish, so they said, "Well, it doesn't understand anything of what we are saying."</s>
 <s id="22">So I said, "Yeah, I'll leave it here for two months.</s>
 <s id="23">Make yourself understood to the computer."</s>
 <s id="24">So the children said, "How do we do that."</s>
 <s id="25">And I said, "I don't know, actually."</s>
 <s id="26">(Laughter) And I left.</s>
 <s id="27">(Laughter) Two months later -- and this is now documented in the Information Technology for International Development journal -- that accents had changed and were remarkably close to the neutral British accent in which I had trained the speech-to-text synthesizer.</s>
 <s id="28">In other words, they were all speaking like James Tooley.</s>
 <s id="29">(Laughter) So they could do that on their own.</s>
 <s id="30">After that, I started to experiment with various other things that they might learn to do on their own.</s>
 <s id="31">I got an interesting phone call once from Columbo, from the late Arthur C. Clarke, who said, "I want to see what's going on."</s>
 <s id="32">And he couldn't travel, so I went over there.</s>
 <s id="33">He said two interesting things, "A teacher that can be replaced by a machine should be."</s>
 <s id="34">(Laughter) The second thing he said was that, "If children have interest, then education happens."</s>
 <s id="35">And I was doing that in the field, so every time I would watch it and think of him.</s>
 <s id="36">(Video) Arthur C. Clarke: And they can definitely help people, because children quickly learn to navigate the web and find things which interest them.</s>
 <s id="37">And when you've got interest, then you have education.</s>
 <s id="38">Sugata Mitra: I took the experiment to South Africa.</s>
 <s id="39">This is a 15 year-old boy.</s>
 <s id="40">(Video) Boy: ... just mention, I play games like animals, and I listen to music.</s>
 <s id="41">SM: And I asked him, "Do you send emails?"</s>
 <s id="42">And he said, "Yes, and they hop across the ocean."</s>
 <s id="43">This is in Cambodia, rural Cambodia -- a fairly silly arithmetic game, which no child would play inside the classroom or at home.</s>
 <s id="44">They would, you know, throw it back at you.</s>
 <s id="45">They'd say, "This is very boring."</s>
 <s id="46">If you leave it on the pavement and if all the adults go away, then they will show off with each other about what they can do.</s>
 <s id="47">This is what these children are doing.</s>
 <s id="48">They are trying to multiply, I think.</s>
 <s id="49">And all over India, at the end of about two years, children were beginning to Google their homework.</s>
 <s id="50">As a result, the teachers reported tremendous improvements in their English -- (Laughter) rapid improvement and all sorts of things.</s>
 <s id="51">They said, "They have become really deep thinkers and so on and so forth.</s>
 <s id="52">(Laughter) And indeed they had.</s>
 <s id="53">I mean, if there's stuff on Google, why would you need to stuff it into your head?</s>
 <s id="54">So at the end of the next four years, I decided that groups of children can navigate the internet to achieve educational objectives on their own.</s>
 <s id="55">At that time, a large amount of money had come into Newcastle University to improve schooling in India.</s>
 <p id="p56">
  <s id="56.1">So Newcastle gave me a call.</s>
  <s id="56.2">I said, "I'll do it from Delhi."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="57">They said, "There's no way you're going to handle a million pounds-worth of University money sitting in Delhi."</s>
 <s id="58">So in 2006, I bought myself a heavy overcoat and moved to Newcastle.</s>
 <s id="59">I wanted to test the limits of the system.</s>
 <s id="60">The first experiment I did out of Newcastle was actually done in India.</s>
 <s id="61">And I set myself and impossible target: can Tamil speaking 12-year-old children in a South Indian village teach themselves biotechnology in English on their own?</s>
 <s id="62">And I thought, I'll test them, they'll get a zero -- I'll give the materials, I'll come back and test them -- they get another zero, I'll go back and say, "Yes, we need teachers for certain things."</s>
 <s id="63">I called in 26 children.</s>
 <s id="64">They all came in there, and I told them that there's some really difficult stuff on this computer.</s>
 <s id="65">I wouldn't be surprised if you didn't understand anything.</s>
 <s id="66">It's all in English, and I'm going.</s>
 <s id="67">(Laughter) So I left them with it.</s>
 <s id="68">I came back after two months, and the 26 children marched in looking very, very quiet.</s>
 <s id="69">I said, "Well, did you look at any of the stuff?"</s>
 <s id="70">They said, "Yes, we did."</s>
 <p id="p71">
  <s id="71.1">"Did you understand anything?"</s>
  <s id="71.2">"No, nothing."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="72">So I said, "Well, how long did you practice on it before you decided you understood nothing?"</s>
 <s id="73">They said, "We look at it every day."</s>
 <s id="74">So I said, "For two months, you were looking at stuff you didn't understand?"</s>
 <s id="75">So a 12 year-old girl raises her hand and says, literally, "Apart from the fact that improper replication of the DNA molecule causes genetic disease, we've understood nothing else."</s>
 <s id="76">(Laughter) (Applause) (Laughter) It took me three years to publish that.</s>
 <s id="77">It's just been published in the British Journal of Educational Technology.</s>
 <s id="78">One of the referees who refereed the paper said, "It's too good to be true," which was not very nice.</s>
 <s id="79">Well, one of the girls had taught herself to become the teacher.</s>
 <s id="80">And then that's her over there.</s>
 <s id="81">Remember, they don't study English.</s>
 <s id="82">I edited out the last bit when I asked, "Where is the neuron?"</s>
 <p id="p83">
  <s id="83.1">and she says, "The neuron?</s>
  <s id="83.2">The neuron," and then she looked and did this.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="84">Whatever the expression, it was not very nice.</s>
 <s id="85">So their scores had gone up from zero to 30 percent, which is an educational impossibility under the circumstances.</s>
 <s id="86">But 30 percent is not a pass.</s>
 <s id="87">So I found that they had a friend, a local accountant, a young girl, and they played football with her.</s>
 <s id="88">I asked that girl, "Would you teach them enough biotechnology to pass?"</s>
 <p id="p89">
  <s id="89.1">And she said, "How would I do that?</s>
  <s id="89.2">I don't know the subject."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="90">I said, "No, use the method of the grandmother."</s>
 <s id="91">She said, "What's that?"</s>
 <s id="92">I said, "Well, what you've got to do is stand behind them and admire them all the time.</s>
 <p id="p93">
  <s id="93.1">Just say to them, 'That's cool.</s>
  <s id="93.2">That's fantastic.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p94">
  <s id="94.1">What is that?</s>
  <s id="94.2">Can you do that again?</s>
  <s id="94.3">Can you show me some more?'"</s>
  <s id="94.4">She did that for two months.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="95">The scores went up to 50, which is what the posh schools of New Delhi, with a trained biotechnology teacher were getting.</s>
 <s id="96">So I came back to Newcastle with these results and decided that there was something happening here that definitely was getting very serious.</s>
 <s id="97">So, having experimented in all sorts of remote places, I came to the most remote place that I could think of.</s>
 <s id="98">(Laughter) Approximately 5,000 miles from Delhi is the little town of Gateshead.</s>
 <s id="99">In Gateshead, I took 32 children and I started to fine-tune the method.</s>
 <s id="100">I made them into groups of four.</s>
 <s id="101">I said, "You make your own groups of four.</s>
 <s id="102">Each group of four can use one computer and not four computers."</s>
 <s id="103">Remember, from the Hole in the Wall.</s>
 <s id="104">"You can exchange groups.</s>
 <s id="105">You can walk across to another group, if you don't like your group, etc.</s>
 <s id="106">You can go to another group, peer over their shoulders, see what they're doing, come back to you own group and claim it as your own work."</s>
 <s id="107">And I explained to them that, you know, a lot of scientific research is done using that method.</s>
 <s id="108">(Laughter) (Applause) The children enthusiastically got after me and said, "Now, what do you want us to do?"</s>
 <s id="109">I gave them six GCSE questions.</s>
 <s id="110">The first group -- the best one -- solved everything in 20 minutes.</s>
 <s id="111">The worst, in 45.</s>
 <s id="112">They used everything that they knew -- news groups, Google, Wikipedia, Ask Jeeves, etc.</s>
 <s id="113">The teachers said, "Is this deep learning?"</s>
 <s id="114">I said, "Well, let's try it.</s>
 <s id="115">I'll come back after two months.</s>
 <s id="116">We'll give them a paper test -- no computers, no talking to each other, etc."</s>
 <s id="117">The average score when I'd done it with the computers and the groups was 76 percent.</s>
 <s id="118">When I did the experiment, when I did the test, after two months, the score was 76 percent.</s>
 <s id="119">There was photographic recall inside the children, I suspect because they're discussing with each other.</s>
 <s id="120">A single child in front of a single computer will not do that.</s>
 <s id="121">I have further results, which are almost unbelievable, of scores which go up with time.</s>
 <s id="122">Because their teachers say that after the session is over, the children continue to Google further.</s>
 <s id="123">Here in Britain, I put out a call for British grandmothers, after my Kuppam experiment.</s>
 <s id="124">Well, you know, they're very vigorous people, British grandmothers.</s>
 <s id="125">200 of them volunteered immediately.</s>
 <s id="126">(Laughter) The deal was that they would give me one hour of broadband time, sitting in their homes, one day in a week.</s>
 <s id="127">So they did that, and over the last two years, over 600 hours of instruction has happened over Skype, using what my students call the granny cloud.</s>
 <s id="128">The granny cloud sits over there.</s>
 <s id="129">I can beam them to whichever school I want to.</s>
 <s id="130">(Video) Teacher: You can't catch me.</s>
 <s id="131">You say it.</s>
 <s id="132">You can't catch me.</s>
 <s id="133">Children: You can't catch me.</s>
 <s id="134">Teacher: I'm the gingerbread man.</s>
 <s id="135">Children: I'm the gingerbread man.</s>
 <p id="p136">
  <s id="136.1">Teacher: Well done.</s>
  <s id="136.2">Very good ...</s>
 </p>
 <s id="137">SM: Back at Gateshead, a 10-year-old girl gets into the heart of Hinduism in 15 minutes.</s>
 <s id="138">You know, stuff which I don't know anything about.</s>
 <s id="139">Two children watch a TEDTalk.</s>
 <s id="140">They wanted to be footballers before.</s>
 <s id="141">After watching eight TEDTalks, he wants to become Leonardo da Vinci.</s>
 <s id="142">(Laughter) (Applause) It's pretty simple stuff.</s>
 <s id="143">This is what I'm building now -- they're called SOLEs: Self Organized Learning Environments.</s>
 <s id="144">The furniture is designed so that children can sit in front of big, powerful screens, big broadband connections, but in groups.</s>
 <s id="145">If they want, they can call the granny cloud.</s>
 <s id="146">This is a SOLE in Newcastle.</s>
 <s id="147">The mediator is from Pune, India.</s>
 <p id="p148">
  <s id="148.1">So how far can we go?</s>
  <s id="148.2">One last little bit and I'll stop.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="149">I went to Turin in May.</s>
 <s id="150">I sent all the teachers away from my group of 10 year-old students.</s>
 <s id="151">I speak only English, they speak only Italian, so we had no way to communicate.</s>
 <s id="152">I started writing English questions on the blackboard.</s>
 <s id="153">The children looked at it and said, "What?"</s>
 <s id="154">I said, "Well, do it."</s>
 <s id="155">They typed it into Google, translated it into Italian, went back into Italian Google.</s>
 <s id="156">Fifteen minutes later -- next question: where is Calcutta?</s>
 <s id="157">This one, they took only 10 minutes.</s>
 <s id="158">I tried a really hard one then.</s>
 <s id="159">Who was Pythagoras, and what did he do?</s>
 <s id="160">There was silence for a while, then they said, "You've spelled it wrong.</s>
 <s id="161">It's Pitagora."</s>
 <s id="162">And then, in 20 minutes, the right-angled triangles began to appear on the screens.</s>
 <s id="163">This sent shivers up my spine.</s>
 <s id="164">These are 10 year-olds.</s>
 <p id="p165">
  <s id="165.1">Text: In another 30 minutes they would reach the Theory of Relativity.</s>
  <s id="165.2">And then?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="166">(Laughter) (Applause) SM: So you know what's happened?</s>
 <s id="167">I think we've just stumbled across a self-organizing system.</s>
 <s id="168">A self-organizing system is one where a structure appears without explicit intervention from the outside.</s>
 <s id="169">Self-organizing systems also always show emergence, which is that the system starts to do things, which it was never designed for.</s>
 <s id="170">Which is why you react the way you do, because it looks impossible.</s>
 <s id="171">I think I can make a guess now -- education is self-organizing system, where learning is an emergent phenomenon.</s>
 <s id="172">It'll take a few years to prove it, experimentally, but I'm going to try.</s>
 <s id="173">But in the meanwhile, there is a method available.</s>
 <s id="174">One billion children, we need 100 million mediators -- there are many more than that on the planet -- 10 million SOLEs, 180 billion dollars and 10 years.</s>
 <s id="175">We could change everything.</s>
 <s id="176">Thanks.</s>
 <s id="177">(Applause)</s>
</text>
