<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In 1982, a young nurse was suffering from severe, unrelenting depression.</s>
 <s id="2">She couldn’t work, socialize, or even concentrate well enough to read the newspaper.</s>
 <s id="3">One treatment changed everything.</s>
 <s id="4">After two courses of electroconvulsive therapy, or ECT, her symptoms lifted.</s>
 <s id="5">She went back to work, then on to graduate school, where she earned high grades.</s>
 <s id="6">At first, she talked openly about her life changing treatment.</s>
 <s id="7">But as she realized many people had an extremely negative impression of ECT, she stopped sharing her experience.</s>
 <s id="8">ECT carried a deep stigma, leftover from a history that bears little resemblance to the modern procedure.</s>
 <s id="9">The therapy was first used in medicine in 1938.</s>
 <s id="10">In its early years, doctors administered a strong electrical current to the brain, causing a whole-body seizure during which patients might bite their tongues or even break bones.</s>
 <s id="11">Modern ECT is very different.</s>
 <s id="12">While a patient is under general anesthesia, electrodes deliver a series of mild electrical pulses to the brain.</s>
 <s id="13">This causes huge numbers of neurons to fire in unison: a brief, controlled seizure.</s>
 <s id="14">A muscle relaxant keeps spasms from spreading to the rest of his body.</s>
 <s id="15">The only physical indication of the electricity flooding the brain is a twitching foot.</s>
 <s id="16">The treatment lasts for about a minute, and most patients are able to resume normal activities about an hour after each session.</s>
 <s id="17">ECT is commonly used to treat severe cases of major depression or bipolar disorder in patients who haven’t responded to other therapies, or who have had adverse reactions to medication.</s>
 <s id="18">Half or more of those who undergo treatment experience an improvement in their symptoms.</s>
 <s id="19">Most patients treated with ECT have two or three sessions per week for several weeks.</s>
 <s id="20">Some begin to notice an improvement in their symptoms after just one session, while others take longer to respond.</s>
 <s id="21">Patients often continue less frequent treatments for several months to a year, and some need occasional maintenance sessions for the rest of their lives.</s>
 <s id="22">Modern ECT is much safer than it used to be, but patients can still experience side effects.</s>
 <s id="23">They may feel achy, fatigued, or nauseated right after treatment.</s>
 <s id="24">Some have trouble remembering what happened right before a session— for example, what they had for dinner the previous evening.</s>
 <s id="25">Rarely, they might have trouble remembering up to weeks and months before.</s>
 <s id="26">For most patients, this memory loss does improve over time.</s>
 <s id="27">What's fascinating is that despite its proven track record, we still don't know exactly why ECT works.</s>
 <s id="28">Neurons in the brain communicate via electrical signals, which influence our brain chemistry, contributing to mood and behavior.</s>
 <s id="29">The flood of electrical activity sparked by ECT alters that chemistry.</s>
 <s id="30">For example, ECT triggers the release of certain neurotransmitters, molecules that help carry signals between neurons and influence mental health.</s>
 <s id="31">ECT also stimulates the flow of hormones that may help reduce symptoms of depression.</s>
 <s id="32">Interestingly, ECT maintenance works better when paired with medication, even in patients who were resistant to medication before.</s>
 <s id="33">As we come to a better understanding of the brain, we’ll likely be able to make ECT even more effective.</s>
 <s id="34">In 1995, more than a decade after her first course of ECT, the nurse decided to publish an account of her experience.</s>
 <s id="35">Because of the stigma surrounding the treatment, she worried that doing so might negatively impact her personal and professional life, but she knew ECT could make a difference for patients when all else failed.</s>
 <s id="36">Though misperceptions about ECT persist, accounts like hers have helped make doctors and patients alike aware of the treatment’s life changing potential.</s>
</text>
