<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">My dear new friends ...</s>
 <s id="2">(Laughter) My name is Eddie Jaku, and I'm standing in front of you today, a survivor of the Holocaust and a witness of the most tragic times in the history of mankind.</s>
 <s id="3">I was a proud young German.</s>
 <s id="4">I thought this was the best civilization that could be given to a young man like me.</s>
 <s id="5">How wrong I was.</s>
 <s id="6">On the 9th of November, 1938, I returned from boarding school where I had lived under a false name for five years because I was a Jew.</s>
 <s id="7">I lived away from my family, like an orphan, getting an education and under enormous pressure and fear that somebody could find out that I was not Walter Shleiss who I pretended to be.</s>
 <s id="8">I was in great danger.</s>
 <s id="9">On that fateful night, I had arrived home, but my family had gone in hiding, and I was alone.</s>
 <s id="10">I went to bed with my dog close by.</s>
 <s id="11">At 5 a.m., on the 10th of November, 1938, ten Nazis broke down the door of our house.</s>
 <s id="12">What they did to me, I am ashamed to tell you.</s>
 <s id="13">It was so bad that I believed, "Eddie, you're going to die today."</s>
 <s id="14">After, they made me witness the demolition of our 200-year-old house and murdering my beloved dog, Lulu, who had tried to protect me, in front of my eyes.</s>
 <s id="15">I lost my dignity, my freedom, and my faith in humanity.</s>
 <s id="16">I lost everything I lived for.</s>
 <s id="17">I was reduced from a man to being nothing.</s>
 <s id="18">What happened to my country where I was born in, the country of my ancestors, the country which produced [Schiller], Goethe, Beethoven, and Mozart?</s>
 <s id="19">What had happened to my German friends who became murderers?</s>
 <s id="20">At the time, none of us understood that "Kristallnacht" - the "Night of Broken Glass" where the fronts of Jewish-owned shops were smashed, and the shops looted, and homes and synagogues were set on fire - was only the beginning of the nightmare of much, much worse to come.</s>
 <s id="21">That day, I was transported to my first concentration camp, Buchenwald, where I was kept with another 11,000 Jewish men for about five months.</s>
 <s id="22">On the 2nd of May, 1939, I was released.</s>
 <s id="23">My father picked me up and brought me to Aachen.</s>
 <s id="24">After 10 hours driving, we made an arrangement with a smuggler to take us into Belgium.</s>
 <s id="25">I spent two weeks there with my dad in an apartment until I was arrested by Belgium police as a German, not a Jew.</s>
 <s id="26">and interned in a camp with 4,000 other Germans.</s>
 <s id="27">On the 10th of May, 1940, the camp was liquidated.</s>
 <s id="28">We split up in Dunkirk, and I continued on to Lyon.</s>
 <s id="29">There, I was arrested by French police and sent to Gurs, a terrible camp with 6,000 Germans.</s>
 <s id="30">After my internments at camps, I was finally transported to what became my hell on earth: Auschwitz.</s>
 <s id="31">My parents and sister were also transported to Auschwitz, and I was never to see my parents again.</s>
 <s id="32">I did not have a chance to say goodbye to my beloved mother, and I have missed her every day of my life.</s>
 <s id="33">If you have the opportunity today, please go home and make sure you tell your mom how much you love her.</s>
 <s id="34">Please do this for your new friend, Eddie.</s>
 <s id="35">I was lucky enough, managed to escape what became known as the death march.</s>
 <s id="36">and I hid in a forest, alone, for many months, before I was found by the American army.</s>
 <s id="37">But I'm standing here today a happy man, who enjoys life with a wonderful wife and a beautiful family.</s>
 <s id="38">I do not hate anyone.</s>
 <s id="39">Hate is a disease which may destroy your enemy, but will also destroy you in the process.</s>
 <s id="40">(Applause) I'm doing everything I can to make this world a better place for everyone, and I implore you all to do your best too.</s>
 <s id="41">Let us ensure that this terrible tragedy, the worst in the history, may never happen again and also will never, ever be forgotten.</s>
 <s id="42">After many years of hardship and hiding, on the 7th September, 1945, after a long journey by train, I entered back into Belgium without any papers.</s>
 <s id="43">Very shortly after that, I met and married my wife, Flore, to whom I have been married for 73 years.</s>
 <s id="44">(Cheers) (Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="45">At that time, I was not a happy man.</s>
 <s id="46">(Laughter) (Chuckles) I did not enjoy being amongst people.</s>
 <s id="47">That was until our first son, Michael, was born.</s>
 <s id="48">At that time, my heart was healed and my happiness returned in abundance.</s>
 <s id="49">I made the promise that from that day until the end of my life, I promised to be happy, smile, be polite, helpful, and kind.</s>
 <s id="50">I also promised to never put my foot on German soil again.</s>
 <s id="51">Today, I stand in front of you, a man who has kept all those promises.</s>
 <s id="52">My greatest happiness comes from my family, my wife, two sons - Michael and Andre - my many grandchildren and great-grandchildren, who all bring so much joy.</s>
 <s id="53">Today, I teach and share happiness with everyone I meet.</s>
 <s id="54">Happiness does not fall from the sky; it's in your hands.</s>
 <s id="55">If you're healthy and happy, you're a millionaire.</s>
 <s id="56">(Chuckles) Happiness also brings good health to the body and mind, and I attribute my 99 years of health mostly to the positive and happy attitude.</s>
 <s id="57">(Applause) One flower is my garden; one good friend is my world.</s>
 <s id="58">Young people today forget to stop.</s>
 <s id="59">They're constantly running and don't know where they're running to.</s>
 <s id="60">(Laughter) You should take time to be happy and enjoy life.</s>
 <s id="61">There's a time to laugh and there's a time to cry.</s>
 <s id="62">I see good things in life.</s>
 <s id="63">Invite a friend or family member for a meal.</s>
 <s id="64">Go for a walk.</s>
 <s id="65">Tomorrow will come, but first enjoy today!</s>
 <s id="66">(Applause) I wonder how people exist without friendship, without people to share their secrets, hopes, and dreams, to share good fortune or sad losses.</s>
 <s id="67">In the sweetness of friendship, let there be laughter and sharing of pleasure, good times made better and bad times forgotten - due to the magic of friendship.</s>
 <s id="68">For me, when I wake up, I'm happy because it is another day to enjoy.</s>
 <s id="69">When I remember that I should have died a miserable death, but instead I'm alive, so I aim to help people who are down.</s>
 <s id="70">I was at the bottom of the pit.</s>
 <s id="71">So If I can make one miserable person smile, I'm happy.</s>
 <s id="72">(Applause) Remember these words: Please do not walk in front of me - I may not be able to follow.</s>
 <s id="73">Please do not walk behind me - I may not be able to lead.</s>
 <s id="74">Just walk beside me and be my friend.</s>
 <s id="75">(Applause) I will end my talk with a wish from my heart to all your hearts.</s>
 <s id="76">May you always have lots of love to share, lots of good health to spare, and lots of good friends that care.</s>
 <s id="77">Thank you for giving me the privilege of speaking to you today.</s>
 <s id="78">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="79">(Applause) (Cheers)</s>
</text>
