<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">JR: Art is not supposed to change the world.</s>
 <s id="2">But art can change the way we see the world.</s>
 <s id="3">(Music) So now my wish is ...</s>
 <s id="4">for you to stand up for what you care about by participating in a global art project.</s>
 <s id="5">And together, we'll turn the world inside out.</s>
 <s id="6">[Great big story in partnership with TED] Narrator: They had a big idea to change the world.</s>
 <s id="7">But they couldn't do it alone.</s>
 <p id="p8">
  <s id="8.1">(Voices overlapping) So, my wish ...</s>
  <s id="8.2">My wish ...</s>
  <s id="8.3">I wish ...</s>
 </p>
 <s id="9">And now, here's my wish.</s>
 <s id="10">[Torchbearers] [Ideas in action] (Camera clicking) JR: My name is JR, I like to call myself an artist.</s>
 <s id="11">There are two ways of thinking about my work.</s>
 <s id="12">The easy way is just -- I'm papering black-and-white images on walls.</s>
 <s id="13">But I believe my work is about connecting people.</s>
 <s id="14">For me, it's the power of bringing people together.</s>
 <s id="15">I went there to do art projects with the community.</s>
 <s id="16">Now I realize that the community wanted to do art projects even more than I wanted.</s>
 <s id="17">And I started thinking: Why I don't take myself out of the equation and let them do it?</s>
 <s id="18">So the wish was pretty simple: we just put up a website and you can send us your photo for whatever you believe in or whatever you want to fight for; we'll send you back your photo in large format, wherever you are in the world.</s>
 <s id="19">Every day, I see rolls leaving around the world.</s>
 <s id="20">The project went much further than the places I've been, and that shows the power of art.</s>
 <s id="21">And the Photobooths truck is the magic of it.</s>
 <s id="22">(Music) Luana: We're a team of four traveling in the Photobooths truck: Josh, Basel, Jamie and I.</s>
 <s id="23">Jamie: To pose, they should look like this.</s>
 <s id="24">(Laughter) We are using two of these trucks to cover 30 cities around America.</s>
 <s id="25">Luana: We're just a tool for people that want to send a positive message.</s>
 <s id="26">Jamie: Step inside and take a seat over here.</s>
 <s id="27">Once the truck is ready and running, anyone can come.</s>
 <s id="28">Wait for the flash.</s>
 <s id="29">(Music) (Camera clicking) Touch the screen, take your picture, type in information.</s>
 <s id="30">In a matter of a minute or so, we print on the side, three by four feet.</s>
 <s id="31">No one is used to seeing their face so big.</s>
 <s id="32">Woman: Oh yeah, there's my funny face for you.</s>
 <s id="33">Jamie: The truck has this magic about bringing photography back to the print.</s>
 <s id="34">Then the posters go to the wall.</s>
 <s id="35">We use wallpaper glue, put them up and that's it.</s>
 <s id="36">We printed more than 300,000 faces already.</s>
 <s id="37">And we sent them to more than 130 countries.</s>
 <s id="38">(Music) Luana: It's the people's art project.</s>
 <s id="39">We don't decide the message.</s>
 <s id="40">It can be political, to bring attention to issues.</s>
 <s id="41">Jamie: I love the idea of using photography to promote change.</s>
 <s id="42">This specific project is to raise awareness about the DREAMers situation.</s>
 <s id="43">Karina Ruiz: INSIDE OUT is bringing the opportunity for DREAMers like myself, a person that came here at young age to have a better future, to come out and give a face to the issue.</s>
 <s id="44">Vianey Perez: When people drive by and they see a lot of faces, they're going to get curious and they're going to wonder who they are.</s>
 <s id="45">That's the face to the issue.</s>
 <s id="46">To humanize it.</s>
 <s id="47">(Music) JR: You do think that just pasting an image up there might have no impact, but it does have an impact.</s>
 <s id="48">You cannot know when and how, but it's worth trying.</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">Jamie: It all starts with believing.</s>
  <s id="49.2">Right?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">And so, if you don't believe that you can make change, change will never happen.</s>
 <s id="51">Even if it's a very small change in one person, that's a positive change.</s>
 <s id="52">This is not about JR anymore.</s>
 <s id="53">It's about everyone who believes that art can change the world.</s>
 <s id="54">JR: I think that definitely art can change the perception we have about the world.</s>
 <s id="55">And if we start seeing the world differently, maybe it's a good path to start changing the world.</s>
 <s id="56">[Be a part of INSIDE OUT InsideOutProject.net]</s>
</text>
