<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">My name is Amit.</s>
 <s id="2">And 18 months ago, I had another job at Google, and I pitched this idea of doing something with museums and art to my boss who's actually here, and she allowed me to do it.</s>
 <s id="3">And it took 18 months.</s>
 <s id="4">A lot of fun, negotiations and stories, I can tell you, with 17 very interesting museums from nine countries.</s>
 <s id="5">But I'm going to focus on the demo.</s>
 <s id="6">There are a lot of stories about why we did this.</s>
 <s id="7">I think my personal story is explained very simply on the slide, and it's access.</s>
 <s id="8">And I grew up in India.</s>
 <s id="9">I had a great education -- I'm not complaining -- but I didn't have access to a lot of these museums and these artworks.</s>
 <s id="10">And so when I started traveling and going to these museums, I started learning a lot.</s>
 <s id="11">And while working at Google, I tried to put this desire to make it more accessible with technology together.</s>
 <s id="12">So we formed a team, a great team of people, and we started doing this.</s>
 <s id="13">I'm going to probably get into the demo and then tell you a couple of the interesting things we've had since launch.</s>
 <s id="14">So, simple: you come to GoogleArtProject.com.</s>
 <s id="15">You look around at all these museums here.</s>
 <s id="16">You've got the Uffizi, you've got the MoMA, the Hermitage, the Rijks, the Van Gogh.</s>
 <s id="17">I'm going to actually get to one of my favorites, the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York.</s>
 <s id="18">Two ways of going in -- very simple.</s>
 <s id="19">Click and, bang, you're in this museum.</s>
 <s id="20">It doesn't matter where you are -- Bombay, Mexico, it doesn't really matter.</s>
 <s id="21">You move around, you have fun.</s>
 <s id="22">You want to navigate around the museum?</s>
 <s id="23">Open the plan up, and, in one click, jump.</s>
 <s id="24">You're in there, you want to go to the end of the corridor.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">Keep going.</s>
  <s id="25.2">Have fun.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">Explore.</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">(Applause) Thanks.</s>
  <s id="27.2">I haven't come to the best part.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="28">(Laughter) So now I'm in front of one of my favorite paintings, "The Harvesters" by Pieter Bruegel at the Met.</s>
 <s id="29">I see this plus sign.</s>
 <s id="30">If the museum has given us the image, you click on it.</s>
 <s id="31">Now this is one of the images.</s>
 <s id="32">So this is all of the meta-data information.</s>
 <s id="33">For those of you who are truly interested in art, you can click this -- but I'm going to click this off right now.</s>
 <s id="34">And this is one of these images that we captured in what we call gigapixel technology.</s>
 <s id="35">So this image, for example, has close to, I think, around 10 billion pixels.</s>
 <s id="36">And I get a lot of people asking me: "What do you get for 10 billion pixels?"</s>
 <s id="37">So I'm going to try and show you what you really get for 10 billion pixels.</s>
 <s id="38">You can zoom around very simply.</s>
 <s id="39">You see some fun stuff happening here.</s>
 <s id="40">I love this guy; his expression is priceless.</s>
 <s id="41">But then you really want to go deep.</s>
 <s id="42">And so I started playing around, and I found something going on over here.</s>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">And I was like, "Hold on.</s>
  <s id="43.2">That sounds interesting."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">Went in, and I started noticing that these kids were actually beating something.</s>
 <s id="45">I did a little research, spoke to a couple of my contacts at the Met, and actually found out that this is a game called squall, which involves beating a goose with a stick on Shrove Tuesday.</s>
 <s id="46">And apparently it was quite popular.</s>
 <s id="47">I don't know why they did it, but I learned something about it.</s>
 <s id="48">Now just to get really deep in, you can really get to the cracks.</s>
 <s id="49">Now just to give you some perspective, I'm going to zoom out so you really see what you get.</s>
 <s id="50">Here is where we were, and this is the painting.</s>
 <s id="51">(Applause) The best is yet to come -- so in a second.</s>
 <s id="52">So now let's just quickly jump into the MoMA, again in New York.</s>
 <s id="53">So another one of my favorites, "The Starry Night."</s>
 <s id="54">Now the example I showed you was all about finding details.</s>
 <s id="55">But what if you want to see brush strokes?</s>
 <s id="56">And what if you want to see how Van Gogh actually created this masterpiece?</s>
 <p id="p57">
  <s id="57.1">You zoom in.</s>
  <s id="57.2">You really go in.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="58">I'm going to go to one of my favorite parts in this painting, and I'm really going to get to the cracks.</s>
 <s id="59">This is "The Starry Night," I think, never seen like this before.</s>
 <s id="60">I'm going to show you my other favorite feature.</s>
 <s id="61">There's a lot of other stuff here, but I don't have time.</s>
 <p id="p62">
  <s id="62.1">This is the real cool part.</s>
  <s id="62.2">It's called Collections.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="63">Any one of you, anybody -- doesn't matter if you're rich, if you're poor, if you have a fancy house -- doesn't matter.</s>
 <s id="64">You can go and create your own museum online -- create your own collection across all these images.</s>
 <s id="65">Very simply, you go in -- and I've created this, called The Power of Zoom -- you can just zoom around.</s>
 <s id="66">This is "The Ambassadors," based in the National Gallery.</s>
 <s id="67">You can annotate the stuff, send it to your friends and really get a conversation going about what you're feeling when you go through these masterpieces.</s>
 <s id="68">So I think, in conclusion, for me, the main thing is that all the amazing stuff here does not really come from Google.</s>
 <s id="69">It doesn't, in my opinion, even come from the museums.</s>
 <s id="70">I probably shouldn't say that.</s>
 <s id="71">It really comes from these artists.</s>
 <s id="72">And that's been my humbling experience in this.</s>
 <s id="73">I mean, I hope in this digital medium that we do justice to their artwork and represent it properly online.</s>
 <s id="74">And the biggest question I get asked nowadays is, "Did you do this to replicate the experience of going to a museum?"</s>
 <s id="75">And the answer is no.</s>
 <s id="76">It's to supplement the experience.</s>
 <p id="p77">
  <s id="77.1">And that's it.</s>
  <s id="77.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="78">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="79">(Applause)</s>
</text>
