<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <p id="p1">
  <s id="1.1">Hi.</s>
  <s id="1.2">I'm here to talk to you about the importance of praise, admiration and thank you, and having it be specific and genuine.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="2">And the way I got interested in this was, I noticed in myself, when I was growing up, and until about a few years ago, that I would want to say thank you to someone, I would want to praise them, I would want to take in their praise of me and I'd just stop it.</s>
 <s id="3">And I asked myself, why?</s>
 <s id="4">I felt shy, I felt embarrassed.</s>
 <s id="5">And then my question became, am I the only one who does this?</s>
 <s id="6">So, I decided to investigate.</s>
 <s id="7">I'm fortunate enough to work in the rehab facility, so I get to see people who are facing life and death with addiction.</s>
 <s id="8">And sometimes it comes down to something as simple as, their core wound is their father died without ever saying he's proud of them.</s>
 <s id="9">But then, they hear from all the family and friends that the father told everybody else that he was proud of him, but he never told the son.</s>
 <s id="10">It's because he didn't know that his son needed to hear it.</s>
 <s id="11">So my question is, why don't we ask for the things that we need?</s>
 <s id="12">I know a gentleman, married for 25 years, who's longing to hear his wife say, "Thank you for being the breadwinner, so I can stay home with the kids," but won't ask.</s>
 <s id="13">I know a woman who's good at this.</s>
 <s id="14">She, once a week, meets with her husband and says, "I'd really like you to thank me for all these things I did in the house and with the kids."</s>
 <s id="15">And he goes, "Oh, this is great, this is great."</s>
 <s id="16">And praise really does have to be genuine, but she takes responsibility for that.</s>
 <s id="17">And a friend of mine, April, who I've had since kindergarten, she thanks her children for doing their chores.</s>
 <s id="18">And she said, "Why wouldn't I thank it, even though they're supposed to do it?"</s>
 <s id="19">So, the question is, why was I blocking it?</s>
 <s id="20">Why were other people blocking it?</s>
 <s id="21">Why can I say, "I'll take my steak medium rare, I need size six shoes," but I won't say, "Would you praise me this way?"</s>
 <s id="22">And it's because I'm giving you critical data about me.</s>
 <s id="23">I'm telling you where I'm insecure.</s>
 <s id="24">I'm telling you where I need your help.</s>
 <s id="25">And I'm treating you, my inner circle, like you're the enemy.</s>
 <s id="26">Because what can you do with that data?</s>
 <s id="27">You could neglect me.</s>
 <s id="28">You could abuse it.</s>
 <s id="29">Or you could actually meet my need.</s>
 <s id="30">And I took my bike into the bike store-- I love this -- same bike, and they'd do something called "truing" the wheels.</s>
 <s id="31">The guy said, "You know, when you true the wheels, it's going to make the bike so much better."</s>
 <s id="32">I get the same bike back, and they've taken all the little warps out of those same wheels I've had for two and a half years, and my bike is like new.</s>
 <s id="33">So, I'm going to challenge all of you.</s>
 <s id="34">I want you to true your wheels: be honest about the praise that you need to hear.</s>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">What do you need to hear?</s>
  <s id="35.2">Go home to your wife -- go ask her, what does she need?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="36">Go home to your husband -- what does he need?</s>
 <s id="37">Go home and ask those questions, and then help the people around you.</s>
 <s id="38">And it's simple.</s>
 <s id="39">And why should we care about this?</s>
 <s id="40">We talk about world peace.</s>
 <s id="41">How can we have world peace with different cultures, different languages?</s>
 <s id="42">I think it starts household by household, under the same roof.</s>
 <s id="43">So, let's make it right in our own backyard.</s>
 <s id="44">And I want to thank all of you in the audience for being great husbands, great mothers, friends, daughters, sons.</s>
 <s id="45">And maybe somebody's never said that to you, but you've done a really, really good job.</s>
 <s id="46">And thank you for being here, just showing up and changing the world with your ideas.</s>
 <s id="47">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="48">(Applause)</s>
</text>
