<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <p id="p1">
  <s id="1.1">Chris Anderson: William, hi.</s>
  <s id="1.2">Good to see you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="2">William Kamkwamba: Thanks.</s>
 <p id="p3">
  <s id="3.1">CA: So, we've got a picture, I think?</s>
  <s id="3.2">Where is this?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">WK: This is my home.</s>
  <s id="4.2">This is where I live.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p5">
  <s id="5.1">CA: Where?</s>
  <s id="5.2">What country?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">WK: In Malawi, Kasungu.</s>
  <s id="6.2">In Kasungu.</s>
  <s id="6.3">Yeah, Mala.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p7">
  <s id="7.1">CA: OK.</s>
  <s id="7.2">Now, you're 19 now?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p8">
  <s id="8.1">WK: Yeah.</s>
  <s id="8.2">I'm 19 years now.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">CA: Five years ago you had an idea.</s>
  <s id="9.2">What was that?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="10">WK: I wanted to make a windmill.</s>
 <s id="11">CA: A windmill?</s>
 <s id="12">WK: Yeah.</s>
 <s id="13">CA: What, to power -- for lighting and stuff?</s>
 <s id="14">WK: Yeah.</s>
 <p id="p15">
  <s id="15.1">CA: So what did you do?</s>
  <s id="15.2">How did you realize that?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="16">WK: After I dropped out of school, I went to library, and I read a book that would -- "Using Energy," and I get information about doing the mill.</s>
 <s id="17">And I tried, and I made it.</s>
 <s id="18">(Applause) CA: So you copied -- you exactly copied the design in the book.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">WK: Ah, no.</s>
  <s id="19.2">I just -- CA: What happened?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">WK: In fact, a design of the windmill that was in the book, it has got four -- ah -- three blades, and mine has got four blades.</s>
 <s id="21">CA: The book had three, yours had four.</s>
 <s id="22">WK: Yeah.</s>
 <s id="23">CA: And you made it out of what?</s>
 <s id="24">WK: I made four blades, just because I want to increase power.</s>
 <s id="25">CA: OK.</s>
 <s id="26">WK: Yeah.</s>
 <s id="27">CA: You tested three, and found that four worked better?</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">WK: Yeah.</s>
  <s id="28.2">I test.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">CA: And what did you make the windmill out of?</s>
 <s id="30">What materials did you use?</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">WK: I use a bicycle frame, and a pulley, and plastic pipe, what then pulls -- CA: Do we have a picture of that?</s>
  <s id="31.2">Can we have the next slide?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">WK: Yeah.</s>
  <s id="32.2">The windmill.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="33">CA: And so, and that windmill, what -- it worked?</s>
 <s id="34">WK: When the wind blows, it rotates and generates.</s>
 <s id="35">CA: How much electricity?</s>
 <s id="36">WK: 12 watts.</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">CA: And so, that lit a light for the house?</s>
  <s id="37.2">How many lights?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="38">WK: Four bulbs and two radios.</s>
 <s id="39">CA: Wow.</s>
 <s id="40">WK: Yeah.</s>
 <s id="41">(Applause) CA: Next slide -- so who's that?</s>
 <s id="42">WK: This is my parents, holding the radio.</s>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">CA: So what did they make of -- that you were 14, 15 at the time -- what did they make of this?</s>
  <s id="43.2">They were impressed?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">WK: Yeah.</s>
 <s id="45">CA: And so what's your -- what are you going to do with this?</s>
 <s id="46">WK: Um -- CA: What do you -- I mean -- do you want to build another one?</s>
 <s id="47">WK: Yeah, I want to build another one -- to pump water and irrigation for crops.</s>
 <s id="48">CA: So this one would have to be bigger?</s>
 <s id="49">WK: Yeah.</s>
 <s id="50">CA: How big?</s>
 <s id="51">WK: I think it will produce more than 20 the watts.</s>
 <s id="52">CA: So that would produce irrigation for the entire village?</s>
 <s id="53">WK: Yeah.</s>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">CA: Wow.</s>
  <s id="54.2">And so you're talking to people here at TED to get people who might be able to help in some way to realize this dream?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">WK: Yeah, if they can help me with materials, yeah.</s>
 <s id="56">CA: And as you think of your life going forward, you're 19 now, do you picture continuing with this dream of working in energy?</s>
 <p id="p57">
  <s id="57.1">WK: Yeah.</s>
  <s id="57.2">I'm still thinking to work on energy.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p58">
  <s id="58.1">CA: Wow.</s>
  <s id="58.2">William, it's a real honor to have you at the TED conference.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="59">Thank you so much for coming.</s>
 <s id="60">WK: Thank you.</s>
 <s id="61">(Applause)</s>
</text>
