<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm going to read a few strips.</s>
 <s id="2">These are, most of these are from a monthly page I do in and architecture and design magazine called Metropolis.</s>
 <s id="3">And the first story is called "The Faulty Switch."</s>
 <s id="4">Another beautifully designed new building ruined by the sound of a common wall light switch.</s>
 <s id="5">It's fine during the day when the main rooms are flooded with sunlight.</s>
 <s id="6">But at dusk everything changes.</s>
 <s id="7">The architect spent hundreds of hours designing the burnished brass switchplates for his new office tower.</s>
 <s id="8">And then left it to a contractor to install these 79-cent switches behind them.</s>
 <s id="9">We know instinctively where to reach when we enter a dark room.</s>
 <s id="10">We automatically throw the little nub of plastic upward.</s>
 <s id="11">But the sound we are greeted with, as the room is bathed in the simulated glow of late-afternoon light, recalls to mind a dirty men's room in the rear of a Greek coffee shop.</s>
 <s id="12">(Laughter) This sound colors our first impression of any room; it can't be helped.</s>
 <s id="13">But where does this sound, commonly described as a click, come from?</s>
 <s id="14">Is it simply the byproduct of a crude mechanical action?</s>
 <s id="15">Or is it an imitation of one half the set of sounds we make to express disappointment?</s>
 <s id="16">The often dental consonant of no Indo-European language.</s>
 <s id="17">Or is it the amplified sound of a synapse firing in the brain of a cockroach?</s>
 <s id="18">In the 1950s they tried their best to muffle this sound with mercury switches and silent knob controls.</s>
 <s id="19">But today these improvements seem somehow inauthentic.</s>
 <s id="20">The click is the modern triumphal clarion proceeding us through life, announcing our entry into every lightless room.</s>
 <s id="21">The sound made flicking a wall switch off is of a completely different nature.</s>
 <s id="22">It has a deep melancholy ring.</s>
 <s id="23">Children don't like it.</s>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">It's why they leave lights on around the house.</s>
  <s id="24.2">(Laughter) Adults find it comforting.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="25">But wouldn't it be an easy matter to wire a wall switch so that it triggers the muted horn of a steam ship?</s>
 <s id="26">Or the recorded crowing of a rooster?</s>
 <s id="27">Or the distant peel of thunder?</s>
 <s id="28">Thomas Edison went through thousands of unlikely substances before he came upon the right one for the filament of his electric light bulb.</s>
 <s id="29">Why have we settled so quickly for the sound of its switch?</s>
 <s id="30">That's the end of that.</s>
 <s id="31">(Applause) The next story is called "In Praise of the Taxpayer."</s>
 <s id="32">That so many of the city's most venerable taxpayers have survived yet another commercial building boom, is cause for celebration.</s>
 <s id="33">These one or two story structures, designed to yield only enough income to cover the taxes on the land on which they stand, were not meant to be permanent buildings.</s>
 <s id="34">Yet for one reason or another they have confounded the efforts of developers to be combined into lots suitable for high-rise construction.</s>
 <s id="35">Although they make no claim to architectural beauty, they are, in their perfect temporariness, a delightful alternative to the large-scale structures that might someday take their place.</s>
 <s id="36">The most perfect examples occupy corner lots.</s>
 <s id="37">They offer a pleasant respite from the high-density development around them.</s>
 <s id="38">A break of light and air, an architectural biding of time.</s>
 <s id="39">So buried in signage are these structures, that it often takes a moment to distinguish the modern specially constructed taxpayer from its neighbor: the small commercial building from an earlier century, whose upper floors have been sealed, and whose groundfloor space now functions as a taxpayer.</s>
 <s id="40">The few surfaces not covered by signs are often clad in a distinctive, dark green-gray, striated aluminum siding.</s>
 <s id="41">Take-out sandwich shops, film processing drop-offs, peep-shows and necktie stores.</s>
 <s id="42">Now these provisional structures have, in some cases, remained standing for the better part of a human lifetime.</s>
 <s id="43">The temporary building is a triumph of modern industrial organization, a healthy sublimation of the urge to build, and proof that not every architectural idea need be set in stone.</s>
 <s id="44">That's the end.</s>
 <s id="45">(Laughter) And the next story is called, "On the Human Lap."</s>
 <s id="46">For the ancient Egyptians the lap was a platform upon which to place the earthly possessions of the dead -- 30 cubits from foot to knee.</s>
 <s id="47">It was not until the 14th century that an Italian painter recognized the lap as a Grecian temple, upholstered in flesh and cloth.</s>
 <s id="48">Over the next 200 years we see the infant Christ go from a sitting to a standing position on the Virgin's lap, and then back again.</s>
 <s id="49">Every child recapitulates this ascension, straddling one or both legs, sitting sideways, or leaning against the body.</s>
 <s id="50">From there, to the modern ventriloquist's dummy, is but a brief moment in history.</s>
 <s id="51">You were late for school again this morning.</s>
 <s id="52">The ventriloquist must first make us believe that a small boy is sitting on his lap.</s>
 <s id="53">The illusion of speech follows incidentally.</s>
 <s id="54">What have you got to say for yourself, Jimmy?</s>
 <s id="55">As adults we admire the lap from a nostalgic distance.</s>
 <s id="56">We have fading memories of that provisional temple, erected each time an adult sat down.</s>
 <s id="57">On a crowded bus there was always a lap to sit on.</s>
 <s id="58">It is children and teenage girls who are most keenly aware of its architectural beauty.</s>
 <s id="59">They understand the structural integrity of a deep avuncular lap, as compared to the shaky arrangement of a neurotic niece in high heels.</s>
 <s id="60">The relationship between the lap and its owner is direct and intimate.</s>
 <s id="61">I envision a 36-story, 450-unit residential high-rise -- a reason to consider the mental health of any architect before granting an important commission.</s>
 <s id="62">The bathrooms and kitchens will, of course, have no windows.</s>
 <s id="63">The lap of luxury is an architectural construct of childhood, which we seek, in vain, as adults, to employ.</s>
 <s id="64">That's the end.</s>
 <s id="65">(Laughter) The next story is called "The Haverpiece Collection" A nondescript warehouse, visible for a moment from the northbound lanes of the Prykushko Expressway, serves as the temporary resting place for the Haverpiece collection of European dried fruit.</s>
 <s id="66">The profound convolutions on the surface of a dried cherry.</s>
 <s id="67">The foreboding sheen of an extra-large date.</s>
 <s id="68">Do you remember wandering as a child through those dark wooden storefront galleries?</s>
 <s id="69">Where everything was displayed in poorly labeled roach-proof bins.</s>
 <s id="70">Pears dried in the form of genital organs.</s>
 <s id="71">Apricot halves like the ears of cherubim.</s>
 <s id="72">In 1962 the unsold stock was purchased by Maurice Haverpiece, a wealthy prune juice bottler, and consolidated to form the core collection.</s>
 <s id="73">As an art form it lies somewhere between still-life painting and plumbing.</s>
 <s id="74">Upon his death in 1967, a quarter of the items were sold off for compote to a high-class hotel restaurant.</s>
 <s id="75">(Laughter) Unsuspecting guests were served stewed turn-of-the-century Turkish figs for breakfast.</s>
 <s id="76">(Laughter) The rest of the collection remains here, stored in plain brown paper bags until funds can be raised to build a permanent museum and study center.</s>
 <s id="77">A shoe made of apricot leather for the daughter of a czar.</s>
 <p id="p78">
  <s id="78.1">That's the end.</s>
  <s id="78.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="79">(Applause)</s>
</text>
