<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">This is the Air Jordan 3 Black Cement.</s>
 <s id="2">This might be the most important sneaker in history.</s>
 <s id="3">First released in 1988, this is the shoe that started Nike marketing as we know it.</s>
 <s id="4">This is the shoe that propelled the entire Air Jordan lineage, and perhaps saved Nike.</s>
 <s id="5">The Air Jordan 3 Black Cement did for sneakers what the iPhone did for phones.</s>
 <s id="6">It's been re-released four times.</s>
 <s id="7">Every celebrity's been seen wearing it.</s>
 <s id="8">There's a site about what to wear with the Black Cement.</s>
 <s id="9">It's been right under your nose for decades and you never looked down.</s>
 <s id="10">And right about now, most of you are probably thinking, "Sneakers?"</s>
 <s id="11">(Laughter) Yes.</s>
 <s id="12">Yes, sneakers.</s>
 <s id="13">Some extraordinary things about sneakers and data and Nike and how they're all related, possibly, to the future of all online commerce.</s>
 <s id="14">In 2011, the last time the Jordan 3 Black Cement was released, at a retail of 160 dollars, it sold out globally in minutes.</s>
 <s id="15">And that's because people were camped outside of sneaker stores for days before it went on sale.</s>
 <s id="16">And just minutes after that, thousands of those pairs were on eBay for two and three times retail.</s>
 <s id="17">In fact, there's over 1,000 pairs on eBay right now, four years later.</s>
 <s id="18">But here's the thing: this happens every single Saturday.</s>
 <s id="19">Every week there's another release or two or three, and every shoe has a story as rich and compelling as the Jordan 3 Black Cement.</s>
 <s id="20">This is Nike building the marketplace for sneakerheads -- people who collect sneakers -- and my daughter.</s>
 <s id="21">(Laughter) That's an "I love Dad" T-shirt.</s>
 <s id="22">For the brands, sneakerheads are a very important demographic.</s>
 <s id="23">These are the tastemakers; these are the Apple fanboys.</s>
 <s id="24">Because who else is going to buy a pair of $8,000 Back to the Future sneakers?</s>
 <s id="25">(Laughter) Yeah, 8,000 dollars.</s>
 <s id="26">And while that's obviously the anomaly, the resell sneaker market is definitely not.</s>
 <s id="27">Thirty years in the making, what started as an underground culture of a few people who like sneakers just a bit too much -- (Laughter) Now we have sneaker addictions.</s>
 <s id="28">In a market where in the past 12 months, there have been over nine million pairs of shoes resold in the United States alone, at a value of 1.2 billion dollars.</s>
 <s id="29">And that's a conservative estimate -- I should know, I am a sneakerhead.</s>
 <s id="30">This is my collection.</s>
 <s id="31">In the pantheon of great collections, mine doesn't even register.</s>
 <s id="32">I have about 250 pairs, but trust me, I am small-time.</s>
 <s id="33">People have thousands.</s>
 <s id="34">I'm a very typical 37-year-old sneakerhead.</s>
 <s id="35">I grew up playing basketball when Michael Jordan played, I always wanted Air Jordans, my mother would never buy me Air Jordans, as soon as I got some money I bought Air Jordans -- literally, we all have the exact same story.</s>
 <s id="36">But here's where mine diverged.</s>
 <s id="37">After starting three companies, I took a job as a strategy consultant, when I very quickly realized that I didn't know the first thing about data.</s>
 <s id="38">But I learned, because I had to, and I liked it.</s>
 <s id="39">So I thought, I wonder if I could get ahold of some sneaker data, just to play with for my own amusement.</s>
 <s id="40">The goal was to develop a price guide, a real data-driven view of the market.</s>
 <s id="41">And four years later, we're analyzing over 25 million transactions, providing real-time analytics on thousands of sneakers.</s>
 <s id="42">Now sneakerheads check prices while camping out for releases.</s>
 <s id="43">Others have used the data to validate insurance claims.</s>
 <s id="44">And the top investment banks in the world now use resell data to analyze the retail footwear industry.</s>
 <s id="45">And here's the best part: sneakerheads have sneaker portfolios.</s>
 <s id="46">(Laughter) Sneakerheads can track the value of their collection over time, compare it to others, and have access to the same analytics you might for your online brokerage account.</s>
 <s id="47">So sneakerhead Dan builds his collection and identifies which 352 are his.</s>
 <s id="48">He can see it's worth 103,000 dollars -- frankly, a modest collection.</s>
 <s id="49">At the asset level, he can see gain-loss by shoe.</s>
 <s id="50">Here he's made over 600 dollars on one pair.</s>
 <s id="51">I have one of those.</s>
 <s id="52">(Laughter) So an unregulated 1.2 billion dollar industry that thrives as much on the street as it does online, and has spawned fundamental financial services for sneakers?</s>
 <s id="53">At some point I asked myself what's really going on in the market, and two comparisons started to emerge.</s>
 <s id="54">Are sneakers more like stocks or drugs?</s>
 <s id="55">(Laughter) In fact, one guy emailed to say he thought his 15-year-old son was selling drugs and later found out he was selling sneakers.</s>
 <s id="56">(Laughter) And now they use the data to do it together.</s>
 <s id="57">And that's because sneakers are an investment opportunity where none other exists.</s>
 <s id="58">And I don't just mean the kid selling sneakers instead of drugs.</s>
 <s id="59">How about all kids?</s>
 <s id="60">You have to be 18 to play the stock market.</s>
 <s id="61">I sold chewing gum in sixth grade, Blow Pops in ninth grade and collected baseball cards through high school.</s>
 <s id="62">The cards are long dead, and the candy market's usually quite local.</s>
 <s id="63">For a lot of people, sneakers are a legal and accessible investment opportunity -- a democratized stock market, but also unregulated.</s>
 <s id="64">Which is why the story you're probably most familiar with is people killing each other for sneakers.</s>
 <s id="65">And while that definitely happens and is tragic, it's not nearly the epidemic some media would have you believe.</s>
 <s id="66">In fact, it's a very small piece of a much bigger and better story.</s>
 <s id="67">So sneakers have clear similarities to both the stock exchange and the illegal drug trade, but perhaps the most fundamental is the existence of a central actor.</s>
 <s id="68">Someone is making the rules.</s>
 <s id="69">In the case of sneakers, that someone is Nike.</s>
 <s id="70">Let me walk you through some numbers.</s>
 <s id="71">The resell market, we know, is $1.2 billion.</s>
 <s id="72">Nike, including Jordan brand, accounts for 96 percent of all shoes sold on the secondary market.</s>
 <s id="73">Just complete domination.</s>
 <s id="74">Sneakerheads love Jordans.</s>
 <s id="75">And profit on the secondary market is about a third.</s>
 <s id="76">That means that sneakerheads made 380 million dollars selling Nikes last year.</s>
 <s id="77">Let's jump to retail for a second.</s>
 <s id="78">Skechers, earlier this year, became the number two footwear brand in the country, surpassing Adidas -- this was a big deal.</s>
 <s id="79">And in the 12 months ending in June, Skechers's net income was 209 million dollars.</s>
 <s id="80">That means that Nike's customers make almost twice as much profit as their closest competitor.</s>
 <s id="81">That -- (Laughter) How is that even possible?</s>
 <s id="82">The sneaker market is just supply and demand, but Nike's gotten very good at using supply -- limited sneakers -- and the distribution of those sneakers to their own benefit.</s>
 <s id="83">So it's really just supply.</s>
 <s id="84">Sneakerheads joke that as long as it's limited and Nike, they'll buy it.</s>
 <s id="85">Shoes that sell for 8,000 dollars do so because they're very rare.</s>
 <s id="86">It's no different than any other collectible market, only this isn't a market at all.</s>
 <s id="87">It's a false construct created by Nike -- ingeniously created by Nike, in the most positive sense -- to sell more shoes.</s>
 <s id="88">And in the process, it provided tens of thousands of people with life-long passions, myself included.</s>
 <s id="89">If Nike wanted to kill the resell market, they could do so tomorrow, all they have to do is release more shoes.</s>
 <s id="90">But we certainly don't want them to, nor is it in their best interest.</s>
 <s id="91">That's because unlike Apple, who will sell an iPhone to anyone who wants one, Nike doesn't make their money by just selling $200 sneakers.</s>
 <s id="92">They sell millions of shoes to millions of people for 60 dollars.</s>
 <s id="93">And sneakerheads are the ones who drive the marketing and the hype and the PR and the brand cachet, and enable Nike to sell millions of $60 sneakers.</s>
 <s id="94">It's marketing.</s>
 <s id="95">It's marketing the likes of which has never been seen before -- this isn't in any textbook.</s>
 <s id="96">For 15 years Nike has propped up an artificial commodities market, with a Facebook-level hyped IPO every single weekend.</s>
 <s id="97">Drive by any Footlocker at 8am on a Saturday morning, and there will be a line down the street and around the block, and sometimes those kids have been waiting there all week.</s>
 <s id="98">You know those crazy iPhone lines you see on the news every other year?</s>
 <s id="99">Nike lines happen 104 times more often.</s>
 <s id="100">So Nike sets the rules.</s>
 <s id="101">And they do so by controlling supply and distribution.</s>
 <s id="102">But once a pair leaves the retail channel, it's the Wild West.</s>
 <s id="103">There are very few -- if any -- legal, unregulated markets of this size.</s>
 <s id="104">So Nike is definitely not the stock exchange.</s>
 <s id="105">In fact, there is no central exchange.</s>
 <s id="106">By last count, there were 48 different online markets that I know of.</s>
 <s id="107">Some are eBay clones, some are mobile markets, and then you have consignment shops and brick-and-mortar stores, and sneaker conventions, and reseller sites, and Facebook and Instagram and Twitter -- literally, anywhere sneakerheads come into contact with each other, shoes will be bought and sold.</s>
 <s id="108">But that means no efficiencies, no transparency, sometimes not even authenticity.</s>
 <s id="109">Can you imagine if that's how stocks were bought?</s>
 <s id="110">What if the way to buy a share of Apple stock was to search over 100 places online and off, including every time you walk down the street just hoping to pass someone wearing some Apple stock?</s>
 <s id="111">Never knowing who had the best price, or even if the stock you were looking at was real.</s>
 <p id="p112">
  <s id="112.1">That would surely make you say: [WTF?]</s>
  <s id="112.2">Of course that's not how we buy stock.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="113">But what if that's not how we need to buy sneakers either?</s>
 <s id="114">What if the inverse is true, and what if we could buy sneakers exactly the same way as we buy stock?</s>
 <s id="115">And what if it wasn't just sneakers, but any similar product, like watches and handbags and women's shoes, and any collectible, any seasonal item and any markdown item?</s>
 <s id="116">What if there was a stock market for commerce?</s>
 <s id="117">A stock market of things.</s>
 <s id="118">And not only could you buy in a much more educated and efficient manner, but you could engage in all the sophisticated financial transactions you can with the stock market.</s>
 <s id="119">Shorts and options and futures and well, maybe you see where this is going.</s>
 <s id="120">Maybe you want to invest in a stock market of things.</s>
 <s id="121">Because if you had invested in a pair of Air Jordan 3 Black Cement in 2011, you could either be wearing them onstage, (Laughter) or have earned 162 percent on your money -- double the S&amp;amp;P and 20 percent more than Apple.</s>
 <s id="122">(Laughter) And that's why we're talking about sneakers.</s>
 <s id="123">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="124">(Applause)</s>
</text>
