<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Banjo plays) (Banjo and guitar play) (Sings) Is this what it's like to be alive?</s>
 <s id="2">I reached the point of no return and I don't know if I've been burned from the burned bridges in my life, thinkin' you were wrong and I was right.</s>
 <s id="3">Maybe I messed up, either way it's too late for us.</s>
 <s id="4">'Cause baby I'm old with regret, wishin' I could hold you and just forget.</s>
 <s id="5">Since I can't I'll just be home but homesick, wishin' you were mine and I didn't hurt you like I did.</s>
 <s id="6">Can't go back to when we had a chance, wishin' I could have a shot at real romance.</s>
 <s id="7">Now I realize all the things I could have had were in your cold hands.</s>
 <s id="8">I'm a fool for a dead romance.</s>
 <s id="9">Gone, gone, gone.</s>
 <s id="10">I'm a fool for a dead romance.</s>
 <s id="11">Gone, gone, gone.</s>
 <s id="12">I'm a fool for a dead romance.</s>
 <s id="13">Is this what it's like to fantasize about a love that never was alive outside my mind or distance?</s>
 <s id="14">With time I clearly lost my sight, thinkin' I was wrong to ever leave your side.</s>
 <s id="15">But time's the harshest judge, makes us think we were in love.</s>
 <s id="16">And now I'm old with regret, wishin' I could hold you and just forget.</s>
 <s id="17">Since I can't I'll just be home but homesick, wishin' you were mine and I didn't hurt you like I did.</s>
 <s id="18">Can't go back to when we had a chance, wishin' I could have a shot at real romance.</s>
 <s id="19">Now I realize all the things I could have had were in your cold hands.</s>
 <s id="20">I'm a fool for a dead romance.</s>
 <s id="21">Gone, gone, gone.</s>
 <s id="22">I'm a fool for a dead romance.</s>
 <s id="23">(Banjo and guitar play) And baby I'm old with regret, wishin' I could hold you and just forget.</s>
 <s id="24">Since I can't I'll just be home but homesick, wishin' you were mine and I didn't hurt you like I did.</s>
 <s id="25">Can't go back to when we had a chance, wishin' I could have a shot at real romance.</s>
 <s id="26">Now I realize all the things I could have had were in your cold hands.</s>
 <s id="27">I'm a fool for a dead romance.</s>
 <s id="28">Gone, gone, gone.</s>
 <s id="29">I'm a fool for a dead romance.</s>
 <s id="30">Gone, gone, gone.</s>
 <s id="31">I'm a fool for a dead romance.</s>
 <s id="32">Is this what it's like?</s>
</text>
