<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Kashmir Hill: So for my birthday last year, my husband got me an Amazon Echo.</s>
 <s id="2">I was kind of shocked, actually, because we both work in privacy and security.</s>
 <s id="3">(Laughter) And this was a device that would sit in the middle of our home with a microphone on, constantly listening.</s>
 <s id="4">We're not alone, though.</s>
 <s id="5">According to a survey by NPR and Edison Research, one in six American adults now has a smart speaker, which means that they have a virtual assistant at home.</s>
 <s id="6">Like, that's wild.</s>
 <s id="7">The future, or the future dystopia, is getting here fast.</s>
 <s id="8">Beyond that, companies are offering us all kinds of internet-connected devices.</s>
 <s id="9">There are smart lights, smart locks, smart toilets, smart toys, smart sex toys.</s>
 <s id="10">Being smart means the device can connect to the internet, it can gather data, and it can talk to its owner.</s>
 <s id="11">But once your appliances can talk to you, who else are they going to be talking to?</s>
 <s id="12">I wanted to find out, so I went all-in and turned my one-bedroom apartment in San Francisco into a smart home.</s>
 <s id="13">I even connected our bed to the internet.</s>
 <s id="14">As far as I know, it was just measuring our sleeping habits.</s>
 <s id="15">I can now tell you that the only thing worse than getting a terrible night's sleep is to have your smart bed tell you the next day that you "missed your goal and got a low sleep score."</s>
 <s id="16">(Laughter) It's like, "Thanks, smart bed.</s>
 <s id="17">As if I didn't already feel like shit today."</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) All together, I installed 18 internet-connected devices in my home.</s>
 <s id="19">I also installed a Surya.</s>
 <s id="20">Surya Mattu: Hi, I'm Surya.</s>
 <s id="21">(Laughter) I monitored everything the smart home did.</s>
 <s id="22">I built a special router that let me look at all the network activity.</s>
 <s id="23">You can think of my router sort of like a security guard, compulsively logging all the network packets as they entered and left the smart home.</s>
 <s id="24">KH: Surya and I are both journalists, he's not my husband, we just work together at Gizmodo.</s>
 <s id="25">SM: Thank you for clarifying.</s>
 <s id="26">The devices Kashmir bought -- we were interested in understanding what they were saying to their manufacturers.</s>
 <s id="27">But we were also interested in understanding what the home's digital emissions look like to the internet service provider.</s>
 <s id="28">We were seeing what the ISP could see, but more importantly, what they could sell.</s>
 <s id="29">KH: We ran the experiment for two months.</s>
 <s id="30">In that two months, there wasn't a single hour of digital silence in the house -- not even when we went away for a week.</s>
 <s id="31">SM: Yeah, it's so true.</s>
 <s id="32">Based on the data, I knew when you guys woke up and went to bed.</s>
 <s id="33">I even knew when Kashmir brushed her teeth.</s>
 <s id="34">I'm not going to out your brushing habits, but let's just say it was very clear to me when you were working from home.</s>
 <s id="35">KH: Uh, I think you just outed them to, like, a lot of people here.</s>
 <s id="36">SM: Don't be embarrassed, it's just metadata.</s>
 <s id="37">I knew when you turned on your TV and how long you watched it for.</s>
 <s id="38">Fun fact about the Hill household: they don't watch a lot of television, but when they do, it's usually in binge mode.</s>
 <s id="39">Favorite shows include "Difficult People" and "Party Down."</s>
 <s id="40">KH: OK, you're right, I loved "Party Down."</s>
 <s id="41">It's a great show, and you should definitely watch it.</s>
 <s id="42">But "Difficult People" was all my husband, Trevor.</s>
 <s id="43">And Trevor was actually a little upset that you knew about his binges, because even though he'd been the one to connect the TV to the router, he forgot that the TV was watching us.</s>
 <s id="44">It's actually not the first time that our TV has spied on us.</s>
 <s id="45">The company that made it, VIZIO, paid a 2.2 million-dollar settlement to the government just last year, because it had been collecting second-by-second information about what millions of people were watching on TV, including us, and then it was selling that information to data brokers and advertisers.</s>
 <s id="46">SM: Ah, classic surveillance economy move.</s>
 <s id="47">The devices Kashmir bought almost all pinged their servers daily.</s>
 <s id="48">But do you know which device was especially chatty?</s>
 <s id="49">The Amazon Echo.</s>
 <s id="50">It contacted its servers every three minutes, regardless of whether you were using it or not.</s>
 <s id="51">KH: In general, it was disconcerting that all these devices were having ongoing conversations that were invisible to me.</s>
 <s id="52">I mean, I would have had no idea, without your router.</s>
 <s id="53">If you buy a smart device, you should probably know -- you're going to own the device, but in general, the company is going to own your data.</s>
 <s id="54">And you know, I mean, maybe that's to be expected -- you buy an internet-connected device, it's going to use the internet.</s>
 <s id="55">But it's strange to have these devices moving into the intimate space that is the home and allowing companies to track our really basic behavior there.</s>
 <s id="56">SM: So true.</s>
 <s id="57">Even the most banal-seeming data can be mined by the surveillance economy.</s>
 <s id="58">For example, who cares how often you brush your teeth?</s>
 <s id="59">Well, as it turns out, there's a dental insurance company called Beam.</s>
 <s id="60">They've been monitoring their customers' smart toothbrushes since 2015 -- for discounts on their premiums, of course.</s>
 <s id="61">KH: We know what some of you are thinking: this is the contract of the modern world.</s>
 <s id="62">You give up a little privacy, and you get some convenience or some price breaks in return.</s>
 <s id="63">But that wasn't my experience in my smart home.</s>
 <s id="64">It wasn't convenient, it was infuriating.</s>
 <s id="65">I'll admit, I love my smart vacuum, but many other things in the house drove me insane: we ran out of electrical outlets, and I had to download over a dozen apps to my phone to control everything.</s>
 <s id="66">And then every device had its own log-in, my toothbrush had a password ...</s>
 <s id="67">(Laughter) And smart coffee, especially, was just a world of hell.</s>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">SM: Wait, really?</s>
  <s id="68.2">Cloud-powered coffee wasn't really working for you?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="69">KH: I mean, maybe I'm naive, but I thought it was going to be great.</s>
 <s id="70">I thought we'd just wake up in the morning and we'd say, "Alexa, make us coffee."</s>
 <s id="71">But that's not how it went down.</s>
 <s id="72">We had to use this really particular, brand-specific phrase to make it work.</s>
 <s id="73">It was, "Alexa, ask the Behmor to run quick start."</s>
 <s id="74">And this was just, like, really hard to remember first thing in the morning, before you have had your caffeine.</s>
 <s id="75">(Laughter) And apparently, it was hard to say, because the Echo Dot that was right next to our bed just couldn't understand us.</s>
 <s id="76">So we would basically start every day by screaming this phrase at the Echo Dot.</s>
 <s id="77">(Laughter) And Trevor hated this.</s>
 <s id="78">He'd be like, "Please, Kashmir, just let me go to the kitchen and push the button to make the coffee run."</s>
 <s id="79">And I'd be like, "No, you can't!</s>
 <s id="80">We have to do it the smart way!"</s>
 <s id="81">(Laughter) I'm happy to report that our marriage survived the experiment, but just barely.</s>
 <s id="82">SM: If you decide to make your home smart, hopefully, you’ll find it less infuriating than Kashmir did.</s>
 <s id="83">But regardless, the smart things you buy can and probably are used to target and profile you.</s>
 <s id="84">Just the number of devices you have can be used to predict how rich or poor you are.</s>
 <s id="85">Facebook's made this tech, and they've also patented it.</s>
 <s id="86">KH: All the anxiety you currently feel every time you go online, about being tracked, is about to move into your living room.</s>
 <s id="87">Or into your bedroom.</s>
 <s id="88">There's this sex toy called the We-Vibe.</s>
 <s id="89">You might wonder why a sex toy connects to the internet, but it's for two people who are in a long-distance relationship, so they can share their love from afar.</s>
 <s id="90">Some hackers took a close look at this toy and saw it was sending a lot of information back to the company that made it -- when it was used, how long it was used for, what the vibration settings were, how hot the toy got.</s>
 <s id="91">It was all going into a database.</s>
 <s id="92">So I reached out to the company, and I said, "Why are you collecting this really sensitive data?"</s>
 <s id="93">And they said, "Well, it's great for market research."</s>
 <s id="94">But they were data-mining their customers' orgasms.</s>
 <s id="95">And they weren't telling them about it.</s>
 <s id="96">I mean, even if you're cavalier about privacy, I hope that you would admit that's a step too far.</s>
 <s id="97">SM: This is why I want to keep my sex toys dumb.</s>
 <s id="98">KH: That's great.</s>
 <s id="99">We're all very glad to know that.</s>
 <s id="100">(Laughter) SM: A data point I'm willing to share.</s>
 <s id="101">(Laughter) The devices Kashmir bought range from useful to annoying.</s>
 <s id="102">But the thing they all had in common was sharing data with the companies that made them.</s>
 <s id="103">With email service providers and social media, we've long been told that if it's free, you're the product.</s>
 <s id="104">But with the internet of things, it seems, even if you pay, you're still the product.</s>
 <s id="105">So you really have to ask: Who's the true beneficiary of your smart home, you or the company mining you?</s>
 <s id="106">KH: Look, we're a tech savvy crowd here.</s>
 <s id="107">I think most of us know that these things connect to the internet and send data out.</s>
 <s id="108">And fine, maybe you're OK with living in that commercial panopticon, but others aren't.</s>
 <s id="109">We need the companies to rethink the design of these devices with our privacy in mind, because we're not all willing to participate in "market research," just because a device we bought has a Wi-Fi connection.</s>
 <s id="110">And I have to tell you, even when you're aware, generally, this is happening, it's really easy to forget that normal household items are spying on you.</s>
 <s id="111">It's easy to forget these things are watching you, because they don't look like cameras.</s>
 <s id="112">They could look like ...</s>
 <s id="113">well, they could look like a dildo.</s>
 <s id="114">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="115">(Applause)</s>
</text>
