<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Greg Gage: Who wouldn't love acing a geography exam, remembering all the locations of the countries on a map or avoiding embarrassing situations of suddenly forgetting the person's name standing right in front of you.</s>
 <s id="2">It turns out that memory, like other muscles in the body, can be strengthened and enhanced.</s>
 <s id="3">But instead of practicing with flash cards, there may be an interesting way that we can hack our memory while we sleep.</s>
 <s id="4">(Music) Why do we sleep?</s>
 <s id="5">This has been a question asked since the early days of civilization.</s>
 <s id="6">And while we may not know the exact answer, there are a number of really good theories about why we need it.</s>
 <s id="7">Sleep is when the brain transfers short-term memories experienced throughout the day into long-term memories.</s>
 <s id="8">This process is called memory consolidation, and it's the memory consolidation theory that has scientists wondering if we can enhance certain memories over others.</s>
 <s id="9">There was a paper recently in the journal "Science" by Ken Paller and his colleagues at Northwestern that seemed to show that this may be true, and that piqued our curiosity.</s>
 <s id="10">Joud has been working on a DIY version of this task to see if we can improve memories through the use of sound in sleep.</s>
 <s id="11">So Joud, how do you test if we can improve our memories with sleep?</s>
 <s id="12">Joud Mar’i: We need a human subject.</s>
 <s id="13">[Step 1: Play a game] We have a memory game that we have on an iPad, and then we make our subject play this game and remember the images and where they appear on the screen.</s>
 <s id="14">GG: So this is like a memory game you used to play as a child, which picture was where.</s>
 <s id="15">And we tie each picture with a sound that represents it.</s>
 <s id="16">JM: So, if you can see a picture of a car, for example, and you would hear the car engine.</s>
 <s id="17">(Car engine starting) GG: Just before you go to sleep we're going to test you.</s>
 <s id="18">We're going to see how well you remember where the pictures are.</s>
 <s id="19">Every time you see the picture, you're going to hear the sound.</s>
 <s id="20">And now comes the experiment.</s>
 <s id="21">You're going to go take a nap.</s>
 <s id="22">[Step 2: Take a nap] And while you're sleeping, we're going to be recording your EEG.</s>
 <s id="23">JM: And then we wait for them to go into what's called the slow-wave sleep, which is the deepest phase of your sleep where it's really hard for you to wake up.</s>
 <s id="24">GG: OK, pause.</s>
 <s id="25">So, here's some information on sleep.</s>
 <s id="26">There are four stages: we have lighter stages of sleep and REM, but what we're interested in is called slow-wave sleep.</s>
 <s id="27">And it gets its name from the electrical signals called Delta waves that we record from the brain.</s>
 <s id="28">This is the part of sleep where scientists believe that memory consolidation can happen.</s>
 <s id="29">In this deep period of sleep, we're going to do something that you don't know we're going to do.</s>
 <s id="30">JM: Here's where the tricky part comes, and we start playing our cues.</s>
 <s id="31">(Car engine starting) GG: Do you play all the cues?</s>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">JM: No.</s>
  <s id="32.2">We only want to play half of them to see if there's a difference.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="33">GG: So your hypothesis is the one that they were listening to while they're sleeping they're going to do better at.</s>
 <s id="34">JM: Yes, exactly.</s>
 <s id="35">GG: When you wake back up and play the game again, do you do better or worse than before a nap?</s>
 <s id="36">What we found is that if we played you a cue during your sleep, for example, a car -- You would remember the position of that car when you woke back up again.</s>
 <s id="37">But if we didn't play you the cue during the sleep, for example, a guitar, you'd be less likely to remember that guitar when you woke up.</s>
 <s id="38">The memories that were cued they remembered better than the ones they weren't, even though they don't remember hearing those sounds?</s>
 <s id="39">JM: Yes, we ask them.</s>
 <s id="40">GG: We know they're sleeping, they can't hear it, they wake up, they do better on those than the ones you didn't play.</s>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">GG: That's amazing.</s>
  <s id="41.2">JM: It's like magic.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">GG: Joud ran this experiment on 12 people and the results were significant.</s>
 <s id="43">It's not that you remember things better; it's that you forget them less.</s>
 <s id="44">I was a huge skeptic when I first heard that you could do better at a memory test just by playing sounds during sleep.</s>
 <s id="45">But we replicated these experiments.</s>
 <s id="46">The facts and memories we collect throughout the day are very fragile, and they are easily lost and forgotten.</s>
 <s id="47">But by reactivating them during sleep, even without us being aware, it seems like we could make them more stable and less prone to forgetting.</s>
 <s id="48">That's pretty incredible.</s>
 <s id="49">Our brains are still active even when we're not.</s>
 <s id="50">So if you're like me and a bit forgetful, perhaps a solution is a pair of headphones and a soft couch.</s>
</text>
