<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So the type of magic I like, and I'm a magician, is magic that uses technology to create illusions.</s>
 <s id="2">So I would like to show you something I've been working on.</s>
 <s id="3">It's an application that I think will be useful for artists -- multimedia artists in particular.</s>
 <s id="4">It synchronizes videos across multiple screens of mobile devices.</s>
 <s id="5">I borrowed these three iPods from people here in the audience to show you what I mean.</s>
 <s id="6">And I'm going to use them to tell you a little bit about my favorite subject: deception.</s>
 <s id="7">(Music) One of my favorite magicians is Karl Germain.</s>
 <s id="8">He had this wonderful trick where a rosebush would bloom right in front of your eyes.</s>
 <s id="9">But it was his production of a butterfly that was the most beautiful.</s>
 <s id="10">(Recording) Announcer: Ladies and gentlemen, the creation of life.</s>
 <s id="11">(Applause) (Music) Marco Tempest: When asked about deception, he said this: Announcer: Magic is the only honest profession.</s>
 <s id="12">A magician promises to deceive you -- and he does.</s>
 <s id="13">MT: I like to think of myself as an honest magician.</s>
 <s id="14">I use a lot of tricks, which means that sometimes I have to lie to you.</s>
 <s id="15">Now I feel bad about that.</s>
 <s id="16">But people lie every day.</s>
 <s id="17">(Ringing) Hold on.</s>
 <s id="18">Phone: Hey, where are you?</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">MT: Stuck in traffic.</s>
  <s id="19.2">I'll be there soon.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">You've all done it.</s>
 <s id="21">(Laughter) (Music) Right: I'll be ready in just a minute, darling.</s>
 <s id="22">Center: It's just what I've always wanted.</s>
 <s id="23">Left: You were great.</s>
 <s id="24">MT: Deception, it's a fundamental part of life.</s>
 <s id="25">Now polls show that men tell twice as many lies as women -- assuming the women they asked told the truth.</s>
 <s id="26">(Laughing) We deceive to gain advantage and to hide our weaknesses.</s>
 <s id="27">The Chinese general Sun Tzu said that all war was based on deception.</s>
 <s id="28">Oscar Wilde said the same thing of romance.</s>
 <s id="29">Some people deceive for money.</s>
 <s id="30">Let's play a game.</s>
 <s id="31">Three cards, three chances.</s>
 <s id="32">Announcer: One five will get you 10, 10 will get you 20.</s>
 <s id="33">Now, where's the lady?</s>
 <s id="34">Where is the queen?</s>
 <s id="35">MT: This one?</s>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">Sorry.</s>
  <s id="36.2">You lose.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="37">Well, I didn't deceive you.</s>
 <s id="38">You deceived yourself.</s>
 <s id="39">Self-deception.</s>
 <s id="40">That's when we convince ourselves that a lie is the truth.</s>
 <s id="41">Sometimes it's hard to tell the two apart.</s>
 <s id="42">Compulsive gamblers are experts at self-deception.</s>
 <s id="43">(Slot machine) They believe they can win.</s>
 <s id="44">They forget the times they lose.</s>
 <s id="45">The brain is very good at forgetting.</s>
 <s id="46">Bad experiences are quickly forgotten.</s>
 <s id="47">Bad experiences quickly disappear.</s>
 <s id="48">Which is why in this vast and lonely cosmos, we are so wonderfully optimistic.</s>
 <s id="49">Our self-deception becomes a positive illusion -- why movies are able to take us onto extraordinary adventures; why we believe Romeo when he says he loves Juliet; and why single notes of music, when played together, become a sonata and conjure up meaning.</s>
 <s id="50">That's "Clair De lune."</s>
 <s id="51">Its composer, called Debussy, said that art was the greatest deception of all.</s>
 <s id="52">Art is a deception that creates real emotions -- a lie that creates a truth.</s>
 <s id="53">And when you give yourself over to that deception, it becomes magic.</s>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">[MAGIC] (Music fades slowly) (Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="54.2">Thank you very much.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">(Applause)</s>
</text>
