<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Someone has tripped the magical alarms in the Element Temple.</s>
 <s id="2">By the time you and the other monks arrive on the scene, you know you have a disaster on your hands.</s>
 <s id="3">Overnight, four young apprentices broke into the temple’s inner chamber to steal the sacred element crystals.</s>
 <s id="4">But when the alarm went off they panicked, and each of them swallowed the crystal they held right before they were caught.</s>
 <s id="5">With no idea how to control the crystals’ vast powers, they’ll soon transform into uncontrollable elemental spirits.</s>
 <s id="6">Improbably enough, the old monk next to you has seen something similar happen before.</s>
 <s id="7">He explains: “You must determine who ate which crystal and get each into the proper containment field before they transform.</s>
 <s id="8">The elements compel their masters: those who ate the Earth and Water Crystals must speak the truth, while those who consumed Fire and Air must lie."</s>
 <s id="9">The youths are too scared to confess their own transgressions.</s>
 <s id="10">Instead, they fall to accusing each other.</s>
 <p id="p11">
  <s id="11.1">“Rikku took the Water crystal!”</s>
  <s id="11.2">Sumi blurts out.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="12">Rikku interrupts angrily.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">“It was Bella, she stole the Fire crystal!”</s>
  <s id="13.2">So Bella yells: “Jonah ate the Air crystal, I saw him!”</s>
  <s id="13.3">Jonah looks up timidly and shakes his head.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">“I… I don’t know what happened, but Sumi doesn’t have the Earth crystal.”</s>
  <s id="14.2">So who ate which crystal?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="15">Pause now to figure it out for yourself.</s>
 <s id="16">There’s no getting around it— this will take some trial and error.</s>
 <s id="17">But that’s not a bad thing.</s>
 <s id="18">If we make a wrong guess, we’ll eventually reach a point where our conclusions contradict each other.</s>
 <s id="19">That would allow us to confirm that our initial guess was wrong and work from there.</s>
 <s id="20">This is a technique known as proof by contradiction.</s>
 <s id="21">The trick is in being strategic about where we begin our guessing.</s>
 <s id="22">Some assumptions might not lead to contradictions without making further assumptions.</s>
 <s id="23">We want to pick one that creates the most constraints on its own, and thus gives us the most information when it turns out to be right or wrong.</s>
 <s id="24">Take, for example, Sumi’s statement.</s>
 <s id="25">If we assume she’s telling the truth, we’d know the identity of both truth tellers.</s>
 <s id="26">Rikku would have the Water crystal, and since she’s not lying about him, Sumi would have Earth.</s>
 <s id="27">So Bella would have the Fire crystal, as Rikku says.</s>
 <s id="28">But then Bella would have to be lying about Jonah having the Air crystal.</s>
 <s id="29">And yet that’s the only remaining option.</s>
 <s id="30">This is a contradiction, and it tells us our initial assumption was wrong.</s>
 <s id="31">So now we can go back to the start, but with the added knowledge that Sumi is lying.</s>
 <s id="32">As a liar, Sumi must either have the Fire or Air crystal.</s>
 <s id="33">That means Jonah was telling the truth about her, so he can’t have taken either of those.</s>
 <s id="34">And that means Bella was lying about him, so she must also have either Fire or Air.</s>
 <s id="35">Since Sumi was lying, Rikku can’t have taken the Water crystal— the only one left who could have it is Jonah.</s>
 <s id="36">And because we’ve already identified the two liars, Rikku must have the Earth crystal.</s>
 <s id="37">That means Bella has the Fire crystal and Sumi has Air.</s>
 <s id="38">You manage to get them all in the proper containment fields just as the crystals’ magic begins to manifest.</s>
 <s id="39">Compared with the difficult task of training these kids to control their new powers, figuring out who had which crystal was elementary.</s>
</text>
