<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">We all know that saving is important and is something that we should be doing.</s>
 <s id="2">And yet, overall, we're doing less and less of it.</s>
 <s id="3">[The Way We Work] We know what we need to do.</s>
 <s id="4">The question is: How do we do it?</s>
 <s id="5">And that's what I'm here to teach you.</s>
 <s id="6">Your savings behavior isn't a question of how smart you are or how much willpower you have.</s>
 <s id="7">The amount we save depends on the environmental cues around us.</s>
 <s id="8">Let me give you an example.</s>
 <s id="9">We ran a study in which, in one group, we showed people their income on a monthly basis.</s>
 <s id="10">In another group, we showed people their income on a weekly basis.</s>
 <s id="11">And what we found was that people who saw their income on a weekly basis were able to budget better throughout the month.</s>
 <s id="12">Now, it's important to know that we didn't change how much money people were receiving, we just changed the environment in which they understood their income.</s>
 <s id="13">And environmental cues like this have an impact.</s>
 <s id="14">So I'm not going to share tricks with you that you already know.</s>
 <s id="15">I'm not going to tell you how to open up a savings account or how to start saving for your retirement.</s>
 <s id="16">What I am going to share with you is how to bridge this gap from your intentions to save and your actions.</s>
 <s id="17">Are you ready?</s>
 <s id="18">Here's number one: harness the power of pre-commitment.</s>
 <s id="19">Fundamentally, we think about ourselves in two different ways: our present self and our future self.</s>
 <s id="20">In the future, we're perfect.</s>
 <s id="21">In the future, we're going to save for retirement, we're going to lose weight, we're going to call our parents more.</s>
 <s id="22">But we oftentimes forget that our future self is exactly the same person as our present self.</s>
 <s id="23">We know that one of the best times to save is when you get your tax return.</s>
 <s id="24">So we tried an A/B test.</s>
 <s id="25">In the first group, we texted people in early February, hopefully before they even filed for their taxes.</s>
 <s id="26">And we asked them, "If you get a tax refund, what percentage would you like to save?"</s>
 <s id="27">Now this is a really hard question.</s>
 <s id="28">They didn't know if they would receive a tax refund or how much.</s>
 <s id="29">But we asked the question anyway.</s>
 <s id="30">In the second group, we asked people right after they received their refund, "What percentage would you like to save?"</s>
 <s id="31">Now, here's what happened.</s>
 <s id="32">In that second condition, when people just received their tax refund, they wanted to save about 17 percent of their tax refund.</s>
 <s id="33">But in the condition when we asked people before they even filed their taxes, savings rates increased from 17 percent to 27 percent when we asked in February.</s>
 <s id="34">Why?</s>
 <s id="35">Because you're committing for your future self, and of course your future self can save 27 percent.</s>
 <s id="36">These large changes in savings behavior came from the fact that we changed the decision-making environment.</s>
 <s id="37">We want you to be able to harness that same power.</s>
 <s id="38">So take a moment and think about the ways in which you can sign up your future self for something that you know today will be a little bit hard.</s>
 <s id="39">Sign up for an app that lets you make savings decisions in advance.</s>
 <s id="40">The trick is, you have to have that binding contract.</s>
 <s id="41">Number two: use transition moments to your advantage.</s>
 <s id="42">We did an experiment with a website that helps older adults share their housing.</s>
 <s id="43">We ran two ads on social media, targeted to the same population of 64-year-olds.</s>
 <s id="44">In one group, we said, "Hey, you're getting older.</s>
 <s id="45">Are you ready for retirement?</s>
 <s id="46">House sharing can help."</s>
 <s id="47">In the second group, we got a little bit more specific and said, "You're 64 turning 65.</s>
 <s id="48">Are you ready for retirement?</s>
 <s id="49">House sharing can help."</s>
 <s id="50">What we're doing in that second group is highlighting that a transition is happening.</s>
 <s id="51">All of a sudden, we saw click-through rates, and ultimately sign-up rates, increase when we highlight that.</s>
 <s id="52">In psychology, we call this the "fresh start effect."</s>
 <s id="53">Whether it's the start of a new year or even a new season, your motivation to act increases.</s>
 <s id="54">So right now, put a meeting request on your calendar for the day before your next birthday.</s>
 <s id="55">Identify the one financial thing you most want to do.</s>
 <s id="56">And commit yourself to it.</s>
 <s id="57">The third and final trick: get a handle on small, frequent purchases.</s>
 <s id="58">We've run a few different studies and found that the number one purchase people say they regret, after bank fees, is eating out.</s>
 <s id="59">It's a frequent purchase we make almost every day, and it's death by a thousand cuts.</s>
 <s id="60">A coffee here, a burrito there ...</s>
 <s id="61">It adds up and decreases our ability to save.</s>
 <s id="62">Back when I lived in New York City, I looked at my expenses and saw that I spent over 2,000 dollars on ride-sharing apps.</s>
 <s id="63">It was more than my New York City rent.</s>
 <s id="64">I vowed to make a change.</s>
 <s id="65">And the next month, I spent 2,000 dollars again -- no change, because the information alone didn't change my behavior.</s>
 <s id="66">I didn't change my environment.</s>
 <s id="67">So now that I was 4,000 dollars in the hole, I did two things.</s>
 <s id="68">The first is that I unlinked my credit card from my car-sharing apps.</s>
 <s id="69">Instead, I linked a debit card that only had 300 dollars a month.</s>
 <s id="70">If I needed more, I had to go through the whole process of adding a new card, and we know that every click, every barrier, changes our behavior.</s>
 <s id="71">We aren't machines.</s>
 <s id="72">We don't carry around an abacus every day, adding up what we're spending, in comparison to what we wanted.</s>
 <s id="73">But what our brains are very good at is counting up the number of times we've done something.</s>
 <s id="74">So I gave myself a limit.</s>
 <s id="75">I can only use ride-sharing apps three times a week.</s>
 <s id="76">It forced me to ration my travels.</s>
 <s id="77">I got a handle on my car-sharing expenses to the benefit of my husband, because of the environmental changes that I did.</s>
 <s id="78">So get a handle on whatever that purchase is for you, and change your environment to make it harder to do so.</s>
 <s id="79">Those are my tips for you.</s>
 <s id="80">But I want you to remember one thing.</s>
 <s id="81">As human beings, we can be irrational when it comes to saving and spending and budgeting.</s>
 <s id="82">But luckily, we know this about ourselves, and we can predict how we'll act under certain environments.</s>
 <s id="83">Let's do that with saving.</s>
 <s id="84">Let's change our environment to help our future selves.</s>
</text>
