<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">It may seem like the semicolon is struggling with an identity crisis.</s>
 <s id="2">It looks like a comma crossed with a period.</s>
 <s id="3">Maybe that's why we toss these punctuation marks around like grammatical confetti.</s>
 <s id="4">We're confused about how to use them properly.</s>
 <s id="5">In fact, it's the semicolon's half-half status that makes it useful.</s>
 <s id="6">It's stronger than a comma, and less final than a period.</s>
 <s id="7">It fills the spaces in between, and for that reason, it has some specific and important tasks.</s>
 <s id="8">For one, it can clarify ideas in a sentence that's already festooned with commas.</s>
 <s id="9">"Semicolons: At first, they may seem frightening, then, they become enlightening, finally, you'll find yourself falling for these delightful punctuation marks."</s>
 <s id="10">Even though the commas separate different parts of the sentence, it's easy to lose track of what belongs where.</s>
 <s id="11">But then the semicolon edges in to the rescue.</s>
 <s id="12">In list-like sentences, it can exert more force than commas do, cutting sentences into compartments and grouping items that belong together.</s>
 <s id="13">The semicolon breaks things up, but it also builds connections.</s>
 <s id="14">Another of its tasks is to link together independent clauses.</s>
 <s id="15">These are sentences that can stand on their own, but when connected by semicolons, look and sound better because they're related in some way.</s>
 <s id="16">"Semicolons were once a great mystery to me.</s>
 <s id="17">I had no idea where to put them."</s>
 <s id="18">Technically, there's nothing wrong with that.</s>
 <s id="19">These two sentences can stand alone.</s>
 <s id="20">But imagine they appeared in a long list of other sentences, all of the same length, each separated by periods.</s>
 <s id="21">Things would get monotonous very fast.</s>
 <s id="22">In that situation, semicolons bring fluidity and variation to writing by connecting related clauses.</s>
 <s id="23">But as beneficial as they are, semicolons don't belong just anywhere.</s>
 <s id="24">There are two main rules that govern their use.</s>
 <s id="25">Firstly, unless they're being used in lists, semicolons should only connect clauses that are related in some way.</s>
 <s id="26">You wouldn't use one here, for instance: "Semicolons were once a great mystery to me; I'd really like a sandwich."</s>
 <s id="27">Periods work best here because these are two totally different ideas.</s>
 <s id="28">A semicolon's job is to reunite two independent clauses that will benefit from one another's company because they refer to the same thing.</s>
 <s id="29">Secondly, you'll almost never find a semicolon willingly stationed before coordinating conjunctions: the words, "and," "but," "for," "nor," "or," "so," and "yet."</s>
 <s id="30">That's a comma's place, in fact.</s>
 <s id="31">But a semicolon can replace a conjunction to shorten a sentence or to give it some variety.</s>
 <s id="32">Ultimately, this underappreciated punctuation mark can give writing clarity, force, and style, all encompassed in one tiny dot and squiggle that's just waiting to be put in the right place.</s>
</text>
