<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Think back to a really vivid memory.</s>
 <s id="2">Got it?</s>
 <s id="3">Okay, now try to remember what you had for lunch three weeks ago.</s>
 <s id="4">That second memory probably isn't as strong, but why not?</s>
 <s id="5">Why do we remember some things, and not others?</s>
 <s id="6">And why do memories eventually fade?</s>
 <s id="7">Let's look at how memories form in the first place.</s>
 <s id="8">When you experience something, like dialing a phone number, the experience is converted into a pulse of electrical energy that zips along a network of neurons.</s>
 <s id="9">Information first lands in short term memory, where it's available from anywhere from a few seconds to a couple of minutes.</s>
 <s id="10">It's then transferred to long-term memory through areas such as the hippocampus, and finally to several storage regions across the brain.</s>
 <s id="11">Neurons throughout the brain communicate at dedicated sites called synapses using specialized neurotransmitters.</s>
 <s id="12">If two neurons communicate repeatedly, a remarkable thing happens: the efficiency of communication between them increases.</s>
 <s id="13">This process, called long term potentiation, is considered to be a mechanism by which memories are stored long-term, but how do some memories get lost?</s>
 <s id="14">Age is one factor.</s>
 <s id="15">As we get older, synapses begin to falter and weaken, affecting how easily we can retrieve memories.</s>
 <s id="16">Scientists have several theories about what's behind this deterioration, from actual brain shrinkage, the hippocampus loses 5% of its neurons every decade for a total loss of 20% by the time you're 80 years old to the drop in the production of neurotransmitters, like acetylcholine, which is vital to learning and memory.</s>
 <s id="17">These changes seem to affect how people retrieve stored information.</s>
 <s id="18">Age also affects our memory-making abilities.</s>
 <s id="19">Memories are encoded most strongly when we're paying attention, when we're deeply engaged, and when information is meaningful to us.</s>
 <s id="20">Mental and physical health problems, which tend to increase as we age, interfere with our ability to pay attention, and thus act as memory thieves.</s>
 <s id="21">Another leading cause of memory problems is chronic stress.</s>
 <s id="22">When we're constantly overloaded with work and personal responsibilites, our bodies are on hyperalert.</s>
 <s id="23">This response has evolved from the physiological mechanism designed to make sure we can survive in a crisis.</s>
 <s id="24">Stress chemicals help mobilize energy and increase alertness.</s>
 <s id="25">However, with chronic stress our bodies become flooded with these chemicals, resulting in a loss of brain cells and an inability to form new ones, which affects our ability to retain new information.</s>
 <s id="26">Depression is another culprit.</s>
 <s id="27">People who are depressed are 40% more likely to develop memory problems.</s>
 <s id="28">Low levels of serotonin, a neurotransmitter connected to arousal, may make depressed individuals less attentive to new information.</s>
 <s id="29">Dwelling on sad events in the past, another symptom of depression, makes it difficult to pay attention to the present, affecting the ability to store short-term memories.</s>
 <s id="30">Isolation, which is tied to depression, is another memory thief.</s>
 <s id="31">A study by the Harvard School of Public Health found that older people with high levels of social integration had a slower rate of memory decline over a six-year period.</s>
 <s id="32">The exact reason remains unclear, but experts suspect that social interaction gives our brain a mental workout.</s>
 <s id="33">Just like muscle strength, we have to use our brain or risk losing it.</s>
 <s id="34">But don't despair.</s>
 <s id="35">There are several steps you can take to aid your brain in preserving your memories.</s>
 <s id="36">Make sure you keep physically active.</s>
 <s id="37">Increased blood flow to the brain is helpful.</s>
 <s id="38">And eat well.</s>
 <s id="39">Your brain needs all the right nutrients to keep functioning correctly.</s>
 <s id="40">And finally, give your brain a workout.</s>
 <s id="41">Exposing your brain to challenges, like learning a new language, is one of the best defenses for keeping your memories intact.</s>
</text>
