<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Hi, my name is Frank, and I collect secrets.</s>
 <s id="2">It all started with a crazy idea in November of 2004.</s>
 <s id="3">I printed up 3,000 self-addressed postcards, just like this.</s>
 <s id="4">They were blank on one side, and on the other side I listed some simple instructions.</s>
 <s id="5">I asked people to anonymously share an artful secret they'd never told anyone before.</s>
 <s id="6">And I handed out these postcards randomly on the streets of Washington, D.C., not knowing what to expect.</s>
 <s id="7">But soon the idea began spreading virally.</s>
 <s id="8">People began to buy their own postcards and make their own postcards.</s>
 <s id="9">I started receiving secrets in my home mailbox, not just with postmarks from Washington, D.C., but from Texas, California, Vancouver, New Zealand, Iraq.</s>
 <s id="10">Soon my crazy idea didn't seem so crazy.</s>
 <s id="11">PostSecret.com is the most visited advertisement-free blog in the world.</s>
 <s id="12">And this is my postcard collection today.</s>
 <s id="13">You can see my wife struggling to stack a brick of postcards on a pyramid of over a half-million secrets.</s>
 <s id="14">What I'd like to do now is share with you a very special handful of secrets from that collection, starting with this one.</s>
 <s id="15">"I found these stamps as a child, and I have been waiting all my life to have someone to send them to.</s>
 <s id="16">I never did have someone."</s>
 <s id="17">Secrets can take many forms.</s>
 <s id="18">They can be shocking or silly or soulful.</s>
 <s id="19">They can connect us to our deepest humanity or with people we'll never meet.</s>
 <s id="20">(Laughter) Maybe one of you sent this one in.</s>
 <s id="21">I don't know.</s>
 <s id="22">This one does a great job of demonstrating the creativity that people have when they make and mail me a postcard.</s>
 <s id="23">This one obviously was made out of half a Starbucks cup with a stamp and my home address written on the other side.</s>
 <s id="24">"Dear Birthmother, I have great parents.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">I've found love.</s>
  <s id="25.2">I'm happy."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">Secrets can remind us of the countless human dramas, of frailty and heroism, playing out silently in the lives of people all around us even now.</s>
 <s id="27">"Everyone who knew me before 9/11 believes I'm dead."</s>
 <s id="28">"I used to work with a bunch of uptight religious people, so sometimes I didn't wear panties, and just had a big smile and chuckled to myself."</s>
 <s id="29">(Laughter) This next one takes a little explanation before I share it with you.</s>
 <s id="30">I love to speak on college campuses and share secrets and the stories with students.</s>
 <s id="31">And sometimes afterwards I'll stick around and sign books and take photos with students.</s>
 <s id="32">And this next postcard was made out of one of those photos.</s>
 <s id="33">And I should also mention that, just like today, at that PostSecret event, I was using a wireless microphone.</s>
 <s id="34">"Your mic wasn't off during sound check.</s>
 <s id="35">We all heard you pee."</s>
 <s id="36">(Laughter) This was really embarrassing when it happened, until I realized it could have been worse.</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">Right.</s>
  <s id="37.2">You know what I'm saying.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="38">(Laughter) "Inside this envelope is the ripped up remains of a suicide note I didn't use.</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">I feel like the happiest person on Earth (now.)"</s>
  <s id="39.2">"One of these men is the father of my son.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">He pays me a lot to keep it a secret."</s>
 <s id="41">(Laughter) "That Saturday when you wondered where I was, well, I was getting your ring.</s>
 <s id="42">It's in my pocket right now."</s>
 <s id="43">I had this postcard posted on the PostSecret blog two years ago on Valentine's Day.</s>
 <s id="44">It was the very bottom, the last secret in the long column.</s>
 <s id="45">And it hadn't been up for more than a couple hours before I received this exuberant email from the guy who mailed me this postcard.</s>
 <s id="46">And he said, "Frank, I've got to share with you this story that just played out in my life."</s>
 <s id="47">He said, "My knees are still shaking."</s>
 <s id="48">He said, "For three years, my girlfriend and I, we've made it this Sunday morning ritual to visit the PostSecret blog together and read the secrets out loud.</s>
 <s id="49">I read some to her, she reads some to me."</s>
 <s id="50">He says, "It's really brought us closer together through the years.</s>
 <s id="51">And so when I discovered that you had posted my surprise proposal to my girlfriend at the very bottom, I was beside myself.</s>
 <s id="52">And I tried to act calm, not to give anything away.</s>
 <s id="53">And just like every Sunday, we started reading the secrets out loud to each other."</s>
 <s id="54">He said, "But this time it seemed like it was taking her forever to get through each one."</s>
 <s id="55">But she finally did.</s>
 <s id="56">She got to that bottom secret, his proposal to her.</s>
 <s id="57">And he said, "She read it once and then she read it again."</s>
 <s id="58">And she turned to him and said, "Is that our cat?"</s>
 <s id="59">(Laughter) And when she saw him, he was down on one knee, he had the ring out.</s>
 <p id="p60">
  <s id="60.1">He popped the question, she said yes.</s>
  <s id="60.2">It was a very happy ending.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="61">So I emailed him back and I said, "Please share with me an image, something, that I can share with the whole PostSecret community and let everyone know your fairy tale ending."</s>
 <s id="62">And he emailed me this picture.</s>
 <s id="63">(Laughter) "I found your camera at Lollapalooza this summer.</s>
 <s id="64">I finally got the pictures developed and I'd love to give them to you."</s>
 <s id="65">This picture never got returned back to the people who lost it, but this secret has impacted many lives, starting with a student up in Canada named Matty.</s>
 <s id="66">Matty was inspired by that secret to start his own website, a website called IFoundYourCamera.</s>
 <s id="67">Matty invites people to mail him digital cameras that they've found, memory sticks that have been lost with orphan photos.</s>
 <s id="68">And Matty takes the pictures off these cameras and posts them on his website every week.</s>
 <s id="69">And people come to visit to see if they can identify a picture they've lost or help somebody else get the photos back to them that they might be desperately searching for.</s>
 <s id="70">This one's my favorite.</s>
 <s id="71">(Laughter) Matty has found this ingenious way to leverage the kindness of strangers.</s>
 <s id="72">And it might seem like a simple idea, and it is, but the impact it can have on people's lives can be huge.</s>
 <s id="73">Matty shared with me an emotional email he received from the mother in that picture.</s>
 <s id="74">"That's me, my husband and son.</s>
 <s id="75">The other pictures are of my very ill grandmother.</s>
 <s id="76">Thank you for making your site.</s>
 <s id="77">These pictures mean more to me than you know.</s>
 <s id="78">My son's birth is on this camera.</s>
 <s id="79">He turns four tomorrow."</s>
 <s id="80">Every picture that you see there and thousands of others have been returned back to the person who lost it -- sometimes crossing oceans, sometimes going through language barriers.</s>
 <s id="81">This is the last postcard I have to share with you today.</s>
 <s id="82">"When people I love leave voicemails on my phone I always save them in case they die tomorrow and I have no other way of hearing their voice ever again."</s>
 <s id="83">When I posted this secret, dozens of people sent voicemail messages from their phones, sometimes ones they'd been keeping for years, messages from family or friends who had died.</s>
 <s id="84">They said that by preserving those voices and sharing them, it helped them keep the spirit of their loved ones alive.</s>
 <s id="85">One young girl posted the last message she ever heard from her grandmother.</s>
 <s id="86">Secrets can take many forms.</s>
 <s id="87">They can be shocking or silly or soulful.</s>
 <s id="88">They can connect us with our deepest humanity or with people we'll never meet again.</s>
 <s id="89">Voicemail recording: First saved voice message.</s>
 <s id="90">Grandma: ♫ It's somebody's birthday today ♫ ♫ Somebody's birthday today ♫ ♫ The candles are lighted ♫ ♫ on somebody's cake ♫ ♫ And we're all invited ♫ ♫ for somebody's sake ♫ You're 21 years old today.</s>
 <s id="91">Have a real happy birthday, and I love you.</s>
 <s id="92">I'll say bye for now.</s>
 <s id="93">FW: Thank you.</s>
 <s id="94">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="95">(Applause) June Cohen: Frank, that was beautiful, so touching.</s>
 <s id="96">Have you ever sent yourself a postcard?</s>
 <s id="97">Have you ever sent in a secret to PostSecret?</s>
 <s id="98">FW: I have one of my own secrets in every book.</s>
 <s id="99">I think in some ways, the reason I started the project, even though I didn't know it at the time, was because I was struggling with my own secrets.</s>
 <s id="100">And it was through crowd-sourcing, it was through the kindness that strangers were showing me, that I could uncover parts of my past that were haunting me.</s>
 <s id="101">JC: And has anyone ever discovered which secret was yours in the book?</s>
 <s id="102">Has anyone in your life been able to tell?</s>
 <s id="103">FW: Sometimes I share that information, yeah.</s>
 <s id="104">(Laughter) (Applause)</s>
</text>
