<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Ever since I was a young girl, I was always fascinated -- (Laughter) Oh!</s>
 <s id="2">(Laughter) OK, I meant younger and more short.</s>
 <s id="3">(Laughter) If that's possible to imagine.</s>
 <s id="4">But ever since I was a young girl, I was always fascinated with how the world worked exactly how it did.</s>
 <s id="5">So this, very early on, led me to the fields of mathematics and chemistry.</s>
 <s id="6">I would keep going further and further, and as I kept going, I realized that all the fields of science are interconnected.</s>
 <s id="7">And without one, the others have little or no value.</s>
 <s id="8">So, inspired by Marie Curie and my local science museum, I decided to start asking these questions myself and engage in my own independent research, whether it be out of my garage or my bedroom.</s>
 <s id="9">I started reading journal papers, started doing science competitions, started participating in science fairs, doing anything I could to get the knowledge that I so desperately wanted.</s>
 <s id="10">So while I was studying anatomy for a competition, I came across the topic of something called chronic wounds.</s>
 <s id="11">And one thing that stood out to me was a statistic that said that the number of people in the United States with chronic wounds exceeds the number of people with breast cancer, colon cancer, lung cancer and leukemia, combined.</s>
 <s id="12">Hold up.</s>
 <s id="13">So what is a chronic wound?</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) And why haven't I heard about a 5K walk for chronic wounds, why haven't I even heard about a chronic wound in general?</s>
 <s id="15">(Laughter) So after I got past those preliminary questions, and one that I will clarify for you, a chronic wound is essentially when someone gets a normal wound, except it fails to heal normally because the patient has some kind of preexisting condition, which in most cases is diabetes.</s>
 <s id="16">So more staggering statistics were to be found as I kept going on in this research.</s>
 <s id="17">In the year 2010 alone, 50 billion dollars were spent worldwide to treat chronic wounds.</s>
 <s id="18">In addition, it's estimated that about two percent of the population will get a chronic wound at some point in their lifetime.</s>
 <s id="19">This was absurd.</s>
 <s id="20">So as I started doing more research, I found that there was a correlation between the moisture level inside a wound dressing and the stage of healing that the chronic wound would be at.</s>
 <s id="21">So I decided, why don't I design something to measure the moisture level within the wound so this can help doctors and patients treat their wounds better.</s>
 <s id="22">And essentially, expedite the healing process.</s>
 <s id="23">So that's exactly what I set out to do.</s>
 <s id="24">Being a 14-year-old working out of her garage-turned-lab, I had a lot of constraints.</s>
 <s id="25">Most being that I wasn't given a grant, I wasn't given a lot of money, and I wasn't given a lot of resources.</s>
 <s id="26">In addition, I had a lot of criteria, as well.</s>
 <s id="27">Since this product would be readily interacting with the body, it had to be biocompatible, it also had to be low-cost, as I was designing it and paying for it myself.</s>
 <s id="28">It also had to be mass-manufacturable, because I wanted it to be made anywhere, for anyone.</s>
 <s id="29">Thus, I drafted up a schematic.</s>
 <s id="30">What you see on the left hand-side is the early schematics in my design, showing both a bird's-eye view and also one stacking variant.</s>
 <s id="31">A stacking variant means that the entire product is consisted of different individual parts that have to work in unison.</s>
 <s id="32">And what's shown there is one possible arrangement.</s>
 <s id="33">So what exactly is this?</s>
 <s id="34">So I had gone on to testing my sensors and as all scientists have stumbles along their work, I also had a couple of problems in my first generation of sensors.</s>
 <s id="35">First of all, I couldn't figure out how to get a nanoparticle ink into a printcheck cartridge without spilling it all over my carpet.</s>
 <s id="36">That was problem number one.</s>
 <s id="37">Problem number two was, I couldn't exactly control the sensitivity of my sensors.</s>
 <s id="38">I couldn't scale them up or down, I couldn't really do anything of that sort.</s>
 <s id="39">So I wanted something to solve it.</s>
 <s id="40">Problem one was easily solved by some scouting on eBay and Amazon for syringes that I could use.</s>
 <s id="41">Problem two, however, required a lot more thought.</s>
 <s id="42">So this is where this factors in.</s>
 <s id="43">So what a space-filling curve does is it aims to take up all the area it can within one unit square.</s>
 <s id="44">And by writing a computer program, you can have different iterations of the different curve, which increasingly get close to one unit square, but never quite reaches there.</s>
 <s id="45">So now I could control the thickness, the size, I could do whatever I want with it, and I could predict my results.</s>
 <s id="46">So I started constructing my sensors and testing them more rigorously, using money that I had gotten from previous science fair awards.</s>
 <s id="47">Lastly, I had to connect this data in order to be read.</s>
 <s id="48">So I interfaced it with a Bluetooth chip, which you can see here by the app screenshots on the right.</s>
 <s id="49">And what this does is that anyone can monitor the progress of their wound, and it can be transmitted over a wireless connection to the doctor, the patient or whoever needs it.</s>
 <s id="50">[Continued Testing and Refinement] So in conclusion, my design was successful -- however, science never ends.</s>
 <s id="51">There's always something to be done, something to be refined.</s>
 <s id="52">So that's what I'm currently in the process of doing.</s>
 <s id="53">However, what I learned was what's more important than the actual thing I designed is an attitude that I had taken on while doing this.</s>
 <s id="54">And that attitude was, even though I'm a 14-year-old working in her garage on something that she doesn't completely understand, I could still make a difference and contribute to the field.</s>
 <s id="55">And that's what inspired me to keep going, and I hope it inspires many others to also do work like this even though they're not very sure about it.</s>
 <s id="56">So I hope that's a message that you all take on today.</s>
 <s id="57">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="58">(Applause)</s>
</text>
