<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <p id="p1">
  <s id="1.1">[Why don't we eat bugs?]</s>
  <s id="1.2">For centuries, people have consumed bugs, everything from beetles to caterpillars, locusts, grasshoppers, termites, and dragonflies.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="2">The practice even has a name: entomophagy.</s>
 <s id="3">Early hunter-gatherers probably learned from animals that foraged for protein-rich insects and followed suit.</s>
 <s id="4">As we evolved and bugs became part of our dietary tradition, they fulfilled the role of both staple food and delicacy.</s>
 <s id="5">In ancient Greece, cicadas were considered luxury snacks.</s>
 <s id="6">And even the Romans found beetle larvae to be scrumptious.</s>
 <s id="7">Why have we lost our taste for bugs?</s>
 <s id="8">The reason for our rejection is historical, and the story probably begins around 10,000 BC in the Fertile Crescent, a place in the Middle East that was a major birthplace of agriculture.</s>
 <s id="9">Back then, our once-nomadic ancestors began to settle in the Crescent.</s>
 <s id="10">And as they learned to farm crops and domesticate animals there, attitudes changed, rippling outwards towards Europe and the rest of the Western world.</s>
 <s id="11">As farming took off, people might have spurned bugs as mere pests that destroyed their crops.</s>
 <s id="12">Populations grew, and the West became urbanized, weakening connections with our foraging past.</s>
 <s id="13">People simply forgot their bug-rich history.</s>
 <s id="14">Today, for people not accustomed to entomophagy, bugs are just an irritant.</s>
 <s id="15">They sting and bite and infest our food.</s>
 <s id="16">We feel an "ick factor" associated with them and are disgusted by the prospect of cooking insects.</s>
 <s id="17">Almost 2,000 insect species are turned into food, forming a big part of everyday diets for two billion people around the world.</s>
 <s id="18">Countries in the tropics are the keenest consumers, because culturally, it's acceptable.</s>
 <s id="19">Species in those regions are also large, diverse, and tend to congregate in groups or swarms that make them easy to harvest.</s>
 <s id="20">Take Cambodia in Southeast Asia where huge tarantulas are gathered, fried, and sold in the marketplace.</s>
 <s id="21">In southern Africa, the juicy mopane worm is a dietary staple, simmered in a spicy sauce or eaten dried and salted.</s>
 <s id="22">And in Mexico, chopped jumiles are toasted with garlic, lemon, and salt.</s>
 <s id="23">Bugs can be eaten whole to make up a meal or ground into flour, powder, and paste to add to food.</s>
 <s id="24">But it's not all about taste.</s>
 <s id="25">They're also healthy.</s>
 <s id="26">In fact, scientists say entomophagy could be a cost-effective solution for developing countries that are food insecure.</s>
 <s id="27">Insects can contain up to 80% protein, the body's vital building blocks, and are also high in energy-rich fat, fiber, and micronutrients like vitamins and minerals.</s>
 <s id="28">Did you know that most edible insects contain the same amount or even more mineral iron than beef, making them a huge, untapped resource when you consider that iron deficiency is currently the most common nutritional problem in the world?</s>
 <s id="29">The mealworm is another nutritious example.</s>
 <s id="30">The yellow beetle larvae are native to America and easy to farm.</s>
 <s id="31">They have a high vitamin content, loads of healthy minerals, and can contain up to 50% protein, almost as much as in an equivalent amount of beef.</s>
 <s id="32">To cook, simply sauté in butter and salt or roast and drizzle with chocolate for a crunchy snack.</s>
 <s id="33">What you have to overcome in "ick factor," you gain in nutrition and taste.</s>
 <s id="34">Indeed, bugs can be delicious.</s>
 <s id="35">Mealworms taste like roasted nuts.</s>
 <s id="36">Locusts are similar to shrimp.</s>
 <s id="37">Crickets, some people say, have an aroma of popcorn.</s>
 <s id="38">Farming insects for food also has less environmental impact than livestock farms do because insects emit far less greenhouse gas and use up less space, water, and food.</s>
 <s id="39">Socioeconomically, bug production could uplift people in developing countries since insect farms can be small scale, highly productive, and yet relatively inexpensive to keep.</s>
 <s id="40">Insects can also be turned into more sustainable food for livestock and can be reared on organic waste, like vegetable peelings, that might otherwise just end up rotting in landfills.</s>
 <s id="41">Feeling hungry yet?</s>
 <s id="42">Faced with a plate of fried crickets, most people today would still recoil, imagining all those legs and feelers getting stuck between their teeth.</s>
 <s id="43">But think of a lobster.</s>
 <s id="44">It's pretty much just a giant insect with legs and feelers galore that was once regarded as an inferior, repulsive food.</s>
 <s id="45">Now, lobster is a delicacy.</s>
 <s id="46">Can the same paradigm shift happen for bugs?</s>
 <s id="47">So, give it a try!</s>
 <s id="48">Pop that insect into your mouth, and savor the crunch.</s>
</text>
