<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Imagine a big explosion as you climb through 3,000 ft.</s>
 <s id="2">Imagine a plane full of smoke.</s>
 <s id="3">Imagine an engine going clack, clack, clack.</s>
 <s id="4">It sounds scary.</s>
 <s id="5">Well, I had a unique seat that day.</s>
 <s id="6">I was sitting in 1D.</s>
 <s id="7">I was the only one who could talk to the flight attendants.</s>
 <p id="p8">
  <s id="8.1">So I looked at them right away, and they said, "No problem.</s>
  <s id="8.2">We probably hit some birds."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="9">The pilot had already turned the plane around, and we weren't that far.</s>
 <s id="10">You could see Manhattan.</s>
 <s id="11">Two minutes later, three things happened at the same time.</s>
 <s id="12">The pilot lines up the plane with the Hudson River.</s>
 <s id="13">That's usually not the route.</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) He turns off the engines.</s>
 <s id="15">Now, imagine being in a plane with no sound.</s>
 <s id="16">And then he says three words.</s>
 <s id="17">The most unemotional three words I've ever heard.</s>
 <s id="18">He says, "Brace for impact."</s>
 <s id="19">I didn't have to talk to the flight attendant anymore.</s>
 <s id="20">(Laughter) I could see in her eyes, it was terror.</s>
 <s id="21">Life was over.</s>
 <s id="22">Now I want to share with you three things I learned about myself that day.</s>
 <s id="23">I learned that it all changes in an instant.</s>
 <s id="24">We have this bucket list, we have these things we want to do in life, and I thought about all the people I wanted to reach out to that I didn't, all the fences I wanted to mend, all the experiences I wanted to have and I never did.</s>
 <s id="25">As I thought about that later on, I came up with a saying, which is, "I collect bad wines."</s>
 <s id="26">Because if the wine is ready and the person is there, I'm opening it.</s>
 <s id="27">I no longer want to postpone anything in life.</s>
 <s id="28">And that urgency, that purpose, has really changed my life.</s>
 <s id="29">The second thing I learned that day -- and this is as we clear the George Washington Bridge, which was by not a lot -- (Laughter) I thought about, wow, I really feel one real regret.</s>
 <s id="30">I've lived a good life.</s>
 <s id="31">In my own humanity and mistakes, I've tried to get better at everything I tried.</s>
 <s id="32">But in my humanity, I also allow my ego to get in.</s>
 <s id="33">And I regretted the time I wasted on things that did not matter with people that matter.</s>
 <s id="34">And I thought about my relationship with my wife, with my friends, with people.</s>
 <s id="35">And after, as I reflected on that, I decided to eliminate negative energy from my life.</s>
 <s id="36">It's not perfect, but it's a lot better.</s>
 <s id="37">I've not had a fight with my wife in two years.</s>
 <s id="38">It feels great.</s>
 <s id="39">I no longer try to be right; I choose to be happy.</s>
 <s id="40">The third thing I learned -- and this is as your mental clock starts going, "15, 14, 13."</s>
 <s id="41">You can see the water coming.</s>
 <s id="42">I'm saying, "Please blow up."</s>
 <s id="43">I don't want this thing to break in 20 pieces like you've seen in those documentaries.</s>
 <s id="44">And as we're coming down, I had a sense of, wow, dying is not scary.</s>
 <s id="45">It's almost like we've been preparing for it our whole lives.</s>
 <s id="46">But it was very sad.</s>
 <s id="47">I didn't want to go; I love my life.</s>
 <s id="48">And that sadness really framed in one thought, which is, I only wish for one thing.</s>
 <s id="49">I only wish I could see my kids grow up.</s>
 <s id="50">About a month later, I was at a performance by my daughter -- first-grader, not much artistic talent -- (Laughter) Yet!</s>
 <s id="51">(Laughter) And I'm bawling, I'm crying, like a little kid.</s>
 <s id="52">And it made all the sense in the world to me.</s>
 <s id="53">I realized at that point, by connecting those two dots, that the only thing that matters in my life is being a great dad.</s>
 <s id="54">Above all, above all, the only goal I have in life is to be a good dad.</s>
 <s id="55">I was given the gift of a miracle, of not dying that day.</s>
 <s id="56">I was given another gift, which was to be able to see into the future and come back and live differently.</s>
 <s id="57">I challenge you guys that are flying today, imagine the same thing happens on your plane -- and please don't -- but imagine, and how would you change?</s>
 <s id="58">What would you get done that you're waiting to get done because you think you'll be here forever?</s>
 <s id="59">How would you change your relationships and the negative energy in them?</s>
 <s id="60">And more than anything, are you being the best parent you can?</s>
 <s id="61">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="62">(Applause)</s>
</text>
