<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">A handful of species on Earth share a seemingly mysterious trait: a menstrual cycle.</s>
 <s id="2">We're one of the select few.</s>
 <s id="3">Monkeys, apes, bats, humans, and possibly elephant shrews are the only mammals on Earth that menstruate.</s>
 <s id="4">We also do it more than any other animal, even though its a waste of nutrients and can be a physical inconvenience.</s>
 <s id="5">So where's the sense in this uncommon biological process?</s>
 <s id="6">The answer begins with pregnancy.</s>
 <s id="7">During this process, the body's resources are cleverly used to shape a suitable environment for a fetus, creating an internal haven for a mother to nurture her growing child.</s>
 <s id="8">In this respect, pregnancy is awe-inspiring, but that's only half the story.</s>
 <s id="9">The other half reveals that pregnancy places a mother and her child at odds.</s>
 <s id="10">As for all living creatures, the human body evolved to promote the spread of its genes.</s>
 <s id="11">For the mother, that means she should try to provide equally for all her offspring.</s>
 <s id="12">But a mother and her fetus don't share exactly the same genes.</s>
 <s id="13">The fetus inherits genes from its father, as well, and those genes can promote their own survival by extracting more than their fair share of resources from the mother.</s>
 <s id="14">This evolutionary conflict of interests places a woman and her unborn child in a biological tug-of-war that plays out inside the womb.</s>
 <s id="15">One factor contributing to this internal tussle is the placenta, the fetal organ that connects to the mother's blood supply and nourishes the fetus while it grows.</s>
 <s id="16">In most mammals, the placenta is confined behind a barrier of maternal cells.</s>
 <s id="17">This barrier lets the mother control the supply of nutrients to the fetus.</s>
 <s id="18">But in humans and a few other species, the placenta actually penetrates right into the mother's circulatory system to directly access her blood stream.</s>
 <s id="19">Through its placenta, the fetus pumps the mother's arteries with hormones that keep them open to provide a permanent flow of nutrient-rich blood.</s>
 <s id="20">A fetus with such unrestricted access can manufacture hormones to increase the mother's blood sugar, dilate her arteries, and inflate her blood pressure.</s>
 <s id="21">Most mammal mothers can expel or reabsorb embryos if required, but in humans, once the fetus is connected to the blood supply, severing that connection can result in hemorrhage.</s>
 <s id="22">If the fetus develops poorly or dies, the mother's health is endangered.</s>
 <s id="23">As it grows, a fetus's ongoing need for resources can cause intense fatigue, high blood pressure, and conditions like diabetes and preeclampsia.</s>
 <s id="24">Because of these risks, pregnancy is always a huge, and sometimes dangerous, investment.</s>
 <s id="25">So it makes sense that the body should screen embryos carefully to find out which ones are worth the challenge.</s>
 <s id="26">This is where menstruation fits in.</s>
 <s id="27">Pregnancy starts with a process called implantation, where the embryo embeds itself in the endometrium that lines the uterus.</s>
 <s id="28">The endometrium evolved to make implantation difficult so that only the healthy embryos could survive.</s>
 <s id="29">But in doing so, it also selected for the most vigorously invasive embryos, creating an evolutionary feedback loop.</s>
 <s id="30">The embryo engages in a complex, exquisitely timed hormonal dialogue that transforms the endometrium to allow implantation.</s>
 <s id="31">What happens when an embryo fails the test?</s>
 <s id="32">It might still manage to attach, or even get partly through the endometrium.</s>
 <s id="33">As it slowly dies, it could leave its mother vulnerable to infection, and all the time, it may be emitting hormonal signals that disrupt her tissues.</s>
 <s id="34">The body avoids this problem by simply removing every possible risk.</s>
 <s id="35">Each time ovulation doesn't result in a healthy pregnancy, the womb gets rid of its endometrial lining, along with any unfertilized eggs, sick, dying, or dead embryos.</s>
 <s id="36">That protective process is known as menstruation, leading to the period.</s>
 <s id="37">This biological trait, bizarre as it may be, sets us on course for the continuation of the human race.</s>
</text>
