<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Gripped with vengeful passion, The Queen of the Night tears across the stage.</s>
 <s id="2">She begins to sing her titular aria, one of the most famous sections from Mozart’s beloved opera, "The Magic Flute."</s>
 <s id="3">The orchestra fills the hall with music, but the queen’s voice soars above the instruments.</s>
 <s id="4">Its melody rings out across thousands of patrons, reaching seats 40 meters away— all without any assistance from a microphone.</s>
 <s id="5">How is it possible that this single voice can be heard so clearly, above the strains of dozens of instruments?</s>
 <s id="6">The answer lies in the physics of the human voice, and the carefully honed technique of an expert opera singer.</s>
 <s id="7">All the music in this opera house originates from the vibrations created by instruments— whether it’s the strings of a violin or the vocal folds of a performer.</s>
 <s id="8">These vibrations send waves into the air, which our brains interpret as sound.</s>
 <s id="9">The frequency of these vibrations–– specifically, the number of waves per second–– is how our brains determine the pitch of a single note.</s>
 <s id="10">But in fact, every note we hear is actually a combination of multiple vibrations.</s>
 <s id="11">Imagine a guitar string vibrating at its lowest frequency.</s>
 <s id="12">This is called the fundamental, and this low pitch is what our ears mostly use to identify a note.</s>
 <s id="13">But this lowest vibration triggers additional frequencies called overtones, which layer on top of the fundamental.</s>
 <s id="14">These overtones break down into specific frequencies called harmonics, or partials— and manipulating them is how opera singers work their magic.</s>
 <s id="15">Every note has a set of frequencies that comprise its harmonic series.</s>
 <s id="16">The first partial vibrates at twice the frequency of the fundamental.</s>
 <s id="17">The next partial is three times the fundamental’s frequency, and so on.</s>
 <s id="18">Virtually all acoustic instruments produce harmonic series, but each instrument’s shape and material changes the balance of its harmonics.</s>
 <s id="19">For example, a flute emphasizes the first few partials, but in a clarinet’s lowest register, the odd-numbered partials resonate most strongly.</s>
 <s id="20">The strength of various partials is part of what gives each instrument its unique sonic signature.</s>
 <s id="21">It also affects an instrument’s ability to stand out in a crowd, because our ears are more strongly attuned to some frequencies than others.</s>
 <s id="22">This is the key to an opera singer’s power of projection.</s>
 <s id="23">An operatic soprano— the highest of the four standard voice parts— can produce notes with fundamental frequencies ranging from 250 to 1,500 vibrations per second.</s>
 <s id="24">Human ears are most sensitive to frequencies between 2,000 and 5,000 vibrations per second.</s>
 <s id="25">So if the singer can bring out the partials in this range, she can target a sensory sweet spot where she’s most likely to be heard.</s>
 <s id="26">Higher partials are also advantageous because there’s less competition from the orchestra, whose overtones are weaker at those frequencies.</s>
 <s id="27">The result of emphasizing these partials is a distinctive ringing timbre called a singer’s squillo.</s>
 <s id="28">Opera singers work for decades to create their squillo.</s>
 <s id="29">They can produce higher frequencies by modifying the shape and tension in their vocal folds and vocal tract.</s>
 <s id="30">And by shifting the position of their tongues and lips, they accentuate some overtones while dampening others.</s>
 <s id="31">Singers also increase their range of partials with vibrato— a musical effect in which a note slightly oscillates in pitch.</s>
 <s id="32">This creates a fuller sound that rings out over the instruments’ comparatively narrow vibratos.</s>
 <s id="33">Once they have the right partials, they employ other techniques to boost their volume.</s>
 <s id="34">Singers expand their lung capacity and perfect their posture for consistent, controlled airflow.</s>
 <s id="35">The concert hall helps as well, with rigid surfaces that reflect sound waves towards the audience.</s>
 <s id="36">All singers take advantage of these techniques, but different vocal signatures demand different physical preparation.</s>
 <s id="37">A Wagnerian singer needs to build up stamina to power through the composer’s four-hour epics.</s>
 <s id="38">While bel canto singers require versatile vocal folds to vault through acrobatic arias.</s>
 <s id="39">Biology also sets some limits— not every technique is feasible for every set of muscles, and voices change as singers age.</s>
 <s id="40">But whether in an opera hall or a shower stall, these techniques can turn un-amplified voices into thundering musical masterpieces.</s>
</text>
