<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">A mosquito lands on your arm, injects its chemicals into your skin, and begins to feed.</s>
 <s id="2">You wouldn’t even know it was there, if not for the red lump that appears, accompanied by a telltale itch.</s>
 <s id="3">It’s a nuisance, but that bump is an important signal that you’re protected by your immune system, your body’s major safeguard against infection, illness, and disease.</s>
 <s id="4">This system is a vast network of cells, tissues, and organs that coordinate your body’s defenses against any threats to your health.</s>
 <s id="5">Without it, you’d be exposed to billions of bacteria, viruses, and toxins that could make something as minor as a paper cut or a seasonal cold fatal.</s>
 <s id="6">The immune system relies on millions of defensive white blood cells, also known as leukocytes, that originate in our bone marrow.</s>
 <s id="7">These cells migrate into the bloodstream and the lymphatic system, a network of vessels which helps clear bodily toxins and waste.</s>
 <s id="8">Our bodies are teeming with leukocytes: there are between 4,000 and 11,000 in every microliter of blood.</s>
 <s id="9">As they move around, leukocytes work like security personnel, constantly screening the blood, tissues, and organs for suspicious signs.</s>
 <s id="10">This system mainly relies on cues called antigens.</s>
 <s id="11">These molecular traces on the surface of pathogens and other foreign substances betray the presence of invaders.</s>
 <s id="12">As soon as the leukocytes detect them, it takes only minutes for the body’s protective immune response to kick in.</s>
 <s id="13">Threats to our bodies are hugely variable, so the immune response has to be equally adaptable.</s>
 <s id="14">That means relying on many different types of leukocytes to tackle threats in different ways.</s>
 <s id="15">Despite this diversity, we classify leukocytes in two main cellular groups, which coordinate a two-pronged attack.</s>
 <s id="16">First, phagocytes trigger the immune response by sending macrophages and dendritic cells into the blood.</s>
 <s id="17">As these circulate, they destroy any foreign cells they encounter, simply by consuming them.</s>
 <s id="18">That allows phagocytes to identify the antigen on the invaders they just ingested and transmit this information to the second major cell group orchestrating the defense, the lymphocytes.</s>
 <s id="19">A group of lymphocyte cells called T-cells go in search of infected body cells and swiftly kill them off.</s>
 <s id="20">Meanwhile, B-cells and helper T-cells use the information gathered from the unique antigens to start producing special proteins called antibodies.</s>
 <s id="21">This is the pièce de résistance: Each antigen has a unique, matching antibody that can latch onto it like a lock and key, and destroy the invading cells.</s>
 <s id="22">B-cells can produce millions of these, which then cycle through the body and attack the invaders until the worst of the threat is neutralized.</s>
 <s id="23">While all of this is going on, familiar symptoms, like high temperatures and swelling, are actually processes designed to aid the immune response.</s>
 <s id="24">A warmer body makes it harder for bacteria and viruses to reproduce and spread because they’re temperature-sensitive.</s>
 <s id="25">And when body cells are damaged, they release chemicals that make fluid leak into the surrounding tissues, causing swelling.</s>
 <s id="26">That also attracts phagocytes, which consume the invaders and the damaged cells.</s>
 <s id="27">Usually, an immune response will eradicate a threat within a few days.</s>
 <s id="28">It won’t always stop you from getting ill, but that’s not its purpose.</s>
 <s id="29">Its actual job is to stop a threat from escalating to dangerous levels inside your body.</s>
 <s id="30">And through constant surveillance over time, the immune system provides another benefit: it helps us develop long-term immunity.</s>
 <s id="31">When B- and T-cells identify antigens, they can use that information to recognize invaders in the future.</s>
 <s id="32">So, when a threat revisits, the cells can swiftly deploy the right antibodies to tackle it before it affects any more cells.</s>
 <s id="33">That’s how you can develop immunity to certain diseases, like chickenpox.</s>
 <s id="34">It doesn’t always work so well.</s>
 <s id="35">Some people have autoimmune diseases, which trick the immune system into attacking the body’s own perfectly healthy cells.</s>
 <s id="36">No one knows exactly what causes them, but these disorders sabotage the immune system to varying degrees, and underlie problems like arthritis, Type I diabetes, and multiple sclerosis.</s>
 <s id="37">For most individuals, however, a healthy immune system will successfully fight off an estimated 300 colds and innumerable other potential infections over the course of a lifetime.</s>
 <s id="38">Without it, those threats would escalate into something far more dangerous.</s>
 <s id="39">So the next time you catch a cold or scratch a mosquito bite, think of the immune system.</s>
 <s id="40">We owe it our lives.</s>
</text>
