<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Juana Ramírez de Asbaje sat before a panel of prestigious theologians, jurists, and mathematicians.</s>
 <s id="2">The viceroy of New Spain had invited them to test the young woman’s knowledge by posing the most difficult questions they could muster.</s>
 <s id="3">But Juana successfully answered every challenge, from complicated equations to philosophical queries.</s>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">Observers would later liken the scene to “a royal galleon fending off a few canoes.”</s>
  <s id="4.2">The woman who faced this interrogation was born in the mid-17th century.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="5">At that time, Mexico had been a Spanish colony for over a century, leading to a complex and stratified class system.</s>
 <s id="6">Juana’s maternal grandparents were born in Spain, making them members of Mexico’s most esteemed class.</s>
 <s id="7">But Juana was born out of wedlock, and her father – a Spanish military captain – left her mother, Doña Isabel, to raise Juana and her sisters alone.</s>
 <s id="8">Fortunately, her grandfather’s moderate means ensured the family a comfortable existence.</s>
 <s id="9">And Doña Isabel set a strong example for her daughters, successfully managing one of her father’s two estates, despite her illiteracy and the misogyny of the time.</s>
 <s id="10">It was perhaps this precedent that inspired Juana’s lifelong confidence.</s>
 <s id="11">At age three, she secretly followed her older sister to school.</s>
 <s id="12">When she later learned that higher education was open only to men, she begged her mother to let her attend in disguise.</s>
 <s id="13">Her request denied, Juana found solace in her grandfather’s private library.</s>
 <s id="14">By early adolescence, she’d mastered philosophical debate, Latin, and the Aztec language Nahuatl.</s>
 <s id="15">Juana’s precocious intellect attracted attention from the royal court in Mexico City, and when she was sixteen, the viceroy and his wife took her in as their lady-in-waiting.</s>
 <s id="16">Here, her plays and poems alternately dazzled and outraged the court.</s>
 <s id="17">Her provocative poem Foolish Men infamously criticized sexist double standards, decrying how men corrupt women while blaming them for immorality.</s>
 <s id="18">Despite its controversy, her work still inspired adoration, and numerous proposals.</s>
 <s id="19">But Juana was more interested in knowledge than marriage.</s>
 <s id="20">And in the patriarchal society of the time, there was only one place she could find it.</s>
 <s id="21">The Church, while still under the zealous influence of the Spanish Inquisition, would allow Juana to retain her independence and respectability while remaining unmarried.</s>
 <s id="22">At age 20, she entered the Hieronymite Convent of Santa Paula and took on her new name: Sor Juana Inés de la Cruz.</s>
 <s id="23">For years, Sor Juana was considered a prized treasure of the church.</s>
 <s id="24">She wrote dramas, comedies, and treatises on philosophy and mathematics, in addition to religious music and poetry.</s>
 <s id="25">She accrued a massive library, and was visited by many prominent scholars.</s>
 <s id="26">While serving as the convent’s treasurer and archivist, she also protected the livelihoods of her niece and sisters from men who tried to exploit them.</s>
 <s id="27">But her outspokenness ultimately brought her into conflict with her benefactors.</s>
 <s id="28">In 1690, a bishop published Sor Juana’s private critique of a respected sermon.</s>
 <s id="29">In the publication, he admonished Sor Juana to devote herself to prayer rather than debate.</s>
 <s id="30">She replied that God would not have given women intellect if he did not want them to use it.</s>
 <s id="31">The exchange caught the attention of the conservative Archbishop of Mexico.</s>
 <s id="32">Slowly, Sor Juana was stripped of her prestige, forced to sell her books and give up writing.</s>
 <s id="33">Furious at this censorship, but unwilling to leave the church, she bitterly renewed her vows.</s>
 <s id="34">In her last act of defiance, she signed them “I, the worst of all,” in her own blood.</s>
 <s id="35">Deprived of scholarship, Sor Juana threw herself into charity work, and in 1695, she died of an illness she contracted while nursing her sisters.</s>
 <s id="36">Today, Sor Juana has been recognized as the first feminist in the Americas.</s>
 <s id="37">She’s the subject of countless documentaries, novels, and operas, and appears on Mexico’s 200-peso banknote.</s>
 <s id="38">In the words of Nobel laureate Octavio Paz: “It is not enough to say that Sor Juana’s work is a product of history; we must add that history is also a product of her work.”</s>
</text>
