<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Dogs have interests.</s>
 <s id="2">They have interest sniffing each other, chasing squirrels.</s>
 <s id="3">And if we don't make that a reward in training, that will be a distraction.</s>
 <s id="4">It's always sort of struck me as really a scary thought that if you see a dog in a park, and the owner is calling it, and the owner says, you know, "Puppy, come here, come here," and the dog thinks, "Hmm, interesting.</s>
 <s id="5">I'm sniffing this other dog's rear end, the owner's calling."</s>
 <s id="6">It's a difficult choice, right?</s>
 <p id="p7">
  <s id="7.1">Rear end, owner.</s>
  <s id="7.2">Rear end wins.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="8">I mean, you lose.</s>
 <s id="9">You cannot compete with the environment, if you have an adolescent dog's brain.</s>
 <s id="10">So, when we train, we're always trying to take into account the dog's point of view.</s>
 <s id="11">Now, I'm here largely because there's kind of a rift in dog training at the moment that -- on one side, we have people who think that you train a dog, number one, by making up rules, human rules.</s>
 <s id="12">We don't take the dog's point of view into account.</s>
 <s id="13">So the human says, "You're going to act this way, damn it.</s>
 <s id="14">We're going to force you to act against your will, to bend to our will."</s>
 <s id="15">Then, number two, we keep these rules a secret from the dog.</s>
 <s id="16">And then number three, now we can punish the dog for breaking rules he didn't even know existed.</s>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">So you get a little puppy, he comes.</s>
  <s id="17.2">His only crime is he grew.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="18">When he was a little puppy, he puts his paws on your leg -- you know, isn't that nice?</s>
 <s id="19">And you go, "Oh, there's a good boy."</s>
 <s id="20">You bend down, you pat him -- you reward him for jumping up.</s>
 <s id="21">His one mistake is he's a Tibetan mastiff, and a few months later, he weighs, you know, 80 pounds.</s>
 <s id="22">Every time he jumps up, he gets all sorts of abuse.</s>
 <s id="23">I mean, it is really very, very scary the abuse that dogs get.</s>
 <s id="24">So, this whole dominance issue -- number one, what we get in dog training is this Mickey-Mouse interpretation of a very complicated social system.</s>
 <s id="25">And they take this stuff seriously.</s>
 <s id="26">Male dogs are very serious about a hierarchy, because it prevents physical fights.</s>
 <s id="27">Of course, female dogs, bitches, on the other hand, have several bitch amendments to male hierarchical rule.</s>
 <s id="28">The number one is, "I have it, you don't."</s>
 <s id="29">And what you will find is a very, very low-ranking bitch will quite easily keep a bone away from a high-ranking male.</s>
 <p id="p30">
  <s id="30.1">So, we get in dog training this notion of dominances, or of the alpha dog.</s>
  <s id="30.2">I'm sure that you've heard this.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="31">Dogs get so abused.</s>
 <s id="32">Dogs, horses and humans -- these are the three species which are so abused in life.</s>
 <s id="33">And the reason is built into their behavior -- is to always come back and apologize.</s>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">Like, "Oh, I'm sorry you had to beat me.</s>
  <s id="34.2">I'm really sorry, yes, it's my fault."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="35">They are just so beatable, and that's why they get beaten.</s>
 <s id="36">The poor puppy jumps up, you open the dog book, what does it say?</s>
 <s id="37">"Hold his front paws, squeeze his front paws, stamp on his hind feet, squirt him in the face with lemon juice, hit him on the head with a rolled-up newspaper, knee him in the chest, flip him over backwards."</s>
 <s id="38">Because he grew?</s>
 <s id="39">And because he's performing a behavior you've trained him to do?</s>
 <s id="40">This is insanity.</s>
 <s id="41">I ask owners, "Well, how would you like the dog to greet you?"</s>
 <s id="42">And people say, "Well, I don't know, to sit, I guess."</s>
 <s id="43">I said, "Let's teach him to sit."</s>
 <s id="44">And then we give him a reason for sitting.</s>
 <s id="45">Because the first stage is basically teaching a dog ESL.</s>
 <s id="46">I could speak to you and say, "Laytay-chai, paisey, paisey."</s>
 <s id="47">Go on, something should happen now.</s>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">Why aren't you responding?</s>
  <s id="48.2">Oh, you don't speak Swahili.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="49">Well, I've got news for you.</s>
 <s id="50">The dog doesn't speak English, or American, or Spanish, or French.</s>
 <s id="51">So the first stage in training is to teach the dog ESL, English as a second language.</s>
 <s id="52">And that's how we use the food lure in the hand, and we use food because we're dealing with owners.</s>
 <s id="53">My wife doesn't need food -- she's a great trainer, much better than I am.</s>
 <s id="54">I don't need food, but the average owner says, "Puppy, sit."</s>
 <s id="55">Or they go, "Sit, sit, sit."</s>
 <s id="56">They're making a hand signal in front of the dog's rectum for some reason, like the dog has a third eye there -- it's insane.</s>
 <s id="57">You know, "Sit, sit."</s>
 <s id="58">No, we go, "Puppy, sit" -- boom, it's got it in six to 10 trials.</s>
 <s id="59">Then we phase out the food as a lure, and now the dog knows that "sit" means sit, and you can actually communicate to a dog in a perfectly constructed English sentence.</s>
 <s id="60">"Phoenix, come here, take this, and go to Jamie, please."</s>
 <s id="61">And I've taught her "Phoenix," "come here," "take this," "go to" and the name of my son, "Jamie."</s>
 <s id="62">And the dog can take a note, and I've got my own little search-and-rescue dog.</s>
 <p id="p63">
  <s id="63.1">He'll find Jamie wherever he is, you know, wherever kids are, crushing rocks by a stream or something, and take him a little message that says, "Hey, dinner's ready.</s>
  <s id="63.2">Come in for dinner."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="64">So, at this point, the dog knows what we want it to do.</s>
 <s id="65">Will it do it?</s>
 <s id="66">Not necessarily, no.</s>
 <s id="67">As I said, if he's in the park and there's a rear end to sniff, why come to the owner?</s>
 <s id="68">The dog lives with you, the dog can get you any time.</s>
 <s id="69">The dog can sniff your butt, if you like, when he wants to.</s>
 <s id="70">At the moment, he's in the park, and you are competing with smells, and other dogs, and squirrels.</s>
 <s id="71">So the second stage in training is to teach the dog to want to do what we want him to do, and this is very easy.</s>
 <s id="72">We use the Premack principle.</s>
 <s id="73">Basically, we follow a low-frequency behavior -- one the dog doesn't want to do -- by a high-frequency behavior, commonly known as a behavior problem, or a dog hobby -- something the dog does like to do.</s>
 <s id="74">That will then become a reward for the lower-frequency behavior.</s>
 <s id="75">So we go, "sit," on the couch; "sit," tummy-rub; "sit," look, I throw a tennis ball; "sit," say hello to that other dog.</s>
 <s id="76">Yes, we put "sniff butt" on queue.</s>
 <s id="77">"Sit," sniff butt.</s>
 <s id="78">So now all of these distractions that worked against training now become rewards that work for training.</s>
 <s id="79">And what we're doing, in essence, is we're teaching the dog, kind of like -- we're letting the dog think that the dog is training us.</s>
 <s id="80">And I can imagine this dog, you know, speaking through the fence to, say, an Akita, saying, "Wow, my owners, they are so incredibly easy to train.</s>
 <s id="81">They're like Golden Retrievers.</s>
 <s id="82">All I have to do is sit, and they do everything.</s>
 <s id="83">They open doors, they drive my car, they massage me, they will throw tennis balls, they will cook for me and serve the food.</s>
 <s id="84">It's like, if I just sit, that's my command.</s>
 <s id="85">Then I have my own personal doorman, chauffeur, masseuse, chef and waiter."</s>
 <s id="86">And now the dog's really happy.</s>
 <s id="87">And this, to me, is always what training is.</s>
 <s id="88">So we really motivate the dog to want to do it, such that the need for punishment seldom comes up.</s>
 <s id="89">Now we move to phase three, when now -- there's times, you know, when daddy knows best.</s>
 <s id="90">And I have a little sign on my fridge, and it says, "Because I'm the daddy, that's why."</s>
 <p id="p91">
  <s id="91.1">Sorry, no more explanation.</s>
  <s id="91.2">"I'm the daddy, you're not.</s>
  <s id="91.3">Sit."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="92">And there's times, for example, if my son's friends leave the door open, the dogs have to know you don't step across this line.</s>
 <s id="93">This is a life-or-death thing.</s>
 <s id="94">You leave this, the sanctity of your house, and you could be hit on the street.</s>
 <s id="95">So some things we have to let the dog know, "You mustn't do this."</s>
 <s id="96">And so we have to enforce, but without force.</s>
 <s id="97">People here get very confused about what a punishment is.</s>
 <s id="98">They think a punishment is something nasty.</s>
 <s id="99">I bet a lot of you do, right?</s>
 <s id="100">You think it's something painful, or scary, or nasty.</s>
 <s id="101">It doesn't have to be.</s>
 <s id="102">There's several definitions of what a punishment is, but one definition, the most popular, is: a punishment is a stimulus that reduces the immediately preceding behavior, such that it's less likely to occur in the future.</s>
 <s id="103">It does not have to be nasty, scary or painful.</s>
 <s id="104">And I would say, if it doesn't have to be, then maybe it shouldn't be.</s>
 <s id="105">I was working with a very dangerous dog about a year ago.</s>
 <s id="106">And this was a dog that put both his owners in hospital, plus the brother-in-law, plus the child.</s>
 <s id="107">And I only agreed to work with it if they promised it would stay in their house, and they never took it outside.</s>
 <s id="108">The dog is actually euthanized now, but this was a dog I worked with for a while.</s>
 <s id="109">A lot of the aggression happened around the kitchen, so while I was there -- this was on the fourth visit -- we did a four and a half hour down-stay, with the dog on his mat.</s>
 <s id="110">And he was kept there by the owner's calm insistence.</s>
 <s id="111">When the dog would try to leave the mat, she would say, "Rover, on the mat, on the mat, on the mat."</s>
 <s id="112">The dog broke his down-stay 22 times in four and a half hours, while she cooked dinner, because we had a lot of aggression related towards food.</s>
 <s id="113">The breaks got fewer and fewer.</s>
 <s id="114">You see, the punishment was working.</s>
 <s id="115">The behavior problem was going away.</s>
 <s id="116">She never raised her voice.</s>
 <s id="117">If she did, she would have got bitten.</s>
 <s id="118">It's not a good dog you shout at.</s>
 <p id="p119">
  <s id="119.1">And a lot of my friends train really neat animals, grizzly bears -- if you've ever seen a grizzly bear on the telly or in film, then it's a friend of mine who's trained it -- killer whales.</s>
  <s id="119.2">I love it because it wires you up.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="120">How are you going to reprimand a grizzly bear?</s>
 <p id="p121">
  <s id="121.1">"Bad bear, bad bear!"</s>
  <s id="121.2">Voom!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="122">Your head now is 100 yards away, sailing through the air, OK?</s>
 <s id="123">This is crazy.</s>
 <s id="124">So, where do we go from here?</s>
 <s id="125">We want a better way.</s>
 <s id="126">Dogs deserve better.</s>
 <s id="127">But for me, the reason for this actually has to do with dogs.</s>
 <s id="128">It has to do with watching people train puppies, and realizing they have horrendous interaction skills, horrendous relationship skills.</s>
 <s id="129">Not just with their puppy, but with the rest of the family at class.</s>
 <s id="130">I mean, my all-time classic is another "come here" one.</s>
 <s id="131">You see someone in the park -- and I'll cover my mic when I say this, because I don't want to wake you up -- and there's the owner in the park, and their dog's over here, and they say, "Rover, come here.</s>
 <p id="p132">
  <s id="132.1">Rover, come here.</s>
  <s id="132.2">Rover, come here, you son of a bitch."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="133">The dog says, "I don't think so."</s>
 <s id="134">(Laughter) I mean, who in their right mind would think that a dog would want to approach them when they're screaming like that?</s>
 <p id="p135">
  <s id="135.1">Instead, the dog says, "I know that tone.</s>
  <s id="135.2">I know that tone.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="136">Previously, when I've approached, I've gotten punished there."</s>
 <s id="137">I was walking onto a plane -- this, for me, was a pivotal moment in my career, and it really cemented what I wanted to do with this whole puppy-training thing, the notion of how to teach puppies in a dog-friendly way to want to do what we want to do, so we don't have to force them.</s>
 <s id="138">You know, I puppy-train my child.</s>
 <s id="139">And the seminal moment was, I was getting on a plane in Dallas, and in row two was a father, I presume, and a young boy about five, kicking the back of the chair.</s>
 <s id="140">"Johnny, don't do that."</s>
 <s id="141">Kick, kick, kick.</s>
 <p id="p142">
  <s id="142.1">"Johnny, don't do that."</s>
  <s id="142.2">Kick, kick, kick.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="143">I'm standing right here with my bag.</s>
 <s id="144">The father leans over, grabs him like this and gives him ugly face.</s>
 <p id="p145">
  <s id="145.1">And ugly face is this -- when you go face-to-face with a puppy or a child, you say, "What are you doing!</s>
  <s id="145.2">Now stop it, stop it, stop it!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="146">And I went, "Oh my God, do I do something?"</s>
 <s id="147">That child has lost everything -- that one of the two people he can trust in this world has absolutely pulled the rug from under his feet.</s>
 <s id="148">And I thought, "Do I tell this jerk to quit it?"</s>
 <s id="149">I thought, "Ian, stay out of it, stay out of it, you know, walk on."</s>
 <s id="150">I walked to the back of the plane, I sat down, and a thought came to me.</s>
 <s id="151">If that had been a dog, I would have laid him out.</s>
 <s id="152">(Laughter) If he had kicked a dog, I would have punched him out.</s>
 <s id="153">He kicked a child, grabs the child like this and I let it go.</s>
 <s id="154">And this is what it's all about.</s>
 <s id="155">These relationship skills are so easy.</s>
 <s id="156">I mean, we as humans, our shallowness when we choose a life-mate based on the three Cs -- coat color, conformation, cuteness.</s>
 <s id="157">You know, kind of like a little robot.</s>
 <s id="158">This is how we go into a relationship, and it's hunky-dory for a year.</s>
 <s id="159">And then, a little behavior problem comes up.</s>
 <s id="160">No different from the dog barking.</s>
 <s id="161">The husband won't clear up his clothes, or the wife's always late for meetings, whatever it is, OK?</s>
 <s id="162">And it then starts, and we get into this thing, and our personal feedback -- there's two things about it.</s>
 <s id="163">When you watch people interacting with animals or other people, there is very little feedback, it's too infrequent.</s>
 <s id="164">And when it happens, it's bad, it's nasty.</s>
 <s id="165">You see it's especially in families, especially with spouses, especially with children, especially with parents.</s>
 <s id="166">You see it especially in the workplace, especially from boss to employee.</s>
 <s id="167">It's as if there's some schadenfreude there, that we actually take delight in people getting things wrong, so that we can then moan and groan and bitch at them.</s>
 <s id="168">And this, I would say, is the biggest human foible that we have.</s>
 <s id="169">It really is.</s>
 <s id="170">We take the good for granted, and we moan and groan at the bad.</s>
 <s id="171">And I think this whole notion of these skills should be taught.</s>
 <s id="172">You know, calculus is wonderful.</s>
 <s id="173">When I was a kid, I was a calculus whiz.</s>
 <s id="174">I don't understand a thing about it now, but I could do it as a kid.</s>
 <p id="p175">
  <s id="175.1">Geometry, fantastic.</s>
  <s id="175.2">You know, quantum mechanics -- these are cool things.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="176">But they don't save marriages and they don't raise children.</s>
 <s id="177">And my look to the future is, and what I want to do with this doggy stuff, is to teach people that you know, your husband's just as easy to train.</s>
 <s id="178">Probably easier -- if you got a Rottie -- much easier to train.</s>
 <s id="179">Your kids are easy to train.</s>
 <s id="180">All you've got to do is to watch them, to time-sample the behavior, and say, every five minutes, you ask the question, "Is it good, or is it bad?"</s>
 <s id="181">If it's good, say, "That was really neat, thank you."</s>
 <s id="182">That is such a powerful training technique.</s>
 <s id="183">This should be taught in schools.</s>
 <s id="184">Relationships -- how do you negotiate?</s>
 <s id="185">How you do negotiate with your friend who wants your toy?</s>
 <s id="186">You know, how to prepare you for your first relationship?</s>
 <s id="187">How on earth about raising children?</s>
 <s id="188">We think how we do it -- one night in bed, we're pregnant, and then we're raising the most important thing in life, a child.</s>
 <s id="189">No, this is what should be taught -- the good living, the good habits, which are just as hard to break as bad habits.</s>
 <s id="190">So, that would be my wish to the future.</s>
 <p id="p191">
  <s id="191.1">Ah, damn, I wanted to end exactly on time, but I got eight, seven, six, five, four, three, two -- so thank you very much.</s>
  <s id="191.2">That's my talk, thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="192">(Applause)</s>
</text>
