<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm an astronaut.</s>
 <s id="2">I flew on the space shuttle twice, and I lived on the International Space Station for almost six months.</s>
 <s id="3">People often ask me the same question, which is, "What's it like in space?"</s>
 <s id="4">as if it was a secret.</s>
 <s id="5">Space belongs to all of us, and I'd like to help you understand why it's a place that is magic for all of us.</s>
 <s id="6">The day after my 50th birthday, I climbed aboard a Russian capsule, in Russia, and launched into space.</s>
 <s id="7">Launching is the most dangerous thing that we do, and it's also the most thrilling.</s>
 <s id="8">Three, two, one ... liftoff!</s>
 <s id="9">I felt every single bit of the controlled fury of those rocket engines as they blasted us off the Earth.</s>
 <s id="10">We went faster and faster and faster, until, after eight and a half minutes, on purpose, those engines stop -- kabunk! -- and we are weightless.</s>
 <s id="11">And the mission and the magic begin.</s>
 <s id="12">Dmitry and Paolo and I are circling the Earth in our tiny spacecraft, approaching the space station carefully.</s>
 <s id="13">It's an intricate dance at 17,500 miles an hour between our capsule, the size of a Smart Car, and the space station, the size of a football field.</s>
 <s id="14">We arrive when those two craft dock with a gentle thunk.</s>
 <s id="15">We open the hatches, have sloppy zero-G hugs with each other, and now we're six.</s>
 <s id="16">We're a space family, an instant family.</s>
 <s id="17">My favorite part about living up there was the flying.</s>
 <s id="18">I loved it.</s>
 <s id="19">It was like being Peter Pan.</s>
 <s id="20">It's not about floating.</s>
 <s id="21">Just the touch of a finger can actually push you across the entire space station, and then you sort of tuck in with your toes.</s>
 <s id="22">One of my favorite things was drifting silently through the space station, which was humming along at night.</s>
 <s id="23">I wondered sometimes if it knew I was there, just silent.</s>
 <s id="24">But sharing the wonder of that with the crew was also part of what was important to me.</s>
 <s id="25">A typical day in space starts with the perfect commute.</s>
 <s id="26">I wake up, cruise down the lab and say hello to the best morning view ever.</s>
 <s id="27">It's a really fast commute, only 30 seconds, and we never get tired of looking out that window.</s>
 <s id="28">I think it reminds us that we're actually still very close to Earth.</s>
 <s id="29">Our crew was the second ever to use the Canadian robotic arm to capture a supply ship the size of a school bus containing about a dozen different experiments and the only chocolate that we would see for the next four months.</s>
 <s id="30">Now, chocolate aside, every single one of those experiments enables yet one more scientific question answered that we can't do down here on Earth.</s>
 <s id="31">And so, it's like a different lens, allowing us to see the answers to questions like, "What about combustion?"</s>
 <s id="32">"What about fluid dynamics?"</s>
 <s id="33">Now, sleeping is delightful.</s>
 <s id="34">My favorite -- I mean, you could be upside down, right side up -- my favorite: curled up in a little ball and floating freely.</s>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">Laundry?</s>
  <s id="35.2">Nope.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="36">We load our dirty clothes into an empty supply ship and send it off into space.</s>
 <s id="37">The bathroom.</s>
 <s id="38">Everyone wants to know.</s>
 <s id="39">It's hard to understand, so I made a little video, because I wanted kids to understand that the principle of vacuum saves the day and that just a gentle breeze helps everything go where it is supposed to.</s>
 <s id="40">Well, in real life it does.</s>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">(Laughter) Recycling?</s>
  <s id="41.2">Of course.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">So we take our urine, we store it, we filter it and then we drink it.</s>
 <s id="43">And it's actually delicious.</s>
 <s id="44">(Laughter) Sitting around the table, eating food that looks bad but actually tastes pretty good.</s>
 <s id="45">But it's the gathering around the table that's important, I think both in space and on Earth, because that's what cements a crew together.</s>
 <s id="46">For me, music was a way to stay connected to the rest of the world.</s>
 <s id="47">I played a duet between Earth and space with Ian Anderson of Jethro Tull on the 50th anniversary of human spaceflight.</s>
 <s id="48">Connecting to family was so important.</s>
 <s id="49">I talked with my family almost every day the whole time I was up there, and I would actually read books to my son as a way for us just to be together.</s>
 <s id="50">So important.</s>
 <s id="51">Now, when the space station would go over Massachusetts, my family would run outside, and they would watch the brightest star sailing across the sky.</s>
 <s id="52">And when I looked down, I couldn't see my house, but it meant a lot to me to know that the people I loved the most were looking up while I was looking down.</s>
 <s id="53">So the space station, for me, is the place where mission and magic come together.</s>
 <s id="54">The mission, the work are vital steps in our quest to go further than our planet and imperative for understanding sustainability here on Earth.</s>
 <s id="55">I loved being a part of that, and if I could have taken my family with me, I never would have come home.</s>
 <s id="56">And so my view from the station showed me that we are all from the same place.</s>
 <s id="57">We all have our roles to play.</s>
 <s id="58">Because, the Earth is our ship.</s>
 <s id="59">Space is our home.</s>
 <s id="60">And we are the crew of Spaceship Earth.</s>
 <s id="61">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="62">(Applause)</s>
</text>
