<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">About 75 years ago, my grandfather, a young man, walked into a tent that was converted into a movie theater like that, and he fell hopelessly in love with the woman he saw on the silver screen: none other than Mae West, the heartthrob of the '30s, and he could never forget her.</s>
 <s id="2">In fact, when he had his daughter many years later, he wanted to name her after Mae West, but can you imagine an Indian child name Mae West?</s>
 <s id="3">The Indian family said, no way!</s>
 <s id="4">So when my twin brother Kaesava was born, he decided to tinker with the spelling of Keshava's name.</s>
 <s id="5">He said, if Mae West can be M-A-E, why can't Keshava be K-A-E?</s>
 <s id="6">So he changed Kaesava's spelling.</s>
 <s id="7">Now Kaesava had a baby boy called Rehan a couple of weeks ago.</s>
 <s id="8">He decided to spell, or, rather, misspell Raehan with an A-E.</s>
 <s id="9">You know, my grandfather died many years ago when I was little, but his love for Mae West lives on as a misspelling in the DNA of his progeny.</s>
 <p id="p10">
  <s id="10.1">That for me is successful legacy.</s>
  <s id="10.2">(Laughs) You know, as for me, my wife and I have our own crazy legacy project.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="11">We actually sit every few years, argue, disagree, fight, and actually come up with our very own 200-year plan.</s>
 <s id="12">Our friends think we're mad.</s>
 <s id="13">Our parents think we're cuckoo.</s>
 <s id="14">Because, you know, we both come from families that really look up to humility and wisdom, but we both like to live larger than life.</s>
 <s id="15">I believe in the concept of a Raja Yogi: Be a dude before you can become an ascetic.</s>
 <s id="16">This is me being a rock star, even if it's in my own house.</s>
 <s id="17">You know?</s>
 <s id="18">So when Netra and I sat down to make our first plan 10 years ago, we said we want the focus of this plan to go way beyond ourselves.</s>
 <s id="19">What do we mean by beyond ourselves?</s>
 <s id="20">Well 200 years, we calculated, is at the end of our direct contact with the world.</s>
 <s id="21">There's nobody I'll meet in my life will ever live beyond 200 years, so we thought that's a perfect place where we should situate our plan and let our imagination take flight.</s>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">You know, I never really believed in legacy.</s>
  <s id="22.2">What am I going to leave behind?</s>
  <s id="22.3">I'm an artist.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">Until I made a cartoon about 9/11.</s>
 <s id="24">It caused so much trouble for me.</s>
 <s id="25">I was so upset.</s>
 <s id="26">You know, a cartoon that was meant to be a cartoon of the week ended up staying so much longer.</s>
 <s id="27">Now I'm in the business of creating art that will definitely even outlive me, and I think about what I want to leave behind through those paintings.</s>
 <s id="28">You know, the 9/11 cartoon upset me so much that I decided I'll never cartoon again.</s>
 <s id="29">I said, I'm never going to make any honest public commentary again.</s>
 <s id="30">But of course I continued creating artwork that was honest and raw, because I forgot about how people reacted to my work.</s>
 <s id="31">You know, sometimes forgetting is so important to remain idealistic.</s>
 <s id="32">Perhaps loss of memory is so crucial for our survival as human beings.</s>
 <s id="33">One of the most important things in my 200-year plan that Netra and I write is what to forget about ourselves.</s>
 <s id="34">You know, we carry so much baggage, from our parents, from our society, from so many people -- fears, insecurities -- and our 200-year plan really lists all our childhood problems that we have to expire.</s>
 <s id="35">We actually put an expiry date on all our childhood problems.</s>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">The latest date I put was, I said, I am going to expire my fear of my leftist, feminist mother-in-law, and this today is the date!</s>
  <s id="36.2">(Laughs) She's watching.</s>
  <s id="36.3">(Laughter) Anyway, you know, I really make decisions all the time about how I want to remember myself, and that's the most important kind of decisions I make.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="37">And this directly translates into my paintings.</s>
 <s id="38">But like my friends, I can do that really well on Facebook, Pinterest, Twitter, Flickr, YouTube.</s>
 <s id="39">Name it, I'm on it.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">I've started outsourcing my memory to the digital world, you know?</s>
  <s id="40.2">But that comes with a problem.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="41">It's so easy to think of technology as a metaphor for memory, but our brains are not perfect storage devices like technology.</s>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">We only remember what we want to.</s>
  <s id="42.2">At least I do.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">And I rather think of our brains as biased curators of our memory, you know?</s>
  <s id="43.2">And if technology is not a metaphor for memory, what is it?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">Netra and I use our technology as a tool in our 200-year plan to really curate our digital legacy.</s>
 <s id="45">That is a picture of my mother, and she recently got a Facebook account.</s>
 <s id="46">You know where this is going.</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">And I've been very supportive until this picture shows up on my Facebook page.</s>
  <s id="47.2">(Laughter) And I actually untagged myself first, then I picked up the phone.</s>
  <s id="47.3">I said, "Mom, you will never put a picture of me in a bikini ever again."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">And she said, "Why?</s>
  <s id="48.2">You look so cute, darling."</s>
  <s id="48.3">I said, "You just don't understand."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="49">Maybe we are among the first generation that really understands this digital curating of ourselves.</s>
 <s id="50">Maybe we are the first to even actively record our lives.</s>
 <s id="51">You know, whether you agree with, you know, legacy or not, we are actually leaving behind digital traces all the time.</s>
 <s id="52">So Netra and I really wanted to use our 200-year plan to curate this digital legacy, and not only digital legacy but we believe in curating the legacy of my past and future.</s>
 <s id="53">How, you may ask?</s>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">Well, when I think of the future, I never see myself moving forward in time.</s>
  <s id="54.2">I actually see time moving backward towards me.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">I can actually visualize my future approaching.</s>
 <s id="56">I can dodge what I don't want and pull in what I want.</s>
 <p id="p57">
  <s id="57.1">It's like a video game obstacle course.</s>
  <s id="57.2">And I've gotten better and better at doing this.</s>
  <s id="57.3">Even when I make a painting, I actually imagine I'm behind the painting, it already exists, and someone's looking at it, and I see whether they're feeling it from their gut.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="58">Are they feeling it from their heart, or is it just a cerebral thing?</s>
 <s id="59">And it really informs my painting.</s>
 <s id="60">Even when I do an art show, I really think about, what should people walk away with?</s>
 <s id="61">I remember when I was 19, I did, I wanted to do my first art exhibition, and I wanted the whole world to know about it.</s>
 <p id="p62">
  <s id="62.1">I didn't know TED then, but what I did was I closed my eyes tight, and I started dreaming.</s>
  <s id="62.2">I could imagine people coming in, dressed up, looking beautiful, my paintings with all the light, and in my visualization I actually saw a very famous actress launching my show, giving credibility to me.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p63">
  <s id="63.1">And I woke up from my visualization and I said, who was that?</s>
  <s id="63.2">I couldn't tell if it was Shabana Azmi or Rekha, two very famous Indian actresses, like the Meryl Streeps of India.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="64">As it turned out, next morning I wrote a letter to both of them, and Shabana Azmi replied, and came and launched my very first show 12 years ago.</s>
 <p id="p65">
  <s id="65.1">And what a bang it started my career with!</s>
  <s id="65.2">You know, when we think of time in this way, we can curate not only the future but also the past.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="66">This is a picture of my family, and that is Netra, my wife.</s>
 <s id="67">She's the co-creator of my 200-year plan.</s>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">Netra's a high school history teacher.</s>
  <s id="68.2">I love Netra, but I hate history.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="69">I keep saying, "Nets, you live in the past while I'll create the future, and when I'm done, you can study about it."</s>
 <s id="70">(Laughter) She gave me an indulgent smile, and as punishment, she said, "Tomorrow I'm teaching a class on Indian history, and you are sitting in it, and I'm grading you."</s>
 <p id="p71">
  <s id="71.1">I'm like, "Oh, God."</s>
  <s id="71.2">I went.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p72">
  <s id="72.1">I actually went and sat in on her class.</s>
  <s id="72.2">She started by giving students primary source documents from India, Pakistan, from Britain, and I said, "Wow."</s>
  <s id="72.3">Then she asked them to separate fact from bias.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="73">I said, "Wow," again.</s>
 <s id="74">Then she said, "Choose your facts and biases and create an image of your own story of dignity."</s>
 <s id="75">History as an imaging tool?</s>
 <s id="76">I was so inspired.</s>
 <s id="77">I went and created my own version of Indian history.</s>
 <s id="78">I actually included stories from my grandmother.</s>
 <s id="79">She used to work for the telephone exchange, and she used to actually overhear conversations between Nehru and Edwina Mountbatten.</s>
 <p id="p80">
  <s id="80.1">And she used to hear all kinds of things she shouldn't have heard.</s>
  <s id="80.2">But, you know, I include things like that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="81">This is my version of Indian history.</s>
 <s id="82">You know, if this is so, it occurred to me that maybe, just maybe, the primary objective of our brains is to serve our dignity.</s>
 <s id="83">Go tell Facebook to figure that out!</s>
 <p id="p84">
  <s id="84.1">Netra and I don't write our 200-year plan for someone else to come and execute it in 150 years.</s>
  <s id="84.2">Imagine receiving a parcel saying, from the past, okay now you're supposed to spend the rest of your life doing all of this.</s>
  <s id="84.3">No.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="85">We actually write it only to set our attitudes right.</s>
 <s id="86">You know, I used to believe that education is the most important tool to leave a meaningful legacy.</s>
 <s id="87">Education is great.</s>
 <s id="88">It really teaches us who we are, and helps us contextualize ourselves in the world, but it's really my creativity that's taught me that I can be much more than what my education told me I am.</s>
 <s id="89">I'd like to make the argument that creativity is the most important tool we have.</s>
 <s id="90">It lets us create who we are, and curate what is to come.</s>
 <s id="91">I like to think -- Thank you.</s>
 <p id="p92">
  <s id="92.1">I like to think of myself as a storyteller, where my past and my future are only stories, my stories, waiting to be told and retold.</s>
  <s id="92.2">I hope all of you one day get a chance to share and write your own 200-year story.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="93">Thank you so much.</s>
 <p id="p94">
  <s id="94.1">Shukran!</s>
  <s id="94.2">(Applause)</s>
 </p>
</text>
