<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">It is a dream of mankind to fly like a bird.</s>
 <s id="2">Birds are very agile.</s>
 <s id="3">They fly, not with rotating components, so they fly only by flapping their wings.</s>
 <s id="4">So we looked at the birds, and we tried to make a model that is powerful, ultralight, and it must have excellent aerodynamic qualities that would fly by its own and only by flapping its wings.</s>
 <s id="5">So what would be better than to use the herring gull, in its freedom, circling and swooping over the sea, and to use this as a role model?</s>
 <s id="6">So we bring a team together.</s>
 <s id="7">There are generalists and also specialists in the field of aerodynamics, in the field of building gliders.</s>
 <s id="8">And the task was to build an ultralight indoor-flying model that is able to fly over your heads.</s>
 <s id="9">So be careful later on.</s>
 <s id="10">(Laughter) And this was one issue: to build it that lightweight that no one would be hurt if it fell down.</s>
 <s id="11">So why do we do all this?</s>
 <s id="12">We are a company in the field of automation, and we'd like to do very lightweight structures because that's energy efficient, and we'd like to learn more about pneumatics and air flow phenomena.</s>
 <s id="13">So I now would like you to put your seat belts on and put your hats on.</s>
 <s id="14">So maybe we'll try it once -- to fly a SmartBird.</s>
 <s id="15">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="16">(Applause) (Cheers) (Applause) (Applause ends) (Applause) So we can now look at the SmartBird.</s>
 <s id="17">So here is one without a skin.</s>
 <s id="18">We have a wingspan of about two meters.</s>
 <s id="19">The length is one meter and six, and the weight is only 450 grams.</s>
 <s id="20">And it is all out of carbon fiber.</s>
 <s id="21">In the middle we have a motor, and we also have a gear in it, and we use the gear to transfer the circulation of the motor.</s>
 <s id="22">So within the motor, we have three Hall sensors, so we know exactly where the wing is.</s>
 <s id="23">And if we now beat up and down -- (Mechanical sounds) We have the possibility to fly like a bird.</s>
 <s id="24">So if you go down, you have the large area of propulsion, and if you go up, the wings are not that large, and it is easier to get up.</s>
 <s id="25">So, the next thing we did, or the challenges we did, was to coordinate this movement.</s>
 <s id="26">We have to turn it, go up and go down.</s>
 <s id="27">We have a split wing.</s>
 <s id="28">With the split wing, we get the lift at the upper wing, and we get the propulsion at the lower wing.</s>
 <s id="29">Also, we see how we measure the aerodynamic efficiency.</s>
 <s id="30">We had knowledge about the electromechanical efficiency and then we can calculate the aerodynamic efficiency.</s>
 <s id="31">So therefore, it rises up from passive torsion to active torsion, from 30 percent up to 80 percent.</s>
 <s id="32">Next thing we have to do, we have to control and regulate the whole structure.</s>
 <s id="33">Only if you control and regulate it, you will get that aerodynamic efficiency.</s>
 <s id="34">So the overall consumption of energy is about 25 watts at takeoff and 16 to 18 watts in flight.</s>
 <s id="35">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="36">(Applause) Bruno Giussani: Markus, we should fly it once more.</s>
 <s id="37">Markus Fischer: Yeah, sure.</s>
 <s id="38">(Audience) Yeah!</s>
 <s id="39">(Laughter) (Gasps) (Cheers) (Applause)</s>
</text>
