<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So today, I want us to reflect on the demise of guys.</s>
 <s id="2">Guys are flaming out academically; they're wiping out socially with girls and sexually with women.</s>
 <s id="3">Other than that, there's not much of a problem.</s>
 <s id="4">So what's the data?</s>
 <s id="5">So the data on dropping out is amazing.</s>
 <s id="6">Boys are 30 percent more likely than girls to drop out of school.</s>
 <s id="7">In Canada, five boys drop out for every three girls.</s>
 <s id="8">Girls outperform boys now at every level, from elementary school to graduate school.</s>
 <s id="9">There's a 10 percent differential between getting BA's and all graduate programs, with guys falling behind girls.</s>
 <s id="10">Two-thirds of all students in special ed. remedial programs are guys.</s>
 <s id="11">And as you all know, boys are five times more likely than girls to be labeled as having attention deficit disorder -- and therefore we drug them with Ritalin.</s>
 <s id="12">What's the evidence of wiping out?</s>
 <s id="13">First, it's a new fear of intimacy.</s>
 <s id="14">Intimacy means physical, emotional connection with somebody else -- and especially with somebody of the opposite sex who gives off ambiguous, contradictory, phosphorescent signals.</s>
 <s id="15">(Laughter) And every year there's research done on self-reported shyness among college students.</s>
 <s id="16">And we're seeing a steady increase among males.</s>
 <s id="17">And this is two kinds.</s>
 <s id="18">It's a social awkwardness.</s>
 <s id="19">The old shyness was a fear of rejection.</s>
 <s id="20">It's a social awkwardness like you're a stranger in a foreign land.</s>
 <s id="21">They don't know what to say, they don't know what to do, especially one-on-one [with the] opposite sex.</s>
 <s id="22">They don't know the language of face contact, the non-verbal and verbal set of rules that enable you to comfortably talk to somebody else, listen to somebody else.</s>
 <s id="23">There's something I'm developing here called social intensity syndrome, which tries to account for why guys really prefer male bonding over female mating.</s>
 <s id="24">It turns out, from earliest childhood, boys, and then men, prefer the company of guys -- physical company.</s>
 <s id="25">And there's actually a cortical arousal we're looking at, because guys have been with guys in teams, in clubs, in gangs, in fraternities, especially in the military, and then in pubs.</s>
 <s id="26">And this peaks at Super Bowl Sunday when guys would rather be in a bar with strangers, watching a totally overdressed Aaron Rodgers of the Green Bay Packers, rather than Jennifer Lopez totally naked in the bedroom.</s>
 <s id="27">The problem is they now prefer [the] asynchronistic Internet world to the spontaneous interaction in social relationships.</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">What are the causes?</s>
  <s id="28.2">Well, it's an unintended consequence.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">I think it's excessive Internet use in general, excessive video gaming, excessive new access to pornography.</s>
 <s id="30">The problem is these are arousal addictions.</s>
 <s id="31">Drug addiction, you simply want more.</s>
 <s id="32">Arousal addiction, you want different.</s>
 <s id="33">Drugs, you want more of the same -- different.</s>
 <s id="34">So you need the novelty in order for the arousal to be sustained.</s>
 <s id="35">And the problem is the industry is supplying it.</s>
 <s id="36">Jane McGonigal told us last year that by the time a boy is 21, he's played 10,000 hours of video games, most of that in isolation.</s>
 <s id="37">As you remember, Cindy Gallop said men don't know the difference between making love and doing porn.</s>
 <s id="38">The average boy now watches 50 porn video clips a week.</s>
 <s id="39">And there's some guy watching a hundred, obviously.</s>
 <s id="40">(Laughter) And the porn industry is the fastest growing industry in America -- 15 billion annually.</s>
 <s id="41">For every 400 movies made in Hollywood, there are 11,000 now made porn videos.</s>
 <s id="42">So the effect, very quickly, is it's a new kind of arousal.</s>
 <s id="43">Boys' brains are being digitally rewired in a totally new way for change, novelty, excitement and constant arousal.</s>
 <s id="44">That means they're totally out of sync in traditional classes, which are analog, static, interactively passive.</s>
 <s id="45">They're also totally out of sync in romantic relationships, which build gradually and subtly.</s>
 <p id="p46">
  <s id="46.1">So what's the solution?</s>
  <s id="46.2">It's not my job.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">I'm here to alarm.</s>
  <s id="47.2">It's your job to solve.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">(Laughter) (Applause) But who should care?</s>
  <s id="48.2">The only people who should care about this is parents of boys and girls, educators, gamers, filmmakers and women who would like a real man who they can talk to, who can dance, who can make love slowly and contribute to the evolutionary pressures to keep our species above banana slugs.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">No offense to banana slug owners.</s>
  <s id="49.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">(Applause)</s>
</text>
