<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Imagine, if you will -- a gift.</s>
 <s id="2">I'd like for you to picture it in your mind.</s>
 <s id="3">It's not too big -- about the size of a golf ball.</s>
 <s id="4">So envision what it looks like all wrapped up.</s>
 <s id="5">But before I show you what's inside, I will tell you, it's going to do incredible things for you.</s>
 <s id="6">It will bring all of your family together.</s>
 <s id="7">You will feel loved and appreciated like never before and reconnect with friends and acquaintances you haven't heard from in years.</s>
 <s id="8">Adoration and admiration will overwhelm you.</s>
 <s id="9">It will recalibrate what's most important in your life.</s>
 <s id="10">It will redefine your sense of spirituality and faith.</s>
 <s id="11">You'll have a new understanding and trust in your body.</s>
 <s id="12">You'll have unsurpassed vitality and energy.</s>
 <s id="13">You'll expand your vocabulary, meet new people, and you'll have a healthier lifestyle.</s>
 <s id="14">And get this -- you'll have an eight-week vacation of doing absolutely nothing.</s>
 <s id="15">You'll eat countless gourmet meals.</s>
 <s id="16">Flowers will arrive by the truckload.</s>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">People will say to you, "You look great.</s>
  <s id="17.2">Have you had any work done?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="18">And you'll have a lifetime supply of good drugs.</s>
 <s id="19">You'll be challenged, inspired, motivated and humbled.</s>
 <s id="20">Your life will have new meaning.</s>
 <s id="21">Peace, health, serenity, happiness, nirvana.</s>
 <s id="22">The price?</s>
 <s id="23">$55,000, and that's an incredible deal.</s>
 <s id="24">By now I know you're dying to know what it is and where you can get one.</s>
 <s id="25">Does Amazon carry it?</s>
 <s id="26">Does it have the Apple logo on it?</s>
 <s id="27">Is there a waiting list?</s>
 <s id="28">Not likely.</s>
 <s id="29">This gift came to me about five months ago.</s>
 <s id="30">It looked more like this when it was all wrapped up -- not quite so pretty.</s>
 <s id="31">And this, and then this.</s>
 <s id="32">It was a rare gem -- a brain tumor, hemangioblastoma -- the gift that keeps on giving.</s>
 <s id="33">And while I'm okay now, I wouldn't wish this gift for you.</s>
 <s id="34">I'm not sure you'd want it.</s>
 <s id="35">But I wouldn't change my experience.</s>
 <s id="36">It profoundly altered my life in ways I didn't expect in all the ways I just shared with you.</s>
 <s id="37">So the next time you're faced with something that's unexpected, unwanted and uncertain, consider that it just may be a gift.</s>
 <s id="38">(Applause)</s>
</text>
