<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">One way to change our genes is to make new ones, as Craig Venter has so elegantly shown.</s>
 <s id="2">Another is to change our lifestyles.</s>
 <s id="3">And what we're learning is how powerful and dynamic these changes can be, that you don't have to wait very long to see the benefits.</s>
 <s id="4">When you eat healthier, manage stress, exercise and love more, your brain actually gets more blood flow and more oxygen.</s>
 <s id="5">But more than that, your brain gets measurably bigger.</s>
 <s id="6">Things that were thought impossible just a few years ago can actually be measured now.</s>
 <s id="7">This was figured out by Robin Williams a few years before the rest of us.</s>
 <s id="8">Now, there's some things that you can do to make your brain grow new brain cells.</s>
 <s id="9">Some of my favorite things, like chocolate and tea, blueberries, alcohol in moderation, stress management and cannabinoids found in marijuana.</s>
 <s id="10">I'm just the messenger.</s>
 <s id="11">(Laughter) What were we just talking about?</s>
 <s id="12">(Laughter) And other things that can make it worse, that can cause you to lose brain cells.</s>
 <s id="13">The usual suspects, like saturated fat and sugar, nicotine, opiates, cocaine, too much alcohol and chronic stress.</s>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">Your skin gets more blood flow when you change your lifestyle, so you age less quickly.</s>
  <s id="14.2">Your skin doesn't wrinkle as much.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="15">Your heart gets more blood flow.</s>
 <s id="16">We've shown that you can actually reverse heart disease.</s>
 <s id="17">That these clogged arteries that you see on the upper left, after only a year become measurably less clogged.</s>
 <s id="18">And the cardiac PET scan shown on the lower left, the blue means no blood flow.</s>
 <s id="19">A year later -- orange and white is maximum blood flow.</s>
 <s id="20">We've shown you may be able to stop and reverse the progression of early prostate cancer and, by extension, breast cancer, simply by making these changes.</s>
 <s id="21">We've found that tumor growth in vitro was inhibited 70 percent in the group that made these changes, whereas only nine percent in the comparison group.</s>
 <s id="22">These differences were highly significant.</s>
 <s id="23">Even your sexual organs get more blood flow, so you increase sexual potency.</s>
 <s id="24">One of the most effective anti-smoking ads was done by the Department of Health Services, showing that nicotine, which constricts your arteries, can cause a heart attack or a stroke, but it also causes impotence.</s>
 <s id="25">Half of guys who smoke are impotent.</s>
 <s id="26">How sexy is that?</s>
 <s id="27">Now we're also about to publish a study -- the first study showing you can change gene expression in men with prostate cancer.</s>
 <s id="28">This is what's called a heat map -- and the different colors -- and along the side, on the right, are different genes.</s>
 <s id="29">And we found that over 500 genes were favorably changed -- in effect, turning on the good genes, the disease-preventing genes, turning off the disease-promoting genes.</s>
 <s id="30">And so these findings I think are really very powerful, giving many people new hope and new choices.</s>
 <s id="31">And companies like Navigenics and DNA Direct and 23andMe, that are giving you your genetic profiles, are giving some people a sense of, "Gosh, well, what can I do about it?"</s>
 <s id="32">Well, our genes are not our fate, and if we make these changes -- they're a predisposition -- but if we make bigger changes than we might have made otherwise, we can actually change how our genes are expressed.</s>
 <s id="33">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="34">(Applause)</s>
</text>
