<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">We are losing our listening.</s>
 <s id="2">We spend roughly 60 percent of our communication time listening, but we're not very good at it.</s>
 <s id="3">We retain just 25 percent of what we hear.</s>
 <s id="4">Now -- not you, not this talk, but that is generally true.</s>
 <s id="5">(Laughter) Let's define listening as making meaning from sound.</s>
 <s id="6">It's a mental process, and it's a process of extraction.</s>
 <s id="7">We use some pretty cool techniques to do this.</s>
 <s id="8">One of them is pattern recognition.</s>
 <s id="9">(Crowd noises) So in a cocktail party like this, if I say, "David, Sara, pay attention" -- some of you just sat up.</s>
 <s id="10">We recognize patterns to distinguish noise from signal, and especially our name.</s>
 <s id="11">Differencing is another technique we use.</s>
 <s id="12">If I left this pink noise on for more than a couple of minutes, (Pink noise) you would literally cease to hear it.</s>
 <s id="13">We listen to differences; we discount sounds that remain the same.</s>
 <s id="14">And then there is a whole range of filters.</s>
 <s id="15">These filters take us from all sound down to what we pay attention to.</s>
 <s id="16">Most people are entirely unconscious of these filters.</s>
 <s id="17">But they actually create our reality in a way, because they tell us what we're paying attention to right now.</s>
 <s id="18">I'll give you one example of that.</s>
 <s id="19">Intention is very important in sound, in listening.</s>
 <s id="20">When I married my wife, I promised her I would listen to her every day as if for the first time.</s>
 <s id="21">Now that's something I fall short of on a daily basis.</s>
 <s id="22">(Laughter) But it's a great intention to have in a relationship.</s>
 <s id="23">(Laughter) But that's not all.</s>
 <s id="24">Sound places us in space and in time.</s>
 <s id="25">If you close your eyes right now in this room, you're aware of the size of the room from the reverberation and the bouncing of the sound off the surfaces; you're aware of how many people are around you, because of the micro-noises you're receiving.</s>
 <s id="26">And sound places us in time as well, because sound always has time embedded in it.</s>
 <s id="27">In fact, I would suggest that our listening is the main way that we experience the flow of time from past to future.</s>
 <s id="28">So, "Sonority is time and meaning" -- a great quote.</s>
 <s id="29">I said at the beginning, we're losing our listening.</s>
 <s id="30">Why did I say that?</s>
 <s id="31">Well, there are a lot of reasons for this.</s>
 <s id="32">First of all, we invented ways of recording -- first writing, then audio recording and now video recording as well.</s>
 <s id="33">The premium on accurate and careful listening has simply disappeared.</s>
 <s id="34">Secondly, the world is now so noisy, (Noise) with this cacophony going on visually and auditorily, it's just hard to listen; it's tiring to listen.</s>
 <s id="35">Many people take refuge in headphones, but they turn big, public spaces like this, shared soundscapes, into millions of tiny, little personal sound bubbles.</s>
 <s id="36">In this scenario, nobody's listening to anybody.</s>
 <s id="37">We're becoming impatient.</s>
 <s id="38">We don't want oratory anymore; we want sound bites.</s>
 <s id="39">And the art of conversation is being replaced -- dangerously, I think -- by personal broadcasting.</s>
 <s id="40">I don't know how much listening there is in this conversation, which is sadly very common, especially in the UK.</s>
 <s id="41">We're becoming desensitized.</s>
 <s id="42">Our media have to scream at us with these kinds of headlines in order to get our attention.</s>
 <s id="43">And that means it's harder for us to pay attention to the quiet, the subtle, the understated.</s>
 <s id="44">This is a serious problem that we're losing our listening.</s>
 <s id="45">This is not trivial, because listening is our access to understanding.</s>
 <s id="46">Conscious listening always creates understanding, and only without conscious listening can these things happen.</s>
 <s id="47">A world where we don't listen to each other at all is a very scary place indeed.</s>
 <s id="48">So I'd like to share with you five simple exercises, tools you can take away with you, to improve your own conscious listening.</s>
 <s id="49">Would you like that?</s>
 <s id="50">Audience: Yes!</s>
 <p id="p51">
  <s id="51.1">Good.</s>
  <s id="51.2">The first one is silence.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="52">Just three minutes a day of silence is a wonderful exercise to reset your ears and to recalibrate, so that you can hear the quiet again.</s>
 <s id="53">If you can't get absolute silence, go for quiet, that's absolutely fine.</s>
 <s id="54">Second, I call this "the mixer."</s>
 <s id="55">(Noise) So even if you're in a noisy environment like this -- and we all spend a lot of time in places like this -- listen in the coffee bar to how many channels of sound can I hear?</s>
 <s id="56">How many individual channels in that mix am I listening to?</s>
 <s id="57">You can do it in a beautiful place as well, like in a lake.</s>
 <s id="58">How many birds am I hearing?</s>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">Where are they?</s>
  <s id="59.2">Where are those ripples?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="60">It's a great exercise for improving the quality of your listening.</s>
 <s id="61">Third, this exercise I call "savoring," and this is a beautiful exercise.</s>
 <s id="62">It's about enjoying mundane sounds.</s>
 <s id="63">This, for example, is my tumble dryer.</s>
 <s id="64">(Dryer) It's a waltz -- one, two, three; one, two, three; one, two, three.</s>
 <s id="65">I love it!</s>
 <s id="66">Or just try this one on for size.</s>
 <s id="67">(Coffee grinder) Wow!</s>
 <s id="68">So, mundane sounds can be really interesting -- if you pay attention.</s>
 <s id="69">I call that the "hidden choir" -- it's around us all the time.</s>
 <s id="70">The next exercise is probably the most important of all of these, if you just take one thing away.</s>
 <s id="71">This is listening positions -- the idea that you can move your listening position to what's appropriate to what you're listening to.</s>
 <s id="72">This is playing with those filters.</s>
 <s id="73">Remember I gave you those filters?</s>
 <s id="74">It's starting to play with them as levers, to get conscious about them and to move to different places.</s>
 <s id="75">These are just some of the listening positions, or scales of listening positions, that you can use.</s>
 <s id="76">There are many.</s>
 <p id="p77">
  <s id="77.1">Have fun with that.</s>
  <s id="77.2">It's very exciting.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="78">And finally, an acronym.</s>
 <s id="79">You can use this in listening, in communication.</s>
 <s id="80">If you're in any one of those roles -- and I think that probably is everybody who's listening to this talk -- the acronym is RASA, which is the Sanskrit word for "juice" or "essence."</s>
 <s id="81">And RASA stands for "Receive," which means pay attention to the person; "Appreciate," making little noises like "hmm," "oh," "OK"; "Summarize" -- the word "so" is very important in communication; and "Ask," ask questions afterwards.</s>
 <s id="82">Now sound is my passion, it's my life.</s>
 <p id="p83">
  <s id="83.1">I wrote a whole book about it.</s>
  <s id="83.2">So I live to listen.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="84">That's too much to ask for most people.</s>
 <s id="85">But I believe that every human being needs to listen consciously in order to live fully -- connected in space and in time to the physical world around us, connected in understanding to each other, not to mention spiritually connected, because every spiritual path I know of has listening and contemplation at its heart.</s>
 <s id="86">That's why we need to teach listening in our schools as a skill.</s>
 <p id="p87">
  <s id="87.1">Why is it not taught?</s>
  <s id="87.2">It's crazy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="88">And if we can teach listening in our schools, we can take our listening off that slippery slope to that dangerous, scary world that I talked about, and move it to a place where everybody is consciously listening all the time, or at least capable of doing it.</s>
 <s id="89">Now, I don't know how to do that, but this is TED, and I think the TED community is capable of anything.</s>
 <s id="90">So I invite you to connect with me, connect with each other, take this mission out.</s>
 <s id="91">And let's get listening taught in schools, and transform the world in one generation to a conscious, listening world -- a world of connection, a world of understanding and a world of peace.</s>
 <s id="92">Thank you for listening to me today.</s>
 <s id="93">(Applause)</s>
</text>
