<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Why do we cringe when we hear "Shakespeare?"</s>
 <s id="2">If you ask me, it's usually because of his words.</s>
 <s id="3">All those thines and thous and therefores and wherefore-art-thous can be more than a little annoying.</s>
 <s id="4">But you have to wonder, why is he so popular?</s>
 <s id="5">Why have his plays been made and remade more than any other playwright?</s>
 <s id="6">It's because of his words.</s>
 <s id="7">Back in the late 1500s and early 1600s, that was the best tool that a person had, and there was a lot to talk about.</s>
 <s id="8">However, most of it was pretty depressing.</s>
 <s id="9">You know, with the Black Plague and all.</s>
 <s id="10">Shakespeare does use a lot of words.</s>
 <s id="11">One of his most impressive accomplishments is his use of insults.</s>
 <s id="12">They would unify the entire audience; and no matter where you sat, you could laugh at what was going on onstage.</s>
 <s id="13">Words, specifically dialogue in a drama setting, are used for many different reasons: to set the mood of the scene, to give some more atmosphere to the setting, and to develop relationships between characters.</s>
 <s id="14">Insults do this in a very short and sharp way.</s>
 <s id="15">Let's first go to "Hamlet."</s>
 <s id="16">Right before this dialogue, Polonius is the father of Ophelia, who is in love with Prince Hamlet.</s>
 <s id="17">King Claudius is trying to figure out why Prince Hamlet is acting so crazy since the king married Prince Hamlet's mother.</s>
 <s id="18">Polonius offers to use his daughter to get information from Prince Hamlet.</s>
 <s id="19">Then we go into Act II Scene 2.</s>
 <s id="20">Polonius: "Do you know me, my lord?"</s>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">Hamlet: "Excellent well.</s>
  <s id="21.2">You're a fishmonger."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="22">Polonius: "Not I, my lord."</s>
 <s id="23">Hamlet: "Then I would you were so honest a man."</s>
 <s id="24">Now, even if you did not know what "fishmonger" meant, you can use some contextual clues.</s>
 <s id="25">One: Polonius reacted in a negative way, so it must be bad.</s>
 <s id="26">Two: Fish smell bad, so it must be bad.</s>
 <s id="27">And three: "monger" just doesn't sound like a good word.</s>
 <s id="28">So from not even knowing the meaning, you're beginning to construct some characterization of the relationship between Hamlet and Polonius, which was not good.</s>
 <s id="29">But if you dig some more, "fishmonger" means a broker of some type, and in this setting, would mean like a pimp, like Polonius is brokering out his daughter for money, which he is doing for the king's favor.</s>
 <s id="30">This allows you to see that Hamlet is not as crazy as he's claiming to be, and intensifies the animosity between these two characters.</s>
 <s id="31">Want another example?</s>
 <s id="32">"Romeo and Juliet" has some of the best insults of any of Shakespeare's plays.</s>
 <s id="33">It's a play about two gangs, and the star-crossed lovers that take their own lives.</s>
 <s id="34">Well, with any fisticuffs you know that there is some serious smack talk going on.</s>
 <s id="35">And you are not disappointed.</s>
 <s id="36">In Act I Scene 1, right from the get-go we are shown the level of distrust and hatred the members of the two families, the Capulets and Montagues, meet.</s>
 <s id="37">Gregory: "I will frown as I pass by, and let them take it as they list."</s>
 <s id="38">Sampson: "Nay, as they dare, I will bite my thumb at them, which is a disgrace to them, if they bear it."</s>
 <s id="39">Enter Abraham and Balthasar.</s>
 <s id="40">Abraham: "Do you bite your thumb at us, sir?"</s>
 <s id="41">Sampson: "I do bite my thumb, sir."</s>
 <s id="42">Abraham: "Do you bite your thumb at us, sir?"</s>
 <s id="43">Okay, so how does this development help us understand mood or character?</s>
 <s id="44">Well, let's break it down to the insult.</s>
 <s id="45">Biting your thumb today may not seem like a big deal, but Sampson says it is an insult to them.</s>
 <s id="46">If they take it so, it must have been one.</s>
 <s id="47">This begins to show us the level of animosity between even the men who work for the two Houses.</s>
 <s id="48">And you normally would not do anything to someone unless you wanted to provoke them into a fight, which is exactly what's about to happen.</s>
 <s id="49">Looking deeper, biting your thumb in the time in which the play was written is like giving someone the finger today.</s>
 <s id="50">A pretty strong feeling comes with that, so we now are beginning to feel the tension in the scene.</s>
 <s id="51">Later on in the scene, Tybalt, from the House of the Capulets, lays a good one on Benvolio from the House of the Montagues.</s>
 <s id="52">Tybalt: "What, art thou drawn among these heartless hinds?</s>
 <s id="53">Turn thee, Benvolio, and look upon thy death."</s>
 <s id="54">Benvolio: "I do but keep the peace; put up thy sword, or manage it to part these men with me."</s>
 <s id="55">Tybalt: "What, drawn and talk of peace!</s>
 <s id="56">I hate the word, as I hate hell, all Montagues, and thee.</s>
 <s id="57">Have at thee, coward!"</s>
 <s id="58">Okay, heartless hinds.</s>
 <s id="59">We know that once again, it's not a good thing.</s>
 <s id="60">Both families hate each other, and this is just adding fuel to the fire.</s>
 <s id="61">But just how bad is this stinger?</s>
 <s id="62">A heartless hind is a coward, and calling someone that in front of his own men, and the rival family, means there's going to be a fight.</s>
 <s id="63">Tybalt basically calls out Benvolio, and in order to keep his honor, Benvolio has to fight.</s>
 <s id="64">This dialogue gives us a good look at the characterization between these two characters.</s>
 <s id="65">Tybalt thinks that the Montagues are nothing but cowardly dogs, and has no respect for them.</s>
 <s id="66">Once again, adding dramatic tension to the scene.</s>
 <s id="67">Okay, now here's a spoiler alert.</s>
 <s id="68">Tybalt's hotheadedness and severe hatred of the Montagues is what we literature people call his hamartia, or what causes his downfall.</s>
 <s id="69">Oh, yes.</s>
 <s id="70">He goes down at the hands of Romeo.</s>
 <s id="71">So when you're looking at Shakespeare, stop and look at the words, because they really are trying to tell you something.</s>
</text>
