<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">At a Maryland country fair in 2017, the prize pigs were not looking their best.</s>
 <s id="2">Farmers reported feverish hogs with inflamed eyes and running snouts.</s>
 <s id="3">But while fair officials worried about the pigs, the Maryland department of health was concerned about a group of sick fairgoers.</s>
 <s id="4">Some had pet the pigs, while others had merely been near their barns; but soon, 40 of these attendees would be diagnosed with swine flu.</s>
 <s id="5">More often than not, sick animals don’t infect humans.</s>
 <s id="6">But when they do, these cross-species infections, or viral host jumps, have the potential to produce deadly epidemics.</s>
 <s id="7">So how can pathogens from one species infect another, and what makes host jumps so dangerous?</s>
 <s id="8">Viruses are a type of organic parasite infecting nearly all forms of life.</s>
 <s id="9">To survive and reproduce, they must move through three stages: contact with a susceptible host, infection and replication, and transmission to other individuals.</s>
 <s id="10">As an example, let’s look at human influenza.</s>
 <s id="11">First, the flu virus encounters a new host and makes its way into their respiratory tract.</s>
 <s id="12">This isn’t so difficult, but to survive in this new body, the virus must mount a successful infection before it’s caught and broken down by an immune response.</s>
 <s id="13">To accomplish this task, viruses have evolved specific interactions with their host species.</s>
 <s id="14">Human flu viruses are covered in proteins adapted to bind with matching receptors on human respiratory cells.</s>
 <s id="15">Once inside a cell, the virus employs additional adaptations to hijack the host cell’s reproductive machinery and replicate its own genetic material.</s>
 <s id="16">Now the virus only needs to suppress or evade the host’s immune system long enough to replicate to sufficient levels and infect more cells.</s>
 <s id="17">At this point, the flu can be passed on to its next victim via any transmission of infected bodily fluid.</s>
 <s id="18">However, this simple sneeze also brings the virus in contact with pets, plants, or even your lunch.</s>
 <s id="19">Viruses are constantly encountering new species and attempting to infect them.</s>
 <s id="20">More often than not, this ends in failure.</s>
 <s id="21">In most cases, the genetic dissimilarity between the two hosts is too great.</s>
 <s id="22">For a virus adapted to infect humans, a lettuce cell would be a foreign and inhospitable landscape.</s>
 <s id="23">But there are a staggering number of viruses circulating in the environment, all with the potential to encounter new hosts.</s>
 <s id="24">And because viruses rapidly reproduce by the millions, they can quickly develop random mutations.</s>
 <s id="25">Most mutations will have no effect, or even prove detrimental; but a small proportion may enable the pathogen to better infect a new species.</s>
 <s id="26">The odds of winning this destructive genetic lottery increase over time, or if the new species is closely related to the virus’ usual host.</s>
 <s id="27">For a virus adapted to another mammal, infecting a human might just take a few lucky mutations.</s>
 <s id="28">And a virus adapted to chimpanzees, one of our closest genetic relatives, might barely require any changes at all.</s>
 <s id="29">It takes more than time and genetic similarity for a host jump to be successful.</s>
 <s id="30">Some viruses come equipped to easily infect a new host’s cells, but are then unable to evade an immune response.</s>
 <s id="31">Others might have a difficult time transmitting to new hosts.</s>
 <s id="32">For example, they might make the host’s blood contagious, but not their saliva.</s>
 <s id="33">However, once a host jump reaches the transmission stage, the virus becomes much more dangerous.</s>
 <s id="34">Now gestating within two hosts, the pathogen has twice the odds of mutating into a more successful virus.</s>
 <s id="35">And each new host increases the potential for a full-blown epidemic.</s>
 <s id="36">Virologists are constantly looking for mutations that might make viruses such as influenza more likely to jump.</s>
 <s id="37">However, predicting the next potential epidemic is a major challenge.</s>
 <s id="38">There’s a huge diversity of viruses that we’re only just beginning to uncover.</s>
 <s id="39">Researchers are tirelessly studying the biology of these pathogens.</s>
 <s id="40">And by monitoring populations to quickly identify new outbreaks, they can develop vaccines and containment protocols to stop these deadly diseases.</s>
</text>
