<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The most complex problems in our time can be solved with simple techniques, if we are able to dream.</s>
 <s id="2">As a child, I discovered that creativity is the key to cross from dreams to reality.</s>
 <s id="3">I learned this from my grandmother, Dr. Ruth Tichauer, a Jewish refugee that settled in the heart of the Andes.</s>
 <s id="4">That is how I grew up: encouraged to see beyond any limitation.</s>
 <s id="5">So part of my education included helping her in remote, indigenous communities.</s>
 <s id="6">I cherish those memories, because they helped me to understand life outside the city, a life with a lot of possibilities, without barriers, as language or culture.</s>
 <p id="p7">
  <s id="7.1">During those trips, my grandmother used to recite a Kipling poem: "Something hidden.</s>
  <s id="7.2">Go and find it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="8">Go and look behind the Mountains.</s>
 <s id="9">Something lost behind the mountains.</s>
 <p id="p10">
  <s id="10.1">Lost and waiting for you.</s>
  <s id="10.2">Go!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="11">In the coming years, I became a medical student.</s>
 <s id="12">One of every hundred children born worldwide has some kind of heart disease.</s>
 <s id="13">There's a part of this problem I think I can solve -- the part of this problem I have spent my life working on.</s>
 <s id="14">The problem starts during pregnancy.</s>
 <s id="15">The fetus needs to survive inside the mother.</s>
 <s id="16">Survival depends on communication between the systemic and the pulmonary blood.</s>
 <s id="17">At the moment of birth, this communication needs to stop.</s>
 <s id="18">If it doesn't close, the baby has a hole in the heart.</s>
 <s id="19">It is caused by prematurity and genetic conditions.</s>
 <s id="20">But what we know today is that a lack of oxygen is also one of the causes.</s>
 <s id="21">As you can see in the chart, the frequency of this kind of hole dramatically increases with altitude.</s>
 <s id="22">Video: (Baby crying) When you look at patients with this condition, they seem desperate to breathe.</s>
 <s id="23">To close the hole, major surgery used to be the only solution.</s>
 <s id="24">One night, my friend Malte, were camping in the Amazon region.</s>
 <s id="25">The only thing that would not burn in the fire was a green avocado branch.</s>
 <s id="26">Then came a moment of inspiration.</s>
 <s id="27">So we used the branch as a mold for our first invention.</s>
 <s id="28">The holes in children's hearts can be closed with it.</s>
 <s id="29">A coil is a piece of wire wrapped onto itself.</s>
 <s id="30">It maybe doesn't look so fancy to you now, but that was our first successful attempt to create a device for this major problem.</s>
 <s id="31">In this video, we can see how a very tiny catheter takes the coil to the heart.</s>
 <s id="32">The coil then closes the hole.</s>
 <s id="33">After that moment of inspiration, there came a very long time of effort developing a prototype.</s>
 <s id="34">In vitro and in vivo studies took thousands of hours of work in the lab.</s>
 <s id="35">The coil, if it works, can save lives.</s>
 <s id="36">I returned from Germany to Bolivia, thinking that wherever we go, we have the opportunity to make a difference.</s>
 <s id="37">With my wife and partner, Dr. Alexandra Heath, we started to see patients.</s>
 <s id="38">After successfully treating patients with our coil, we felt really enthusiastic.</s>
 <s id="39">But we live in a place that is 12,000 feet high.</s>
 <s id="40">And, the patients there need a special device to solve their heart condition.</s>
 <s id="41">The hole in altitude patients is different, because the orifice between the arteries is larger.</s>
 <s id="42">Most patients cannot afford to be treated on time, and they die.</s>
 <s id="43">The first coil could successfully treat only half of the patients in Bolivia.</s>
 <s id="44">The search started again.</s>
 <s id="45">We went back to the drawing board.</s>
 <s id="46">After many trials, and with the help of my grandmother's indigenous friends in the mountains, we obtained a new device.</s>
 <s id="47">For centuries, indigenous women told stories by weaving complex patterns on looms, and an unexpected skill helped us for the new device.</s>
 <s id="48">We take this traditional method of weaving and make a design made by a smart material that records shape.</s>
 <s id="49">It seems this time, the weaving allows us to create a seamless device that doesn't rust because it's made of only one piece.</s>
 <s id="50">It can change by itself into very complex structures by a procedure that took decades to develop.</s>
 <s id="51">As you can see, the device enters the body through the natural channels.</s>
 <s id="52">Doctors have only to close the catheter through the hole.</s>
 <s id="53">Our device expands, places itself and closes the hole.</s>
 <s id="54">We have this beautiful delivery system that is so simple to use because it works by itself.</s>
 <s id="55">No open surgery was necessary.</s>
 <s id="56">(Applause) As doctors, we fight with diseases that take a long time and effort to heal -- if they do.</s>
 <s id="57">This is the child from before, after the procedure.</s>
 <s id="58">As you can see -- (Applause) As you can see, once the device is in place, the patient is 100 percent healed.</s>
 <s id="59">From start to finish, the whole procedure takes only 30 minutes.</s>
 <s id="60">That's very rewarding from the medical and human point of view.</s>
 <s id="61">We are so proud that some of our former patients are part of our team -- a team, thanks to added close interaction with patients that work with us.</s>
 <s id="62">Together, we have only one idea: the best solutions need to be simple.</s>
 <s id="63">We lost the fear of creating something new.</s>
 <s id="64">The path, it's not easy.</s>
 <s id="65">Many obstacles arise all the time.</s>
 <s id="66">But we receive strength from our patients.</s>
 <s id="67">Their resilience and courage inspire our creativity.</s>
 <s id="68">Our goal is to make sure that no child is left behind, not because of cost or access.</s>
 <s id="69">So we have to start a foundation with a one-to-one model.</s>
 <s id="70">We will give one device for free to make sure that every child is treated.</s>
 <s id="71">We are in many countries now, but we need to be everywhere.</s>
 <s id="72">This whole thing began with one impossible idea as will continue it, really: No child is left behind.</s>
 <s id="73">Muchas gracias.</s>
 <s id="74">(Applause)</s>
</text>
