<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">How big was that fish you caught?</s>
 <s id="2">This big?</s>
 <s id="3">This big?</s>
 <s id="4">This big?</s>
 <s id="5">Without photographic evidence, there's nothing that proves you caught a whopper, and that's been true since the dawn of fishing.</s>
 <s id="6">In fact, hundreds of years ago, long before photography could capture the moment, Japanese fishermen invented their own way to record trophy catches.</s>
 <s id="7">They called it Gyotaku.</s>
 <s id="8">Gyotaku is the ancient art of printing fish that originated in Japan as a way to record trophy catches prior to the modern day camera.</s>
 <s id="9">Gyo means fish and taku means impression.</s>
 <s id="10">There are several different stories about how Gyotaku came about, but it basically started with fishermen needing a way to record the species and size of the fish they caught over 100 years ago.</s>
 <s id="11">Fishermen took paper, ink, and brushes out to sea with them.</s>
 <s id="12">They told stories of great adventures at sea.</s>
 <s id="13">Since the Japanese revered certain fish, the fishermen would take a rubbing from these fish and release them.</s>
 <s id="14">To make the rubbing, they would paint the fish with non-toxic sumi-e ink and print them on rice paper.</s>
 <s id="15">This way they could be released or cleaned and sold at market.</s>
 <s id="16">The first prints like this were for records only with no extra details.</s>
 <s id="17">It wasn't until the mid 1800's that they began painting eye details and other embellishments onto the prints.</s>
 <s id="18">One famous nobleman, Lord Sakai, was an avid fisherman, and, when he made a large catch, he wanted to preserve the memory of the large, red sea bream.</s>
 <s id="19">To do so, he commissioned a fisherman to print his catch.</s>
 <s id="20">After this, many fisherman would bring their Gyotaku prints to Lord Sakai, and if he liked their work, he would hire them to print for him.</s>
 <s id="21">Many prints hung in the palace during the Edo period.</s>
 <s id="22">After this period, Gyotaku was not as popular and began to fade away.</s>
 <s id="23">Today, Gyotaku has become a popular art form, enjoyed by many.</s>
 <s id="24">And the prints are said to bring good luck to the fishermen.</s>
 <s id="25">But the art form is quite different than it used to be.</s>
 <s id="26">Most artists today learn on their own by trial and error.</s>
 <s id="27">Before the artist begins to print, the fish needs to be prepared for printing.</s>
 <s id="28">First, the artist places the fish on a hollowed out surface.</s>
 <s id="29">Then the artist spreads the fins out and pins them down on the board to dry.</s>
 <s id="30">They then clean the fish with water.</s>
 <s id="31">When it comes time to print, there are two different methods.</s>
 <s id="32">The indirect method begins with pasting moist fabric or paper onto the fish using rice paste.</s>
 <s id="33">Then, the artist uses a tompo, or a cotton ball covered in silk, to put ink on the fabric or paper to produce the print.</s>
 <s id="34">This method requires more skill and great care needs to be taken when pulling the paper off the fish so the paper doesn't tear.</s>
 <s id="35">In the direct method, the artist paints directly on the fish, and then gently presses the moist fabric or paper into the fish.</s>
 <s id="36">With both of these methods, no two prints are exactly alike, but both reveal dramatic images of the fish.</s>
 <s id="37">For the final touch, the artist uses a chop, or a stamp, and signs their work, and can hold it up to say, "The fish was exactly this big!"</s>
</text>
