<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Imagine being unable to say, "I am hungry," "I am in pain," "thank you," or "I love you."</s>
 <s id="2">Being trapped inside your body, a body that doesn't respond to commands.</s>
 <s id="3">Surrounded by people, yet utterly alone.</s>
 <s id="4">Wishing you could reach out, to connect, to comfort, to participate.</s>
 <s id="5">For 13 long years, that was my reality.</s>
 <s id="6">Most of us never think twice about talking, about communicating.</s>
 <s id="7">I've thought a lot about it.</s>
 <s id="8">I've had a lot of time to think.</s>
 <s id="9">For the first 12 years of my life, I was a normal, happy, healthy little boy.</s>
 <s id="10">Then everything changed.</s>
 <s id="11">I contracted a brain infection.</s>
 <s id="12">The doctors weren't sure what it was, but they treated me the best they could.</s>
 <s id="13">However, I progressively got worse.</s>
 <s id="14">Eventually, I lost my ability to control my movements, make eye contact, and finally, my ability to speak.</s>
 <s id="15">While in hospital, I desperately wanted to go home.</s>
 <s id="16">I said to my mother, "When home?"</s>
 <s id="17">Those were the last words I ever spoke with my own voice.</s>
 <s id="18">I would eventually fail every test for mental awareness.</s>
 <s id="19">My parents were told I was as good as not there.</s>
 <s id="20">A vegetable, having the intelligence of a three-month-old baby.</s>
 <s id="21">They were told to take me home and try to keep me comfortable until I died.</s>
 <s id="22">My parents, in fact my entire family's lives, became consumed by taking care of me the best they knew how.</s>
 <s id="23">Their friends drifted away.</s>
 <s id="24">One year turned to two, two turned to three.</s>
 <s id="25">It seemed like the person I once was began to disappear.</s>
 <s id="26">The Lego blocks and electronic circuits I'd loved as a boy were put away.</s>
 <s id="27">I had been moved out of my bedroom into another more practical one.</s>
 <s id="28">I had become a ghost, a faded memory of a boy people once knew and loved.</s>
 <s id="29">Meanwhile, my mind began knitting itself back together.</s>
 <s id="30">Gradually, my awareness started to return.</s>
 <s id="31">But no one realized that I had come back to life.</s>
 <s id="32">I was aware of everything, just like any normal person.</s>
 <s id="33">I could see and understand everything, but I couldn't find a way to let anybody know.</s>
 <s id="34">My personality was entombed within a seemingly silent body, a vibrant mind hidden in plain sight within a chrysalis.</s>
 <s id="35">The stark reality hit me that I was going to spend the rest of my life locked inside myself, totally alone.</s>
 <s id="36">I was trapped with only my thoughts for company.</s>
 <s id="37">I would never be rescued.</s>
 <s id="38">No one would ever show me tenderness.</s>
 <s id="39">I would never talk to a friend.</s>
 <s id="40">No one would ever love me.</s>
 <s id="41">I had no dreams, no hope, nothing to look forward to.</s>
 <s id="42">Well, nothing pleasant.</s>
 <s id="43">I lived in fear, and, to put it bluntly, was waiting for death to finally release me, expecting to die all alone in a care home.</s>
 <s id="44">I don't know if it's truly possible to express in words what it's like not to be able to communicate.</s>
 <s id="45">Your personality appears to vanish into a heavy fog and all of your emotions and desires are constricted, stifled and muted within you.</s>
 <s id="46">For me, the worst was the feeling of utter powerlessness.</s>
 <s id="47">I simply existed.</s>
 <s id="48">It's a very dark place to find yourself because in a sense, you have vanished.</s>
 <s id="49">Other people controlled every aspect of my life.</s>
 <s id="50">They decided what I ate and when.</s>
 <s id="51">Whether I was laid on my side or strapped into my wheelchair.</s>
 <s id="52">I often spent my days positioned in front of the TV watching Barney reruns.</s>
 <s id="53">I think because Barney is so happy and jolly, and I absolutely wasn't, it made it so much worse.</s>
 <s id="54">I was completely powerless to change anything in my life or people's perceptions of me.</s>
 <s id="55">I was a silent, invisible observer of how people behaved when they thought no one was watching.</s>
 <s id="56">Unfortunately, I wasn't only an observer.</s>
 <s id="57">With no way to communicate, I became the perfect victim: a defenseless object, seemingly devoid of feelings that people used to play out their darkest desires.</s>
 <s id="58">For more than 10 years, people who were charged with my care abused me physically, verbally and sexually.</s>
 <s id="59">Despite what they thought, I did feel.</s>
 <s id="60">The first time it happened, I was shocked and filled with disbelief.</s>
 <s id="61">How could they do this to me?</s>
 <s id="62">I was confused.</s>
 <s id="63">What had I done to deserve this?</s>
 <s id="64">Part of me wanted to cry and another part wanted to fight.</s>
 <s id="65">Hurt, sadness and anger flooded through me.</s>
 <s id="66">I felt worthless.</s>
 <s id="67">There was no one to comfort me.</s>
 <s id="68">But neither of my parents knew this was happening.</s>
 <s id="69">I lived in terror, knowing it would happen again and again.</s>
 <s id="70">I just never knew when.</s>
 <s id="71">All I knew was that I would never be the same.</s>
 <s id="72">I remember once listening to Whitney Houston singing, "No matter what they take from me, they can't take away my dignity."</s>
 <s id="73">And I thought to myself, "You want to bet?"</s>
 <s id="74">Perhaps my parents could have found out and could have helped.</s>
 <s id="75">But the years of constant caretaking, having to wake up every two hours to turn me, combined with them essentially grieving the loss of their son, had taken a toll on my mother and father.</s>
 <s id="76">Following yet another heated argument between my parents, in a moment of despair and desperation, my mother turned to me and told me that I should die.</s>
 <s id="77">I was shocked, but as I thought about what she had said, I was filled with enormous compassion and love for my mother, yet I could do nothing about it.</s>
 <s id="78">There were many moments when I gave up, sinking into a dark abyss.</s>
 <s id="79">I remember one particularly low moment.</s>
 <s id="80">My dad left me alone in the car while he quickly went to buy something from the store.</s>
 <s id="81">A random stranger walked past, looked at me and he smiled.</s>
 <s id="82">I may never know why, but that simple act, the fleeting moment of human connection, transformed how I was feeling, making me want to keep going.</s>
 <s id="83">My existence was tortured by monotony, a reality that was often too much to bear.</s>
 <s id="84">Alone with my thoughts, I constructed intricate fantasies about ants running across the floor.</s>
 <s id="85">I taught myself to tell the time by noticing where the shadows were.</s>
 <s id="86">As I learned how the shadows moved as the hours of the day passed, I understood how long it would be before I was picked up and taken home.</s>
 <s id="87">Seeing my father walk through the door to collect me was the best moment of the day.</s>
 <s id="88">My mind became a tool that I could use to either close down to retreat from my reality or enlarge into a gigantic space that I could fill with fantasies.</s>
 <s id="89">I hoped that my reality would change and someone would see that I had come back to life.</s>
 <s id="90">But I had been washed away like a sand castle built too close to the waves, and in my place was the person people expected me to be.</s>
 <s id="91">To some I was Martin, a vacant shell, the vegetable, deserving of harsh words, dismissal and even abuse.</s>
 <s id="92">To others, I was the tragically brain-damaged boy who had grown to become a man.</s>
 <s id="93">Someone they were kind to and cared for.</s>
 <s id="94">Good or bad, I was a blank canvas onto which different versions of myself were projected.</s>
 <s id="95">It took someone new to see me in a different way.</s>
 <s id="96">An aromatherapist began coming to the care home about once a week.</s>
 <s id="97">Whether through intuition or her attention to details that others failed to notice, she became convinced that I could understand what was being said.</s>
 <s id="98">She urged my parents to have me tested by experts in augmentative and alternative communication.</s>
 <s id="99">And within a year, I was beginning to use a computer program to communicate.</s>
 <s id="100">It was exhilarating, but frustrating at times.</s>
 <s id="101">I had so many words in my mind, that I couldn't wait to be able to share them.</s>
 <s id="102">Sometimes, I would say things to myself simply because I could.</s>
 <s id="103">In myself, I had a ready audience, and I believed that by expressing my thoughts and wishes, others would listen, too.</s>
 <s id="104">But as I began to communicate more, I realized that it was in fact only just the beginning of creating a new voice for myself.</s>
 <s id="105">I was thrust into a world I didn't quite know how to function in.</s>
 <s id="106">I stopped going to the care home and managed to get my first job making photocopies.</s>
 <s id="107">As simple as this may sound, it was amazing.</s>
 <s id="108">My new world was really exciting but often quite overwhelming and frightening.</s>
 <s id="109">I was like a man-child, and as liberating as it often was, I struggled.</s>
 <s id="110">I also learned that many of those who had known me for a long time found it impossible to abandon the idea of Martin they had in their heads.</s>
 <s id="111">While those I had only just met struggled to look past the image of a silent man in a wheelchair.</s>
 <s id="112">I realized that some people would only listen to me if what I said was in line with what they expected.</s>
 <s id="113">Otherwise, it was disregarded and they did what they felt was best.</s>
 <s id="114">I discovered that true communication is about more than merely physically conveying a message.</s>
 <s id="115">It is about getting the message heard and respected.</s>
 <s id="116">Still, things were going well.</s>
 <s id="117">My body was slowly getting stronger.</s>
 <s id="118">I had a job in computing that I loved, and had even got Kojak, the dog I had been dreaming about for years.</s>
 <s id="119">However, I longed to share my life with someone.</s>
 <s id="120">I remember staring out the window as my dad drove me home from work, thinking I have so much love inside of me and nobody to give it to.</s>
 <s id="121">Just as I had resigned myself to being single for the rest of my life, I met Joan.</s>
 <s id="122">Not only is she the best thing that has ever happened to me, but Joan helped me to challenge my own misconceptions about myself.</s>
 <s id="123">Joan said it was through my words that she fell in love with me.</s>
 <s id="124">However, after all I had been through, I still couldn't shake the belief that nobody could truly see beyond my disability and accept me for who I am.</s>
 <s id="125">I also really struggled to comprehend that I was a man.</s>
 <s id="126">The first time someone referred to me as a man, it stopped me in my tracks.</s>
 <s id="127">I felt like looking around and asking, "Who, me?"</s>
 <s id="128">That all changed with Joan.</s>
 <s id="129">We have an amazing connection and I learned how important it is to communicate openly and honestly.</s>
 <s id="130">I felt safe, and it gave me the confidence to truly say what I thought.</s>
 <s id="131">I started to feel whole again, a man worthy of love.</s>
 <s id="132">I began to reshape my destiny.</s>
 <s id="133">I spoke up a little more at work.</s>
 <s id="134">I asserted my need for independence to the people around me.</s>
 <s id="135">Being given a means of communication changed everything.</s>
 <s id="136">I used the power of words and will to challenge the preconceptions of those around me and those I had of myself.</s>
 <s id="137">Communication is what makes us human, enabling us to connect on the deepest level with those around us -- telling our own stories, expressing wants, needs and desires, or hearing those of others by really listening.</s>
 <s id="138">All this is how the world knows who we are.</s>
 <s id="139">So who are we without it?</s>
 <s id="140">True communication increases understanding and creates a more caring and compassionate world.</s>
 <s id="141">Once, I was perceived to be an inanimate object, a mindless phantom of a boy in a wheelchair.</s>
 <s id="142">Today, I am so much more.</s>
 <s id="143">A husband, a son, a friend, a brother, a business owner, a first-class honors graduate, a keen amateur photographer.</s>
 <s id="144">It is my ability to communicate that has given me all this.</s>
 <s id="145">We are told that actions speak louder than words.</s>
 <s id="146">But I wonder, do they?</s>
 <s id="147">Our words, however we communicate them, are just as powerful.</s>
 <s id="148">Whether we speak the words with our own voices, type them with our eyes, or communicate them non-verbally to someone who speaks them for us, words are among our most powerful tools.</s>
 <s id="149">I have come to you through a terrible darkness, pulled from it by caring souls and by language itself.</s>
 <s id="150">The act of you listening to me today brings me farther into the light.</s>
 <s id="151">We are shining here together.</s>
 <s id="152">If there is one most difficult obstacle to my way of communicating, it is that sometimes I want to shout and other times simply to whisper a word of love or gratitude.</s>
 <s id="153">It all sounds the same.</s>
 <s id="154">But if you will, please imagine these next two words as warmly as you can: Thank you.</s>
 <s id="155">(Applause)</s>
</text>
