<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Server: May I help you, sir?</s>
 <s id="2">Customer: Uh, let's see.</s>
 <s id="3">Server: We have pan seared registry error sprinkled with the finest corrupted data, binary brioche, RAM sandwiches, Conficker fitters, and a scripting salad with or without polymorphic dressing, and a grilled coding kabob.</s>
 <s id="4">Customer: I'd like a RAM sandwich and a glass of your finest Code 39.</s>
 <s id="5">Server: Would you like any desserts, sir?</s>
 <s id="6">Our special is tracking cookie.</s>
 <s id="7">Customer: I'd like a batch of some zombie tracking cookies, thank you.</s>
 <s id="8">Server: Coming right up, sir.</s>
 <s id="9">Your food will be served shortly.</s>
 <s id="10">(Applause) Maya Penn: I've been drawing ever since I could hold a crayon, and I've been making animated flip books since I was three years old.</s>
 <s id="11">At that age, I also learned about what an animator was.</s>
 <s id="12">There was a program on TV about jobs most kids don't know about.</s>
 <s id="13">When I understood that an animator makes the cartoons I saw on TV, I immediately said, "That's what I want to be."</s>
 <s id="14">I don't know if I said it mentally or out loud, but that was a greatly defining moment in my life.</s>
 <s id="15">Animation and art has always been my first love.</s>
 <s id="16">It was my love for technology that sparked the idea for "Malicious Dishes."</s>
 <s id="17">There was a virus on my computer, and I was trying to get rid of it, and all of a sudden, I just thought, what if viruses have their own little world inside the computer?</s>
 <s id="18">Maybe a restaurant where they meet up and do virusy things?</s>
 <s id="19">And thus, "Malicious Dishes" was born.</s>
 <s id="20">At four years old, my dad showed me how to take apart a computer and put it back together again.</s>
 <s id="21">That started my love for technology.</s>
 <s id="22">I built my first website myself in HTML, and I'm learning JavaScript and Python.</s>
 <s id="23">I'm also working on an animated series called "The Pollinators."</s>
 <s id="24">It's about bees and other pollinators in our environment and why they're so important.</s>
 <s id="25">If plants aren't pollinated by the pollinators, then all creatures, including ourselves, that depend on these plants, would starve.</s>
 <s id="26">So I decided to take these cool creatures and make a superhero team.</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">(Applause) (Foot stomp) (Music) (Roar) Pollinator: Deforestsaurus!</s>
  <s id="27.2">I should have known!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="28">I need to call on the rest of the Pollinators!</s>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">(Music) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="29.2">(Applause) All of my animations start with ideas, but what are ideas?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">Ideas can spark a movement.</s>
 <s id="31">Ideas are opportunities and innovation.</s>
 <s id="32">Ideas truly are what make the world go round.</s>
 <s id="33">If it wasn't for ideas, we wouldn't be where we are now with technology, medicine, art, culture, and how we even live our lives.</s>
 <s id="34">At eight years old, I took my ideas and started my own business called Maya's Ideas, and my nonprofit, Maya's Ideas for the Planet.</s>
 <s id="35">(Laughter) And I make eco-friendly clothing and accessories.</s>
 <s id="36">I'm 13 now, and although I started my business in 2008, my artistic journey started way before then.</s>
 <s id="37">I was greatly influenced by art, and I wanted to incorporate it in everything I did, even my business.</s>
 <s id="38">I would find different fabrics around the house, and say, &amp;amp;quot;This could be a scarf or a hat,&amp;amp;quot; and I had all these ideas for designs.</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">I noticed when I wore my creations, people would stop me and say, "Wow, that's really cute.</s>
  <s id="39.2">Where can I get one?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">And I thought, I can start my own business.</s>
 <s id="41">Now I didn't have any business plans at only eight years old.</s>
 <s id="42">I only knew I wanted to make pretty creations that were safe for the environment and I wanted to give back.</s>
 <s id="43">My mom taught me how to sew, and on my back porch, I would sit and make little headbands out of ribbon, and I would write down the names and the price of each item.</s>
 <s id="44">I started making more items like hats, scarves and bags.</s>
 <s id="45">Soon, my items began selling all over the world, and I had customers in Denmark, Italy, Australia, Canada and more.</s>
 <s id="46">Now, I had a lot to learn about my business, like branding and marketing, staying engaged with my customers, and seeing what sold the most and the least.</s>
 <s id="47">Soon, my business really started to take off.</s>
 <s id="48">Then one day, Forbes magazine contacted me when I was 10 years old.</s>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) They wanted to feature me and my company in their article.</s>
 <s id="50">Now a lot of people ask me, why is your business eco-friendly?</s>
 <s id="51">I've had a passion for protecting the environment and its creatures since I was little.</s>
 <s id="52">My parents taught me at an early age about giving back and being a good steward to the environment.</s>
 <s id="53">I heard about how the dyes in some clothing or the process of even making the items was harmful to the people and the planet, so I started doing my own research, and I discovered that even after dyeing has being completed, there is a waste issue that gives a negative impact on the environment.</s>
 <s id="54">For example, the grinding of materials, or the dumping of dried powder materials.</s>
 <s id="55">These actions can pollute the air, making it toxic to anyone or anything that inhales it.</s>
 <s id="56">So when I started my business, I knew two things: All of my items had to be eco-friendly, and 10 to 20 percent of the profits I made went to local and global charities and environmental organizations.</s>
 <s id="57">(Applause) I feel I'm part of the new wave of entrepreneurs that not only seeks to have a successful business, but also a sustainable future.</s>
 <s id="58">I feel that I can meet the needs of my customers without compromising the ability of future generations to live in a greener tomorrow.</s>
 <s id="59">We live in a big, diverse and beautiful world, and that makes me even more passionate to save it.</s>
 <s id="60">But it's never enough to just to get it through your heads about the things that are happening in our world.</s>
 <s id="61">It takes to get it through your hearts, because when you get it through your heart, that is when movements are sparked.</s>
 <s id="62">That is when opportunities and innovation are created, and that is why ideas come to life.</s>
 <s id="63">Thank you, and peace and blessings.</s>
 <p id="p64">
  <s id="64.1">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="64.2">(Applause) Pat Mitchell: So, you heard Maya talk about the amazing parents who are behind this incredible woman.</s>
  <s id="64.3">Where are they?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p65">
  <s id="65.1">Please, Mr. and Mrs. Penn.</s>
  <s id="65.2">Would you just -- Ah!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="66">(Applause)</s>
</text>
