<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Do you know that we have 1.4 million cellular radio masts deployed worldwide?</s>
 <s id="2">And these are base stations.</s>
 <s id="3">And we also have more than five billion of these devices here.</s>
 <s id="4">These are cellular mobile phones.</s>
 <s id="5">And with these mobile phones, we transmit more than 600 terabytes of data every month.</s>
 <s id="6">This is a 6 with 14 zeroes -- a very large number.</s>
 <s id="7">And wireless communications has become a utility like electricity and water.</s>
 <p id="p8">
  <s id="8.1">We use it everyday.</s>
  <s id="8.2">We use it in our everyday lives now -- in our private lives, in our business lives.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="9">And we even have to be asked sometimes, very kindly, to switch off the mobile phone at events like this for good reasons.</s>
 <s id="10">And it's this importance why I decided to look into the issues that this technology has, because it's so fundamental to our lives.</s>
 <s id="11">And one of the issues is capacity.</s>
 <s id="12">The way we transmit wireless data is by using electromagnetic waves -- in particular, radio waves.</s>
 <s id="13">And radio waves are limited.</s>
 <s id="14">They are scarce; they are expensive; and we only have a certain range of it.</s>
 <s id="15">And it's this limitation that doesn't cope with the demand of wireless data transmissions and the number of bytes and data which are transmitted every month.</s>
 <s id="16">And we are simply running out of spectrum.</s>
 <s id="17">There's another problem.</s>
 <s id="18">That is efficiency.</s>
 <s id="19">These 1.4 million cellular radio masts, or base stations, consume a lot of energy.</s>
 <s id="20">And mind you, most of the energy is not used to transmit the radio waves, it is used to cool the base stations.</s>
 <s id="21">Then the efficiency of such a base station is only at about five percent.</s>
 <s id="22">And that creates a big problem.</s>
 <s id="23">Then there's another issue that you're all aware of.</s>
 <s id="24">You have to switch off your mobile phone during flights.</s>
 <s id="25">In hospitals, they are security issues.</s>
 <s id="26">And security is another issue.</s>
 <s id="27">These radio waves penetrate through walls.</s>
 <s id="28">They can be intercepted, and somebody can make use of your network if he has bad intentions.</s>
 <s id="29">So these are the main four issues.</s>
 <s id="30">But on the other hand, we have 14 billion of these: light bulbs, light.</s>
 <s id="31">And light is part of the electromagnetic spectrum.</s>
 <s id="32">So let's look at this in the context of the entire electromagnetic spectrum, where we have gamma rays.</s>
 <s id="33">You don't want to get close to gamma rays, it could be dangerous.</s>
 <s id="34">X-rays, useful when you go to hospitals.</s>
 <s id="35">Then there's ultraviolet light.</s>
 <s id="36">it's good for a nice suntan, but otherwise dangerous for the human body.</s>
 <s id="37">Infrared -- due to eye safety regulations, can be only used with low power.</s>
 <s id="38">And then we have the radio waves, they have the issues I've just mentioned.</s>
 <s id="39">And in the middle there, we have this visible light spectrum.</s>
 <s id="40">It's light, and light has been around for many millions of years.</s>
 <s id="41">And in fact, it has created us, has created life, has created all the stuff of life.</s>
 <s id="42">So it's inherently safe to use.</s>
 <s id="43">And wouldn't it be great to use that for wireless communications?</s>
 <s id="44">Not only that, I compared [it to] the entire spectrum.</s>
 <s id="45">I compared the radio waves spectrum -- the size of it -- with the size of the visible light spectrum.</s>
 <s id="46">And guess what?</s>
 <s id="47">We have 10,000 times more of that spectrum, which is there for us to use.</s>
 <s id="48">So not only do we have this huge amount of spectrum, let's compare that with a number I've just mentioned.</s>
 <s id="49">We have 1.4 million expensively deployed, inefficient radio cellular base stations.</s>
 <s id="50">And multiply that by 10,000, then you end up at 14 billion.</s>
 <s id="51">14 billion is the number of light bulbs installed already.</s>
 <s id="52">So we have the infrastructure there.</s>
 <s id="53">Look at the ceiling, you see all these light bulbs.</s>
 <s id="54">Go to the main floor, you see these light bulbs.</s>
 <s id="55">Can we use them for communications?</s>
 <s id="56">Yes.</s>
 <s id="57">What do we need to do?</s>
 <s id="58">The one thing we need to do is we have to replace these inefficient incandescent light bulbs, florescent lights, with this new technology of LED, LED light bulbs.</s>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">An LED is a semiconductor.</s>
  <s id="59.2">It's an electronic device.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="60">And it has a very nice acute property.</s>
 <s id="61">Its intensity can be modulated at very high speeds, and it can be switched off at very high speeds.</s>
 <s id="62">And this is a fundamental basic property that we exploit with our technology.</s>
 <s id="63">So let's show how we do that.</s>
 <s id="64">Let's go to the closest neighbor to the visible light spectrum -- go to remote controls.</s>
 <s id="65">You all know remote controls have an infrared LED -- basically you switch on the LED, and if it's off, you switch it off.</s>
 <s id="66">And it creates a simple, low-speed data stream in 10,000 bits per second, 20,000 bits per second.</s>
 <s id="67">Not usable for a YouTube video.</s>
 <s id="68">What we have done is we have developed a technology with which we can furthermore replace the remote control of our light bulb.</s>
 <s id="69">We transmit with our technology, not only a single data stream, we transmit thousands of data streams in parallel, at even higher speeds.</s>
 <s id="70">And the technology we have developed -- it's called SIM OFDM.</s>
 <s id="71">And it's spacial modulation -- these are the only technical terms, I'm not going into details -- but this is how we enabled that light source to transmit data.</s>
 <s id="72">You will say, "Okay, this is nice -- a slide created in 10 minutes."</s>
 <s id="73">But not only that.</s>
 <s id="74">What we've done is we have also developed a demonstrator.</s>
 <s id="75">And I'm showing for the first time in public this visible light demonstrator.</s>
 <s id="76">And what we have here is no ordinary desk lamp.</s>
 <s id="77">We fit in an LED light bulb, worth three U.S. dollars, put in our signal processing technology.</s>
 <s id="78">And then what we have here is a little hole.</s>
 <s id="79">And the light goes through that hole.</s>
 <s id="80">There's a receiver.</s>
 <s id="81">The receiver will convert these little, subtle changes in the amplitude that we create there into an electrical signal.</s>
 <s id="82">And that signal is then converted back to a high-speed data stream.</s>
 <s id="83">In the future we hope that we can integrate this little hole into these smart phones.</s>
 <s id="84">And not only integrate a photo detector here, but maybe use the camera inside.</s>
 <s id="85">So what happens when I switch on that light?</s>
 <s id="86">As you would expect, it's a light, a desk lamp.</s>
 <s id="87">Put your book beneath it and you can read.</s>
 <s id="88">It's illuminating the space.</s>
 <s id="89">But at the same time, you see this video coming up here.</s>
 <s id="90">And that's a video, a high-definition video that is transmitted through that light beam.</s>
 <s id="91">You're critical.</s>
 <s id="92">You think, "Ha, ha, ha.</s>
 <s id="93">This is a smart academic doing a little bit of tricks here."</s>
 <s id="94">But let me do this.</s>
 <s id="95">(Applause) Once again.</s>
 <s id="96">Still don't believe?</s>
 <s id="97">It is this light that transmits this high-definition video in a split stream.</s>
 <s id="98">And if you look at the light, it is illuminating as you would expect.</s>
 <s id="99">You don't notice with your human eye.</s>
 <s id="100">You don't notice the subtle changes in the amplitude that we impress onto this light bulb.</s>
 <s id="101">It's serving the purpose of illumination, but at the same time, we are able to transmit this data.</s>
 <s id="102">And you see, even light from the ceiling comes down here to the receiver.</s>
 <s id="103">It can ignore that constant light, because all the receiver's interested in are subtle changes.</s>
 <s id="104">You also have a critical question now, and you say, "Okay, do I have to have the light on all the time to have this working?"</s>
 <s id="105">And the answer is yes.</s>
 <s id="106">But, you can dim down the light to a level that it appears to be off.</s>
 <s id="107">And you are still able to transmit data -- that's possible.</s>
 <s id="108">So I've mentioned to you the four challenges.</s>
 <s id="109">Capacity: We have 10,000 times more spectrum, 10,000 times more LEDs installed already in the infrastructure there.</s>
 <s id="110">You would agree with me, hopefully, there's no issue of capacity anymore.</s>
 <s id="111">Efficiency: This is data through illumination -- it's first of all an illumination device.</s>
 <s id="112">And if you do the energy budget, the data transmission comes for free -- highly energy efficient.</s>
 <s id="113">I don't mention the high energy efficiency of these LED light bulbs.</s>
 <s id="114">If the whole world would deploy them, you would save hundreds of power plants.</s>
 <s id="115">That's aside.</s>
 <s id="116">And then I've mentioned the availability.</s>
 <s id="117">You will agree with me that we have lights in the hospital.</s>
 <s id="118">You need to see what to do.</s>
 <s id="119">You have lights in an aircraft.</s>
 <s id="120">So it's everywhere in a day there is light.</s>
 <p id="p121">
  <s id="121.1">Look around.</s>
  <s id="121.2">Everywhere.</s>
  <s id="121.3">Look at your smart phone.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="122">It has a flashlight, an LED flashlight.</s>
 <s id="123">These are potential sources for high-speed data transmission.</s>
 <s id="124">And then there's security.</s>
 <s id="125">You would agree with me that light doesn't penetrate through walls.</s>
 <s id="126">So no one, if I have a light here, if I have secure data, no one on the other side of this room through that wall would be able to read that data.</s>
 <s id="127">And there's only data where there is light.</s>
 <s id="128">So if I don't want that receiver to receive the data, then what I could do, turn it away.</s>
 <s id="129">So the data goes in that direction, not there anymore.</s>
 <s id="130">Now we can in fact see where the data is going to.</s>
 <s id="131">So for me, the applications of it, to me, are beyond imagination at the moment.</s>
 <s id="132">We have had a century of very nice, smart application developers.</s>
 <s id="133">And you only have to notice, where we have light, there is a potential way to transmit data.</s>
 <s id="134">But I can give you a few examples.</s>
 <s id="135">Well you may see the impact already now.</s>
 <s id="136">This is a remote operated vehicle beneath the ocean.</s>
 <s id="137">And they use light to illuminate space down there.</s>
 <s id="138">And this light can be used to transmit wireless data that these things [use] to communicate with each other.</s>
 <s id="139">Intrinsically safe environments like this petrochemical plant -- you can't use RF, it may generate antenna sparks, but you can use light -- you see plenty of light there.</s>
 <s id="140">In hospitals, for new medical instruments; in streets for traffic control.</s>
 <s id="141">Cars have LED-based headlights, LED-based back lights, and cars can communicate with each other and prevent accidents in the way that they exchange information.</s>
 <s id="142">Traffic lights can communicate to the car and so on.</s>
 <s id="143">And then you have these millions of street lamps deployed around the world.</s>
 <s id="144">And every street lamp could be a free access point.</s>
 <s id="145">We call it, in fact, a Li-Fi, light-fidelity.</s>
 <s id="146">And then we have these aircraft cabins.</s>
 <s id="147">There are hundreds of lights in an aircraft cabin, and each of these lights could be a potential transmitter of wireless data.</s>
 <s id="148">So you could enjoy your most favorite TED video on your long flight back home.</s>
 <p id="p149">
  <s id="149.1">Online life.</s>
  <s id="149.2">So that is a vision, I think, that is possible.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="150">So, all we would need to do is to fit a small microchip to every potential illumination device.</s>
 <s id="151">And this would then combine two basic functionalities: illumination and wireless data transmission.</s>
 <s id="152">And it's this symbiosis that I personally believe could solve the four essential problems that face us in wireless communication these days.</s>
 <s id="153">And in the future, you would not only have 14 billion light bulbs, you may have 14 billion Li-Fis deployed worldwide -- for a cleaner, a greener, and even a brighter future.</s>
 <s id="154">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="155">(Applause)</s>
</text>
