<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">As the sun rises on a fall morning in 55 BCE, Camma lays two pigeons on the altar at the center of her village.</s>
 <s id="2">She offers a prayer to Matrona mother goddess of the Earth, and Lugus chief of the gods.</s>
 <s id="3">Then, she wrings the birds’ necks and cuts them open to examine their entrails for divine messages.</s>
 <s id="4">Camma is a druid.</s>
 <s id="5">This means she conducts religious rites, but she also serves as a judge, healer, and scholar, teaching children and mediating conflict between Celtic tribes.</s>
 <s id="6">She began her studies as a child, memorizing the countless details necessary to perform her many roles, since the druids’ knowledge is considered too sacred to record in writing.</s>
 <s id="7">Like many druids, she spent years studying in Britain.</s>
 <s id="8">Now, she is a resident Druid of the Veneti tribe in a small farming village near the western coast of Gaul, in what is now France.</s>
 <s id="9">Since returning to Gaul, she has received many offers of marriage– but she has decided to devote herself to her work, at least for now.</s>
 <s id="10">This morning, the omens are troubling.</s>
 <s id="11">They tell of war and strife, as they often have in recent months.</s>
 <s id="12">A neighboring tribe, the Redones, have raided their village and stolen cattle in broad daylight twice this fall.</s>
 <s id="13">The children have gathered around to watch her work.</s>
 <s id="14">Camma plays her lyre and sings to them.</s>
 <s id="15">She weaves stories of the powerful kings who once ruled their land – brave warriors who were slain naked in combat but who will be reborn, as will all the Celts.</s>
 <s id="16">When the children go off to help in the fields, Camma heads across the village to visit an old woman with an eye infection.</s>
 <s id="17">On the way to the old woman’s hut, she passes men salting pigs for the winter food supply and women weaving clothing from dyed wool.</s>
 <s id="18">She delivers a remedy for the injured eye– it’s made from mistletoe, a sacred healing plant, but deadly if used incorrectly.</s>
 <s id="19">From there, Camma visits the chieftain to discuss the omens.</s>
 <s id="20">She convinces him to go and talk through their problems with their neighbors.</s>
 <s id="21">Accompanied by several warriors, they head through the forest and demand a meeting outside the Redones’ village walls.</s>
 <s id="22">The Redones’ representatives bring their own druid, who Camma recognizes from the annual gathering in central Gaul where head druids are elected.</s>
 <s id="23">The chieftains immediately begin to argue and threaten each other.</s>
 <s id="24">Camma steps between the opposing sides to stop them from fighting— they must honor her authority.</s>
 <s id="25">Finally, the Redones agree to pay Camma’s tribe several cattle.</s>
 <s id="26">In spite of this resolution, Camma still feels uneasy on the long walk home.</s>
 <s id="27">As they approach the village walls, a bright streak shoots across the sky— another omen, but of what?</s>
 <s id="28">Back home, Camma sits among the elders for her evening meal of porridge, a bit of meat, and a cup of wine.</s>
 <s id="29">While they were out during the day, an intercepted parchment arrived.</s>
 <s id="30">Camma recognizes the writing immediately.</s>
 <s id="31">Although the druids are forbidden from recording their knowledge, she and many other young druids can read Latin.</s>
 <s id="32">From the message, she learns that the Romans are drawing closer to their lands.</s>
 <s id="33">Some of the elders say that the tribe should flee to the nearby hills and hide, but Camma counsels them to trust in the gods and remain in their home.</s>
 <s id="34">Privately, she has her doubts.</s>
 <s id="35">Should the Romans reach them, her power to help might be limited.</s>
 <s id="36">Unlike the other Celtic tribes, Roman legions have no regard for the druids’ sacred role as peacemakers.</s>
 <s id="37">Before going to bed, she observes the course of the planets and consults her charts, trying to make sense of the meteor she saw earlier.</s>
 <s id="38">The signs are converging on a larger threat than their neighbors.</s>
</text>
