<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">How does your smartphone know exactly where you are?</s>
 <s id="2">The answer lies 12,000 miles over your head in an orbiting satellite that keeps time to the beat of an atomic clock powered by quantum mechanics.</s>
 <s id="3">Phew.</s>
 <s id="4">Let's break that down.</s>
 <s id="5">First of all, why is it so important to know what time it is on a satellite when location is what we're concerned about?</s>
 <s id="6">The first thing your phone needs to determine is how far it is from a satellite.</s>
 <s id="7">Each satellite constantly broadcasts radio signals that travel from space to your phone at the speed of light.</s>
 <s id="8">Your phone records the signal arrival time and uses it to calculate the distance to the satellite using the simple formula, distance = c x time, where c is the speed of light and time is how long the signal traveled.</s>
 <s id="9">But there's a problem.</s>
 <s id="10">Light is incredibly fast.</s>
 <s id="11">If we were only able to calculate time to the nearest second, every location on Earth, and far beyond, would seem to be the same distance from the satellite.</s>
 <s id="12">So in order to calculate that distance to within a few dozen feet, we need the best clock ever invented.</s>
 <s id="13">Enter atomic clocks, some of which are so precise that they would not gain or lose a second even if they ran for the next 300 million years.</s>
 <s id="14">Atomic clocks work because of quantum physics.</s>
 <s id="15">All clocks must have a constant frequency.</s>
 <s id="16">In other words, a clock must carry out some repetitive action to mark off equivalent increments of time.</s>
 <s id="17">Just as a grandfather clock relies on the constant swinging back and forth of a pendulum under gravity, the tick tock of an atomic clock is maintained by the transition between two energy levels of an atom.</s>
 <s id="18">This is where quantum physics comes into play.</s>
 <s id="19">Quantum mechanics says that atoms carry energy, but they can't take on just any arbitrary amount.</s>
 <s id="20">Instead, atomic energy is constrained to a precise set of levels.</s>
 <s id="21">We call these quanta.</s>
 <s id="22">As a simple analogy, think about driving a car onto a freeway.</s>
 <s id="23">As you increase your speed, you would normally continuously go from, say, 20 miles/hour up to 70 miles/hour.</s>
 <s id="24">Now, if you had a quantum atomic car, you wouldn't accelerate in a linear fashion.</s>
 <s id="25">Instead, you would instantaneously jump, or transition, from one speed to the next.</s>
 <s id="26">For an atom, when a transition occurs from one energy level to another, quantum mechanics says that the energy difference is equal to a characteristic frequency, multiplied by a constant, where the change in energy is equal to a number, called Planck's constant, times the frequency.</s>
 <s id="27">That characteristic frequency is what we need to make our clock.</s>
 <s id="28">GPS satellites rely on cesium and rubidium atoms as frequency standards.</s>
 <s id="29">In the case of cesium 133, the characteristic clock frequency is 9,192,631,770 Hz.</s>
 <s id="30">That's 9 billion cycles per second.</s>
 <s id="31">That's a really fast clock.</s>
 <s id="32">No matter how skilled a clockmaker may be, every pendulum, wind-up mechanism and quartz crystal resonates at a slightly different frequency.</s>
 <s id="33">However, every cesium 133 atom in the universe oscillates at the same exact frequency.</s>
 <s id="34">So thanks to the atomic clock, we get a time reading accurate to within 1 billionth of a second, and a very precise measurement of the distance from that satellite.</s>
 <s id="35">Let's ignore the fact that you're almost definitely on Earth.</s>
 <s id="36">We now know that you're at a fixed distance from the satellite.</s>
 <s id="37">In other words, you're somewhere on the surface of a sphere centered around the satellite.</s>
 <s id="38">Measure your distance from a second satellite and you get another overlapping sphere.</s>
 <s id="39">Keep doing that, and with just four measurements, and a little correction using Einstein's theory of relativity, you can pinpoint your location to exactly one point in space.</s>
 <s id="40">So that's all it takes: a multibillion-dollar network of satellites, oscillating cesium atoms, quantum mechanics, relativity, a smartphone, and you.</s>
 <s id="41">No problem.</s>
</text>
