<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I want us to start by thinking about this device, the phone that's very likely in your pockets right now.</s>
 <s id="2">Over 40 percent of Americans check their phones within five minutes of waking up every morning.</s>
 <s id="3">And then they look at it another 50 times during the day.</s>
 <s id="4">Grownups consider this device to be a necessity.</s>
 <s id="5">But now I want you to imagine it in the hands of a three-year-old, and as a society, we get anxious.</s>
 <s id="6">Parents are very worried that this device is going to stunt their children's social growth; that it's going to keep them from getting up and moving; that somehow, this is going to disrupt childhood.</s>
 <s id="7">So, I want to challenge this attitude.</s>
 <s id="8">I can envision a future where we would be excited to see a preschooler interacting with a screen.</s>
 <s id="9">These screens can get kids up and moving even more.</s>
 <s id="10">They have the power to tell us more about what a child is learning than a standardized test can.</s>
 <s id="11">And here's the really crazy thought: I believe that these screens have the power to prompt more real-life conversations between kids and their parents.</s>
 <s id="12">Now, I was perhaps an unlikely champion for this cause.</s>
 <s id="13">I studied children's literature because I was going to work with kids and books.</s>
 <s id="14">But about 20 years ago, I had an experience that shifted my focus.</s>
 <s id="15">I was helping lead a research study about preschoolers and websites.</s>
 <s id="16">And I walked in and was assigned a three-year-old named Maria.</s>
 <s id="17">Maria had actually never seen a computer before.</s>
 <s id="18">So the first thing I had to do was teach her how to use the mouse, and when I opened up the screen, she moved it across the screen, and she stopped on a character named X the Owl.</s>
 <s id="19">And when she did that, the owl lifted his wing and waved at her.</s>
 <s id="20">Maria dropped the mouse, pushed back from the table, leaped up and started waving frantically back at him.</s>
 <s id="21">Her connection to that character was visceral.</s>
 <s id="22">This wasn't a passive screen experience.</s>
 <s id="23">This was a human experience.</s>
 <s id="24">And it was exactly appropriate for a three-year-old.</s>
 <s id="25">I've now worked at PBS Kids for more than 15 years, and my work there is focused on harnessing the power of technology as a positive in children's lives.</s>
 <s id="26">I believe that as a society, we're missing a big opportunity.</s>
 <s id="27">We're letting our fear and our skepticism about these devices hold us back from realizing their potential in our children's lives.</s>
 <s id="28">Fear about kids and technology is nothing new; we've been here before.</s>
 <s id="29">Over 50 years ago, the debate was raging about the newly dominant media: the television.</s>
 <s id="30">That box in the living room?</s>
 <s id="31">It might be separating kids from one another.</s>
 <s id="32">It might keep them away from the outside world.</s>
 <s id="33">But this is the moment when Fred Rogers, the long-running host of "Mister Rogers' Neighborhood," challenged society to look at television as a tool, a tool that could promote emotional growth.</s>
 <s id="34">Here's what he did: he looked out from the screen, and he held a conversation, as if he were speaking to each child individually about feelings.</s>
 <s id="35">And then he would pause and let them think about them.</s>
 <s id="36">You can see his influence across the media landscape today, but at the time, this was revolutionary.</s>
 <s id="37">He shifted the way we looked at television in the lives of children.</s>
 <s id="38">Today it's not just one box.</s>
 <s id="39">Kids are surrounded by devices.</s>
 <s id="40">And I'm also a parent -- I understand this feeling of anxiety.</s>
 <s id="41">But I want us to look at three common fears that parents have, and see if we can shift our focus to the opportunity that's in each of them.</s>
 <s id="42">So.</s>
 <s id="43">Fear number one: "Screens are passive.</s>
 <s id="44">This is going to keep our kids from getting up and moving."</s>
 <s id="45">Chris Kratt and Martin Kratt are zoologist brothers who host a show about animals called "Wild Kratts."</s>
 <s id="46">And they approached the PBS team to say, "Can we do something with those cameras that are built into every device now?</s>
 <s id="47">Could those cameras capture a very natural kid play pattern -- pretending to be animals?"</s>
 <s id="48">So we started with bats.</s>
 <s id="49">And when kids came in to play this game, they loved seeing themselves on-screen with wings.</s>
 <s id="50">But my favorite part of this, when the game was over and we turned off the screens?</s>
 <s id="51">The kids kept being bats.</s>
 <s id="52">They kept flying around the room, they kept veering left and right to catch mosquitoes.</s>
 <s id="53">And they remembered things.</s>
 <s id="54">They remembered that bats fly at night.</s>
 <s id="55">And they remembered that when bats sleep, they hang upside down and fold their wings in.</s>
 <s id="56">This game definitely got kids up and moving.</s>
 <s id="57">But also, now when kids go outside, do they look at a bird and think, "How does a bird fly differently than I flew when I was a bat?"</s>
 <s id="58">The digital technology prompted embodied learning that kids can now take out into the world.</s>
 <s id="59">Fear number two: "Playing games on these screens is just a waste of time.</s>
 <s id="60">It's going to distract children from their education."</s>
 <s id="61">Game developers know that you can learn a lot about a player's skill by looking at the back-end data: Where did a player pause?</s>
 <s id="62">Where did they make a few mistakes before they found the right answer?</s>
 <s id="63">My team wanted to take that tool set and apply it to academic learning.</s>
 <s id="64">Our producer in Boston, WGBH, created a series of Curious George games focused on math.</s>
 <s id="65">And researchers came in and had 80 preschoolers play these games.</s>
 <s id="66">They then gave all 80 of those preschoolers a standardized math test.</s>
 <s id="67">We could see early on that these games were actually helping kids understand some key skills.</s>
 <s id="68">But our partners at UCLA wanted us to dig deeper.</s>
 <s id="69">They focus on data analysis and student assessment.</s>
 <s id="70">And they wanted to take that back-end game-play data and see if they could use it to predict a child's math scores.</s>
 <s id="71">So they made a neural net -- they essentially trained the computer to use this data, and here are the results.</s>
 <s id="72">This is a subset of the children's standardized math scores.</s>
 <s id="73">And this is the computer's prediction of each child's score, based on playing some Curious George games.</s>
 <s id="74">The prediction is astonishingly accurate, especially considering the fact that these games weren't built for assessment.</s>
 <s id="75">The team that did this study believes that games like these can teach us more about a child's cognitive learning than a standardized test can.</s>
 <s id="76">What if games could reduce testing time in the classroom?</s>
 <s id="77">What if they could reduce testing anxiety?</s>
 <s id="78">How could they give teachers snapshots of insight to help them better focus their individualized learning?</s>
 <s id="79">So the third fear I want to address is the one that I think is often the biggest.</s>
 <s id="80">And that's this: "These screens are isolating me from my child."</s>
 <s id="81">Let's play out a scenario.</s>
 <s id="82">Let's say that you are a parent, and you need 25 minutes of uninterrupted time to get dinner ready.</s>
 <s id="83">And in order to do that, you hand a tablet to your three-year-old.</s>
 <s id="84">Now, this is a moment where you probably feel very guilty about what you just did.</s>
 <s id="85">But now imagine this: Twenty minutes later, you receive a text message.</s>
 <s id="86">on that cell phone that's always within arm's reach.</s>
 <s id="87">And it says: "Alex just matched five rhyming words.</s>
 <s id="88">Ask him to play this game with you.</s>
 <s id="89">Can you think of a word that rhymes with 'cat'?</s>
 <s id="90">Or how about 'ball'?"</s>
 <s id="91">In our studies, when parents receive simple tips like these, they felt empowered.</s>
 <s id="92">They were so excited to play these games at the dinner table with their kids.</s>
 <s id="93">And the kids loved it, too.</s>
 <s id="94">Not only did it feel like magic that their parents knew what they had been playing, kids love to play games with their parents.</s>
 <s id="95">Just the act of talking to kids about their media can be incredibly powerful.</s>
 <s id="96">Last summer, Texas Tech University published a study that the show "Daniel Tiger's Neighborhood" could promote the development of empathy among children.</s>
 <s id="97">But there was a really important catch to this study: the greatest benefit was only when parents talked to kids about what they watched.</s>
 <s id="98">Neither just watching nor just talking about it was enough; it was the combination that was key.</s>
 <s id="99">So when I read this study, I started thinking about how rarely parents of preschoolers actually talk to kids about the content of what they're playing and what they're watching.</s>
 <s id="100">And so I decided to try it with my four-year-old.</s>
 <s id="101">I said, "Were you playing a car game earlier today?"</s>
 <p id="p102">
  <s id="102.1">And Benjamin perked up and said, "Yes!</s>
  <s id="102.2">And did you see that I made my car out of a pickle?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="103">It was really hard to open the trunk."</s>
 <s id="104">(Laughter) This hilarious conversation about what was fun in the game and what could have been better continued all the way to school that morning.</s>
 <s id="105">I'm not here to suggest to you that all digital media is great for kids.</s>
 <s id="106">There are legitimate reasons for us to be concerned about the current state of children's content on these screens.</s>
 <s id="107">And it's right for us to be thinking about balance: Where do screens fit against all the other things that a child needs to do to learn and to grow?</s>
 <s id="108">But when we fixate on our fears about it, we forget a really major point, and that is, that kids are living in the same world that we live in, the world where the grownups check their phones more than 50 times a day.</s>
 <s id="109">Screens are a part of children's lives.</s>
 <s id="110">And if we pretend that they aren't, or if we get overwhelmed by our fear, kids are never going to learn how and why to use them.</s>
 <s id="111">What if we start raising our expectations for this media?</s>
 <s id="112">What if we start talking to kids regularly about the content on these screens?</s>
 <s id="113">What if we start looking for the positive impacts that this technology can have in our children's lives?</s>
 <s id="114">That's when the potential of these tools can become a reality.</s>
 <s id="115">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="116">(Applause)</s>
</text>
