<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm often asked why I do art, what do I want to say with my art photography, and what is the use of it?</s>
 <s id="2">Once in a while I start to worry how to actually measure the impact from the art like we do with medicine or technology, where we can see the results and calculate it.</s>
 <s id="3">Then I would finally be able to explain to my mother my art with real numbers.</s>
 <s id="4">But my art is so far from metrics, and moreover, my photography is widely exposing the theme of escapism.</s>
 <s id="5">My theory is that all of us struggle sometimes to escape in order to analyze our reality, appreciate it or change.</s>
 <s id="6">I don't work with daily life as it is, and I'm not a documentary photographer in the common sense.</s>
 <s id="7">But I am a documentary photographer in a different sense.</s>
 <s id="8">I document dreams.</s>
 <s id="9">I work with daily life as it could be, as I imagine it.</s>
 <s id="10">I am a daydreamer, but at the same time I love things that are authentic and deal with our innermost nature, which I would never want to escape from.</s>
 <s id="11">I adore complicated personalities, and real life inspires me to create my images.</s>
 <s id="12">Real life inspires our escape, and sometimes that escape is very needed.</s>
 <s id="13">I believe heroes are not created easily, and I choose to work with individuals who are survivors and facing everyday routines that are not always full of color, people who are on their way to a better life, fighting against life circumstances.</s>
 <s id="14">Why do I choose people like that for my models?</s>
 <s id="15">Because I've been in that position myself, when I had to learn how to survive in real life.</s>
 <s id="16">I was a student living abroad in London.</s>
 <s id="17">I was working at two places at the same time as a waitress.</s>
 <s id="18">Obviously that wasn't my dream job, but I decided to play a game where I imagined that I am taking a role in a film, and in the film I am a waitress, and I need to act great.</s>
 <s id="19">I used to dye my hair and brows to gingerette, I changed my hair to curly perm, I lost weight and made myself believe I am just a character acting in a film.</s>
 <s id="20">That isn't forever, that is all just temporary.</s>
 <s id="21">That helped me a lot.</s>
 <s id="22">It motivated me to change my life and take a hard time as a game.</s>
 <s id="23">Now, as an artist, I am creating different lives for my models in order to give them the experience of being someone else in reality.</s>
 <s id="24">Through the photographic process, all of my models become like silent movie actors.</s>
 <s id="25">They are captured at the moment when they believe in being someone else entirely.</s>
 <s id="26">In order to create a new reality in its entirety, I physically create every single thing in my work, sometimes from outfits to the stage.</s>
 <s id="27">Because I work with analogues, and I don't make any digital manipulations to my photographs, I need everything to take place in reality, in spite of the fact that nowadays, digitally, you can create pretty much everything.</s>
 <s id="28">I don't like this path.</s>
 <s id="29">Even if that reaches perfection, I see the beauty in authenticity of making, and that's impossible without flaws.</s>
 <s id="30">A digitally manipulated photograph is not true for me.</s>
 <s id="31">It doesn't capture anything real.</s>
 <s id="32">It's not experienced, not motivating.</s>
 <s id="33">It's like, instead of going traveling, you look at someone else's travel photographs.</s>
 <s id="34">What I find so exciting is the ability to make people's dreams of being someone else a reality.</s>
 <s id="35">That's like a drug which pushes me to keep working, even without metrics.</s>
 <s id="36">One of my models had always dreamed of being seen as a warrior, but she wasn't able to do sports because of her health problems.</s>
 <s id="37">Half a year ago, she passed away from heart disease at the age of 22.</s>
 <s id="38">But two days before her death, the images we spent months working on together of her as a warrior she dreamed of becoming were published at a large exhibition in Milan by Vogue Magazine.</s>
 <s id="39">All her life was about overcoming.</s>
 <s id="40">Before she died, she had known that thousands of people saw her image from the land of escapism and believed in her as a brave and fearless warrior.</s>
 <s id="41">For my work, I invite people to play a game like we all used to as children when we pretend to be someone else and that process made us really happy.</s>
 <s id="42">To my mind it is important for grown-ups.</s>
 <s id="43">We need these transformations to enact this in the name of art.</s>
 <s id="44">It gives us the very real feeling of being important and powerful in order to influence our reality.</s>
 <s id="45">I know this from my own personal experience.</s>
 <s id="46">I have had so many versions of myself through my self-portraits that I've been many different characters.</s>
 <s id="47">Being someone else in the land of escapism doesn't exactly give us numbers that we can gauge, but it's like a real lost form of magic which exists but can't be measured.</s>
 <s id="48">There is a unique power in art to transform and lift our limits.</s>
 <s id="49">Art creates what I call a conjured life, which helps our existence and pushes, motivates and inspires us to dwell and express ourselves without metrics or calculations.</s>
 <s id="50">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="51">(Applause)</s>
</text>
