<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I wrote this poem after hearing a pretty well known actress tell a very well known interviewer on television, "I'm really getting into the Internet lately.</s>
 <s id="2">I just wish it were more organized."</s>
 <s id="3">So ...</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) If I controlled the Internet, you could auction your broken heart on eBay.</s>
 <s id="5">Take the money; go to Amazon; buy a phonebook for a country you've never been to -- call folks at random until you find someone who flirts really well in a foreign language.</s>
 <s id="6">(Laughter) If I were in charge of the Internet, you could Mapquest your lover's mood swings.</s>
 <s id="7">Hang left at cranky, right at preoccupied, U-turn on silent treatment, all the way back to tongue kissing and good lovin'.</s>
 <s id="8">You could navigate and understand every emotional intersection.</s>
 <s id="9">Some days, I'm as shallow as a baking pan, but I still stretch miles in all directions.</s>
 <s id="10">If I owned the Internet, Napster, Monster and Friendster.com would be one big website.</s>
 <s id="11">That way you could listen to cool music while you pretend to look for a job and you're really just chattin' with your pals.</s>
 <s id="12">(Laughter) Heck, if I ran the Web, you could email dead people.</s>
 <s id="13">(Laughter) They would not email you back (Laughter) -- but you'd get an automated reply.</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) Their name in your inbox (Laughter) -- it's all you wanted anyway.</s>
 <p id="p15">
  <s id="15.1">And a message saying, "Hey, it's me.</s>
  <s id="15.2">I miss you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="16">(Laughter) Listen, you'll see being dead is dandy.</s>
 <s id="17">Now you go back to raising kids and waging peace and craving candy."</s>
 <s id="18">If I designed the Internet, childhood.com would be a loop of a boy in an orchard, with a ski pole for a sword, trashcan lid for a shield, shouting, "I am the emperor of oranges.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">I am the emperor of oranges.</s>
  <s id="19.2">I am the emperor of oranges."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">Now follow me, OK?</s>
 <s id="21">(Laughter) Grandma.com would be a recipe for biscuits and spit-bath instructions.</s>
 <s id="22">One, two, three.</s>
 <s id="23">That links with hotdiggitydog.com.</s>
 <s id="24">That is my grandfather.</s>
 <s id="25">They take you to gruff-ex-cop-on-his-fourth-marriage.dad.</s>
 <s id="26">He forms an attachment to kind-of-ditzy-but-still-sends-ginger-snaps-for-Christmas.mom, who downloads the boy in the orchard, the emperor of oranges, who grows up to be me -- the guy who usually goes too far.</s>
 <s id="27">So if I were emperor of the Internet, I guess I'd still be mortal, huh?</s>
 <s id="28">But at that point, I would probably already have the lowest possible mortgage and the most enlarged possible penis (Laughter) -- so I would outlaw spam on my first day in office.</s>
 <s id="29">I wouldn't need it.</s>
 <s id="30">I'd be like some kind of Internet genius, and me, I'd like to upgrade to deity and maybe just like that -- pop! -- I'd go wireless.</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">(Laughter) Huh?</s>
  <s id="31.2">Maybe Google would hire this.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">I could zip through your servers and firewalls like a virus until the World Wide Web is as wise, as wild and as organized as I think a modern-day miracle/oracle can get, but, ooh-eee, you want to bet just how whack and un-PC your Mac or PC is going to be when I'm rocking hot-shit-hot-shot-god.net?</s>
 <s id="33">I guess it's just like life.</s>
 <s id="34">It is not a question of if you can -- it's: do ya?</s>
 <s id="35">We can interfere with the interface.</s>
 <s id="36">We can make "You've got Hallelujah" the national anthem of cyberspace every lucky time we log on.</s>
 <s id="37">You don't say a prayer.</s>
 <s id="38">You don't write a psalm.</s>
 <s id="39">You don't chant an "om."</s>
 <s id="40">You send one blessed email to whomever you're thinking of at dah-da-la-dat-da-dah-da-la-dat.com.</s>
 <s id="41">Thank you, TED.</s>
 <s id="42">(Applause)</s>
</text>
