<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">4,300 years ago in ancient Sumer, the most powerful person in the city of Ur was banished to wander the vast desert.</s>
 <s id="2">Her name was Enheduanna.</s>
 <s id="3">She was the high priestess of the moon god and history’s first known author.</s>
 <s id="4">By the time of her exile, she had written 42 hymns and three epic poems— and Sumer hadn’t heard the last of her.</s>
 <s id="5">Enheduanna lived 1,700 years before Sappho, 1,500 years before Homer, and about 500 years before the biblical patriarch Abraham.</s>
 <s id="6">She was born in Mesopotamia, the land between the Tigris and Euphrates rivers, and the birthplace of the first cities and high cultures.</s>
 <s id="7">Her father was King Sargon the Great, history’s first empire builder, who conquered the independent city-states of Mesopotamia under a unified banner.</s>
 <s id="8">Sargon was a northern Semite who spoke Akkadian, and the older Sumerian cities in the south viewed him as a foreign invader.</s>
 <s id="9">They frequently revolted to regain their independence, fracturing his new dynasty.</s>
 <s id="10">To bridge the gap between cultures, Sargon appointed his only daughter, Enheduanna, as high priestess in the empire’s most important temple.</s>
 <s id="11">Female royalty traditionally served religious roles, and she was educated to read and write in both Sumerian and Akkadian, and make mathematical calculations.</s>
 <s id="12">The world's first writing started in Sumer as a system of accounting, allowing merchants to communicate over long distances with traders abroad.</s>
 <s id="13">Their pictogram system of record keeping developed into a script about 300 years before Enheduanna’s birth.</s>
 <s id="14">This early writing style, called cuneiform, was written with a reed stylus pressed into soft clay to make wedge-shaped marks.</s>
 <s id="15">But until Enheduanna, this writing mostly took the form of record keeping and transcription, rather than original works attributable to individual writers.</s>
 <s id="16">Enheduanna’s Ur was a city of 34,000 people with narrow streets, multi-storied brick homes, granaries, and irrigation.</s>
 <s id="17">As high priestess, Enheduanna managed grain storage for the city, oversaw hundreds of temple workers, interpreted sacred dreams, and presided over the monthly new moon festival and rituals celebrating the equinoxes.</s>
 <s id="18">Enheduanna set about unifying the older Sumerian culture with the newer Akkadian civilization.</s>
 <s id="19">To accomplish this, she wrote 42 religious hymns that combined both mythologies.</s>
 <s id="20">Each Mesopotamian city was ruled by a patron deity, so her hymns were dedicated to the ruling god of each major city.</s>
 <s id="21">She praised the city’s temple, glorified the god’s attributes, and explained the god’s relationship to other deities within the pantheon.</s>
 <s id="22">In her writing, she humanized the once aloof gods— now they suffered, fought, loved, and responded to human pleading.</s>
 <s id="23">Enheduanna’s most valuable literary contribution was the poetry she wrote to Inanna, goddess of war and desire, the divinely chaotic energy that gives spark to the universe.</s>
 <s id="24">Inanna delighted in all forms of sexual expression and was considered so powerful that she transcended gender boundaries, as did her earthly attendants, who could be prostitutes, eunuchs or cross-dressers.</s>
 <s id="25">Enheduanna placed Inanna at the top of the pantheon as the most powerful deity.</s>
 <s id="26">Her odes to Inanna mark the first time an author writes using the pronoun “I,” and the first time writing is used to explore deep, private emotions.</s>
 <s id="27">After the death of Enheduanna’s father, King Sargon, a general took advantage of the power vacuum and staged a coup.</s>
 <s id="28">As a powerful member of the ruling family, Enheduanna was a target, and the general exiled her from Ur.</s>
 <s id="29">Her nephew, the legendary Sumerian king Naram-Sin, ultimately crushed the uprising and restored his aunt as high priestess.</s>
 <s id="30">In total, Enheduanna served as high priestess for 40 years.</s>
 <s id="31">After her death, she became a minor deity, and her poetry was copied, studied, and performed throughout the empire for over 500 years.</s>
 <s id="32">Her poems influenced the Hebrew Old Testament, the epics of Homer, and Christian hymns.</s>
 <s id="33">Today, Enheduanna’s legacy still exists, on clay tablets that have stood the test of time.</s>
</text>
