<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I love airplanes.</s>
 <s id="2">Oh -- I love airplanes.</s>
 <s id="3">So, when I went to college in the late 90s, it was obvious that I was going to study aerospace.</s>
 <s id="4">And you wouldn't believe how many people told me, "Oh no, not aerospace.</s>
 <s id="5">Aerospace is going to be boring, everything in aerospace has already been done."</s>
 <s id="6">Well, they were a little bit off the mark.</s>
 <s id="7">And in fact, I think the next decade is going to be another golden age for aviation.</s>
 <s id="8">For one thing, and this is where I get excited, flight is about to get a lot more personal.</s>
 <s id="9">So, a little compare and contrast.</s>
 <s id="10">In the last century, large commercial airplanes have connected cities across the globe.</s>
 <s id="11">And 100 years ago, it would have been unthinkable for all of us to fly here from around the world for a five-day conference.</s>
 <s id="12">But we did, and most of us probably without a second thought.</s>
 <s id="13">And that's a remarkable achievement for humanity.</s>
 <s id="14">But on a day-to-day basis, we still spend a lot of time in cars.</s>
 <s id="15">Or actively trying to avoid it.</s>
 <s id="16">Some of my best friends live in San Francisco, I live in Mountain View, about 40 miles away.</s>
 <s id="17">We're all busy.</s>
 <s id="18">At the end of the day, we're separated by something like two hours of heavy traffic.</s>
 <s id="19">So frankly, we haven't seen each other in a few months.</s>
 <s id="20">Now, I work in downtown San Jose, which is near the airport.</s>
 <s id="21">And there are actually days when I can leave work, get on a plane and fly to Los Angeles faster than I can drive to San Francisco.</s>
 <s id="22">Cities are only getting more populated, the roads are full, and it's really difficult to expand them.</s>
 <s id="23">And so in a lot of places, there really aren't a lot of good solutions for getting around traffic.</s>
 <s id="24">But what if you could fly over it?</s>
 <s id="25">The sky is underutilized, and I would argue it will never be as congested as the roads are.</s>
 <s id="26">First of all, you've got a whole other dimension, but also just safety considerations and air-traffic management will not allow bumper-to-bumper traffic in the sky.</s>
 <s id="27">Which means, in many cases, flying can be a long-term, compelling alternative to traveling on the ground.</s>
 <s id="28">So imagine this: you call an Uber, it takes you to a nearby landing spot -- we call these vertiports -- there's an airplane waiting for you there, flies you over all of the traffic in the middle, and on the other side, another Uber takes you to your friend's house.</s>
 <s id="29">And I said Uber, but I really think we need to congratulate the Lyft branding team for their forward thinking in choosing their brand.</s>
 <s id="30">(Laughter) So in that example, OK, there are a few extra steps, I admit.</s>
 <s id="31">But it's 30 minutes versus two hours, it costs around 60 dollars, and you get to fly.</s>
 <s id="32">We're not there yet, but we are a lot closer than you might think.</s>
 <s id="33">So one of the first things we need is we need an aircraft that can take off and land in small spaces and quickly take you where you want to go.</s>
 <s id="34">And helicopters can do that today, but traditionally, helicopters have been just a little bit too expensive, just a little too hard to pilot and just a little too noisy to be used for daily transportation in cities.</s>
 <s id="35">Well, electric flight and autonomy are changing that.</s>
 <s id="36">Electric flight, in particular, unlocks new possibilities for vehicle configurations that we just could not explore in the past.</s>
 <s id="37">If you use electric motors, you can have many of them around the aircraft, and it doesn't add a lot of extra weight.</s>
 <s id="38">And that gives you redundancy and safety.</s>
 <s id="39">And also, they are cleaner, cheaper and quieter than internal combustion engines.</s>
 <s id="40">Autonomy allows the transportation network to scale, and I actually think it makes the aircraft safer.</s>
 <s id="41">Commercial flights are already automated for most of their duration, and I believe there will come a day when we won't even trust an airplane that required a human to fly.</s>
 <s id="42">So, one of our teams at A3 wanted to see just how close this future really was.</s>
 <s id="43">So they built and flew a prototype of one such vehicle.</s>
 <s id="44">And they made a point of only using mature, commercially available technologies today.</s>
 <s id="45">We call it Vahana.</s>
 <s id="46">It's fully electric.</s>
 <s id="47">It takes off and lands vertically, but flies forward like a regular airplane.</s>
 <s id="48">It's fully self-piloted.</s>
 <s id="49">You push a button, it takes off, flies and lands, all by itself.</s>
 <s id="50">The prototype that you see here is designed to carry a single passenger and luggage.</s>
 <s id="51">And it can go about 20 miles in 15 minutes.</s>
 <s id="52">And our estimate for a trip like that is it would cost around 40 dollars, which you can really build a business around.</s>
 <s id="53">It has multiple redundant motors and batteries, you can lose one, it will continue flying and land normally.</s>
 <s id="54">It's pretty quiet.</s>
 <s id="55">When it's flying overhead, it will be quieter than a Prius on the highway.</s>
 <s id="56">It's intelligent and has cameras, lidar and radar, so it can detect and avoid unexpected obstacles.</s>
 <s id="57">And the team really focused on making it efficient, so the batteries are small, light, and they last longer.</s>
 <s id="58">For reference, the Vahana battery is less than half the size of a Tesla Model S battery.</s>
 <s id="59">It's about 40 kilowatt-hours.</s>
 <s id="60">And you can hot swap the batteries in just a few minutes.</s>
 <s id="61">And I do think that in a few years, people will be comfortable getting by themselves in a self-piloted, electric, VTOL air taxi.</s>
 <s id="62">But the team is busy working on the next version, which is going to carry at least two passengers and fly quite a bit farther.</s>
 <s id="63">But more importantly, there are over 20 companies around the world working on vehicles just like this one right now.</s>
 <s id="64">My best guess is in the next five years, you'll start seeing vertiports in some cities, and little airplane icons on your ride-sharing apps.</s>
 <s id="65">And it might begin with a dozen, but eventually, we could have hundreds of these, flying around our cities.</s>
 <s id="66">And it will fundamentally transform our relationship with local travel.</s>
 <s id="67">In the past century, flight connected our planet, in the next, it will reconnect our local communities, and I hope it will reconnect us to each other.</s>
 <s id="68">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="69">(Applause) Chris Anderson: OK, so when these things first roll out -- right now, it's a single person aircraft, right?</s>
 <s id="70">Rodin Lyasoff: Ours is, yes.</s>
 <s id="71">CA: Yours is.</s>
 <s id="72">I mean, someone comes out of their car, the door opens, they get in, there's no one else in there.</s>
 <s id="73">This thing takes off.</s>
 <s id="74">Could we do a poll here?</s>
 <s id="75">Because these are early adopters in this room.</s>
 <s id="76">I want to know who here is excited about the idea of being picked up solo in an auto-flying -- Well, there you go!</s>
 <s id="77">RL: It's pretty good.</s>
 <s id="78">CA: That is pretty awesome, half of TED is completely stark staring bonkers.</s>
 <s id="79">(Laughter) RL: So, one of the things we're really focusing on is, really, the cost.</s>
 <s id="80">So you can really wrap a business around that.</s>
 <s id="81">And so, that's why some of the features are really driven by price.</s>
 <s id="82">And the 40-dollar price tag is really a target that we're aiming for.</s>
 <s id="83">Which should make it accessible to a larger crowd than this one.</s>
 <s id="84">CA: The biggest blockage in terms of when this rolls out is probably not the technology at this point -- it's regulation, right?</s>
 <s id="85">RL: That's probably true, yes, I would agree with that.</s>
 <s id="86">The technology need to mature in terms of safety, to get to the safety levels that we expect from aircraft.</s>
 <s id="87">But I don't think there are any blockers there, just work needs to get done.</s>
 <s id="88">CA: So, first, this is ride sharing.</s>
 <s id="89">Are we that far away from a time when lots of people have one of these in their garage and just kind of, go direct to their friend's house?</s>
 <s id="90">RL: My personal view is that ride sharing actually allows you to operate that entire business much more efficiently.</s>
 <s id="91">You know, there are millennials that say they never want to own a car.</s>
 <s id="92">I think they'll probably feel even stronger about aircraft.</s>
 <s id="93">So -- (Laughter) I really think that the network scales and operates a lot better as a ride-sharing platform, also because the integration with air-traffic management works a lot better if it's handled centrally.</s>
 <p id="p94">
  <s id="94.1">CA: Cool.</s>
  <s id="94.2">Thank you for that.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p95">
  <s id="95.1">RL: Thank you.</s>
  <s id="95.2">CA: That was amazing.</s>
 </p>
</text>
