<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">What do Charles Darwin, Michael Jordan, and Yoda have in common?</s>
 <s id="2">They, like many other historical and fictive individuals, are bald, in some cases by their own choice.</s>
 <s id="3">For centuries, a shining dome has been a symbol of intelligence, but despite this, many balding people still wish their hair would return.</s>
 <s id="4">Scientists have long pondered, "Why do some people lose their hair, and how can we bring it back?"</s>
 <s id="5">The full-headed among us have about 100,000 to 150,000 hairs on our scalps, and scientists have discovered two things about this dense thicket.</s>
 <s id="6">Firstly, the sprouting hair we see is mostly made up of keratin, the protein leftover from dead cells that are forced upwards as new cells grow beneath them.</s>
 <s id="7">Secondly, the structures that drive hair growth are called hair follicles, a network of complex organs that forms before we're born, and grows hair in an everlasting cycle.</s>
 <s id="8">This cycle has three main phases.</s>
 <s id="9">The first is anagen, the growth phase, which up to 90% of your hair follicles are experiencing right now, causing them to push up hair at a rate of one centimeter per month.</s>
 <s id="10">Anagen can last for two to seven years, depending on your genes.</s>
 <s id="11">After this productive period, signals within the skin instruct some follicles to enter a new phase known as catagen, or the regressing stage, causing hair follicles to shrink to a fraction of their original length.</s>
 <s id="12">Catagen lasts for about two to three weeks and cuts blood supply to the follicle, creating a club hair, meaning it's ready to be shed.</s>
 <s id="13">Finally, hairs enter telogen, the resting phase, which lasts for ten to twelve weeks, and affects about 5-15% of your scalp follicles.</s>
 <s id="14">During telogen, up to 200 club hairs can be shed in a day, which is quite normal.</s>
 <s id="15">Then, the growth cycle begins anew.</s>
 <s id="16">But not all heads are hairy, and, in fact, some of them grow increasingly patchy over time in response to bodily changes.</s>
 <s id="17">95% of baldness in men can be attributed to male pattern baldness.</s>
 <s id="18">Baldness is inherited, and in people with this condition, follicles become incredibly sensitive to the effects of dihydrotestosterone, a hormonal product made from testosterone.</s>
 <s id="19">DHT causes shrinkage in these overly sensitive follicles, making hair shorter and wispier.</s>
 <s id="20">But loss isn't sudden.</s>
 <s id="21">It happens gradually, along a metric known as the Norwood Scale, which describes the severity of hair loss.</s>
 <s id="22">First, hair recedes along the temples, then hair on the crown begins to thin in a circular pattern.</s>
 <s id="23">At the highest rating on the scale, these balding areas meet and expand dramatically, eventually leaving only a ring of sparse hair around the temples and the back of the head.</s>
 <s id="24">Genetics isn't all that drives hair loss.</s>
 <s id="25">Long periods of stress can release signals that shock follicles and force them into the resting phase prematurely.</s>
 <s id="26">Some women experience this after childbirth.</s>
 <s id="27">Follicles might also lose the ability to go into anagen, the growth phase.</s>
 <s id="28">People going through chemotherapy treatment temporarily experience this.</s>
 <s id="29">But while balding may look permanent, scientific investigation has revealed the opposite.</s>
 <s id="30">Below the skin's surface, the roots that give rise to our hair actually remain alive.</s>
 <s id="31">Using this knowledge, scientists have developed drugs that shorten the resting phase, and force follicles into anagen.</s>
 <s id="32">Other drugs combat male pattern baldness by blocking the conversion of testosterone to DHT so that it doesn't affect those sensitive follicles.</s>
 <s id="33">Stem cells also play a role in regulating the growth cycle, and so scientists are investigating whether they can manipulate the activity of these cells to encourage follicles to start producing hair again.</s>
 <s id="34">And in the meantime, while scientists hone their hair-reviving methods, anyone going bald, or considering baldness, can remember that they're in great company.</s>
</text>
