<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Have you ever noticed something swimming in your field of vision?</s>
 <s id="2">It may look like a tiny worm or a transparent blob, and whenever you try to get a closer look, it disappears, only to reappear as soon as you shift your glance.</s>
 <s id="3">But don't go rinsing out your eyes!</s>
 <s id="4">What you are seeing is a common phenomenon known as a floater.</s>
 <s id="5">The scientific name for these objects is Muscae volitantes, Latin for "flying flies," and true to their name, they can be somewhat annoying.</s>
 <s id="6">But they're not actually bugs or any kind of external objects at all.</s>
 <s id="7">Rather, they exist inside your eyeball.</s>
 <s id="8">Floaters may seem to be alive, since they move and change shape, but they are not alive.</s>
 <s id="9">Floaters are tiny objects that cast shadows on the retina, the light-sensitive tissue at the back of your eye.</s>
 <s id="10">They might be bits of tissue, red blood cells, or clumps of protein.</s>
 <s id="11">And because they're suspended within the vitreous humor, the gel-like liquid that fills the inside of your eye, floaters drift along with your eye movements, and seem to bounce a little when your eye stops.</s>
 <s id="12">Floaters may be only barely distinguishable most of the time.</s>
 <s id="13">They become more visible the closer they are to the retina, just as holding your hand closer to a table with an overhead light will result in a more sharply defined shadow.</s>
 <s id="14">And floaters are particularly noticeable when you are looking at a uniform bright surface, like a blank computer screen, snow, or a clear sky, where the consistency of the background makes them easier to distinguish.</s>
 <s id="15">The brighter the light is, the more your pupil contracts.</s>
 <s id="16">This has an effect similar to replacing a large diffuse light fixture with a single overhead light bulb, which also makes the shadow appear clearer.</s>
 <s id="17">There is another visual phenomenon that looks similar to floaters but is in fact unrelated.</s>
 <s id="18">If you've seen tiny dots of light darting about when looking at a bright blue sky, you've experienced what is known as the blue field entoptic phenomenon.</s>
 <s id="19">In some ways, this is the opposite of seeing floaters.</s>
 <s id="20">Here, you are not seeing shadows but little moving windows letting light through to your retina.</s>
 <s id="21">The windows are actually caused by white blood cells moving through the capillaries along your retina's surface.</s>
 <s id="22">These leukocytes can be so large that they nearly fill a capillary causing a plasma space to open up in front of them.</s>
 <s id="23">Because the space and the white blood cells are both more transparent to blue light than the red blood cells normally present in capillaries, we see a moving dot of light wherever this happens, following the paths of your capillaries and moving in time with your pulse.</s>
 <s id="24">Under ideal viewing conditions, you might even see what looks like a dark tail following the dot.</s>
 <s id="25">This is the red blood cells that have bunched up behind the leukocyte.</s>
 <s id="26">Some science museums have an exhibit which consists of a screen of blue light, allowing you to see these blue sky sprites much more clearly than you normally would.</s>
 <s id="27">While everybody's eyes experience these sort of effects, the number and type vary greatly.</s>
 <s id="28">In the case of floaters, they often go unnoticed, as our brain learns to ignore them.</s>
 <s id="29">However, abnormally numerous or large floaters that interfere with vision may be a sign of a more serious condition, requiring immediate medical treatment.</s>
 <s id="30">But the majority of the time entoptic phenomena, such as floaters and blue sky sprites, are just a gentle reminder that what we think we see depends just as much on our biology and minds as it does on the external world.</s>
</text>
