<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Corn currently accounts for more than one tenth of our global crop production.</s>
 <s id="2">The United States alone has enough cornfields to cover Germany.</s>
 <s id="3">But while other crops we grow come in a range of varieties, over 99% of cultivated corn is the exact same type: Yellow Dent #2.</s>
 <s id="4">This means that humans grow more Yellow Dent #2 than any other plant on the planet.</s>
 <s id="5">So how did this single variety of this single plant become the biggest success story in agricultural history?</s>
 <s id="6">Nearly 9,000 years ago, corn, also called maize, was first domesticated from teosinte, a grass native to Mesoamerica.</s>
 <s id="7">Teosinte’s rock-hard seeds were barely edible, but its fibrous husk could be turned into a versatile material.</s>
 <s id="8">Over the next 4,700 years, farmers bred the plant into a staple crop, with larger cobs and edible kernels.</s>
 <s id="9">As maize spread throughout the Americas, it took on an important role, with multiple indigenous societies revering a “Corn Mother” as the goddess who created agriculture.</s>
 <s id="10">When Europeans first arrived in America, they shunned the strange plant.</s>
 <s id="11">Many even believed it was the source of physical and cultural differences between them and the Mesoamericans.</s>
 <s id="12">However, their attempts to cultivate European crops in American soil quickly failed, and the settlers were forced to expand their diet.</s>
 <s id="13">Finding the crop to their taste, maize soon crossed the Atlantic, where its ability to grow in diverse climates made it a popular grain in many European countries.</s>
 <s id="14">But the newly established United States was still the corn capital of the world.</s>
 <s id="15">In the early 1800’s, different regions across the country produced strains of varying size and taste.</s>
 <s id="16">In the 1850’s, however, these unique varieties proved difficult for train operators to package, and for traders to sell.</s>
 <s id="17">Trade boards in rail hubs like Chicago encouraged corn farmers to breed one standardized crop.</s>
 <s id="18">This dream would finally be realized at 1893’s World’s Fair, where James Reid’s yellow dent corn won the Blue Ribbon.</s>
 <s id="19">Over the next 50 years, yellow dent corn swept the nation.</s>
 <s id="20">Following the technological developments of World War II, mechanized harvesters became widely available.</s>
 <s id="21">This meant a batch of corn that previously took a full day to harvest by hand could now be collected in just 5 minutes.</s>
 <s id="22">Another wartime technology, the chemical explosive ammonium nitrate, also found new life on the farm.</s>
 <s id="23">With this new synthetic fertilizer, farmers could plant dense fields of corn year after year, without the need to rotate their crops and restore nitrogen to the soil.</s>
 <s id="24">While these advances made corn an attractive crop to American farmers, US agricultural policy limited the amount farmers could grow to ensure high sale prices.</s>
 <s id="25">But in 1972, President Richard Nixon removed these limitations while negotiating massive grain sales to the Soviet Union.</s>
 <s id="26">With this new trade deal and WWII technology, corn production exploded into a global phenomenon.</s>
 <s id="27">These mountains of maize inspired numerous corn concoctions.</s>
 <s id="28">Cornstarch could be used as a thickening agent for everything from gasoline to glue or processed into a low-cost sweetener known as High-Fructose Corn Syrup.</s>
 <s id="29">Maize quickly became one of the cheapest animal feeds worldwide.</s>
 <s id="30">This allowed for inexpensive meat production, which in turn increased the demand for meat and corn feed.</s>
 <s id="31">Today, humans eat only 40% of all cultivated corn, while the remaining 60% supports consumer good industries worldwide.</s>
 <s id="32">Yet the spread of this wonder-crop has come at a price.</s>
 <s id="33">Global water sources are polluted by excess ammonium nitrate from cornfields.</s>
 <s id="34">Corn accounts for a large portion of agriculture-related carbon emissions, partly due to the increased meat production it enables.</s>
 <s id="35">The use of high fructose corn syrup may be a contributor to diabetes and obesity.</s>
 <s id="36">And the rise of monoculture farming has left our food supply dangerously vulnerable to pests and pathogens— a single virus could infect the world’s supply of this ubiquitous crop.</s>
 <s id="37">Corn has gone from a bushy grass to an essential element of the world’s industries.</s>
 <s id="38">But only time will tell if it has led us into a maze of unsustainability.</s>
</text>
