<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">It was less than a year after September 11, and I was at the Chicago Tribune writing about shootings and murders, and it was leaving me feeling pretty dark and depressed.</s>
 <s id="2">I had done some activism in college, so I decided to help a local group hang door knockers against animal testing.</s>
 <s id="3">I thought it would be a safe way to do something positive, but of course I have the absolute worst luck ever, and we were all arrested.</s>
 <s id="4">Police took this blurry photo of me holding leaflets as evidence.</s>
 <s id="5">My charges were dismissed, but a few weeks later, two FBI agents knocked on my door, and they told me that unless I helped them by spying on protest groups, they would put me on a domestic terrorist list.</s>
 <s id="6">I'd love to tell you that I didn't flinch, but I was terrified, and when my fear subsided, I became obsessed with finding out how this happened, how animal rights and environmental activists who have never injured anyone could become the FBI's number one domestic terrorism threat.</s>
 <s id="7">A few years later, I was invited to testify before Congress about my reporting, and I told lawmakers that, while everybody is talking about going green, some people are risking their lives to defend forests and to stop oil pipelines.</s>
 <s id="8">They're physically putting their bodies on the line between the whalers' harpoons and the whales.</s>
 <s id="9">These are everyday people, like these protesters in Italy who spontaneously climbed over barbed wire fences to rescue beagles from animal testing.</s>
 <s id="10">And these movements have been incredibly effective and popular, so in 1985, their opponents made up a new word, eco-terrorist, to shift how we view them.</s>
 <s id="11">They just made it up.</s>
 <s id="12">Now these companies have backed new laws like the Animal Enterprise Terrorism Act, which turns activism into terrorism if it causes a loss of profits.</s>
 <s id="13">Now most people never even heard about this law, including members of Congress.</s>
 <s id="14">Less than one percent were in the room when it passed the House.</s>
 <s id="15">The rest were outside at a new memorial.</s>
 <s id="16">They were praising Dr. King as his style of activism was branded as terrorism if done in the name of animals or the environment.</s>
 <s id="17">Supporters say laws like this are needed for the extremists: the vandals, the arsonists, the radicals.</s>
 <s id="18">But right now, companies like TransCanada are briefing police in presentations like this one about how to prosecute nonviolent protesters as terrorists.</s>
 <s id="19">The FBI's training documents on eco-terrorism are not about violence, they're about public relations.</s>
 <s id="20">Today, in multiple countries, corporations are pushing new laws that make it illegal to photograph animal cruelty on their farms.</s>
 <s id="21">The latest was in Idaho just two weeks ago, and today we released a lawsuit challenging it as unconstitutional as a threat to journalism.</s>
 <s id="22">The first of these ag-gag prosecutions, as they're called, was a young woman named Amy Meyer, and Amy saw a sick cow being moved by a bulldozer outside of a slaughterhouse as she was on the public street.</s>
 <s id="23">And Amy did what any of us would: She filmed it.</s>
 <s id="24">When I found out about her story, I wrote about it, and within 24 hours, it created such an uproar that the prosecutors just dropped all the charges.</s>
 <s id="25">But apparently, even exposing stuff like that is a threat.</s>
 <s id="26">Through the Freedom of Information Act, I learned that the counter-terrorism unit has been monitoring my articles and speeches like this one.</s>
 <s id="27">They even included this nice little write-up of my book.</s>
 <s id="28">They described it as "compelling and well-written."</s>
 <s id="29">(Applause) Blurb on the next book, right?</s>
 <s id="30">The point of all of this is to make us afraid, but as a journalist, I have an unwavering faith in the power of education.</s>
 <s id="31">Our best weapon is sunlight.</s>
 <s id="32">Dostoevsky wrote that the whole work of man is to prove he's a man and not a piano key.</s>
 <s id="33">Over and over throughout history, people in power have used fear to silence the truth and to silence dissent.</s>
 <s id="34">It's time we strike a new note.</s>
 <s id="35">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="36">(Applause)</s>
</text>
