<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Everybody in our society's life is touched by cancer -- if not personally, then through a loved one, a family member, colleague, friend.</s>
 <s id="2">And once our lives are touched by cancer, we quickly learn that there are basically three weapons, or three tools, that are available to fight the disease: surgery, radiation and chemotherapy.</s>
 <s id="3">And once we get involved in the therapeutic decisions, again either personally or with our loved ones and family members, we also very quickly learn the benefits, the trade-offs and the limitations of these tools.</s>
 <s id="4">I'm very thankful to Jay and to Mark and the TEDMED team for inviting me today to describe a fourth tool, a new tool, that we call Tumor Treating Fields.</s>
 <s id="5">Tumor Treating Fields were invented by Dr. Yoram Palti, professor emeritus at the Technion in Israel.</s>
 <s id="6">And they use low-intensity electric fields to fight cancer.</s>
 <s id="7">To understand how Tumor Treating Fields work, we first need to understand what are electric fields.</s>
 <s id="8">Let me first address a few popular misconceptions.</s>
 <s id="9">First of all, electric fields are not an electric current that is coursing through the tissue.</s>
 <s id="10">Electric fields are not ionizing radiation, like X-rays or proton beams, that bombard tissue to disrupt DNA.</s>
 <s id="11">And electric fields are not magnetism.</s>
 <s id="12">What electric fields are are a field of forces.</s>
 <s id="13">And these forces act on, attract, bodies that have an electrical charge.</s>
 <s id="14">The best way to visualize an electric field is to think of gravity.</s>
 <s id="15">Gravity is also a field of forces that act on masses.</s>
 <s id="16">We can all picture astronauts in space.</s>
 <s id="17">They float freely in three dimensions without any forces acting on them.</s>
 <s id="18">But as that space shuttle returns to Earth, and as the astronauts enter the Earth's gravitational field, they begin to see the effects of gravity.</s>
 <s id="19">They begin to be attracted towards Earth.</s>
 <s id="20">And as they land, they're fully aligned in the gravitational field.</s>
 <s id="21">We're, of course, all stuck in the Earth's gravitational field right now.</s>
 <s id="22">That's why you're all in your chairs.</s>
 <s id="23">And that's why we have to use our muscle energy to stand up, to walk around and to lift things.</s>
 <s id="24">In cancer, cells rapidly divide and lead to uncontrolled tumor growth.</s>
 <s id="25">We can think of a cell from an electrical perspective as if it's a mini space station.</s>
 <s id="26">And in that space station we have the genetic material, the chromosomes, within a nucleus.</s>
 <s id="27">And out in the cytoplasmic soup we have special proteins that are required for cell division that float freely in this soup in three dimensions.</s>
 <s id="28">Importantly, those special proteins are among the most highly charged objects in our body.</s>
 <s id="29">As cell division begins the nucleus disintegrates, the chromosomes line up in the middle of the cell and those special proteins undergo a three-dimensional sequence whereby they attach and they literally click into place end-on-end to form chains.</s>
 <s id="30">These chains then progress and attach to the genetic material and pull the genetic material from one cell into two cells.</s>
 <s id="31">And this is exactly how one cancer cell becomes two cancer cells, two cancer cells become four cancer cells, and we have ultimately uncontrolled tumor growth.</s>
 <s id="32">Tumor Treating Fields use externally placed transducers attached to a field generator to create an artificial electric field on that space station.</s>
 <s id="33">And when that cellular space station is within the electric field, it acts on those highly charged proteins and aligns them.</s>
 <s id="34">And it prevents them from forming those chains, those mitotic spindles, that are necessary to pull the genetic material into the daughter cells.</s>
 <s id="35">What we see is that the cells will attempt to divide for several hours.</s>
 <s id="36">And they will either enter into this so-called cellular suicide, programmed cell death, or they will form unhealthy daughter cells and enter into apoptosis once they have divided.</s>
 <s id="37">And we can observe this.</s>
 <s id="38">What I'm going to show you next are two in vitro experiments.</s>
 <s id="39">This is cultures, identical cultures, of cervical cancer cells.</s>
 <s id="40">And we've stained these cultures with a green florescent dye so that we can look at these proteins that form these chains.</s>
 <s id="41">The first clip shows a normal cell division without the Tumor Treating Fields.</s>
 <s id="42">What we see are, first of all, a very active culture, a lot of divisions, and then very clear nuclei once the cells have separated.</s>
 <s id="43">And we can see them dividing throughout.</s>
 <s id="44">When we apply the fields -- again, in the identical time-scale to the identical culture -- you're going to see something different.</s>
 <s id="45">The cells round up for division, but they're very static in that position.</s>
 <s id="46">We'll see two cells in the upper part of the screen attempting to divide.</s>
 <s id="47">The one within the circle manages.</s>
 <s id="48">But see how much of the protein is still throughout the nucleus, even in the dividing cell.</s>
 <s id="49">The one up there can't divide at all.</s>
 <s id="50">And then this bubbling, this membrane bubbling, is the hallmark of apoptosis in this cell.</s>
 <s id="51">Formation of healthy mitotic spindles is necessary for division in all cell types.</s>
 <s id="52">We've applied Tumor Treating Fields to over 20 different cancers in the lab, and we see this effect in all of them.</s>
 <s id="53">Now importantly, these Tumor Treating Fields have no effect on normal undividing cells.</s>
 <s id="54">10 years ago, Dr. Palti founded a company called Novocure to develop his discovery into a practical therapy for patients.</s>
 <s id="55">In that time, Novocure's developed two systems -- one system for cancers in the head and another system for cancers in the trunk of the body.</s>
 <s id="56">The first cancer that we have focused on is the deadly brain cancer, GBM.</s>
 <s id="57">GBM affects about 10,000 people in the U.S. each year.</s>
 <s id="58">It's a death sentence.</s>
 <s id="59">The expected five year survival is less than five percent.</s>
 <s id="60">And the typical patient with optimal therapy survives just a little over a year, and only about seven months from the time that the cancer is first treated and then comes back and starts growing again.</s>
 <s id="61">Novocure conducted its first phase three randomized trial in patients with recurrent GBM.</s>
 <s id="62">So these are patients who had received surgery, high dose radiation to the head and first-line chemotherapy, and that had failed and their tumors had grown back.</s>
 <s id="63">We divided the patients into two groups.</s>
 <s id="64">The first group received second-line chemotherapy, which is expected to double the life expectancy, versus no treatment at all.</s>
 <s id="65">And then the second group received only Tumor Treating Field therapy.</s>
 <s id="66">What we saw in that trial is that that the life expectancies of both groups -- so the chemotherapy treated group and the Tumor Treating Field group -- was the same.</s>
 <s id="67">But importantly, the Tumor Treating Field group suffered none of the side effects typical of chemotherapy patients.</s>
 <s id="68">They had no pain, suffered none of the infections.</s>
 <s id="69">They had no nausea, diarrhea, constipation, fatigue that would be expected.</s>
 <s id="70">Based on this trial, in April of this year, the FDA approved Tumor Treating Fields for the treatment of patients with recurrent GBM.</s>
 <s id="71">Importantly, it was the first time ever that the FDA included in their approval of an oncology treatment a quality of life claim.</s>
 <s id="72">So I'm going to show you now one of the patients from this trial.</s>
 <s id="73">Robert Dill-Bundi is a famous Swiss cycling champion.</s>
 <s id="74">He won the gold medal in Moscow in the 4,000 meter pursuit.</s>
 <s id="75">And five years ago, Robert was diagnosed with GBM.</s>
 <s id="76">He received the standard treatments.</s>
 <s id="77">He received surgery.</s>
 <s id="78">He received high dose radiation to the head.</s>
 <s id="79">And he received first-line chemotherapy.</s>
 <s id="80">A year after this treatment -- in fact, this is his baseline MRI.</s>
 <s id="81">You can see that the black regions in the upper right quadrant are the areas where he had surgery.</s>
 <s id="82">And a year after that treatment, his tumor grew back with a vengeance.</s>
 <s id="83">That cloudy white mass that you see is the recurrence of the tumor.</s>
 <s id="84">At this point, he was told by his doctors that he had about 3 months to live.</s>
 <s id="85">He entered our trial.</s>
 <s id="86">And here we can see him getting the therapy.</s>
 <s id="87">First of all, these electrodes are noninvasive.</s>
 <s id="88">They're attached to the skin in the area of the tumor.</s>
 <s id="89">Here you can see that a technician is placing them on there much like bandages.</s>
 <s id="90">The patients learn to do this themselves And then the patients can undergo all the activities of their daily life.</s>
 <s id="91">There's none of the tiredness.</s>
 <s id="92">There's none of what is called the "chemo head."</s>
 <s id="93">There's no sensation.</s>
 <s id="94">It doesn't interfere with computers or electrical equipment.</s>
 <s id="95">And the therapy is delivered continuously at home, without having to go into the hospital either periodically or continually.</s>
 <s id="96">These are Robert's MRIs, again, under only TTField treatment.</s>
 <s id="97">This is a therapy that takes time to work.</s>
 <s id="98">It's a medical device; it works when it's on.</s>
 <s id="99">But what we can see is, by month six, the tumor has responded and it's begun to melt away.</s>
 <s id="100">It's still there.</s>
 <s id="101">By month 12, we could argue whether there's a little bit of material around the edges, but it's essentially completely gone.</s>
 <s id="102">It's now five years since Robert's diagnosis, and he's alive, but importantly, he's healthy and he's at work.</s>
 <s id="103">I'm going to let him, in this very short clip, describe his impressions of the therapy in his own words.</s>
 <s id="104">(Video) Robert Dill-Bundi: My quality of life, I rate what I have today a bit different than what most people would assume.</s>
 <s id="105">I am the happiest, the happiest person in the world.</s>
 <s id="106">And every single morning I appreciate life.</s>
 <s id="107">Every night I fall asleep very well, and I am, I repeat, the happiest man in the world, and I'm thankful I am alive.</s>
 <s id="108">BD: Novocure's also working on lung cancer as the second target.</s>
 <s id="109">We've run a phase two trial in Switzerland on, again, recurrent patients -- patients who have received standard therapy and whose cancer has come back.</s>
 <s id="110">I'm going to show you another clip of a woman named Lydia.</s>
 <s id="111">Lydia's a 66 year-old farmer in Switzerland.</s>
 <s id="112">She was diagnosed with lung cancer five years ago.</s>
 <s id="113">She underwent four different regimes of chemotherapy over two years, none of which had an effect.</s>
 <s id="114">Her cancer continued to grow.</s>
 <s id="115">Three years ago, she entered the Novocure lung cancer trial.</s>
 <s id="116">You can see, in her case, she's wearing her transducer arrays, one of the front of her chest, one on the back, and then the second pair side-to-side over the liver.</s>
 <s id="117">You can see the Tumor Treating Field field generator, but importantly you can also see that she is living her life.</s>
 <s id="118">She is managing her farm.</s>
 <s id="119">She's interacting with her kids and her grand kids.</s>
 <s id="120">And when we talked to her, she said that when she was undergoing chemotherapy, she had to go to the hospital every month for her infusions.</s>
 <s id="121">Her whole family suffered as her side effect profile came and went.</s>
 <s id="122">Now she can run all of the activities of her farm.</s>
 <s id="123">It's only the beginning.</s>
 <s id="124">(Applause) In the lab, we've observed tremendous synergies between chemotherapy and Tumor Treating Fields.</s>
 <s id="125">There's research underway now at Harvard Medical School to pick the optimum pairs to maximize that benefit.</s>
 <s id="126">We also believe that Tumor Treating Fields will work with radiation and interrupt the self-repair mechanisms that we have.</s>
 <s id="127">There's now a new research project underway at the Karolinska in Sweden to prove that hypothesis.</s>
 <s id="128">We have more trials planned for lung cancer, pancreatic cancer, ovarian cancer and breast cancer.</s>
 <s id="129">And I firmly believe that in the next 10 years Tumor Treating Fields will be a weapon available to doctors and patients for all of these most-difficult-to-treat solid tumors.</s>
 <s id="130">I'm also very hopeful that in the next decades, we will make big strides on reducing that death rate that has been so challenging in this disease.</s>
 <s id="131">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="132">(Applause)</s>
</text>
