<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Guys, we have an issue.</s>
 <s id="2">(Laughter) Growth is fading away, and it's a big deal.</s>
 <s id="3">Our global economy stops growing.</s>
 <s id="4">And it's not new.</s>
 <s id="5">Growth has actually declined for the last 50 years.</s>
 <s id="6">If we continue like this, we need to learn how to live in a world with no growth in the next decade.</s>
 <s id="7">This is scary because when the economy doesn't grow, our children don't get better lives.</s>
 <s id="8">What's even scarier is that when the pie does not grow, each of us get a smaller piece.</s>
 <s id="9">We're then ready to fight for a bigger one.</s>
 <s id="10">This creates tensions and serious conflicts.</s>
 <s id="11">Growth matters a lot.</s>
 <s id="12">If we look at the history of growth, times of big growth have always been fueled by big manufacturing revolutions.</s>
 <s id="13">It happened three times, every 50-60 years.</s>
 <s id="14">The steam engine in the middle of the 19th century, the mass-production model in the beginning of the 20th century -- thanks, Mr. Ford.</s>
 <s id="15">And the first automation wave in the 1970s.</s>
 <s id="16">Why did these manufacturing revolutions create huge growth in our economies?</s>
 <s id="17">Because they have injected huge productivity improvement.</s>
 <s id="18">It's rather simple: in order to grow, you need to be producing more, putting more into our economy.</s>
 <s id="19">This means either more labor or more capital or more productivity.</s>
 <s id="20">Each time, productivity has been the growth lever.</s>
 <s id="21">I'm here today to tell you that we are on the verge of another huge change, and that this change, surprisingly enough, is going to come from manufacturing, again.</s>
 <s id="22">It will get us out of our growth slump and it will change radically the way globalization has been shaped over the last decade.</s>
 <s id="23">I'm here to tell you about the amazing fourth manufacturing revolution that is currently underway.</s>
 <s id="24">It's not as if we've done nothing with manufacturing since the last revolution.</s>
 <s id="25">Actually, we've made some pretty lame attempts to try to revitalize it.</s>
 <s id="26">But none of them have been the big overhaul we really need to get us growing again.</s>
 <s id="27">For example, we've tried to relocate our factories offshore in order to reduce cost and take advantage of cheap labor.</s>
 <s id="28">Not only did this not inspire productivity, but it only saved money for a short period of time, because cheap labor didn't stay cheap for long.</s>
 <s id="29">Then, we've tried to make our factories larger and we specialized them by product.</s>
 <s id="30">The idea was that we can make a lot of one product and stockpile it to be sold with demand.</s>
 <s id="31">This did help productivity for a while.</s>
 <s id="32">But it introduced a lot of rigidities in our supply chain.</s>
 <s id="33">Let's take fashion retail.</s>
 <s id="34">Traditional clothing companies have built offshore, global, rigid supply chains.</s>
 <s id="35">When fast-fashion competitors like Zara started replenishing their stocks faster from two collections a year to one collection a month, none of them have been able to keep up with the pace.</s>
 <s id="36">Most of them are in great difficulties today.</s>
 <s id="37">Yet, with all of their shortcomings, those are the factories we know today.</s>
 <s id="38">When you open the doors, they look the same as they did 50 years ago.</s>
 <s id="39">We've just changed the location, the size, the way they operate.</s>
 <s id="40">Can you name anything else that looks the same as it did 50 years ago?</s>
 <s id="41">It's crazy.</s>
 <s id="42">We've made all the tweaks to the model that we could, and now we hit its limits.</s>
 <s id="43">After all of our attempts to fix the manufacturing model failed, we thought growth could come from elsewhere.</s>
 <s id="44">We turned to the tech sector -- there's been quite a lot of innovations there.</s>
 <s id="45">Just to name one: the Internet.</s>
 <s id="46">We hoped it could produce growth.</s>
 <s id="47">And indeed, it changed our lives.</s>
 <s id="48">It made big waves in the media, the service, the entertainment spaces.</s>
 <s id="49">But it hasn't done much for productivity.</s>
 <s id="50">Actually, what's surprising is that productivity is on the decline despite all of those innovation efforts.</s>
 <s id="51">Imagine that -- sitting at work, scrolling through Facebook, watching videos on YouTube has made us less productive.</s>
 <s id="52">Weird.</s>
 <s id="53">(Laughter) This is why we are not growing.</s>
 <s id="54">We failed at reinventing the manufacturing space, and large technological innovations have played away from it.</s>
 <s id="55">But what if we could combine those forces?</s>
 <s id="56">What if the existing manufacturing and large technological innovation came together to create the next big manufacturing reinvention.</s>
 <s id="57">Bingo!</s>
 <s id="58">This is the fourth manufacturing revolution, and it's happening right now.</s>
 <s id="59">Major technologies are entering the manufacturing space, big time.</s>
 <s id="60">They will boost industrial productivity by more than a third.</s>
 <s id="61">This is massive, and it will do a lot in creating growth.</s>
 <s id="62">Let me tell you about some of them.</s>
 <s id="63">Have you already met advanced manufacturing robots?</s>
 <s id="64">They are the size of humans, they actually collaborate with them, and they can be programmed in order to perform complex, non-repetitive tasks.</s>
 <s id="65">Today in our factories, only 8 percent of the tasks are automated.</s>
 <s id="66">The less complex, the more repetitive ones.</s>
 <s id="67">It will be 25 percent in 10 years.</s>
 <s id="68">It means that by 2025, advanced robots will complement workers to be, together, 20 percent more productive, to manufacture 20 percent more outputs, to achieve 20 percent additional growth.</s>
 <s id="69">This isn't some fancy, futuristic idea.</s>
 <s id="70">These robots are working for us right now.</s>
 <s id="71">Last year in the US, they helped Amazon prepare and ship all the products required for Cyber Monday, the annual peak of online retail.</s>
 <s id="72">Last year in the US, it was the biggest online shopping day of the year and of history.</s>
 <s id="73">Consumers spent 3 billion dollars on electronics that day.</s>
 <s id="74">That's real economic growth.</s>
 <s id="75">Then there's additive manufacturing, 3D printing.</s>
 <s id="76">3D printing has already improved plastic manufacturing and it's now making its way through metal.</s>
 <s id="77">Those are not small industries.</s>
 <s id="78">Plastic and metals represent 25 percent of global manufacturing production.</s>
 <s id="79">Let's take a real example.</s>
 <s id="80">In the aerospace industry, fuel nozzles are some of the most complex parts to manufacture, for one reason: they are made up of 20 different parts that need to be separately produced and then painstakingly assembled.</s>
 <s id="81">Aerospace companies are now using 3D printing, which allows them to turn those 20 different parts into just one.</s>
 <s id="82">The results?</s>
 <s id="83">40 percent more productivity, 40 percent more output produced, 40 percent more growth for this specific industry.</s>
 <s id="84">But actually, the most exciting part of this new manufacturing revolution goes much beyond productivity.</s>
 <s id="85">It's about producing better, smarter products.</s>
 <s id="86">It's about scale customization.</s>
 <s id="87">Imagine a world where you can buy the exact products you want with the functionalities you need, with the design you want, with the same cost and lead time as a product that's been mass produced, like your car, or your clothes or your cell phone.</s>
 <s id="88">The new manufacturing revolution makes it possible.</s>
 <s id="89">Advanced robots can be programmed in order to perform any product configuration without any setup time or ramp up.</s>
 <s id="90">3D printers instantaneously produce any customized design.</s>
 <s id="91">We are now able to produce a batch of one product, your product, at the same cost and lead time as a batch of many.</s>
 <s id="92">Those are only a few examples of the manufacturing revolution at play.</s>
 <s id="93">Not only will manufacturing become more productive, it will also become more flexible, and those were exactly the elements of growth that we are missing.</s>
 <s id="94">But actually, there are even some bigger implications for all of us when manufacturing will find its way back into the limelight.</s>
 <s id="95">It will create a huge macroeconomic shift.</s>
 <s id="96">First, our factories will be relocated into our home markets.</s>
 <s id="97">In the world of scale customization, consumer proximity is the new norm.</s>
 <s id="98">Then, our factories will be smaller, agile.</s>
 <s id="99">Scale does not matter anymore, flexibility does.</s>
 <s id="100">They will be operating on a multi-product, made-to-order basis.</s>
 <s id="101">The change will be drastic.</s>
 <s id="102">Globalization will enter a new era.</s>
 <s id="103">The East-to-West trade flows will be replaced by regional trade flows.</s>
 <s id="104">East for East, West for West.</s>
 <s id="105">When you think about that, the old model was pretty much insane.</s>
 <s id="106">Piling up stocks, making products travel the whole world before they reach their end consumers.</s>
 <s id="107">The new model, producing just next to the consumer market, will be much cleaner, much better for our environment.</s>
 <s id="108">In mature economies, manufacturing will be back home, creating more employment, more productivity and more growth.</s>
 <s id="109">Good news, isn't it?</s>
 <s id="110">But here's the thing with growth -- it does not come automatically.</s>
 <s id="111">Mature economies will have to seize it.</s>
 <s id="112">We'll have to massively re-train our workforce.</s>
 <s id="113">In most countries, like in my country, France, we've told our children that manufacturing had no future.</s>
 <s id="114">That it was something happening far away.</s>
 <s id="115">We need to reverse that and teach manufacturing again at university.</s>
 <s id="116">Only the countries that will boldly transform will be able to seize this growth.</s>
 <s id="117">It's also a chance for developing economies.</s>
 <s id="118">Of course China and other emerging economies won't be the factory of the world anymore.</s>
 <s id="119">Actually, it was not a sustainable model in the long term, as those countries are becoming richer.</s>
 <s id="120">Last year, it was already as expensive to produce in Brazil as to produce in France.</s>
 <s id="121">By 2018, manufacturing costs in China will be on par with the US.</s>
 <s id="122">The new manufacturing revolution will accelerate the transition of those emerging economies towards a model driven by domestic consumption.</s>
 <s id="123">And this is good, because this is where growth will be created.</s>
 <s id="124">In the next five years, the next billion consumers in China will inject more growth in our economies than the top five European markets together.</s>
 <s id="125">This fourth manufacturing revolution is a chance for all of us.</s>
 <s id="126">If we play it right, we'll see sustainable growth in all of our economies.</s>
 <s id="127">This means more wealth distributed to all of us and a better future for our children.</s>
 <s id="128">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="129">(Applause)</s>
</text>
