<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The story I wanted to share with you today is my challenge as an Iranian artist, as an Iranian woman artist, as an Iranian woman artist living in exile.</s>
 <s id="2">Well, it has its pluses and minuses.</s>
 <s id="3">On the dark side, politics doesn't seem to escape people like me.</s>
 <s id="4">Every Iranian artist, in one form or another, is political.</s>
 <s id="5">Politics have defined our lives.</s>
 <s id="6">If you're living in Iran, you're facing censorship, harassment, arrest, torture -- at times, execution.</s>
 <s id="7">If you're living outside like me, you're faced with life in exile -- the pain of the longing and the separation from your loved ones and your family.</s>
 <s id="8">Therefore, we don't find the moral, emotional, psychological and political space to distance ourselves from the reality of social responsibility.</s>
 <s id="9">Oddly enough, an artist such as myself finds herself also in the position of being the voice, the speaker of my people, even if I have, indeed, no access to my own country.</s>
 <s id="10">Also, people like myself, we're fighting two battles on different grounds.</s>
 <s id="11">We're being critical of the West, the perception of the West about our identity -- about the image that is constructed about us, about our women, about our politics, about our religion.</s>
 <s id="12">We are there to take pride and insist on respect.</s>
 <s id="13">And at the same time, we're fighting another battle.</s>
 <s id="14">That is our regime, our government -- our atrocious government, [that] has done every crime in order to stay in power.</s>
 <s id="15">Our artists are at risk.</s>
 <s id="16">We are in a position of danger.</s>
 <s id="17">We pose a threat to the order of the government.</s>
 <s id="18">But ironically, this situation has empowered all of us, because we are considered, as artists, central to the cultural, political, social discourse in Iran.</s>
 <s id="19">We are there to inspire, to provoke, to mobilize, to bring hope to our people.</s>
 <s id="20">We are the reporters of our people, and are communicators to the outside world.</s>
 <s id="21">Art is our weapon.</s>
 <s id="22">Culture is a form of resistance.</s>
 <s id="23">I envy sometimes the artists of the West for their freedom of expression.</s>
 <s id="24">For the fact that they can distance themselves from the question of politics.</s>
 <s id="25">From the fact that they are only serving one audience, mainly the Western culture.</s>
 <s id="26">But also, I worry about the West, because often in this country, in this Western world that we have, culture risks being a form of entertainment.</s>
 <s id="27">Our people depend on our artists, and culture is beyond communication.</s>
 <s id="28">My journey as an artist started from a very, very personal place.</s>
 <s id="29">I did not start to make social commentary about my country.</s>
 <s id="30">The first one that you see in front of you is actually when I first returned to Iran after being separated for a good 12 years.</s>
 <s id="31">It was after the Islamic Revolution of 1979.</s>
 <s id="32">While I was absent from Iran, the Islamic Revolution had descended on Iran and had entirely transformed the country from Persian to the Islamic culture.</s>
 <s id="33">I came mainly to be reunited with my family and to reconnect in a way that I found my place in the society.</s>
 <s id="34">But instead, I found a country that was totally ideological and that I didn't recognize anymore.</s>
 <s id="35">More so, I became very interested, as I was facing my own personal dilemmas and questions, I became immersed in the study of the Islamic Revolution -- how, indeed, it had incredibly transformed the lives of Iranian women.</s>
 <s id="36">I found the subject of Iranian women immensely interesting, in the way the women of Iran, historically, seemed to embody the political transformation.</s>
 <s id="37">So in a way, by studying a woman, you can read the structure and the ideology of the country.</s>
 <s id="38">So I made a group of work that at once faced my own personal questions in life, and yet it brought my work into a larger discourse -- the subject of martyrdom, the question of those who willingly stand in that intersection of love of God, faith, but violence and crime and cruelty.</s>
 <s id="39">For me, this became incredibly important.</s>
 <s id="40">And yet, I had an unusual position toward this.</s>
 <s id="41">I was an outsider who had come back to Iran to find my place, but I was not in a position to be critical of the government or the ideology of the Islamic Revolution.</s>
 <s id="42">This changed slowly as I found my voice and I discovered things that I didn't know I would discover.</s>
 <s id="43">So my art became slightly more critical.</s>
 <s id="44">My knife became a little sharper.</s>
 <s id="45">And I fell into a life in exile.</s>
 <s id="46">I am a nomadic artist.</s>
 <s id="47">I work in Morocco, in Turkey, in Mexico.</s>
 <s id="48">I go everywhere to make believe it's Iran.</s>
 <s id="49">Now I am making films.</s>
 <s id="50">Last year, I finished a film called "Women Without Men."</s>
 <s id="51">"Women Without Men" returns to history, but another part of our Iranian history.</s>
 <s id="52">It goes to 1953 when American CIA exercised a coup and removed a democratically elected leader, Dr. Mossadegh.</s>
 <s id="53">The book is written by an Iranian woman, Shahrnush Parsipur.</s>
 <s id="54">It's a magical realist novel.</s>
 <s id="55">This book is banned, and she spent five years in prison.</s>
 <s id="56">My obsession with this book, and the reason I made this into a film, is because it at once was addressing the question of being a female -- traditionally, historically in Iran -- and the question of four women who are all looking for an idea of change, freedom and democracy -- while the country of Iran, equally, as if another character, also struggled for an idea of freedom and democracy and independence from the foreign interventions.</s>
 <s id="57">I made this film because I felt it's important for it to speak to the Westerners about our history as a country.</s>
 <s id="58">That all of you seem to remember Iran after the Islamic Revolution.</s>
 <s id="59">That Iran was once a secular society, and we had democracy, and this democracy was stolen from us by the American government, by the British government.</s>
 <s id="60">This film also speaks to the Iranian people in asking them to return to their history and look at themselves before they were so Islamicized -- in the way we looked, in the way we played music, in the way we had intellectual life.</s>
 <s id="61">And most of all, in the way that we fought for democracy.</s>
 <s id="62">These are some of the shots actually from my film.</s>
 <s id="63">These are some of the images of the coup.</s>
 <s id="64">And we made this film in Casablanca, recreating all the shots.</s>
 <s id="65">This film tried to find a balance between telling a political story, but also a feminine story.</s>
 <s id="66">Being a visual artist, indeed, I am foremost interested to make art -- to make art that transcends politics, religion, the question of feminism, and become an important, timeless, universal work of art.</s>
 <s id="67">The challenge I have is how to do that.</s>
 <s id="68">How to tell a political story but an allegorical story.</s>
 <s id="69">How to move you with your emotions, but also make your mind work.</s>
 <s id="70">These are some of the images and the characters of the film.</s>
 <s id="71">Now comes the green movement -- the summer of 2009, as my film is released -- the uprising begins in the streets of Tehran.</s>
 <s id="72">What is unbelievably ironic is the period that we tried to depict in the film, the cry for democracy and social justice, repeats itself now again in Tehran.</s>
 <s id="73">The green movement significantly inspired the world.</s>
 <s id="74">It brought a lot of attention to all those Iranians who stand for basic human rights and struggle for democracy.</s>
 <s id="75">What was most significant for me was, once again, the presence of the women.</s>
 <s id="76">They're absolutely inspirational for me.</s>
 <s id="77">If in the Islamic Revolution, the images of the woman portrayed were submissive and didn't have a voice, now we saw a new idea of feminism in the streets of Tehran -- women who were educated, forward thinking, non-traditional, sexually open, fearless and seriously feminist.</s>
 <s id="78">These women and those young men united Iranians across the world, inside and outside.</s>
 <s id="79">I then discovered why I take so much inspiration from Iranian women.</s>
 <s id="80">That, under all circumstances, they have pushed the boundary.</s>
 <s id="81">They have confronted the authority.</s>
 <s id="82">They have broken every rule in the smallest and the biggest way.</s>
 <s id="83">And once again, they proved themselves.</s>
 <s id="84">I stand here to say that Iranian women have found a new voice, and their voice is giving me my voice.</s>
 <s id="85">And it's a great honor to be an Iranian woman and an Iranian artist, even if I have to operate in the West only for now.</s>
 <s id="86">Thank you so much.</s>
 <s id="87">(Applause)</s>
</text>
