<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So what's image got do with it?</s>
 <s id="2">And I must say, I think Emeka is trying to send a lot of subliminal messages, because I'm going to keep harping on some of the issues that have come up.</s>
 <s id="3">But I'm going to try and do something different, and try and just close the loop with some of my personal stories, and try and put a face to a lot of the issues that we've been talking about.</s>
 <s id="4">So, Africa is a complex continent full of contradictions, as you can see.</s>
 <s id="5">We're not the only ones.</s>
 <s id="6">(Laughter) (Applause) And you know, it's amazing.</s>
 <s id="7">I mean, we need a whole conference just devoted to telling the good stories about the continent.</s>
 <s id="8">Just think about that, you know?</s>
 <s id="9">And this is typically what we've been talking about, the role that the media plays in focusing just on the negative stuff.</s>
 <s id="10">Now, why is that a problem?</s>
 <s id="11">A typical disaster story: disease, corruption, poverty.</s>
 <s id="12">And some of you might be standing here thinking, saying, "OK, you know, Ory, you're Harvard-educated, and all you privileged people come here, saying, 'Forget the poor people.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">Let's focus on business and the markets, and whatever.'</s>
  <s id="13.2">" And they're all, "There's the 80 percent of Africans who really need help."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">And I want to tell you that this is my story, OK?</s>
 <s id="15">And it's the story of many of the Africans who are here.</s>
 <s id="16">We start with poverty.</s>
 <s id="17">I didn't grow up in the slums or anything that dire, but I know what it is to grow up without having money, or being able to support family.</s>
 <s id="18">Euvin was talking about bellwether signs.</s>
 <s id="19">The bellwether for whether our family was broke or not was breakfast.</s>
 <s id="20">You know, when things were good, we had eggs and sausages.</s>
 <s id="21">When things were bad, we had porridge.</s>
 <s id="22">And like many African families, my parents could never save because they supported siblings, cousins, you know, their parents, and things were always dicey.</s>
 <s id="23">Now, when I was born, they realized they had a pretty smart kid, and they didn't want me to go to the neighborhood school, which was free.</s>
 <s id="24">And they adopted a very interesting approach to education, which was they were going to take me to a school that they can barely afford.</s>
 <s id="25">So they took me to a private, Catholic, elementary school, which set the foundation for what ended up being my career.</s>
 <s id="26">And what happened was, because they could afford it sometimes, sometimes not, I got kicked out pretty much every term.</s>
 <s id="27">You know, someone would come in with a list of the people who haven't paid school fees, and when they started getting pretty strict, you had to leave, until your school fees could be paid.</s>
 <s id="28">And I remember thinking, I mean, why don't these guys just take me to a cheap school?</s>
 <s id="29">Because you know, as a kid you're embarrassed and you're sensitive, and everyone knows you guys don't have money.</s>
 <s id="30">But they kept at it, and I now understand why they did what they did.</s>
 <s id="31">They talk about corruption.</s>
 <s id="32">In Kenya, we have an entrance exam to go into high school.</s>
 <s id="33">And there's national schools, which are like the best schools, and provincial schools.</s>
 <s id="34">My dream school at that time was Kenya High School, a national school.</s>
 <s id="35">I missed the cutoff by one point.</s>
 <s id="36">And I was so disappointed, and I was like, "Oh my God, you know, what am I going to do?"</s>
 <s id="37">And my father said, "OK, listen.</s>
 <s id="38">Let's go and try and talk to the headmistress.</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">You know, it's just one point.</s>
  <s id="39.2">I mean, maybe she'll let you in if that slot's still there."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">So we went to the school, and because we were nobodies, and because we didn't have privilege, and because my father didn't have the right last name, he was treated like dirt.</s>
 <s id="41">And I sat and listened to the headmistress talk to him, saying, you know, who do you think you are?</s>
 <s id="42">And, you know, you must be joking if you think you can get a slot.</s>
 <s id="43">And I had gone to school with other girls, who were kids of politicians, and who had done much, much worse than I did, and they had slots there.</s>
 <s id="44">And there's nothing worse than seeing your parent being humiliated in front of you, you know?</s>
 <s id="45">And we left, and I swore to myself, and I was like, "I'm never, ever going to have to beg for anything in my life."</s>
 <p id="p46">
  <s id="46.1">They called me two weeks later, they're like, oh, yeah, you can come now.</s>
  <s id="46.2">And I told them to stuff it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="47">(Laughter) (Applause) Final story, and I sort of have to speak quickly.</s>
 <s id="48">Disease.</s>
 <s id="49">My father, who I've been talking about, died of AIDS in 1999.</s>
 <s id="50">He never told anyone that he had AIDS, his fear of the stigma was so strong.</s>
 <s id="51">And I'm pretty much the one who figured it out, because I was a nerd.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">And I was in the States at the time, and they called me.</s>
  <s id="52.2">He was very sick, the first time he got sick.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="53">And he had Cryptococcal meningitis.</s>
 <s id="54">And so I went on to Google, Cryptococcal meningitis, you know.</s>
 <s id="55">Because of doctor-patient privilege, they couldn't really tell us what was going on.</s>
 <s id="56">But they were like, you know, this is a long-term thing.</s>
 <s id="57">And when I went online and looked at the infectious -- read about the disease, I pretty much realized what was going on.</s>
 <s id="58">The first time he got sick, he recovered.</s>
 <s id="59">But what happened was that he had to be on medication that, at that time -- Diflucan, which in the States is used for yeast infections -- cost 30 dollars a pill.</s>
 <s id="60">He had to be on that pill for the rest of his life.</s>
 <s id="61">You know, so money ran out.</s>
 <s id="62">He got sick again.</s>
 <s id="63">And up until that time, he had a friend who used to travel to India, and he used to import, bring him, could get him a generic version of it.</s>
 <s id="64">And that kept him going.</s>
 <s id="65">But the money ran out.</s>
 <p id="p66">
  <s id="66.1">He got sick again.</s>
  <s id="66.2">He got sick on a Friday.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p67">
  <s id="67.1">At that time, there was only one bank that had ATMs in Kenya, and we could not get cash.</s>
  <s id="67.2">The family couldn't get cash for him to start the treatment until Monday.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="68">The hospital put him on a water drip for three days.</s>
 <s id="69">And finally, we figured, well, OK, we'd better just try and take him to a public hospital.</s>
 <s id="70">At least he'll get treated while we try to figure out the money situation.</s>
 <s id="71">And he died when the ambulance was coming to the hospital to take him.</s>
 <s id="72">And, you know, now, imagine if -- and I could go on and on -- imagine if this is all you know about me.</s>
 <s id="73">How would you look at me?</s>
 <p id="p74">
  <s id="74.1">With pity, you know.</s>
  <s id="74.2">Sadness.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="75">And this is how you look at Africa.</s>
 <s id="76">This is the damage it causes.</s>
 <s id="77">You don't see the other side of me.</s>
 <s id="78">You don't see the blogger, you don't see the Harvard-educated lawyer, the vibrant person, you know?</s>
 <s id="79">And I just wanted to personalize that.</s>
 <s id="80">Because we talk about it in big terms, and you wonder, you know, so what?</s>
 <s id="81">But it's damaging.</s>
 <s id="82">And I'm not unique, right?</s>
 <s id="83">Imagine if all you knew about William was the fact that he grew up in a poor village.</s>
 <s id="84">And you didn't know about the windmill, you know?</s>
 <s id="85">And I was just moved.</s>
 <s id="86">I was actually crying during his presentation.</s>
 <s id="87">He was like, I try and I make.</s>
 <s id="88">I was like Nike should hire him, you know, "Just do it!"</s>
 <s id="89">(Laughter) And this is, again, the point I'm trying to make.</s>
 <s id="90">When you focus just on the disasters -- (Laughter) (Applause) -- we're ignoring the potential.</s>
 <s id="91">So, what is to be done?</s>
 <s id="92">First of all, Africans, we need to get better at telling our stories.</s>
 <s id="93">We heard about that yesterday.</s>
 <s id="94">We had some of them this morning.</s>
 <s id="95">And this is an example, you know, blogging is one way of doing that.</s>
 <s id="96">Afrigator is an aggregator of African blogs that was developed in South Africa.</s>
 <s id="97">So we need to start getting better.</s>
 <s id="98">If no one else will tell our stories, let's do it.</s>
 <s id="99">And going back to the point I was trying to make, this is the Swahili Wikipedia.</s>
 <s id="100">Swahili is spoken by about 50 million people in East Africa.</s>
 <s id="101">It only has five contributors.</s>
 <s id="102">Four of them are white males -- non-native speakers.</s>
 <s id="103">The other person is -- Ndesanjo, if you're here, stand up -- is a Tanzanian, [the] first Swahili blogger.</s>
 <s id="104">He's the only African who's contributing to this.</s>
 <p id="p105">
  <s id="105.1">People, please.</s>
  <s id="105.2">We can't whine and complain the West is doing this.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="106">What are we doing?</s>
 <s id="107">Where are the rest of the Swahili speakers?</s>
 <s id="108">Why are we not generating our own content?</s>
 <p id="p109">
  <s id="109.1">You know, it's not enough to complain.</s>
  <s id="109.2">We need to act.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="110">Reuters now integrates African blogs into their coverage of Africa.</s>
 <s id="111">So, that's a start, and we've heard of all their other initiatives.</s>
 <s id="112">The cheetah generation.</s>
 <s id="113">The aid approach, you know, is flawed.</s>
 <s id="114">And after all the hoopla of Live 8, we're still not anywhere in the picture.</s>
 <s id="115">No, you're not.</s>
 <s id="116">(Laughter) But the point I'm trying to make, though, is that it's not enough for us to criticize.</s>
 <s id="117">And for those of you in the diaspora who are struggling with where should I be, should I move back, should I stay?</s>
 <s id="118">You know, just jump.</s>
 <s id="119">The continent needs you.</s>
 <s id="120">And I can't emphasize that enough, you know.</s>
 <s id="121">I walked away from a job with one of the top firms in D.C., Covington and Burling, six figures.</s>
 <s id="122">With two paychecks, or three paychecks, I could solve a lot of my family's problems.</s>
 <s id="123">But I walked away from that, because my passion was here, and because I wanted to do things that were fulfilling.</s>
 <s id="124">And because I'm needed here, you know?</s>
 <s id="125">I probably can win a prize for the most ways to use a Harvard Law School degree because of all the things I'm doing.</s>
 <s id="126">One is because I'm pretty aggressive, and I try and find, you know, opportunities.</s>
 <s id="127">But there is such a need, you know?</s>
 <s id="128">I'm a corporate lawyer most of the time for an organization called Enablis that supports entrepreneurs in South Africa.</s>
 <s id="129">We're now moving into East Africa.</s>
 <s id="130">And we give them business development services, as well as financing loan and equity.</s>
 <s id="131">I've also set up a project in Kenya, and what we do is we track the performance of Kenyan MPs.</s>
 <s id="132">My partner, M, who's a tech guru, hacked WordPress.</s>
 <s id="133">It costs us, like, 20 dollars a month just for hosting.</s>
 <s id="134">Everything else on there is a labor of love.</s>
 <s id="135">We've manually entered all the data there.</s>
 <s id="136">And you can get profiles of each MP, questions they've asked in parliament.</s>
 <s id="137">We have a comment function, where people can ask their MPs questions.</s>
 <s id="138">There are some MPs who participate, and come back and ask.</s>
 <s id="139">And basically, we started this because we were tired of complaining about our politicians.</s>
 <s id="140">You know, I believe that accountability stems from demand.</s>
 <s id="141">You're not just going to be accountable out of the goodness of your heart.</s>
 <s id="142">And we as Africans need to start challenging our leaders.</s>
 <s id="143">What are they doing?</s>
 <s id="144">You know, they're not going to change just out of nowhere.</s>
 <s id="145">So we need new policies, we need -- where's that coming from, you know?</s>
 <s id="146">Another thing is that these leaders are a reflection of our society.</s>
 <s id="147">We talk about African governments like they've been dropped from Mars, you know?</s>
 <s id="148">They come from us.</s>
 <s id="149">And what is it about our society that is generating leaders that we don't like?</s>
 <s id="150">And how can we change that?</s>
 <s id="151">So Mzalendo was one small way we thought we could start inspiring people to start holding their leaders accountable.</s>
 <s id="152">Where do we go from here?</s>
 <s id="153">I believe in the power of ideas.</s>
 <s id="154">I believe in the power of sharing knowledge.</s>
 <s id="155">And I'd ask all of you, when you leave here, please just share, and keep the ideas that you've gotten out of here going, because it can make a difference.</s>
 <s id="156">The other thing I want to urge you to do is take an interest in the individual.</s>
 <s id="157">I've had lots of conversations about things I think need to be happening in Africa.</s>
 <s id="158">People are like, "OK, if you don't do aid, I'm a bleeding heart liberal, what can I do?"</s>
 <s id="159">And when I talk about my ideas, they're like, "BBut it's not scalable, you know.</s>
 <s id="160">Give me something I can do with Paypal."</s>
 <s id="161">It's not that easy, you know?</s>
 <s id="162">And sometimes just taking an interest in the individual, in the fellows you've met, and the businesspeople you've met, it can make a huge difference, especially in Africa, because usually the individual in Africa carries a lot of people behind them.</s>
 <p id="p163">
  <s id="163.1">Practically.</s>
  <s id="163.2">I mean, when I was a first-year student in law school, my mom's business had collapsed, so I was supporting her.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="164">My sister was struggling to get through undergrad.</s>
 <s id="165">I was helping her pay her tuition.</s>
 <s id="166">My cousin ran out of school fees, and she's really smart.</s>
 <s id="167">I was paying her school fees.</s>
 <s id="168">A cousin of mine died of AIDS, left an orphan, so we said, well, what are we going to do with her?</s>
 <s id="169">You know, she's now my baby sister.</s>
 <s id="170">And because of the opportunities that were afforded to me, I am able to lift all those people.</s>
 <s id="171">So, don't underestimate that.</s>
 <p id="p172">
  <s id="172.1">An example.</s>
  <s id="172.2">This man changed my life.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p173">
  <s id="173.1">He's a professor.</s>
  <s id="173.2">He's now at Vanderbilt.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="174">He's an undergrad professor, Mitchell Seligson.</s>
 <s id="175">And because of him, I got into Harvard Law School, because he took an interest.</s>
 <s id="176">I was taking a class of his, and he was just like, this is an overeager student, which we don't normally get in the United States, because everyone else is cynical and jaded.</s>
 <s id="177">He called me to his office and said, "What do you want to do when you grow up?"</s>
 <s id="178">I said, "I want to be a lawyer."</s>
 <p id="p179">
  <s id="179.1">And he was like, "Why?</s>
  <s id="179.2">You know, we don't need another lawyer in the United States."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="180">And he tried to talk me out of it, but it was like, "OK, I know nothing about applying to law school, I'm poli-sci Ph.D.</s>
 <s id="181">But, you know, let's figure out what I need you to do, what I need to do to help you out."</s>
 <s id="182">It was like, "Where do you want to go?"</s>
 <s id="183">And to me at that time university -- I was at University of Pitts for undergrad, and that was like heaven, OK, because compared to what could have been in Kenya.</s>
 <s id="184">So I'm like, "Yeah, I'm just applying to Pitt for law school."</s>
 <p id="p185">
  <s id="185.1">He was like, "Why?</s>
  <s id="185.2">You know, you're smart, you have all these things going for you."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="186">And I'm like, "Because I'm here and it's cheap, and you know, I kind of like Pittsburgh."</s>
 <s id="187">Like, that's the dumbest reason I've ever heard for applying to law school.</s>
 <s id="188">And, you know, so he took me under his wing, and he encouraged me.</s>
 <s id="189">And he said, "Look, you can get into Harvard, you're that good, OK?</s>
 <s id="190">And if they don't admit you, they're the ones who are messed up."</s>
 <s id="191">And he built me up, you know?</s>
 <s id="192">And this is just an illustration.</s>
 <s id="193">You can meet other individuals here.</s>
 <s id="194">We just need a push.</s>
 <s id="195">That's all I needed was a push to go to the next level.</s>
 <s id="196">Basically, I want to end with my vision for Africa, you know?</s>
 <s id="197">A gentleman spoke yesterday about the indignity of us having to leave the continent so that we can fulfill our potential.</s>
 <s id="198">You know, my vision is that my daughter, and any other African child being born today, can be whoever they want to be here, without having to leave.</s>
 <s id="199">And they can have the possibility of transcending the circumstances under which they were born.</s>
 <s id="200">That's one thing you Americans take for granted, you know?</s>
 <s id="201">That you can grow up, you know, not so good circumstances, and you can move.</s>
 <s id="202">Just because you are born in rural Arkansas, whatever, that doesn't define who you are.</s>
 <s id="203">For most Africans today, where you live, or where you were born, and the circumstances under which you were born, determine the rest of your life.</s>
 <s id="204">I would like to see that change, and the change starts with us.</s>
 <s id="205">And as Africans, we need to take responsibility for our continent.</s>
 <s id="206">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="207">(Applause)</s>
</text>
