<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">My name is Joshua Walters.</s>
 <s id="2">I'm a performer.</s>
 <s id="3">(Beatboxing) (Laughter) (Applause) But as far as being a performer, I'm also diagnosed bipolar.</s>
 <s id="4">I reframe that as a positive because the crazier I get onstage, the more entertaining I become.</s>
 <s id="5">When I was 16 in San Francisco, I had my breakthrough manic episode in which I thought I was Jesus Christ.</s>
 <s id="6">Maybe you thought that was scary, but actually there's no amount of drugs you can take that can get you as high as if you think you're Jesus Christ.</s>
 <s id="7">(Laughter) I was sent to a place, a psych ward, and in the psych ward, everyone is doing their own one-man show.</s>
 <s id="8">(Laughter) There's no audience like this to justify their rehearsal time.</s>
 <s id="9">They're just practicing.</s>
 <s id="10">One day they'll get here.</s>
 <s id="11">Now when I got out, I was diagnosed and I was given medications by a psychiatrist.</s>
 <s id="12">"Okay, Josh, why don't we give you some -- why don't we give you some Zyprexa.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">Okay?</s>
  <s id="13.2">Mmhmm?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">At least that's what it says on my pen."</s>
 <s id="15">(Laughter) Some of you are in the field, I can see.</s>
 <s id="16">I can feel your noise.</s>
 <s id="17">The first half of high school was the struggle of the manic episode, and the second half was the overmedications of these drugs, where I was sleeping through high school.</s>
 <s id="18">The second half was just one big nap, pretty much, in class.</s>
 <s id="19">When I got out I had a choice.</s>
 <s id="20">I could either deny my mental illness or embrace my mental skillness.</s>
 <s id="21">(Bugle sound) There's a movement going on right now to reframe mental illness as a positive -- at least the hypomanic edge part of it.</s>
 <s id="22">Now if you don't know what hypomania is, it's like an engine that's out of control, maybe a Ferrari engine, with no breaks.</s>
 <s id="23">Many of the speakers here, many of you in the audience, have that creative edge, if you know what I'm talking about.</s>
 <s id="24">You're driven to do something that everyone has told you is impossible.</s>
 <s id="25">And there's a book -- John Gartner.</s>
 <s id="26">John Gartner wrote this book called "The Hypomanic Edge" in which Christopher Columbus and Ted Turner and Steve Jobs and all these business minds have this edge to compete.</s>
 <s id="27">A different book was written not too long ago in the mid-90s called "Touched With Fire" by Kay Redfield Jamison in which it was looked at in a creative sense in which Mozart and Beethoven and Van Gogh all have this manic depression that they were suffering with.</s>
 <s id="28">Some of them committed suicide.</s>
 <s id="29">So it wasn't all the good side of the illness.</s>
 <s id="30">Now recently, there's been development in this field.</s>
 <s id="31">And there was an article written in the New York Times, September 2010, that stated: "Just Manic Enough."</s>
 <s id="32">Just be manic enough in which investors who are looking for entrepreneurs that have this kind of spectrum -- you know what I'm talking about -- not maybe full bipolar, but they're in the bipolar spectrum -- where on one side, maybe you think you're Jesus, and on the other side maybe they just make you a lot of money.</s>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">(Laughter) Your call.</s>
  <s id="33.2">Your call.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="34">And everyone's somewhere in the middle.</s>
 <s id="35">Everyone's somewhere in the middle.</s>
 <s id="36">So maybe, you know, there's no such thing as crazy, and being diagnosed with a mental illness doesn't mean you're crazy.</s>
 <s id="37">But maybe it just means you're more sensitive to what most people can't see or feel.</s>
 <s id="38">Maybe no one's really crazy.</s>
 <s id="39">Everyone is just a little bit mad.</s>
 <s id="40">How much depends on where you fall in the spectrum.</s>
 <s id="41">How much depends on how lucky you are.</s>
 <s id="42">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="43">(Applause)</s>
</text>
