<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">We all start life as one single cell.</s>
 <s id="2">Then that cell divides and we are two cells, then four, then eight.</s>
 <s id="3">Cells form tissues, tissues form organs, organs form us.</s>
 <s id="4">These cell divisions, by which we go from a single cell to 100 trillion cells, are called growth.</s>
 <s id="5">And growth seems like a simple thing because when we think of it, we typically think of someone getting taller or, later in life, wider, but to cells, growth isn't simple.</s>
 <s id="6">Cell division is an intricate chemical dance that's part individual, part community-driven.</s>
 <s id="7">And in a neighborhood of 100 trillion cells, some times things go wrong.</s>
 <s id="8">Maybe an individual cell's set of instructions, or DNA, gets a typo, what we call a mutation.</s>
 <s id="9">Most of the time, the cell senses mistakes and shuts itself down, or the system detects a troublemaker and eliminates it.</s>
 <s id="10">But, enough mutations can bypass the fail-safes, driving the cell to divide recklessly.</s>
 <s id="11">That one rogue cell becomes two, then four, then eight.</s>
 <s id="12">At every stage, the incorrect instructions are passed along to the cells' offspring.</s>
 <s id="13">Weeks, months, or years after that one rogue cell transformed, you might see your doctor about a lump in your breast.</s>
 <s id="14">Difficulty going to the bathroom could reveal a problem in your intestine, prostate, or bladder.</s>
 <s id="15">Or, a routine blood test might count too many white cells or elevated liver enzymes.</s>
 <s id="16">Your doctor delivers the bad news: it's cancer.</s>
 <s id="17">From here your strategy will depend on where the cancer is and how far it's progressed.</s>
 <s id="18">If the tumor is slow-growing and in one place, surgery might be all you need, if anything.</s>
 <s id="19">If the tumor is fast-growing or invading nearby tissue, your doctor might recommend radiation or surgery followed by radiation.</s>
 <s id="20">If the cancer has spread, or if it's inherently everywhere like a leukemia, your doctor will most likely recommend chemotherapy or a combination of radiation and chemo.</s>
 <s id="21">Radiation and most forms of chemo work by physically shredding the cells' DNA or disrupting the copying machinery.</s>
 <s id="22">But neither radiation nor chemotherapeutic drugs target only cancer cells.</s>
 <s id="23">Radiation hits whatever you point it at, and your blood stream carries chemo-therapeutics all over your body.</s>
 <s id="24">So, what happens when different cells get hit?</s>
 <s id="25">Let's look at a healthy liver cell, a healthy hair cell, and a cancerous cell.</s>
 <s id="26">The healthy liver cell divides only when it is stressed; the healthy hair cell divides frequently; and the cancer cell divides even more frequently and recklessly.</s>
 <s id="27">When you take a chemotherapeutic drug, it will hit all of these cells.</s>
 <s id="28">And remember that the drugs work typically by disrupting cell division.</s>
 <s id="29">So, every time a cell divides, it opens itself up to attack, and that means the more frequently a cell divides, the more likely the drug is to kill it.</s>
 <s id="30">So, remember that hair cell?</s>
 <s id="31">It divides frequently and isn't a threat.</s>
 <s id="32">And, there are other frequently dividing cells in your body like skin cells, gut cells, and blood cells.</s>
 <s id="33">So the list of unpleasant side effects of cancer treatment parallels these tissue types: hair loss, skin rashes, nausea, vomiting, fatigue, weight loss, and pain.</s>
 <s id="34">That makes sense because these are the cells that get hit the hardest.</s>
 <s id="35">So, in the end, it is all about growth.</s>
 <s id="36">Cancer hijacks cells' natural division machinery and forces them to put the pedal to the metal, growing rapidly and recklessly.</s>
 <s id="37">But, using chemotherapeutic drugs, we take advantage of that aggressiveness, and we turn cancer's main strength into a weakness.</s>
</text>
