<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In 132 CE, Chinese polymath Zhang Heng presented the Han court with his latest invention.</s>
 <s id="2">This large vase, he claimed, could tell them whenever an earthquake occurred in their kingdom– including the direction they should send aid.</s>
 <s id="3">The court was somewhat skeptical, especially when the device triggered on a seemingly quiet afternoon.</s>
 <s id="4">But when messengers came for help days later, their doubts turned to gratitude.</s>
 <s id="5">Today, we no longer rely on pots to identify seismic events, but earthquakes still offer a unique challenge to those trying to track them.</s>
 <s id="6">So why are earthquakes so hard to anticipate, and how could we get better at predicting them?</s>
 <s id="7">To answer that, we need to understand some theories behind how earthquakes occur.</s>
 <s id="8">Earth’s crust is made from several vast, jagged slabs of rock called tectonic plates, each riding on a hot, partially molten layer of Earth’s mantle.</s>
 <s id="9">This causes the plates to spread very slowly, at anywhere from 1 to 20 centimeters per year.</s>
 <s id="10">But these tiny movements are powerful enough to cause deep cracks in the interacting plates.</s>
 <s id="11">And in unstable zones, the intensifying pressure may ultimately trigger an earthquake.</s>
 <s id="12">It’s hard enough to monitor these miniscule movements, but the factors that turn shifts into seismic events are far more varied.</s>
 <s id="13">Different fault lines juxtapose different rocks– some of which are stronger–or weaker– under pressure.</s>
 <s id="14">Diverse rocks also react differently to friction and high temperatures.</s>
 <s id="15">Some partially melt, and can release lubricating fluids made of superheated minerals that reduce fault line friction.</s>
 <s id="16">But some are left dry, prone to dangerous build-ups of pressure.</s>
 <s id="17">And all these faults are subject to varying gravitational forces, as well as the currents of hot rocks moving throughout Earth’s mantle.</s>
 <s id="18">So which of these hidden variables should we be analyzing, and how do they fit into our growing prediction toolkit?</s>
 <s id="19">Because some of these forces occur at largely constant rates, the behavior of the plates is somewhat cyclical.</s>
 <s id="20">Today, many of our most reliable clues come from long-term forecasting, related to when and where earthquakes have previously occurred.</s>
 <s id="21">At the scale of millennia, this allows us to make predictions about when highly active faults, like the San Andreas, are overdue for a massive earthquake.</s>
 <s id="22">But due to the many variables involved, this method can only predict very loose timeframes.</s>
 <s id="23">To predict more imminent events, researchers have investigated the vibrations Earth elicits before a quake.</s>
 <s id="24">Geologists have long used seismometers to track and map these tiny shifts in the earth’s crust.</s>
 <s id="25">And today, most smartphones are also capable of recording primary seismic waves.</s>
 <s id="26">With a network of phones around the globe, scientists could potentially crowdsource a rich, detailed warning system that alerts people to incoming quakes.</s>
 <s id="27">Unfortunately, phones might not be able to provide the advance notice needed to enact safety protocols.</s>
 <s id="28">But such detailed readings would still be useful for prediction tools like NASA’s Quakesim software, which can use a rigorous blend of geological data to identify regions at risk.</s>
 <s id="29">However, recent studies indicate the most telling signs of a quake might be invisible to all these sensors.</s>
 <s id="30">In 2011, just before an earthquake struck the east coast of Japan, nearby researchers recorded surprisingly high concentrations of the radioactive isotope pair: radon and thoron.</s>
 <s id="31">As stress builds up in the crust right before an earthquake, microfractures allow these gases to escape to the surface.</s>
 <s id="32">These scientists think that if we built a vast network of radon-thoron detectors in earthquake-prone areas, it could become a promising warning system– potentially predicting quakes a week in advance.</s>
 <s id="33">Of course, none of these technologies would be as helpful as simply looking deep inside the earth itself.</s>
 <s id="34">With a deeper view we might be able to track and predict large-scale geological changes in real time, possibly saving tens of thousands of lives a year.</s>
 <s id="35">But for now, these technologies can help us prepare and respond quickly to areas in need– without waiting for directions from a vase.</s>
</text>
