<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Hephaestus, god of technology, was hard at work on his most ingenious invention yet.</s>
 <s id="2">He was creating a new defense system for King Minos, who wanted fewer intruders on his island kingdom of Crete.</s>
 <s id="3">But mortal guards and ordinary weapons wouldn’t suffice, so the visionary god devised an indomitable new defender.</s>
 <s id="4">In the fires of his forge, Hephaestus cast his invention in the shape of a giant man.</s>
 <s id="5">Made of gleaming bronze; endowed with superhuman strength, and powered by ichor, the life fluid of the gods, this automaton was unlike anything Hephaestus had forged before.</s>
 <s id="6">The god named his creation Talos: the first robot.</s>
 <s id="7">Three times a day, the bronze guardian marched around the island's perimeter searching for interlopers.</s>
 <s id="8">When he identified ships approaching the coast, he hurled massive boulders into their path.</s>
 <s id="9">If any survivors made it ashore, he would heat his metal body red-hot and crush victims to his chest.</s>
 <s id="10">Talos was intended to fulfill his duties day after day, with no variation.</s>
 <s id="11">But despite his robotic behavior, he possessed an internal life his victims could scarcely imagine.</s>
 <s id="12">And soon, the behemoth would encounter a ship of invaders that would test his mettle.</s>
 <s id="13">The bedraggled crew of Jason, Medea, and the Argonauts were returning from their hard-won quest to retrieve the Golden Fleece.</s>
 <s id="14">Their adventure had taken many dark turns, and the weary sailors were desperate to rest in a safe harbor.</s>
 <s id="15">They’d heard tales of Crete’s invulnerable bronze colossus, and made for a sheltered cove.</s>
 <s id="16">But before they could even drop anchor, Talos spotted them.</s>
 <s id="17">While the Argonauts cowered at the approach of the awesome automaton, the sorceress Medea spotted a glinting bolt on the robot’s ankle— and devised a clever gambit.</s>
 <s id="18">Medea offered Talos a bargain: she claimed that she could make Talos immortal in exchange for removing the bolt.</s>
 <s id="19">Medea's promise resonated deep within his core.</s>
 <s id="20">Unaware of his own mechanical nature, and human enough to long for eternal life, Talos agreed.</s>
 <s id="21">While Medea muttered incantations, Jason removed the bolt.</s>
 <s id="22">As Medea suspected, the bolt was a weak point in Hephaestus’ design.</s>
 <s id="23">The ichor flowed out like molten lead, draining Talos of his power source.</s>
 <s id="24">The robot collapsed with a thunderous crash, and the Argonauts were free to travel home.</s>
 <s id="25">This story, first recorded in roughly 700 BCE, raises some familiar anxieties about artificial intelligence— and even provides an ancient blueprint for science fiction.</s>
 <s id="26">But according to historians, ancient robots were more than just myths.</s>
 <s id="27">By the 4th century BCE, Greek engineers began making actual automatons including robotic servants and flying models of birds.</s>
 <s id="28">None of these creations were as famous as Talos, who appeared on Greek coins, vase paintings, public frescoes, and in theatrical performances.</s>
 <s id="29">Even 2,500 years ago, Greeks had already begun to investigate the uncertain line between human and machine.</s>
 <s id="30">And like many modern myths about artificial intelligence, Talos’ tale is as much about his robotic heart as it is about his robotic brain.</s>
 <s id="31">Illustrating the demise of Talos on a vase of the fifth century BCE, one painter captured the dying automaton’s despair with a tear rolling down his bronze cheek.</s>
</text>
