<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">It’s June, just after a heavy rainfall, and the sky is filling with creatures we wouldn’t normally expect to find there.</s>
 <s id="2">At first glance, this might be a disturbing sight.</s>
 <s id="3">But for the lucky males and females of Solenopsis invicta, otherwise known as fire ants, it’s a day of romance.</s>
 <s id="4">This is the nuptial flight, when thousands of reproduction-capable male and female ants, called alates, take wing for the first and last time.</s>
 <s id="5">But even for successful males who manage to avoid winged predators, this mating frenzy will prove lethal.</s>
 <s id="6">And for a successfully mated female, her work is only beginning.</s>
 <s id="7">Having secured a lifetime supply of sperm from her departed mate, our new queen must now single-handedly start an entire colony.</s>
 <s id="8">Descending to the ground, she searches for a suitable spot to build her nest.</s>
 <s id="9">Ideally, she can find somewhere with loose, easy-to-dig soil— like farmland already disturbed by human activity.</s>
 <s id="10">Once she finds the perfect spot, she breaks off her wings— creating the stubs that establish her royal status.</s>
 <s id="11">Then, she starts digging a descending tunnel ending in a chamber.</s>
 <s id="12">Here the queen begins laying her eggs, about ten per day, and the first larvae hatch within a week.</s>
 <s id="13">Over the next three weeks, the new queen relies on a separate batch of unfertilized eggs to nourish both herself and her brood, losing half her body weight in the process.</s>
 <s id="14">Thankfully, after about 20 days, these larvae grow into the first generation of workers, ready to forage for food and sustain their shrunken queen.</s>
 <s id="15">Her daughters will have to work quickly though— returning their mother to good health is urgent.</s>
 <s id="16">In the surrounding area, dozens of neighboring queens are building their own ant armies.</s>
 <s id="17">These colonies have peacefully coexisted so far, but once workers appear, a phenomenon known as brood-raiding begins.</s>
 <s id="18">Workers from nests up to several meters away begin to steal offspring from our queen.</s>
 <s id="19">Our colony retaliates, but new waves of raiders from even further away overwhelm the workers.</s>
 <s id="20">Within hours, the raiders have taken our queen’s entire brood supply to the largest nearby nest— and the queen’s surviving daughters abandon her.</s>
 <s id="21">Chasing her last chance of survival, the queen follows the raiding trail to the winning nest.</s>
 <s id="22">She fends off other losing queens and the defending nest’s workers, fighting her way to the top of the brood pile.</s>
 <s id="23">Her daughters help their mother succeed where other queens fail— defeating the reigning monarch, and usurping the brood pile.</s>
 <s id="24">Eventually, all the remaining challengers fail, until only one queen— and one brood pile— remains.</s>
 <s id="25">Now presiding over several hundred workers in the neighborhood’s largest nest, our victorious queen begins aiding her colony in its primary goal: reproduction.</s>
 <s id="26">For the next several years, the colony only produces sterile workers.</s>
 <s id="27">But once their population exceeds about 23,000, it changes course.</s>
 <s id="28">From now on, every spring, the colony will produce fertile alate males and females.</s>
 <s id="29">The colony spawns these larger ants throughout the early summer, and returns to worker production in the fall.</s>
 <s id="30">After heavy rainfalls, these alates take to the skies, and spread their queen’s genes up to a couple hundred meters downwind.</s>
 <s id="31">But to contribute to this annual mating frenzy, the colony must continue to thrive as one massive super-organism.</s>
 <s id="32">Every day, younger ants feed the queen and tend to the brood, while older workers forage for food and defend the nest.</s>
 <s id="33">When intruders strike, these older warriors fend them off using poisonous venom.</s>
 <s id="34">After rainfalls, the colony comes together, using the wet dirt to expand their nest.</s>
 <s id="35">And when a disastrous flood drowns their home, the sisters band together into a massive living raft— carrying their queen to safety.</s>
 <s id="36">But no matter how resilient, the life of a colony must come to an end.</s>
 <s id="37">After about 8 years, our queen runs out of sperm and can no longer replace dying workers.</s>
 <s id="38">The nest’s population dwindles, and eventually, they’re taken over by a neighboring colony.</s>
 <s id="39">Our queen’s reign is over, but her genetic legacy lives on.</s>
</text>
