<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">When I was seven, my father took me to a classical music concert for the first time and I went out crying.</s>
 <s id="2">They performed Beethoven's 5th Symphony.</s>
 <s id="3">(Music) How do you prepare a child to attend a classical music concert for the first time?</s>
 <s id="4">A few days before, we sat down and listened to a recording he had.</s>
 <s id="5">There, he explained a couple of simple things to me, for instance, the insistence of "ta-ta-ta-tan" throughout the first movement.</s>
 <s id="6">But that it also comes back later in the symphony.</s>
 <s id="7">He explained that this symphony had four movements.</s>
 <s id="8">Or that the end of it would be a victory.</s>
 <s id="9">A human, musical, concrete or abstract kind of victory.</s>
 <s id="10">He explained that what starts with an insistent and sententious call, becomes a triumph, full of validation and optimism.</s>
 <s id="11">We even played a game: every time a section started, of which we had spoken about, I would squeeze his hand as a sign of recognition.</s>
 <s id="12">With this information I arrived at the theater.</s>
 <s id="13">This, and my natural curiosity filled me with expectations.</s>
 <s id="14">I was so focused enjoying the music, but also the experience of being there: the public paying attention, the orchestra, the passionate sound.</s>
 <s id="15">Everything was like what I anticipated, until something incredible happened.</s>
 <s id="16">Something that to this day I consider one of the most perfect musical moments ever written.</s>
 <s id="17">A miracle.</s>
 <s id="18">The music had been repeating a gesture for quite a while, (Plays the piano) Do you recognize it?</s>
 <s id="19">But also, a progression of chords that made me think that after this, surely, this would come.</s>
 <s id="20">A kind of "musical common sense."</s>
 <s id="21">But there is no miracle on that.</s>
 <s id="22">Humbly, I could have written that resolution myself, so we would've finished the movement, and let people cough happily and compulsively, or check their phones.</s>
 <s id="23">But I didn't write this piece of music.</s>
 <s id="24">And Beethoven is Beethoven for a reason.</s>
 <s id="25">Let's go back a few seconds: (Music) All this follows a pattern and we already know how it should end.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">And this?</s>
  <s id="26.2">This is not what I expected.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">A child would say: it's like cheating you.</s>
 <s id="28">That note coming from another musical universe surprises us.</s>
 <s id="29">The music, the rhythm, barely beats on the edge of its extinction.</s>
 <s id="30">Little by little it stabilizes, showing vital signs.</s>
 <s id="31">From that pulse, the violins sprout and an erratic intermittent melodic line, until both find consistency, too.</s>
 <s id="32">In that way the music captures our attention.</s>
 <s id="33">A moment charged with the promise of an imminent outcome.</s>
 <s id="34">That something that we know will happen; that without realizing it, we already expected it.</s>
 <s id="35">(Music) After that my father looked at me and hugged me, deeply moved.</s>
 <s id="36">I was crying.</s>
 <s id="37">I looked at him and said: "I don't know why I'm crying, for it is not sadness what I feel."</s>
 <s id="38">That moment marked my life.</s>
 <s id="39">At that moment, being seven years old, I decided to dedicate my life to music.</s>
 <s id="40">Because I wanted to recreate that moment, understand it and then share and spread it.</s>
 <s id="41">Let's see if we can do it here now, I think it's contagious.</s>
 <s id="42">When I talked about this unexpected note, that key to new options that finally become the door to this great musical triumph, I was pointing to a very simple and common phenomenon of life itself: expectations.</s>
 <s id="43">Had the third movement effectively finished like this, (Plays the piano) our perception of what happened would've stayed within certain range of expectations.</s>
 <s id="44">We basically receive what we expect.</s>
 <s id="45">The music ends, the audience coughs and accommodates their seats.</s>
 <s id="46">(Laughter) The musicians relax for a second until the director raises his hands again in a sign of onslaught to conquest the last movement.</s>
 <s id="47">It works.</s>
 <s id="48">The music impacts anyway.</s>
 <s id="49">But it's not the same.</s>
 <s id="50">This transition Beethoven wrote not only succeeds in connecting one music with another, but it creates another kind of expectations.</s>
 <s id="51">From that unexpected note, until the search for new stability in the rhythm, the melody, the harmony and the texture that grows to end up in something even greater.</s>
 <s id="52">But in the meantime, our mind reacts.</s>
 <s id="53">It starts looking for alternatives, possible scenarios.</s>
 <s id="54">And Beethoven knows it.</s>
 <s id="55">That's why that dissolution and rambling of the music confuses us.</s>
 <s id="56">And that confusion brings on expectations which are a mix of prediction and willingness to keep on being surprised, since the same music showed us that everything is possible.</s>
 <s id="57">On another extra musical level it looks like my own attitude before and during the concert.</s>
 <s id="58">The information from my father was an incentive to get to the theater full of expectations.</s>
 <s id="59">To recognize what I already knew, to verify it.</s>
 <s id="60">But once I was surprised, everything was possible.</s>
 <s id="61">The evocative power of music comes to an extent from its ability to create, prolong, suspend, or even betray expectations.</s>
 <s id="62">But what do we expect from it, from music itself?</s>
 <s id="63">A melody and an accompaniment.</s>
 <s id="64">An idea that presents itself, talks and finds a closure.</s>
 <s id="65">A new, more happy idea.</s>
 <s id="66">Everything peaceful and expected.</s>
 <s id="67">Expectations fulfilled.</s>
 <s id="68">Aha!</s>
 <s id="69">An unexpected turn ...</s>
 <p id="p70">
  <s id="70.1">Drama!</s>
  <s id="70.2">Opera!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="71">You didn't see that coming.</s>
 <s id="72">Because it is easier to predict from consistency.</s>
 <s id="73">Like in this prelude from Bach.</s>
 <s id="74">We are designed to look for stability and reaffirm a prediction.</s>
 <s id="75">Associations are triggered and our memory draws conclusions.</s>
 <s id="76">Consistency allows us anticipate and guess rightly.</s>
 <s id="77">And one of the sources of pleasure when listening to music is when our expectations are met.</s>
 <s id="78">But, what happens when we lose control on the predictions?</s>
 <s id="79">When they are not met?</s>
 <s id="80">A great tool of Romanticism.</s>
 <s id="81">Franz Liszt plays with surprises.</s>
 <s id="82">A passionate, raptured melody, that begins a journey.</s>
 <s id="83">But comes back.</s>
 <s id="84">And then, when everything seems to go on the same, safe and predictable path, this!</s>
 <s id="85">A door opens, another alternative.</s>
 <s id="86">Which destabilizes, but fascinates.</s>
 <s id="87">One more!</s>
 <s id="88">It was like finding options that were not possible.</s>
 <s id="89">And that challenge to our expectations seduces us.</s>
 <s id="90">Or a contrast.</s>
 <p id="p91">
  <s id="91.1">Mahler declares: "Dark is life.</s>
  <s id="91.2">Dark is death."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="92">Serious and hopeless, the music takes a new turn.</s>
 <s id="93">But also, this music has a hint of movement, of a dance, of a waltz.</s>
 <s id="94">Of course!</s>
 <s id="95">The style, tradition and heritage also generate expectations.</s>
 <s id="96">Because Mahler is an heir of a whole Viennese tradition where this music is part of its DNA.</s>
 <s id="97">And of ours?</s>
 <s id="98">Didn't some of you smile when recognizing this waltz from Strauss?</s>
 <s id="99">Which is also full of small games of expectations.</s>
 <s id="100">Like these subtle changes in tempo.</s>
 <s id="101">That coming and going, that brings about so much grace.</s>
 <s id="102">Or more radical surprises.</s>
 <s id="103">A new waltz!</s>
 <s id="104">Like I told you, tradition lies in the collective unconscious and through gestures like this: one two three, one two three ...</s>
 <s id="105">we can even recognize a distorted and decadent waltz written before the First World War.</s>
 <s id="106">Isn't it like a spooky echo of that Viennese waltz?</s>
 <s id="107">Those notes, apparently unconnected, are the product of years of transformation of musical rules.</s>
 <s id="108">Wagner was one who contributed, in his case, by being a great manipulator of expectations.</s>
 <s id="109">Suggestive music, full of eroticism where each note, each sound clings to the next one, crawling and sticking to it.</s>
 <s id="110">But, permanently changing direction.</s>
 <s id="111">Not everything that sounds can be unexpected.</s>
 <s id="112">A silence can also be provocative and leave open questions.</s>
 <s id="113">The deafening silence ...</s>
 <s id="114">Debussy and his sensual "Prelude to the afternoon of a faun" and that suggestive silence at the beginning.</s>
 <s id="115">Silence, that essential element of music.</s>
 <s id="116">More than an absence of sound, it is a fundamental expressive resource.</s>
 <s id="117">And one of my favorite silences is that complicit silence.</s>
 <s id="118">Loaded with expectations.</s>
 <s id="119">The one that happens before music is.</s>
 <s id="120">(Music) But also every new silence.</s>
 <s id="121">Giving moments of lucubration.</s>
 <s id="122">Being part of the speech and connecting ideas that can continue to grow.</s>
 <s id="123">Contrasts, stability and instability.</s>
 <s id="124">By the way, the stability of the pulse, and how we group it is an instinctive reaction we have as soon as we identify regularity.</s>
 <s id="125">One, two, one, two ...</s>
 <s id="126">But, what happens when we can't even anticipate this grouping?</s>
 <s id="127">And we are just left at the mercy of the unstable?</s>
 <s id="128">Listening to music can be like reading a good detective story.</s>
 <s id="129">Like those in which you even doubt the dead.</s>
 <s id="130">(Laughter) Where the plot and the impending outcome will make you more sensitive to how the thickness of the pages decreases.</s>
 <s id="131">Expectations on the weight over the tip of your fingers.</s>
 <s id="132">The state of attention changes, it's active and increasingly speculative.</s>
 <s id="133">It is no longer, "if this, then that."</s>
 <p id="p134">
  <s id="134.1">But, "and if this, then that?</s>
  <s id="134.2">This other or that one?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="135">Like everything in life, in the nature of art it is also present this idea that you have to expect the unexpected.</s>
 <s id="136">But notice that the unexpected doesn't just taste like first time.</s>
 <s id="137">That's why we read a book or watch a movie many times, or we listen to that music we like so much on repeat.</s>
 <s id="138">Partly, this is because we like to experiment from security.</s>
 <s id="139">Like a child who reads the same story tale every night, with the relief of knowing how it ends.</s>
 <s id="140">But also rereading through memory gives us other details.</s>
 <s id="141">It makes us pay attention to other places.</s>
 <s id="142">We listen now not to the melody, but the accompaniment for example, to discover that beautiful music that had gone unnoticed, even when it was always there.</s>
 <s id="143">To recognize, but also to rediscover.</s>
 <s id="144">An infinite game of expectations.</s>
 <p id="p145">
  <s id="145.1">Or the relationship between the performer and the listener, "How will he do it?</s>
  <s id="145.2">Surely different from the recordings that I know!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="146">But that's the idea!</s>
 <s id="147">Because music is an organism, that breathes and it's alive at the very moment it sounds.</s>
 <s id="148">Only there music is.</s>
 <s id="149">And listening to it live allows us to live that moment full of expectations.</s>
 <s id="150">When the concert ended, my dad took me to meet the director.</s>
 <s id="151">I saw him and I started crying again.</s>
 <s id="152">(Laughter) Without saying anything, I thought: you are responsible for these tears!</s>
 <s id="153">He gave me a puzzled look.</s>
 <s id="154">He asked if anything had happened, for many reasons can make a seven-year-old boy cry.</s>
 <s id="155">My father, still moved, summed it up and understanding now the impact that music had had me, the director hugged me and said: "Well, that's why we do what we do."</s>
 <s id="156">That day changed my life.</s>
 <s id="157">Ever since, my expectations are to change yours.</s>
 <s id="158">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="159">(Applause)</s>
</text>
