<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Basically, there's a major demographic event going on.</s>
 <p id="p2">
  <s id="2.1">And it may be that passing the 50 percent urban point is an economic tipping point.</s>
  <s id="2.2">So the world now is a map of connectivity.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="3">It used to be that Paris and London and New York were the largest cities.</s>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">What we have now is the end of the rise of the West.</s>
  <s id="4.2">That's over.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="5">The aggregate numbers are overwhelming.</s>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">So what's really going on?</s>
  <s id="6.2">Well, villages of the world are emptying out.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="7">The question is, why?</s>
 <p id="p8">
  <s id="8.1">And here's the unromantic truth -- and the city air makes you free, they said in Renaissance Germany.</s>
  <s id="8.2">So some people go to places like Shanghai but most go to the squatter cities where aesthetics rule.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="9">And these are not really a people oppressed by poverty.</s>
 <s id="10">They're people getting out of poverty as fast as they can.</s>
 <s id="11">They're the dominant builders and to a large extent, the dominant designers.</s>
 <s id="12">They have home-brewed infrastructure and vibrant urban life.</s>
 <s id="13">One-sixth of the GDP in India is coming out of Mumbai.</s>
 <s id="14">They are constantly upgrading, and in a few cases, the government helps.</s>
 <s id="15">Education is the main event that can happen in cities.</s>
 <s id="16">What's going on in the street in Mumbai?</s>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">Al Gore knows.</s>
  <s id="17.2">It's basically everything.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">There's no unemployment in squatter cities.</s>
  <s id="18.2">Everyone works.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">One-sixth of humanity is there.</s>
  <s id="19.2">It's soon going to be more than that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">So here's the first punch line: cities have defused the population bomb.</s>
 <s id="21">And here's the second punch line.</s>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">That's the news from downtown.</s>
  <s id="22.2">Here it is in perspective.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">Stars have shined down on earth's life for billions of years.</s>
 <s id="24">Now we're shining right back up.</s>
 <s id="25">Thank you.</s>
</text>
