<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I want to give you a new perspective.</s>
 <s id="2">That sounds grandiose, and it is.</s>
 <s id="3">I left Ireland yesterday morning.</s>
 <s id="4">I traveled from Dublin to New York independently.</s>
 <s id="5">But the design of an airport, plane and terminal offers little independence when you're 105 and a half centimeters tall.</s>
 <s id="6">For Americans, that's 3' 5".</s>
 <s id="7">I was whisked through the airport by airline assistants in a wheelchair.</s>
 <s id="8">Now, I don't need to use a wheelchair, but the design of an airport and its lack of accessibility means that it's my only way to get through.</s>
 <s id="9">With my carry-on bag between my feet, I was wheeled through security, preclearance and I arrived at my boarding gate.</s>
 <s id="10">I use the accessibility services in the airport because most of the terminal is just not designed with me in mind.</s>
 <s id="11">Take security, for example.</s>
 <s id="12">I'm not strong enough to lift my carry-on bag from the ground to the carousel.</s>
 <s id="13">I stand at eye level with it.</s>
 <s id="14">And those who work in that space for safety purposes cannot help me and cannot do it for me.</s>
 <s id="15">Design inhibits my autonomy and my independence.</s>
 <s id="16">But traveling at this size, it isn't all bad.</s>
 <s id="17">The leg room in economy is like business class.</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) I often forget that I'm a little person.</s>
 <s id="19">It's the physical environment and society that remind me.</s>
 <s id="20">Using a public bathroom is an excruciating experience.</s>
 <s id="21">I walk into the cubicle but I can't reach the lock on the door.</s>
 <s id="22">I'm creative and resilient.</s>
 <s id="23">I look around and see if there's a bin that I can turn upside down.</s>
 <s id="24">Is it safe?</s>
 <s id="25">Not really.</s>
 <s id="26">Is it hygienic and sanitary?</s>
 <s id="27">Definitely not.</s>
 <s id="28">But the alternative is much worse.</s>
 <s id="29">If that doesn't work, I use my phone.</s>
 <s id="30">It gives me an additional four- to six-inch reach, and I try to jam the lock closed with my iPhone.</s>
 <s id="31">Now, I imagine that's not what Jony Ive had in mind when he designed the iPhone, but it works.</s>
 <s id="32">The alternative is that I approach a stranger.</s>
 <s id="33">I apologize profusely and I ask them to stand guard outside my cubicle door.</s>
 <s id="34">They do and I emerge grateful but absolutely mortified, and hope that they didn't notice that I left the bathroom without washing my hands.</s>
 <s id="35">I carry hand sanitizer with me every single day because the sink, soap dispenser, hand dryer and mirror are all out of my reach.</s>
 <s id="36">Now, the accessible bathroom is somewhat of an option.</s>
 <s id="37">In this space, I can reach the lock on the door, the sink, the soap dispenser, the hand dryer and the mirror.</s>
 <s id="38">Yet, I cannot use the toilet.</s>
 <s id="39">It is deliberately designed higher so that wheelchair users can transfer across with ease.</s>
 <s id="40">This is a wonderful and necessary innovation, but in the design world, when we describe a new project or idea as accessible, what does that mean?</s>
 <s id="41">Who is it accessible to?</s>
 <s id="42">And whose needs are not being accommodated for?</s>
 <s id="43">Now, the bathroom is an example of where design impinges upon my dignity, but the physical environment impacts upon me in much more casual ways too, something as simple as ordering a cup of coffee.</s>
 <s id="44">Now, I'll admit it.</s>
 <s id="45">I drink far too much coffee.</s>
 <s id="46">My order is a skinny vanilla latte, but I'm trying to wean myself off the syrup.</s>
 <s id="47">But the coffee shop, it's not designed well, at least not for me.</s>
 <s id="48">Queuing, I'm standing beside the pastry cabinet and the barista calls for the next order.</s>
 <s id="49">"Next, please!" they shout.</s>
 <s id="50">They can't see me.</s>
 <s id="51">The person next to me in the queue points to my existence and everyone is embarrassed.</s>
 <s id="52">I order as quick as I can and I move along to collect my coffee.</s>
 <s id="53">Now, think just for a second.</s>
 <s id="54">Where do they put it?</s>
 <s id="55">Up high and without a lid.</s>
 <s id="56">Reaching up to collect a coffee that I have paid for is an incredibly dangerous experience.</s>
 <s id="57">But design also impinges on the clothes that I want to wear.</s>
 <s id="58">I want garments that reflect my personality.</s>
 <s id="59">It's difficult to find in the childrenswear department.</s>
 <s id="60">And often womenswear requires far too many alterations.</s>
 <s id="61">I want shoes that affect my maturity, professionalism and sophistication.</s>
 <s id="62">Instead, I'm offered sneakers with Velcro straps and light-up shoes.</s>
 <s id="63">Now, I'm not totally opposed to light-up shoes.</s>
 <s id="64">(Laughter) But design also impacts on such simple things, like sitting on a chair.</s>
 <s id="65">I cannot go from a standing to a seating position with grace.</s>
 <s id="66">Due to the standards of design heights of chairs, I have to crawl on my hands and knees just to get on top of it, whilst also being conscious that it might tip over at any stage.</s>
 <s id="67">But whilst design impacts on me whether it's a chair, a bathroom, a coffee shop, or clothes, I rely on and benefit from the kindness of strangers.</s>
 <s id="68">But not everybody is so nice.</s>
 <s id="69">I'm reminded that I'm a little person when a stranger points, stares, laughs, calls me a name, or takes a photograph of me.</s>
 <s id="70">This happens almost every day.</s>
 <s id="71">With the rise of social media, it has given me an opportunity and a platform to have a voice as a blogger and as an activist, but it has also made me nervous that I might become a meme or a viral sensation, all without my consent.</s>
 <s id="72">So let's take a moment right now to make something very clear.</s>
 <s id="73">The word "midget" is a slur.</s>
 <s id="74">It evolved from PT Barnum's era of circuses and freak shows.</s>
 <s id="75">Society has evolved.</s>
 <s id="76">So should our vocabulary.</s>
 <s id="77">Language is a powerful tool.</s>
 <s id="78">It does not just name our society.</s>
 <s id="79">It shapes it.</s>
 <s id="80">I am incredibly proud to be a little person, to have inherited the condition of achondroplasia.</s>
 <s id="81">But I am most proud to be Sinead.</s>
 <s id="82">Achondroplasia is the most common form of dwarfism.</s>
 <s id="83">Achondroplasia translates as "without cartilage formation."</s>
 <s id="84">I have short limbs and achondroplastic facial features, my forehead and my nose.</s>
 <s id="85">My arms do not straighten fully, but I can lick my elbow.</s>
 <s id="86">I'm not showing you that one.</s>
 <s id="87">Achondroplasia occurs in approximately one in every 20,000 births.</s>
 <s id="88">80 percent of little people are born to two average-height parents.</s>
 <s id="89">That means that anybody in this room could have a child with achondroplasia.</s>
 <s id="90">Yet, I inherited my condition from my dad.</s>
 <s id="91">I'd like to show you a photo of my family.</s>
 <s id="92">My mother is average height, my father is a little person and I am the eldest of five children.</s>
 <s id="93">I have three sisters and one brother.</s>
 <s id="94">They are all average height.</s>
 <s id="95">I am incredibly fortunate to have been born into a family that cultivated my curiosity and my tenacity, that protected me from the unkindness and ignorance of strangers and that armed me with the resilience, creativity and confidence that I needed to survive and manipulate the physical environment and society.</s>
 <s id="96">If I was to pinpoint any reason why I am successful, it is because I was and I am a loved child, now, a loved child with a lot of sass and sarcasm, but a loved child nonetheless.</s>
 <s id="97">In giving you an insight into who I am today I wanted to offer you a new perspective.</s>
 <s id="98">I wanted to challenge the idea that design is but a tool to create function and beauty.</s>
 <s id="99">Design greatly impacts upon people's lives, all lives.</s>
 <s id="100">Design is a way in which we can feel included in the world, but it is also a way in which we can uphold a person's dignity and their human rights.</s>
 <s id="101">Design can also inflict vulnerability on a group whose needs aren't considered.</s>
 <s id="102">So today, I want your perceptions challenged.</s>
 <s id="103">Who are we not designing for?</s>
 <s id="104">How can we amplify their voices and their experiences?</s>
 <s id="105">What is the next step?</s>
 <s id="106">Design is an enormous privilege, but it is a bigger responsibility.</s>
 <s id="107">I want you to open your eyes.</s>
 <s id="108">Thank you so much.</s>
 <s id="109">(Applause)</s>
</text>
