<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Before empires and royalty, before pottery and writing, before metal tools and weapons – there was cheese.</s>
 <s id="2">As early as 8000 BCE, the earliest Neolithic farmers living in the Fertile Crescent began a legacy of cheesemaking almost as old as civilization itself.</s>
 <s id="3">The rise of agriculture led to domesticated sheep and goats, which ancient farmers harvested for milk.</s>
 <s id="4">But when left in warm conditions for several hours, that fresh milk began to sour.</s>
 <s id="5">Its lactic acids caused proteins to coagulate, binding into soft clumps.</s>
 <s id="6">Upon discovering this strange transformation, the farmers drained the remaining liquid – later named whey – and found the yellowish globs could be eaten fresh as a soft, spreadable meal.</s>
 <s id="7">These clumps, or curds, became the building blocks of cheese, which would eventually be aged, pressed, ripened, and whizzed into a diverse cornucopia of dairy delights.</s>
 <s id="8">The discovery of cheese gave Neolithic people an enormous survival advantage.</s>
 <s id="9">Milk was rich with essential proteins, fats, and minerals.</s>
 <s id="10">But it also contained high quantities of lactose – a sugar which is difficult to process for many ancient and modern stomachs.</s>
 <s id="11">Cheese, however, could provide all of milk’s advantages with much less lactose.</s>
 <s id="12">And since it could be preserved and stockpiled, these essential nutrients could be eaten throughout scarce famines and long winters.</s>
 <s id="13">Some 7th millennium BCE pottery fragments found in Turkey still contain telltale residues of the cheese and butter they held.</s>
 <s id="14">By the end of the Bronze Age, cheese was a standard commodity in maritime trade throughout the eastern Mediterranean.</s>
 <s id="15">In the densely populated city-states of Mesopotamia, cheese became a staple of culinary and religious life.</s>
 <s id="16">Some of the earliest known writing includes administrative records of cheese quotas, listing a variety of cheeses for different rituals and populations across Mesopotamia.</s>
 <s id="17">Records from nearby civilizations in Turkey also reference rennet.</s>
 <s id="18">This animal byproduct, produced in the stomachs of certain mammals, can accelerate and control coagulation.</s>
 <s id="19">Eventually this sophisticated cheesemaking tool spread around the globe, giving way to a wide variety of new, harder cheeses.</s>
 <s id="20">And though some conservative food cultures rejected the dairy delicacy, many more embraced cheese, and quickly added their own local flavors.</s>
 <s id="21">Nomadic Mongolians used yaks’ milk to create hard, sundried wedges of Byaslag.</s>
 <s id="22">Egyptians enjoyed goats’ milk cottage cheese, straining the whey with reed mats.</s>
 <s id="23">In South Asia, milk was coagulated with a variety of food acids, such as lemon juice, vinegar, or yogurt and then hung to dry into loafs of paneer.</s>
 <s id="24">This soft mild cheese could be added to curries and sauces, or simply fried as a quick vegetarian dish.</s>
 <s id="25">The Greeks produced bricks of salty brined feta cheese, alongside a harder variety similar to today’s pecorino romano.</s>
 <s id="26">This grating cheese was produced in Sicily and used in dishes all across the Mediterranean.</s>
 <s id="27">Under Roman rule, “dry cheese” or “caseus aridus,” became an essential ration for the nearly 500,000 soldiers guarding the vast borders of the Roman Empire.</s>
 <s id="28">And when the Western Roman Empire collapsed, cheesemaking continued to evolve in the manors that dotted the medieval European countryside.</s>
 <s id="29">In the hundreds of Benedictine monasteries scattered across Europe, medieval monks experimented endlessly with different types of milk, cheesemaking practices, and aging processes that led to many of today’s popular cheeses.</s>
 <s id="30">Parmesan, Roquefort, Munster and several Swiss types were all refined and perfected by these cheesemaking clergymen.</s>
 <s id="31">In the Alps, Swiss cheesemaking was particularly successful – producing a myriad of cow’s milk cheeses.</s>
 <s id="32">By the end of the 14th century, Alpine cheese from the Gruyere region of Switzerland had become so profitable that a neighboring state invaded the Gruyere highlands to take control of the growing cheese trade.</s>
 <s id="33">Cheese remained popular through the Renaissance, and the Industrial Revolution took production out of the monastery and into machinery.</s>
 <s id="34">Today, the world produces roughly 22 billion kilograms of cheese a year, shipped and consumed around the globe.</s>
 <s id="35">But 10,000 years after its invention, local farms are still following in the footsteps of their Neolithic ancestors, hand crafting one of humanity’s oldest and favorite foods.</s>
</text>
