<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Forrest North: The beginning of any collaboration starts with a conversation.</s>
 <s id="2">And I would like to share with you some of the bits of the conversation that we started with.</s>
 <s id="3">I grew up in a log cabin in Washington state with too much time on my hands.</s>
 <s id="4">Yves Behar: And in scenic Switzerland for me.</s>
 <s id="5">FN: I always had a passion for alternative vehicles.</s>
 <s id="6">This is a land yacht racing across the desert in Nevada.</s>
 <s id="7">YB: Combination of windsurfing and skiing into this invention there.</s>
 <s id="8">FN: And I also had an interest in dangerous inventions.</s>
 <s id="9">This is a 100,000-volt Tesla coil that I built in my bedroom, much to the dismay of my mother.</s>
 <s id="10">YB: To the dismay of my mother, this is dangerous teenage fashion right there.</s>
 <s id="11">(Laughter) FN: And I brought this all together, this passion with alternative energy and raced a solar car across Australia -- also the U.S. and Japan.</s>
 <s id="12">YB: So, wind power, solar power -- we had a lot to talk about.</s>
 <s id="13">We had a lot that got us excited.</s>
 <s id="14">So we decided to do a special project together.</s>
 <s id="15">To combine engineering and design and ...</s>
 <s id="16">FN: Really make a fully integrated product, something beautiful.</s>
 <s id="17">YB: And we made a baby.</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) FN: Can you bring out our baby?</s>
 <s id="19">(Applause) This baby is fully electric.</s>
 <s id="20">It goes 150 miles an hour.</s>
 <s id="21">It's twice the range of any electric motorcycle.</s>
 <s id="22">Really the exciting thing about a motorcycle is just the beautiful integration of engineering and design.</s>
 <s id="23">It's got an amazing user experience.</s>
 <s id="24">It was wonderful working with Yves Behar.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">He came up with our name and logo.</s>
  <s id="25.2">We're Mission Motors.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">And we've only got three minutes, but we could talk about it for hours.</s>
 <s id="27">YB: Thank you.</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">FN: Thank you TED.</s>
  <s id="28.2">And thank you Chris, for having us.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">(Applause)</s>
</text>
