<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">These rocks have been hitting our earth for about three billion years, and are responsible for much of what’s gone on on our planet.</s>
 <s id="2">This is an example of a real meteorite, and you can see all the melting of the iron from the speed and the heat when a meteorite hits the earth, and just how much of it survives and melts.</s>
 <s id="3">From a meteorite from space, we’re over here with an original Sputnik.</s>
 <s id="4">This is one of the seven surviving Sputniks that was not launched into space.</s>
 <s id="5">This is not a copy.</s>
 <s id="6">The space age began 50 years ago in October, and that’s exactly what Sputnik looked like.</s>
 <s id="7">And it wouldn’t be fun to talk about the space age without seeing a flag that was carried to the moon and back, on Apollo 11.</s>
 <s id="8">The astronauts each got to carry about ten silk flags in their personal kits.</s>
 <s id="9">They would bring them back and mount them.</s>
 <s id="10">So this has actually been carried to the moon and back.</s>
 <s id="11">So that’s for fun.</s>
 <s id="12">The dawn of books is, of course, important.</s>
 <s id="13">And it wouldn’t be interesting to talk about the dawn of books without having a copy of a Guttenberg Bible.</s>
 <s id="14">You can see how portable and handy it was to have your own Guttenberg in 1455.</s>
 <s id="15">But what’s interesting about the Guttenberg Bible, and the dawn of this technology, is not the book.</s>
 <s id="16">You see, the book was not driven by reading.</s>
 <s id="17">In 1455, nobody could read.</s>
 <s id="18">So why did the printing press succeed?</s>
 <s id="19">This is an original page of a Guttenberg Bible.</s>
 <s id="20">So you’re looking here at one of the first printed books using movable type in the history of man, 550 years ago.</s>
 <s id="21">We are living at the age here at the end of the book, where electronic paper will undoubtedly replace it.</s>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">But why is this so interesting?</s>
  <s id="22.2">Here’s the quick story.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">It turns out that in the 1450s, the Catholic Church needed money, and so they actually hand-wrote these things called indulgences, which were forgiveness’s on pieces of paper.</s>
 <s id="24">They traveled all around Europe and sold by the hundreds or by the thousands.</s>
 <s id="25">They got you out of purgatory faster.</s>
 <s id="26">And when the printing press was invented what they found was they could print indulgences, which was the equivalent of printing money.</s>
 <s id="27">And so all of Western Europe started buying printing presses in 1455 -- to print out thousands, and then hundreds of thousands, and then ultimately millions of single, small pieces of paper that got you out of middle hell and into heaven.</s>
 <s id="28">That is why the printing press succeeded, and that is why Martin Luther nailed his 90 theses to the door: because he was complaining that the Catholic Church had gone amok in printing out indulgences and selling them in every town and village and city in all of Western Europe.</s>
 <s id="29">So the printing press, ladies and gentlemen, was driven entirely by the printing of forgivenesses and had nothing to do with reading.</s>
 <p id="p30">
  <s id="30.1">More tomorrow.</s>
  <s id="30.2">I also have pictures coming of the library for those of you that have asked for pictures.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="31">We’re going to have some tomorrow.</s>
 <s id="32">(Applause) Instead of showing an object from the stage I’m going to do something special for the first time.</s>
 <s id="33">We are going to show, actually, what the library looks like, OK?</s>
 <s id="34">So, I am married to the most wonderful woman in the world.</s>
 <s id="35">You’re going to find out why in a minute, because when I went to see Eileen, this is what I said I wanted to build.</s>
 <s id="36">This is the Library of Human Imagination.</s>
 <s id="37">The room itself is three stories tall.</s>
 <s id="38">In the glass panels are 5,000 years of human imagination that are computer controlled.</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">The room is a theatre.</s>
  <s id="39.2">It changes colors.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">And all throughout the library are different objects, different spaces.</s>
 <s id="41">It’s designed like an Escher print.</s>
 <s id="42">Here is some of the lower level of the library, where the exhibits constantly change.</s>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">You can walk through.</s>
  <s id="43.2">You can touch.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">You can see exactly how many of these types of items would fit in a room.</s>
 <s id="45">There’s my very own Saturn V.</s>
 <p id="p46">
  <s id="46.1">Everybody should have one, OK?</s>
  <s id="46.2">(Laughter) So you can see here in the lower level of the library the books and the objects.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="47">In the glass panels all along is sort of the history of imagination.</s>
 <s id="48">There is a glass bridge that you walk across that’s suspended in space.</s>
 <s id="49">So it’s a leap of imagination.</s>
 <s id="50">How do we create?</s>
 <s id="51">Part of the question that I have answered is, is we create by surrounding ourselves with stimuli: with human achievement, with history, with the things that drive us and make us human -- the passionate discovery, the bones of dinosaurs long gone, the maps of space that we’ve experienced, and ultimately the hallways that stimulate our mind and our imagination.</s>
 <s id="52">So hopefully tomorrow I’ll show one or two more objects from the stage, but for today I just wanted to say thank you for all the people that came and talked to us about it.</s>
 <s id="53">And Eileen and I are thrilled to open our home and share it with the TED community.</s>
 <s id="54">(Applause) TED is all about patterns in the clouds.</s>
 <s id="55">It’s all about connections.</s>
 <s id="56">It’s all about seeing things that everybody else has seen before but thinking about them in ways that nobody has thought of them before.</s>
 <s id="57">And that’s really what discovery and imagination is all about.</s>
 <s id="58">For example, we can look at a DNA molecule model here.</s>
 <s id="59">None of us really have ever seen one, but we know it exists because we’ve been taught to understand this molecule.</s>
 <s id="60">But we can also look at an Enigma machine from the Nazis in World War II that was a coding and decoding machine.</s>
 <s id="61">Now, you might say, what does this have to do with this?</s>
 <s id="62">Well, this is the code for life, and this is a code for death.</s>
 <s id="63">These two molecules code and decode.</s>
 <s id="64">And yet, looking at them, you would see a machine and a molecule.</s>
 <s id="65">But once you’ve seen them in a new way, you realize that both of these things really are connected.</s>
 <s id="66">And they’re connected primarily because of this here.</s>
 <s id="67">You see, this is a human brain model, OK?</s>
 <s id="68">And it’s rare, because we never really get to see a brain.</s>
 <p id="p69">
  <s id="69.1">We get to see a skull.</s>
  <s id="69.2">But there it is.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="70">All of imagination -- everything that we think, we feel, we sense -- comes through the human brain.</s>
 <s id="71">And once we create new patterns in this brain, once we shape the brain in a new way, it never returns to its original shape.</s>
 <s id="72">And I’ll give you a quick example.</s>
 <s id="73">We think about the Internet; we think about information that goes across the Internet.</s>
 <s id="74">And we never think about the hidden connection.</s>
 <s id="75">But I brought along here a lump of coal -- right here, one lump of coal.</s>
 <s id="76">And what does a lump of coal have to do with the Internet?</s>
 <s id="77">You see, it takes the energy in one lump of coal to move one megabyte of information across the net.</s>
 <s id="78">So every time you download a file, each megabyte is a lump of coal.</s>
 <p id="p79">
  <s id="79.1">What that means is, a 200-megabyte file looks like this, ladies and gentlemen.</s>
  <s id="79.2">OK?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="80">So the next time you download a gigabyte, or two gigabytes, it’s not for free, OK?</s>
 <s id="81">The connection is the energy it takes to run the web , and to make everything we think possible, possible.</s>
 <s id="82">Thanks, Chris.</s>
 <s id="83">(Applause)</s>
</text>
