<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I think the future of this planet depends on humans, not technology, and we already have the knowledge -- we’re kind of at the endgame with knowledge.</s>
 <s id="2">But we’re nowhere near the endgame when it comes to our perception.</s>
 <s id="3">We still have one foot in the dark ages.</s>
 <s id="4">And when you listen to some of the presentations here -- and the extraordinary range of human capability, our understandings -- and then you contrast it with the fact we still call this planet, "Earth:" it’s pretty extraordinary -- we have one foot in the dark ages.</s>
 <s id="5">Just quickly: Aristotle, his thing was, "It’s not flat, stupid, it’s round."</s>
 <s id="6">Galileo -- he had the Inquisition, so he had to be a little bit more polite -- his was, "It’s not in the middle, you know."</s>
 <s id="7">And Hawkes: "it’s not earth, stupid, it’s ocean."</s>
 <s id="8">This is an ocean planet.</s>
 <s id="9">T.S. Eliot really said it for me -- and this should give you goose bumps: "we shall not cease from exploration and the end of our exploring shall be to return where we started and know the place for the first time."</s>
 <s id="10">And the next lines are, "Through the unknown remembered gate, where the last of earth discovered is that which is the beginning."</s>
 <s id="11">So I have one message.</s>
 <s id="12">It seems to me that we’re all pointed in the wrong direction.</s>
 <s id="13">For the rocketeers in the audience: I love what you’re doing, I admire the guts, I admire the courage -- but your rockets are pointed in the wrong goddamn direction.</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) And it’s all a question of perspective.</s>
 <s id="15">Let me try and tell you -- I don’t mean to insult you, but look, if I -- and I’m not doing this for real because it would be an insult, so I’m going to pretend, and it softens the blow -- I’m going to tell you what you’re thinking.</s>
 <s id="16">If I held up a square that was one foot square and the color of earth, and I held up another square that was the root two square -- so it’s 1.5 times bigger -- and was the color of the oceans; and I said, what is the relative value of these two things?</s>
 <s id="17">Well, it’s the relative importance.</s>
 <s id="18">You would say -- yeah, yeah, yeah, we all know this; water covers twice the area of the planet than dry land.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">But it’s a question of perception, and if that’s what you’re thinking, if that’s what you think I mean when I say, "This is an ocean planet stupidly called 'Earth.'"</s>
  <s id="19.2">If you think that that’s the relative importance, two to one, you’re wrong by a factor of ten.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">Now, you’re not as thick as two short planks, but you sound like it when you say "Earth," because that demonstration, if I turned around this way -- that earth plane would be as thin as paper.</s>
 <s id="21">It’s a thin film, two-dimensional existence.</s>
 <s id="22">The ocean representation would have a depth to it.</s>
 <s id="23">And if you hefted those two things you might find that the relative scale of those is 20 to 1.</s>
 <s id="24">It turns out that something more than 94 percent of life on earth is aquatic.</s>
 <s id="25">That means that us terrestrials occupy a minority.</s>
 <s id="26">The problem we have in believing that is -- you just have to give up this notion that this Earth was created for us.</s>
 <s id="27">Because it’s a problem we have.</s>
 <s id="28">If this is an ocean planet and we only have a small minority of this planet, it just interferes with a lot of what humanity thinks.</s>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">Okay.</s>
  <s id="29.2">Let me criticize this thing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">I’m not talking about James Cameron -- although I could, but I won’t.</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">You really do have to go and see his latest film, "Aliens of the Deep."</s>
  <s id="31.2">It’s incredible.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">It features two of these deep rovers, and I can criticize them because these sweet things are mine.</s>
 <s id="33">This, I think, represents one of the most beautiful classic submersibles built.</s>
 <s id="34">If you look at that sub, you’ll see a sphere.</s>
 <s id="35">This is an acryclic sphere.</s>
 <s id="36">It generates all of the buoyancy, all of the payload for the craft, and the batteries are down here hanging underneath, exactly like a balloon.</s>
 <s id="37">This is the envelope, and this is the gondola, the payload.</s>
 <s id="38">Also coming up later for criticism are these massive lights.</s>
 <s id="39">And this one actually carries two great manipulators.</s>
 <s id="40">It actually is a very good working sub -- that’s what it was designed for.</s>
 <s id="41">The problem with it is -- and the reason I will never build another one like it -- is that this is a product of two-dimensional thinking.</s>
 <s id="42">It’s what we humans do when we go in the ocean as engineers; we take all our terrestrial hang-ups, all our constraints -- importantly, these two-dimensional constraints that we have, and they’re so constrained we don’t even understand it -- and we take them underwater.</s>
 <s id="43">You notice that Jim Cameron is sitting in a seat.</s>
 <s id="44">A seat works in a two-dimensional world, where gravity blasts down on that seat, OK?</s>
 <s id="45">And in a two-dimensional world, we do know about the third dimension but we don’t use it because to go up requires an awful lot of energy against gravity.</s>
 <s id="46">And then our mothers tell us, "Careful you don’t fall down" -- because you’ll fall over.</s>
 <s id="47">Now, go into the real atmosphere of this planet.</s>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">This planet has an inner atmosphere of water; it’s its inner atmosphere.</s>
  <s id="48.2">It has two atmospheres -- a lesser, outer gaseous atmosphere, a lighter one.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="49">Most of life on earth is in that inner atmosphere.</s>
 <s id="50">And that life enjoys a three-dimensional existence, which is alien to us.</s>
 <s id="51">Fish do not sit in seats.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">(Laughter) They don’t.</s>
  <s id="52.2">Their mothers don’t say to little baby fish, "Careful you don’t fall over."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p53">
  <s id="53.1">They don’t fall over.</s>
  <s id="53.2">They don’t fall.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="54">They live in a three-dimensional world where there is no difference in energy between going this way, that way, that way or that way.</s>
 <s id="55">It’s truly a three-dimensional space.</s>
 <s id="56">And we’re only just beginning to grasp it.</s>
 <s id="57">I don’t know of any other submersible, or even remote, that just takes advantage that this is a three-dimensional space.</s>
 <s id="58">This is the way we should be going into the oceans.</s>
 <s id="59">This is a three-dimensional machine.</s>
 <s id="60">What we need to do is go down into the ocean with the freedom of the animals, and move in this three-dimensional space.</s>
 <s id="61">OK, this is good stuff.</s>
 <s id="62">This is man’s first attempt at flying underwater.</s>
 <s id="63">Right now, I’m just coming down on this gorgeous, big, giant manta ray.</s>
 <s id="64">She has twice the wingspan that I do.</s>
 <s id="65">There I’m coming; she sees me.</s>
 <s id="66">And just notice how she rolls under and turns; she doesn’t sit there and try and blow air into a tank and kind of flow up or sink down -- she just rolls.</s>
 <s id="67">And the craft that I’m in -- this hasn’t been shown before.</s>
 <s id="68">Chris asked us to show stuff that hasn’t been shown before.</s>
 <s id="69">I wanted you to notice that she actually turned to come back up.</s>
 <s id="70">There I am; I see her coming back, coming up underneath me.</s>
 <s id="71">I put reverse thrust and I try and pull gently down.</s>
 <s id="72">I’m trying to do everything very gently.</s>
 <s id="73">We spent about three hours together and she’s beginning to trust me.</s>
 <s id="74">And this ballet is controlled by this lady here.</s>
 <s id="75">She gets about that close and then she pulls away.</s>
 <s id="76">So now I try and go after her, but I’m practicing flying.</s>
 <p id="p77">
  <s id="77.1">This is the first flying machine.</s>
  <s id="77.2">This was the first prototype.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p78">
  <s id="78.1">This was a fly by wire.</s>
  <s id="78.2">It has wings.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="79">There’re no silly buoyancy tanks -- it’s permanently, positively buoyant.</s>
 <s id="80">And then by moving through the water it’s able to take that control.</s>
 <s id="81">Now, look at that; look, it’s -- she just blew me away.</s>
 <s id="82">She just rolled right away from underneath.</s>
 <s id="83">Really that’s the only real dive I’ve ever made in this machine.</s>
 <s id="84">It took 10 years to build.</s>
 <s id="85">But this lady here taught me, hah, taught me so much.</s>
 <s id="86">We just learned so much in three hours in the water there.</s>
 <s id="87">I just had to go and build another machine.</s>
 <p id="p88">
  <s id="88.1">But look here.</s>
  <s id="88.2">Instead of blowing tanks and coming up slowly without thinking about it, it’s a little bit of back pressure, and that sub just comes straight back up out of the water.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p89">
  <s id="89.1">This is an internal Sony camera.</s>
  <s id="89.2">Thank you, Sony.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="90">I don’t really look that ugly, but the camera is so close that it’s just distorted.</s>
 <s id="91">Now, there she goes, right overhead.</s>
 <s id="92">This is a wide-angle camera.</s>
 <s id="93">She’s just a few inches off the top of my head.</s>
 <s id="94">"Aah, ha, oh, he just crossed over the top of my head about, oh, I don’t know, just so close."</s>
 <s id="95">I come back up, not for air.</s>
 <p id="p96">
  <s id="96.1">"This is an incredible encounter with a manta.</s>
  <s id="96.2">I’m speechless.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p97">
  <s id="97.1">We’ve been just feet apart.</s>
  <s id="97.2">I’m going back down now."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p98">
  <s id="98.1">Okay, can we cut that?</s>
  <s id="98.2">Lights back up please.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="99">(Applause) Trying to fly and keep up with that animal -- it wasn’t the lack of maneuverability that we had.</s>
 <s id="100">It was the fact she was going so slow.</s>
 <s id="101">I actually designed that to move faster through the water because I thought that was the thing that we needed to do: to move fast and get range.</s>
 <s id="102">But after that encounter I really did want to go back with that animal and dance.</s>
 <s id="103">She wanted to dance.</s>
 <s id="104">And so what we needed to do was increase the wing area so that we just had more grip, develop higher forces.</s>
 <s id="105">So the sub that was outside last year -- this is the one.</s>
 <s id="106">You see the larger wing area here.</s>
 <s id="107">Also, clearly, it was such a powerful thing, we wanted to try and bring other people but we couldn't figure out how to do it.</s>
 <s id="108">So we opened the world’s first flight school.</s>
 <s id="109">The rational for the world’s first flight school goes something like: when the coastguards come up to me and say -- they used to leave us alone when we were diving these goofy little spherical things, but when we started flying around in underwater jet fighters they got a little nervous -- they would come up and say, "Do you have a license for that?"</s>
 <s id="110">And then I’d put my sunglasses on, the beard that would all sprout out, and I would say, "I don’t need no stinking license."</s>
 <s id="111">(Laughter) "I write these stinking license," which I do.</s>
 <s id="112">So Bob Gelfond's around here -- but somebody in the audience here has license number 20.</s>
 <s id="113">They’re one of the first subsea aviators.</s>
 <s id="114">So we’ve run two flight schools.</s>
 <s id="115">Where the hell that goes, I don’t know, but it’s a lot of fun.</s>
 <p id="p116">
  <s id="116.1">What comes next in 30 seconds?</s>
  <s id="116.2">I can’t tell you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="117">But the patent for underwater flight -- Karen and I, we were looking at it, some business partners wanted us to patent it -- we weren’t sure about that.</s>
 <s id="118">We’ve decided we’re just going to let that go.</s>
 <s id="119">It just seems wrong to try and patent -- (Applause) -- the freedom for underwater flight.</s>
 <s id="120">So anybody who wants to copy us and come and join us, go for it.</s>
 <s id="121">The other thing is that we’ve got much lower costs.</s>
 <s id="122">We developed some other technology called spider optics, and Craig Ventner asked me to make an announcement here this morning: we’re going to be building a beautiful, little, small version of this -- unmanned, super deep -- for his boat to go and get back some deep sea DNA stuff.</s>
 <s id="123">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
</text>
