<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I love making movies.</s>
 <s id="2">Motion pictures have been in existence for more than a hundred years.</s>
 <s id="3">Filmmaking hasn't changed for the dimensional mindset.</s>
 <s id="4">Placing the camera in a scene and pressing "record" hasn't changed.</s>
 <s id="5">Filmmaking is still a frontal experience, and creating the film has the possibility to follow the same direction of the content creation.</s>
 <s id="6">We still stand in front of a flat image, watching the fiction.</s>
 <s id="7">There's nothing wrong with it.</s>
 <s id="8">I love watching movies and going to the theaters.</s>
 <s id="9">The experiences can be such emotional experiences.</s>
 <s id="10">The art and craft of emotional experiences within a frame can be so strong to drive a stronger emotion.</s>
 <s id="11">The question we're asking is, How the experience of motion pictures can exist beyond the flat screen.</s>
 <s id="12">How can we start creating content for the next generation of content experiences?</s>
 <s id="13">Traditionally, when we imagine a scene, we look at the frame and the composition.</s>
 <s id="14">We have to think about how we create depth and parallax using foreground, background elements as the camera moves.</s>
 <s id="15">With the technology today and devices of VR glasses, AR glasses, smart devices, allowing three-dimensional and full navigation in space, we have the possibility to enable audiences to experience content from multiple perspectives.</s>
 <s id="16">What we have to think about is how we take this technology, all the capabilities, and enable the experience to move farther away inside the scene.</s>
 <s id="17">Now we're not talking about video games or computer-generated actors, which look tremendously realistic.</s>
 <s id="18">We're talking about real actors and real performance, performing onstage.</s>
 <s id="19">We have to start thinking how we capture the actors and how we capture the real scene in order to immerse inside.</s>
 <s id="20">Now, we're familiar with the 360-degree video, where you place a camera inside the scene and you can create this beautiful panoramic image all around you, but from the same aspect, filmmaking is still frontal.</s>
 <s id="21">In order to emerge fully inside the scene, we will need to capture the light from all the possible directions.</s>
 <s id="22">We will have to surround the scene with an enormous amount of sensors, with all possible capabilities to capture the light and enable us to emerge inside afterwards again.</s>
 <s id="23">Now, in this setup, there's no more foreground or background or a camera placed in space but hundreds of sensors capturing the light and capturing the motion from all the possible directions.</s>
 <s id="24">With the new technological advancements, we can start looking at 3D photography, capturing the light from multiple perspectives, enabling us to reconstruct the object.</s>
 <s id="25">This is like photography in 3D space.</s>
 <s id="26">Now, with these technological advancements, we can record video not just as a flat image but as a volume.</s>
 <s id="27">This is what we call "volumetric video," and it has the capability to record every action of the scene as a full three-dimensional volume.</s>
 <s id="28">Now, what is a voxel?</s>
 <s id="29">A voxel is like a three-dimensional pixel, but instead of being a flat image square, staying light and colored, it's like a three-dimensional cube in space, with x, y, and z positions.</s>
 <s id="30">This enables us to create a full capture of the scene from any perspective.</s>
 <s id="31">Now this renders a fully light-immersive scene from multiple perspectives.</s>
 <s id="32">This capability requires an insane amount of information to be processed.</s>
 <s id="33">We will have to capture the light from an enormous amount of cameras to create this information.</s>
 <s id="34">Now, in order to do such a thing, we would need a setup that would host a numerous amount of cameras installed in a stage and a stage big enough in order to fit a full cinematic experience.</s>
 <s id="35">Now that sounds like a crazy idea, but that's exactly what we did.</s>
 <s id="36">For the last three years, we have been building a huge volumetric camera chamber.</s>
 <s id="37">It's 10,000 square feet of a stage, enabling to capture the action from any location.</s>
 <s id="38">We have deployed hundreds of cameras, sending a tremendous amount of information to a huge data center powered by Intel supercomputers.</s>
 <s id="39">The ability to have this 10,000 feet enables us to fit any kind of action, any kind of performance.</s>
 <s id="40">It is the size of an average Broadway stage.</s>
 <s id="41">We call it Intel Studios, and it's the largest volumetric stage in the world, with the objective of enabling and exploring the next generation of this immersive media filmmaking.</s>
 <s id="42">Now, to test these ideas, we were thinking about what we can do as the first scene to try it out.</s>
 <s id="43">So we chose the Western scene.</s>
 <s id="44">We brought horses, set designers, dirt, everything needed to create the full scene of a Western.</s>
 <s id="45">But this time, there was no camera inside.</s>
 <s id="46">There was nothing really moving besides all the cameras installed outside.</s>
 <s id="47">The challenge of the actors was tremendous.</s>
 <s id="48">They have to perform a flawless action visible from all the directions.</s>
 <s id="49">There's no possibility to hide a punch or not show the action.</s>
 <s id="50">Everything is captured and everything is seen.</s>
 <s id="51">The output of the capture -- this is our future capture -- opened our eyes for the immense capabilities.</s>
 <s id="52">It was like a full 3D scan of the entire scene.</s>
 <s id="53">We were able to move around and travel in the space.</s>
 <s id="54">The thing about this, it's not anymore about perceiving the light emitted from a screen but now traveling inside the light, traveling inside the scene.</s>
 <s id="55">This obviously opens possibilities for an enormous amount of storytelling and methodologies of creation.</s>
 <s id="56">This is the possibilities of your personal narrative, the possibility of creating your own story inside, or maybe following other stories.</s>
 <s id="57">Let's take a look at one of the last renders and see.</s>
 <s id="58">(Music) What you're seeing here is full volumetric video, and there's no physical camera in the scene.</s>
 <s id="59">(Music) We have the full control (Music, sounds of combat) of space and time.</s>
 <s id="60">(Music, sounds of combat) Now, again, no physical camera was here.</s>
 <s id="61">Everything was captured surrounding.</s>
 <s id="62">Now, this is very nice, but what if we wanted to see the scene, maybe, from the eyes of the horse?</s>
 <s id="63">Well, we can do that as well.</s>
 <s id="64">(Horse galloping) So what you're seeing right now is the same action, but this time, we're watching exactly from the eyes of the horse.</s>
 <s id="65">The possibilities are, well, unlimited.</s>
 <s id="66">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="67">(Applause) So this is all great for creators and storytellers.</s>
 <s id="68">It really opens a huge canvas for a different type of storytelling and moviemaking.</s>
 <s id="69">But what about the audience?</s>
 <s id="70">How can the audience experience this differently?</s>
 <s id="71">In order to [create] our explorations, we partnered with Paramount Pictures in order to explore immersive media in a Hollywood movie production.</s>
 <s id="72">Together with the director Randal Kleiser, we reimagined the iconic movie of 1978, "Grease."</s>
 <s id="73">Some of you know it, some of you don't.</s>
 <s id="74">A 40-year-old movie, amazing experience.</s>
 <s id="75">And our goal was really to look at how we can take this iconic action and dance and bring it deeper into the experience, bring it deeper into the audience.</s>
 <s id="76">Imagine that you can not just watch the movie but get inside it and dance with the actors and dance with the performance.</s>
 <s id="77">Now we're breaking, really, the traditional 2D mindset of thinking, and bringing a much richer possibility of moviemaking and content creation.</s>
 <s id="78">But why watch it on the screen?</s>
 <s id="79">Let's try to bring these actors here on the stage.</s>
 <s id="80">So they're not going to really come -- I'm going to use an iPad.</s>
 <s id="81">(Laughter) Sorry.</s>
 <s id="82">I'm going to use an iPad in order to bring in augmented reality.</s>
 <s id="83">Now, obviously, these devices have their own limitations in terms of the data-computing process, so we have to reduce the amount of resolution.</s>
 <s id="84">So what I'm doing now, I'm placing here a marker, so I'll be able to position exactly where I want everyone to appear.</s>
 <s id="85">OK.</s>
 <s id="86">I think we have them here.</s>
 <s id="87">(Applause) John Travolta, or -- (Laughter) a version of him.</s>
 <s id="88">Let's take a look.</s>
 <s id="89">(Video) Female: Hey.</s>
 <s id="90">Male: And that is how it's done.</s>
 <s id="91">Female: Your turn.</s>
 <p id="p92">
  <s id="92.1">Male: Hey, guys!</s>
  <s id="92.2">Check this out.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="93">(Song: "You're the one that I want") Danny: Sandy!</s>
 <s id="94">Sandy: Tell me about it, stud.</s>
 <p id="p95">
  <s id="95.1">(Singing) I got chills.</s>
  <s id="95.2">They're multiplying And I'm losing control 'Cause the power you're supplying It's electrifying!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="96">(Video ends) (Applause and cheers) Diego Prilusky: Thank you.</s>
 <s id="97">(Applause and cheers) So as you can see, we can watch and experience content in the traditional way or in an immersive way.</s>
 <s id="98">Really, the possibilities are open.</s>
 <s id="99">We're not trying to change or replace movies.</s>
 <s id="100">We're enhancing them.</s>
 <s id="101">The technologies enable new possibilities to start thinking beyond the flat screen.</s>
 <s id="102">We're in immersive and really exciting times in filmmaking.</s>
 <s id="103">We're at the threshold of a new era.</s>
 <s id="104">We're opening the gates for new possibilities of immersive storytelling, and exploration and defining what immersive media filmmaking means.</s>
 <s id="105">We're really just at the beginning, and we invite you all to join us.</s>
 <s id="106">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="107">(Applause)</s>
</text>
