<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">How do you know you're real?</s>
 <s id="2">It's an obvious question until you try to answer it, but let's take it seriously.</s>
 <s id="3">How do you really know you exist?</s>
 <s id="4">In his "Meditations on First Philosophy," René Descartes tried to answer that very question, demolishing all his preconceived notions and opinions to begin again from the foundations.</s>
 <s id="5">All his knowledge had come from his sensory perceptions of the world.</s>
 <s id="6">Same as you, right?</s>
 <s id="7">You know you're watching this video with your eyes, hearing it with your ears.</s>
 <s id="8">Your senses show you the world as it is.</s>
 <s id="9">They aren't deceiving you, but sometimes they do.</s>
 <s id="10">You might mistake a person far away for someone else, or you're sure you're about to catch a flyball, and it hits the ground in front of you.</s>
 <s id="11">But come on, right here and now, you know what's right in front of you is real.</s>
 <s id="12">Your eyes, your hands, your body: that's you.</s>
 <s id="13">Only crazy people would deny that, and you know you're not crazy.</s>
 <s id="14">Anyone who'd doubt that must be dreaming.</s>
 <s id="15">Oh no, what if you're dreaming?</s>
 <s id="16">Dreams feel real.</s>
 <s id="17">You can believe you're swimming, flying or fighting off monsters with your bare hands, when your real body is lying in bed.</s>
 <s id="18">No, no, no.</s>
 <s id="19">When you're awake, you know you're awake.</s>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">Ah!</s>
  <s id="20.2">But when you aren't, you don't know you aren't, so you can't prove you aren't dreaming.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="21">Maybe the body you perceive yourself to have isn't really there.</s>
 <s id="22">Maybe all of reality, even its abstract concepts, like time, shape, color and number are false, all just deceptions concocted by an evil genius!</s>
 <s id="23">No, seriously.</s>
 <s id="24">Descartes asks if you can disprove the idea that an evil genius demon has tricked you into believing reality is real.</s>
 <s id="25">Perhaps this diabolical deceiver has duped you.</s>
 <s id="26">The world, your perceptions of it, your very body.</s>
 <s id="27">You can't disprove that they're all just made up, and how could you exist without them?</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">You couldn't!</s>
  <s id="28.2">So, you don't.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">Life is but a dream, and I bet you aren't row, row, rowing the boat merrily at all, are you?</s>
 <s id="30">No, you're rowing it wearily like the duped, nonexistent doof you are/aren't.</s>
 <s id="31">Do you find that convincing?</s>
 <s id="32">Are you persuaded?</s>
 <s id="33">If you aren't, good; if you are, even better, because by being persuaded, you would prove that you're a persuaded being.</s>
 <s id="34">You can't be nothing if you think you're something, even if you think that something is nothing because no matter what you think, you're a thinking thing, or as Descartes put it, "I think, therefore I am," and so are you, really.</s>
 <s id="35">(Airplane engine)</s>
</text>
