<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Speaking up is hard to do.</s>
 <s id="2">I understood the true meaning of this phrase exactly one month ago, when my wife and I became new parents.</s>
 <s id="3">It was an amazing moment.</s>
 <s id="4">It was exhilarating and elating, but it was also scary and terrifying.</s>
 <s id="5">And it got particularly terrifying when we got home from the hospital, and we were unsure whether our little baby boy was getting enough nutrients from breastfeeding.</s>
 <s id="6">And we wanted to call our pediatrician, but we also didn't want to make a bad first impression or come across as a crazy, neurotic parent.</s>
 <s id="7">So we worried.</s>
 <s id="8">And we waited.</s>
 <s id="9">When we got to the doctor's office the next day, she immediately gave him formula because he was pretty dehydrated.</s>
 <s id="10">Our son is fine now, and our doctor has reassured us we can always contact her.</s>
 <s id="11">But in that moment, I should've spoken up, but I didn't.</s>
 <s id="12">But sometimes we speak up when we shouldn't, and I learned that over 10 years ago when I let my twin brother down.</s>
 <s id="13">My twin brother is a documentary filmmaker, and for one of his first films, he got an offer from a distribution company.</s>
 <s id="14">He was excited, and he was inclined to accept the offer.</s>
 <s id="15">But as a negotiations researcher, I insisted he make a counteroffer, and I helped him craft the perfect one.</s>
 <s id="16">And it was perfect -- it was perfectly insulting.</s>
 <s id="17">The company was so offended, they literally withdrew the offer and my brother was left with nothing.</s>
 <s id="18">And I've asked people all over the world about this dilemma of speaking up: when they can assert themselves, when they can push their interests, when they can express an opinion, when they can make an ambitious ask.</s>
 <s id="19">And the range of stories are varied and diverse, but they also make up a universal tapestry.</s>
 <s id="20">Can I correct my boss when they make a mistake?</s>
 <s id="21">Can I confront my coworker who keeps stepping on my toes?</s>
 <s id="22">Can I challenge my friend's insensitive joke?</s>
 <s id="23">Can I tell the person I love the most my deepest insecurities?</s>
 <s id="24">And through these experiences, I've come to recognize that each of us have something called a range of acceptable behavior.</s>
 <s id="25">Now, sometimes we're too strong; we push ourselves too much.</s>
 <s id="26">That's what happened with my brother.</s>
 <s id="27">Even making an offer was outside his range of acceptable behavior.</s>
 <s id="28">But sometimes we're too weak.</s>
 <s id="29">That's what happened with my wife and I.</s>
 <s id="30">And this range of acceptable behaviors -- when we stay within our range, we're rewarded.</s>
 <s id="31">When we step outside that range, we get punished in a variety of ways.</s>
 <s id="32">We get dismissed or demeaned or even ostracized.</s>
 <s id="33">Or we lose that raise or that promotion or that deal.</s>
 <s id="34">Now, the first thing we need to know is: What is my range?</s>
 <s id="35">But the key thing is, our range isn't fixed; it's actually pretty dynamic.</s>
 <s id="36">It expands and it narrows based on the context.</s>
 <s id="37">And there's one thing that determines that range more than anything else, and that's your power.</s>
 <s id="38">Your power determines your range.</s>
 <s id="39">What is power?</s>
 <s id="40">Power comes in lots of forms.</s>
 <s id="41">In negotiations, it comes in the form of alternatives.</s>
 <s id="42">So my brother had no alternatives; he lacked power.</s>
 <s id="43">The company had lots of alternatives; they had power.</s>
 <s id="44">Sometimes it's being new to a country, like an immigrant, or new to an organization or new to an experience, like my wife and I as new parents.</s>
 <s id="45">Sometimes it's at work, where someone's the boss and someone's the subordinate.</s>
 <s id="46">Sometimes it's in relationships, where one person's more invested than the other person.</s>
 <s id="47">And the key thing is that when we have lots of power, our range is very wide.</s>
 <s id="48">We have a lot of leeway in how to behave.</s>
 <s id="49">But when we lack power, our range narrows.</s>
 <s id="50">We have very little leeway.</s>
 <s id="51">The problem is that when our range narrows, that produces something called the low-power double bind.</s>
 <s id="52">The low-power double bind happens when, if we don't speak up, we go unnoticed, but if we do speak up, we get punished.</s>
 <s id="53">Now, many of you have heard the phrase the "double bind" and connected it with one thing, and that's gender.</s>
 <s id="54">The gender double bind is women who don't speak up go unnoticed, and women who do speak up get punished.</s>
 <s id="55">And the key thing is that women have the same need as men to speak up, but they have barriers to doing so.</s>
 <s id="56">But what my research has shown over the last two decades is that what looks like a gender difference is not really a gender double bind, it's a really a low-power double bind.</s>
 <s id="57">And what looks like a gender difference are really often just power differences in disguise.</s>
 <p id="p58">
  <s id="58.1">Oftentimes we see a difference between a man and a woman or men and women, and think, "Biological cause.</s>
  <s id="58.2">There's something fundamentally different about the sexes."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="59">But in study after study, I've found that a better explanation for many sex differences is really power.</s>
 <s id="60">And so it's the low-power double bind.</s>
 <s id="61">And the low-power double bind means that we have a narrow range, and we lack power.</s>
 <s id="62">We have a narrow range, and our double bind is very large.</s>
 <s id="63">So we need to find ways to expand our range.</s>
 <s id="64">And over the last couple decades, my colleagues and I have found two things really matter.</s>
 <s id="65">The first: you seem powerful in your own eyes.</s>
 <s id="66">The second: you seem powerful in the eyes of others.</s>
 <s id="67">When I feel powerful, I feel confident, not fearful; I expand my own range.</s>
 <s id="68">When other people see me as powerful, they grant me a wider range.</s>
 <s id="69">So we need tools to expand our range of acceptable behavior.</s>
 <s id="70">And I'm going to give you a set of tools today.</s>
 <s id="71">Speaking up is risky, but these tools will lower your risk of speaking up.</s>
 <s id="72">The first tool I'm going to give you got discovered in negotiations in an important finding.</s>
 <s id="73">On average, women make less ambitious offers and get worse outcomes than men at the bargaining table.</s>
 <s id="74">But Hannah Riley Bowles and Emily Amanatullah have discovered there's one situation where women get the same outcomes as men and are just as ambitious.</s>
 <s id="75">That's when they advocate for others.</s>
 <s id="76">When they advocate for others, they discover their own range and expand it in their own mind.</s>
 <s id="77">They become more assertive.</s>
 <s id="78">This is sometimes called "the mama bear effect."</s>
 <s id="79">Like a mama bear defending her cubs, when we advocate for others, we can discover our own voice.</s>
 <s id="80">But sometimes, we have to advocate for ourselves.</s>
 <s id="81">How do we do that?</s>
 <s id="82">One of the most important tools we have to advocate for ourselves is something called perspective-taking.</s>
 <s id="83">And perspective-taking is really simple: it's simply looking at the world through the eyes of another person.</s>
 <s id="84">It's one of the most important tools we have to expand our range.</s>
 <s id="85">When I take your perspective, and I think about what you really want, you're more likely to give me what I really want.</s>
 <s id="86">But here's the problem: perspective-taking is hard to do.</s>
 <s id="87">So let's do a little experiment.</s>
 <s id="88">I want you all to hold your hand just like this: your finger -- put it up.</s>
 <s id="89">And I want you to draw a capital letter E on your forehead as quickly as possible.</s>
 <s id="90">OK, it turns out that we can draw this E in one of two ways, and this was originally designed as a test of perspective-taking.</s>
 <s id="91">I'm going to show you two pictures of someone with an E on their forehead -- my former student, Erika Hall.</s>
 <s id="92">And you can see over here, that's the correct E.</s>
 <s id="93">I drew the E so it looks like an E to another person.</s>
 <s id="94">That's the perspective-taking E because it looks like an E from someone else's vantage point.</s>
 <s id="95">But this E over here is the self-focused E.</s>
 <s id="96">We often get self-focused.</s>
 <s id="97">And we particularly get self-focused in a crisis.</s>
 <s id="98">I want to tell you about a particular crisis.</s>
 <s id="99">A man walks into a bank in Watsonville, California.</s>
 <s id="100">And he says, "Give me $2,000, or I'm blowing the whole bank up with a bomb."</s>
 <s id="101">Now, the bank manager didn't give him the money.</s>
 <s id="102">She took a step back.</s>
 <s id="103">She took his perspective, and she noticed something really important.</s>
 <s id="104">He asked for a specific amount of money.</s>
 <s id="105">So she said, "Why did you ask for $2,000?"</s>
 <s id="106">And he said, "My friend is going to be evicted unless I get him $2,000 immediately."</s>
 <p id="p107">
  <s id="107.1">And she said, "Oh!</s>
  <s id="107.2">You don't want to rob the bank -- you want to take out a loan."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="108">(Laughter) "Why don't you come back to my office, and we can have you fill out the paperwork."</s>
 <s id="109">(Laughter) Now, her quick perspective-taking defused a volatile situation.</s>
 <s id="110">So when we take someone's perspective, it allows us to be ambitious and assertive, but still be likable.</s>
 <s id="111">Here's another way to be assertive but still be likable, and that is to signal flexibility.</s>
 <s id="112">Now, imagine you're a car salesperson, and you want to sell someone a car.</s>
 <s id="113">You're going to more likely make the sale if you give them two options.</s>
 <s id="114">Let's say option A: $24,000 for this car and a five-year warranty.</s>
 <s id="115">Or option B: $23,000 and a three-year warranty.</s>
 <s id="116">My research shows that when you give people a choice among options, it lowers their defenses, and they're more likely to accept your offer.</s>
 <s id="117">And this doesn't just work with salespeople; it works with parents.</s>
 <s id="118">When my niece was four, she resisted getting dressed and rejected everything.</s>
 <s id="119">But then my sister-in-law had a brilliant idea.</s>
 <s id="120">What if I gave my daughter a choice?</s>
 <p id="p121">
  <s id="121.1">This shirt or that shirt?</s>
  <s id="121.2">OK, that shirt.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p122">
  <s id="122.1">This pant or that pant?</s>
  <s id="122.2">OK, that pant.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="123">And it worked brilliantly.</s>
 <s id="124">She got dressed quickly and without resistance.</s>
 <s id="125">When I've asked the question around the world when people feel comfortable speaking up, the number one answer is: "When I have social support in my audience; when I have allies."</s>
 <s id="126">So we want to get allies on our side.</s>
 <s id="127">How do we do that?</s>
 <s id="128">Well, one of the ways is be a mama bear.</s>
 <s id="129">When we advocate for others, we expand our range in our own eyes and the eyes of others, but we also earn strong allies.</s>
 <s id="130">Another way we can earn strong allies, especially in high places, is by asking other people for advice.</s>
 <s id="131">When we ask others for advice, they like us because we flatter them, and we're expressing humility.</s>
 <s id="132">And this really works to solve another double bind.</s>
 <s id="133">And that's the self-promotion double bind.</s>
 <s id="134">The self-promotion double bind is that if we don't advertise our accomplishments, no one notices.</s>
 <s id="135">And if we do, we're not likable.</s>
 <s id="136">But if we ask for advice about one of our accomplishments, we are able to be competent in their eyes but also be likeable.</s>
 <s id="137">And this is so powerful it even works when you see it coming.</s>
 <s id="138">There have been multiple times in life when I have been forewarned that a low-power person has been given the advice to come ask me for advice.</s>
 <s id="139">I want you to notice three things about this: First, I knew they were going to come ask me for advice.</s>
 <s id="140">Two, I've actually done research on the strategic benefits of asking for advice.</s>
 <s id="141">And three, it still worked!</s>
 <s id="142">I took their perspective, I became more invested in their cause, I became more committed to them because they asked for advice.</s>
 <s id="143">Now, another time we feel more confident speaking up is when we have expertise.</s>
 <s id="144">Expertise gives us credibility.</s>
 <s id="145">When we have high power, we already have credibility.</s>
 <s id="146">We only need good evidence.</s>
 <s id="147">When we lack power, we don't have the credibility.</s>
 <s id="148">We need excellent evidence.</s>
 <s id="149">And one of the ways we can come across as an expert is by tapping into our passion.</s>
 <s id="150">I want everyone in the next few days to go up to friend of theirs and just say to them, "I want you to describe a passion of yours to me."</s>
 <s id="151">I've had people do this all over the world and I asked them, "What did you notice about the other person when they described their passion?"</s>
 <s id="152">And the answers are always the same.</s>
 <s id="153">"Their eyes lit up and got big."</s>
 <s id="154">"They smiled a big beaming smile."</s>
 <s id="155">"They used their hands all over -- I had to duck because their hands were coming at me."</s>
 <s id="156">"They talk quickly with a little higher pitch."</s>
 <s id="157">(Laughter) "They leaned in as if telling me a secret."</s>
 <s id="158">And then I said to them, "What happened to you as you listened to their passion?"</s>
 <s id="159">They said, "My eyes lit up.</s>
 <s id="160">I smiled.</s>
 <s id="161">I leaned in."</s>
 <s id="162">When we tap into our passion, we give ourselves the courage, in our own eyes, to speak up, but we also get the permission from others to speak up.</s>
 <s id="163">Tapping into our passion even works when we come across as too weak.</s>
 <s id="164">Both men and women get punished at work when they shed tears.</s>
 <s id="165">But Lizzie Wolf has shown that when we frame our strong emotions as passion, the condemnation of our crying disappears for both men and women.</s>
 <s id="166">I want to end with a few words from my late father that he spoke at my twin brother's wedding.</s>
 <s id="167">Here's a picture of us.</s>
 <s id="168">My dad was a psychologist like me, but his real love and his real passion was cinema, like my brother.</s>
 <s id="169">And so he wrote a speech for my brother's wedding about the roles we play in the human comedy.</s>
 <s id="170">And he said, "The lighter your touch, the better you become at improving and enriching your performance.</s>
 <s id="171">Those who embrace their roles and work to improve their performance grow, change and expand the self.</s>
 <s id="172">Play it well, and your days will be mostly joyful."</s>
 <s id="173">What my dad was saying is that we've all been assigned ranges and roles in this world.</s>
 <s id="174">But he was also saying the essence of this talk: those roles and ranges are constantly expanding and evolving.</s>
 <s id="175">So when a scene calls for it, be a ferocious mama bear and a humble advice seeker.</s>
 <s id="176">Have excellent evidence and strong allies.</s>
 <s id="177">Be a passionate perspective taker.</s>
 <s id="178">And if you use those tools -- and each and every one of you can use these tools -- you will expand your range of acceptable behavior, and your days will be mostly joyful.</s>
 <s id="179">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="180">(Applause)</s>
</text>
