<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <p id="p1">
  <s id="1.1">On simplicity.</s>
  <s id="1.2">What a great way to start.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="2">First of all, I've been watching this trend where we have these books like such and such "For Dummies."</s>
 <s id="3">Do you know these books, these such and such "For Dummies?"</s>
 <s id="4">My daughters pointed out that I'm very similar looking, so this is a bit of a problem.</s>
 <s id="5">(Laughter) But I was looking online at Amazon.com for other books like this.</s>
 <s id="6">You know, there's also something called the "Complete Idiot's Guide?"</s>
 <s id="7">There's a sort of business model around being stupid in some sense.</s>
 <s id="8">We like to have technology make us feel bad, for some strange reason.</s>
 <s id="9">But I really like that, so I wrote a book called "The Laws of Simplicity."</s>
 <s id="10">I was in Milan last week, for the Italian launch.</s>
 <s id="11">It's kind of a book about questions, questions about simplicity.</s>
 <p id="p12">
  <s id="12.1">Very few answers.</s>
  <s id="12.2">I'm also wondering myself, what is simplicity?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">Is it good?</s>
  <s id="13.2">Is it bad?</s>
  <s id="13.3">Is complexity better?</s>
  <s id="13.4">I'm not sure.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">After I wrote "The Laws of Simplicity," I was very tired of simplicity, as you can imagine.</s>
 <s id="15">And so in my life, I've discovered that vacation is the most important skill for any kind of over-achiever.</s>
 <s id="16">Because your companies will always take away your life, but they can never take away your vacation -- in theory.</s>
 <s id="17">(Laughter) So, I went to the Cape last summer to hide from simplicity, and I went to the Gap, because I only have black pants.</s>
 <s id="18">So I went and bought khaki shorts or whatever, and unfortunately, their branding was all about "Keep It Simple."</s>
 <s id="19">(Laughter) I opened up a magazine, and Visa's branding was, "Business Takes Simplicity."</s>
 <s id="20">I develop photographs, and Kodak said, "Keep It Simple."</s>
 <s id="21">So, I felt kind of weird that simplicity was sort of following me around.</s>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">So, I turned on the TV, and I don't watch TV very much, but you know this person?</s>
  <s id="22.2">This is Paris Hilton, apparently.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">And she has this show, "The Simple Life."</s>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">So I watched this.</s>
  <s id="24.2">It's not very simple, a little bit confusing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="25">(Laughter) So, I looked for a different show to watch.</s>
 <s id="26">So, I opened up this TV Guide thing, and on the E! channel, this "Simple Life" show is very popular.</s>
 <s id="27">They'll play it over, and over, and over.</s>
 <s id="28">(Laughter) So it was traumatizing, actually.</s>
 <s id="29">So, I wanted to escape again, so I went out to my car.</s>
 <s id="30">And Cape Cod, there are idyllic roads, and all of us can drive in this room.</s>
 <s id="31">And when you drive, these signs are very important.</s>
 <s id="32">It's a very simple sign, it says, "road" and "road approaching."</s>
 <s id="33">So I'm mostly driving along, okay, and then I saw this sign.</s>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">(Laughter) So, I thought complexity was attacking me suddenly, so I thought, "Ah, simplicity.</s>
  <s id="34.2">Very important."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">But then I thought, "Oh, simplicity.</s>
  <s id="35.2">What would that be like on a beach?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">What if the sky was 41 percent gray?</s>
  <s id="36.2">Wouldn't that be the perfect sky?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="37">I mean that simplicity sky.</s>
 <p id="p38">
  <s id="38.1">But in reality, the sky looked like this.</s>
  <s id="38.2">It was a beautiful, complex sky.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">You know, with the pinks and blues.</s>
  <s id="39.2">We can't help but love complexity.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">We're human beings: we love complex things.</s>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">We love relationships -- very complex.</s>
  <s id="41.2">So we love this kind of stuff.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">I'm at this place called the Media Lab.</s>
 <s id="43">Maybe some of you guys have heard of this place.</s>
 <s id="44">It's designed by I. M. Pei, one of the premier modernist architects.</s>
 <s id="45">Modernism means white box, and it's a perfect white box.</s>
 <s id="46">(Laughter) And some of you guys are entrepreneurs, etc., whatever.</s>
 <s id="47">Last month, I was at Google, and, boy, that cafeteria, man.</s>
 <s id="48">You guys have things here in Silicon Valley like stock options.</s>
 <s id="49">See, in academia, we get titles, lots of titles.</s>
 <p id="p50">
  <s id="50.1">Last year at TED, these were all my titles.</s>
  <s id="50.2">I had a lot of titles.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="51">I have a default title as a father of a bunch of daughters.</s>
 <s id="52">This year at TED, I'm happy to report that I have new titles, in addition to my previous titles.</s>
 <s id="53">Another "Associate Director of Research."</s>
 <s id="54">And this also happened, so I have five daughters now.</s>
 <p id="p55">
  <s id="55.1">(Laughter) That's my baby Reina.</s>
  <s id="55.2">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p56">
  <s id="56.1">And so, my life is much more complex because of the baby, actually, but that's okay.</s>
  <s id="56.2">We will still stay married, I think.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="57">But looking way back, when I was a child -- you see, I grew up in a tofu factory in Seattle.</s>
 <p id="p58">
  <s id="58.1">Many of you may not like tofu because you haven't had good tofu, but tofu's a good food.</s>
  <s id="58.2">It's a very simple kind of food.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="59">It's very hard work to make tofu.</s>
 <s id="60">As a child, we used to wake up at 1 a.m. and work till 6 p.m., six days a week.</s>
 <s id="61">My father was kind of like Andy Grove, paranoid of the competition.</s>
 <p id="p62">
  <s id="62.1">So often, seven days a week.</s>
  <s id="62.2">Family business equals child labor.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p63">
  <s id="63.1">We were a great model.</s>
  <s id="63.2">So, I loved going to school.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="64">School was great, and maybe going to school helped me get to this Media Lab place, I'm not sure.</s>
 <s id="65">(Laughter) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="66">But the Media Lab is an interesting place, and it's important to me because as a student, I was a computer science undergrad, and I discovered design later on in my life.</s>
 <s id="67">And there was this person, Muriel Cooper.</s>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">Who knows Muriel Cooper?</s>
  <s id="68.2">Muriel Cooper?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p69">
  <s id="69.1">Wasn't she amazing?</s>
  <s id="69.2">Muriel Cooper.</s>
  <s id="69.3">She was wacky.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="70">And she was a TEDster, exactly, and she showed us, she showed the world how to make the computer beautiful again.</s>
 <s id="71">And she's very important in my life, because she's the one that told me to leave MIT and go to art school.</s>
 <p id="p72">
  <s id="72.1">It was the best advice I ever got.</s>
  <s id="72.2">So I went to art school, because of her.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="73">She passed away in 1994, and I was hired back to MIT to try to fill her shoes, but it's so hard.</s>
 <s id="74">This amazing person, Muriel Cooper.</s>
 <s id="75">When I was in Japan -- I went to an art school in Japan -- I had a nice sort of situation, because somehow I was connected to Paul Rand.</s>
 <s id="76">Some of you guys know Paul Rand, the greatest graphic designer -- I'm sorry -- out there.</s>
 <s id="77">The great graphic designer Paul Rand designed the IBM logo, the Westinghouse logo.</s>
 <s id="78">He basically said, "I've designed everything."</s>
 <p id="p79">
  <s id="79.1">And also Ikko Tanaka was a very important mentor in my life -- the Paul Rand of Japan.</s>
  <s id="79.2">He designed most of the major icons of Japan, like Issey Miyake's brand and also Muji.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="80">When you have mentors -- and yesterday, Kareem Abdul-Jabbar talked about mentors, these people in your life -- the problem with mentors is that they all die.</s>
 <s id="81">This is a sad thing, but it's actually a happy thing in a way, because you can remember them in their pure form.</s>
 <s id="82">I think that the mentors that we all meet sort of humanize us.</s>
 <s id="83">When you get older, and you're all freaked out, whatever, the mentors calm us down.</s>
 <s id="84">And I'm grateful for my mentors, and I'm sure all of you are too.</s>
 <s id="85">Because the human thing is very hard when you're at MIT.</s>
 <s id="86">The T doesn't stand for "human," it stands for "technology."</s>
 <s id="87">And because of that, I always wondered about this human thing.</s>
 <s id="88">So, I've always been Googling this word, "human," to find out how many hits I get.</s>
 <p id="p89">
  <s id="89.1">And in 2001, I had 26 million hits, and for "computer," because computers are against humans a bit, I have 42 million hits.</s>
  <s id="89.2">Let me do an Al Gore here.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="90">So, if you sort of compare that, like this, you'll see that computer versus human -- I've been tracking this for the last year -- computer versus human over the last year has changed.</s>
 <p id="p91">
  <s id="91.1">It used to be kind of two to one.</s>
  <s id="91.2">Now, humans are catching up.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p92">
  <s id="92.1">Very good, us humans!</s>
  <s id="92.2">We're catching up with the computers.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="93">In the simplicity realm, it's also interesting.</s>
 <s id="94">So if you compare complexities to simplicity, it's also catching up in a way, too.</s>
 <s id="95">So, somehow humans and simplicity are intertwined, I think.</s>
 <s id="96">I have a confession: I'm not a man of simplicity.</s>
 <s id="97">I spent my entire early career making complex stuff.</s>
 <s id="98">Lots of complex stuff.</s>
 <s id="99">I wrote computer programs to make complex graphics like this.</s>
 <s id="100">I had clients in Japan to make really complex stuff like this.</s>
 <s id="101">And I've always felt bad about it, in a sense.</s>
 <s id="102">So, I hid in a time dimension.</s>
 <s id="103">I built things in a time-graphics dimension.</s>
 <s id="104">I did this series of calendars for Shiseido.</s>
 <p id="p105">
  <s id="105.1">This is a floral theme calendar in 1997, and this is a firework calendar.</s>
  <s id="105.2">So, you launch the number into space, because the Japanese believe that when you see fireworks, you're cooler for some reason.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="106">This is why they have fireworks in the summer.</s>
 <s id="107">A very extreme culture.</s>
 <s id="108">Lastly, this is a fall-based calendar, because I have so many leaves in my yard.</s>
 <s id="109">So this is the leaves in my yard, essentially.</s>
 <s id="110">And so I made a lot of these types of things.</s>
 <s id="111">I've been lucky to have been there before people made these kind of things, and so I made all this kind of stuff that messes with your eyes.</s>
 <s id="112">I feel kind of bad about that.</s>
 <p id="p113">
  <s id="113.1">Tomorrow, Paola Antonelli is speaking.</s>
  <s id="113.2">I love Paola.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="114">She has this show right now at MoMA, where some of these early works are here on display at MoMA, on the walls.</s>
 <s id="115">If you're in New York, please go and see that.</s>
 <s id="116">But I've had a problem, because I make all this flying stuff and people say, "Oh, I know your work.</s>
 <s id="117">You're the guy that makes eye candy."</s>
 <s id="118">And when you're told this, you feel kind of weird.</s>
 <s id="119">"Eye candy" -- sort of pejorative, don't you think?</s>
 <s id="120">So, I say, "No, I make eye meat," instead.</s>
 <p id="p121">
  <s id="121.1">(Laughter) And eye meat is something different, something more fibrous, something more powerful, perhaps.</s>
  <s id="121.2">But what could that be, eye meat?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="122">I've been interested in computer programs all my life, actually.</s>
 <s id="123">Computer programs are essentially trees, and when you make art with a computer program, there's kind of a problem.</s>
 <s id="124">Whenever you make art with a computer program, you're always on the tree, and the paradox is that for excellent art, you want to be off the tree.</s>
 <s id="125">So, this is sort of a complication I've found.</s>
 <s id="126">So, to get off the tree, I began to use my old computers.</s>
 <s id="127">I took these to Tokyo in 2001 to make computer objects.</s>
 <s id="128">This is a new way to type, on my old, color Classic.</s>
 <s id="129">You can't type very much on this.</s>
 <s id="130">I also discovered that an IR mouse responds to CRT emissions and starts to move by itself, so this is a self-drawing machine.</s>
 <s id="131">And also, one year, the G3 Bondi Blue thing -- that caddy would come out, like, dangerous, like, "whack," like that.</s>
 <p id="p132">
  <s id="132.1">But I thought, "This is very interesting.</s>
  <s id="132.2">What if I make like a car crash test?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="133">So I have a crash test.</s>
 <p id="p134">
  <s id="134.1">(Laughter) And sort of measure the impact.</s>
  <s id="134.2">Stuff like this are things I made, just to sort of understand what these things are.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="135">(Laughter) Shortly after this, 9/11 happened, and I was very depressed.</s>
 <s id="136">I was concerned with contemporary art that was all about piss, and sort of really sad things, and so I wanted to think about something happy.</s>
 <s id="137">So I focused on food as my area -- these sort of clementine peel things.</s>
 <p id="p138">
  <s id="138.1">In Japan, it's a wonderful thing to remove the clementine peel just in one piece.</s>
  <s id="138.2">Who's done that before?</s>
  <s id="138.3">One-piece clementine?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="139">Oh, you guys are missing out, if you haven't done it yet.</s>
 <s id="140">It was very good, and I discovered I can make sculptures out of this, actually, in different forms.</s>
 <s id="141">If you dry them quick, you can make, like, elephants and steers and stuff, and my wife didn't like these, because they mold, so I had to stop that.</s>
 <p id="p142">
  <s id="142.1">So, I went back to the computer, and I bought five large fries, and scanned them all.</s>
  <s id="142.2">And I was looking for some kind of food theme, and I wrote some software to automatically lay out french-fry images.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="143">And as a child, I'd hear that song, you know, "Oh, beautiful, for spacious skies, for amber waves of grain," so I made this amber waves image.</s>
 <s id="144">It's sort of a Midwest cornfield out of french fries.</s>
 <p id="p145">
  <s id="145.1">And also, as a child, I was the fattest kid in class, so I used to love Cheetos.</s>
  <s id="145.2">Oh, I love Cheetos, yummy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="146">So, I wanted to play with Cheetos in some way.</s>
 <p id="p147">
  <s id="147.1">I wasn't sure where to go with this.</s>
  <s id="147.2">I invented Cheeto paint.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="148">Cheeto paint is a very simple way to paint with Cheetos.</s>
 <s id="149">(Laughter) I discovered that Cheetos are good, expressive material.</s>
 <s id="150">And with these Cheetos, I began to think, "What can I make with these Cheetos?"</s>
 <s id="151">And so, I began to crinkle up potato chip flecks, and also pretzels.</s>
 <p id="p152">
  <s id="152.1">I was looking for some kind of form, and in the end, I made 100 butter-fries.</s>
  <s id="152.2">Do you get it?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="153">(Laughter) And each butter-fry is composed of different pieces.</s>
 <s id="154">People ask me how they make the antenna.</s>
 <p id="p155">
  <s id="155.1">Sometimes, they find a hair in the food.</s>
  <s id="155.2">That's my hair.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="156">My hair's clean -- it's okay.</s>
 <s id="157">I'm a tenured professor, which means, basically, I don't have to work anymore.</s>
 <p id="p158">
  <s id="158.1">It's a strange business model.</s>
  <s id="158.2">I can come into work everyday and staple five pieces of paper and just stare at it with my latte.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="159">End of story.</s>
 <s id="160">(Laughter) But I realized that life could be very boring, so I've been thinking about life, and I notice that my camera -- my digital camera versus my car, a very strange thing.</s>
 <s id="161">The car is so big, the camera is so small, yet the manual for the camera is so much bigger than the car manual.</s>
 <s id="162">It doesn't make any sense.</s>
 <s id="163">(Laughter) So, I was in the Cape one time, and I typed the word "simplicity," and I discovered, in this weird, M. Night Shyamalan way, that I discovered [the] letters, M, I, T. You know the word?</s>
 <s id="164">In the words "simplicity" and "complexity," M, I, T occur in perfect sequence.</s>
 <s id="165">It's a bit eerie, isn't it?</s>
 <s id="166">So, I thought, maybe I'll do this for the next twenty years or something.</s>
 <s id="167">And I wrote this book, "The Laws of Simplicity."</s>
 <p id="p168">
  <s id="168.1">It's a very short, simple book.</s>
  <s id="168.2">There are ten laws and three keys.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="169">The ten laws and three keys -- I won't go over them because that's why I have a book, and also that's why it's on the Web for free.</s>
 <s id="170">But the laws are kind of like sushi in a way: there are all kinds.</s>
 <s id="171">In Japan, they say that sushi is challenging.</s>
 <s id="172">You know the uni is the most challenging, so number ten is challenging.</s>
 <s id="173">People hate number ten like they hate uni, actually.</s>
 <s id="174">The three keys are easy to eat, so this is anago, cooked already, so easy to eat.</s>
 <s id="175">So enjoy your sushi meal later, with the laws of simplicity.</s>
 <s id="176">Because I want to simplify them for you.</s>
 <p id="p177">
  <s id="177.1">Because that's what this is about.</s>
  <s id="177.2">I have to simplify this thing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="178">So, if I simplify the laws of simplicity, I have what's called the cookie versus laundry thing.</s>
 <p id="p179">
  <s id="179.1">Anyone who has kids knows that if you offer a kid a big cookie or a small cookie, which cookie are they going to take?</s>
  <s id="179.2">The big cookie.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p180">
  <s id="180.1">You can say the small cookie has Godiva chocolate bits in it, but it doesn't work.</s>
  <s id="180.2">They want the big cookie.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="181">But if you offer kids two piles of laundry to fold, the small pile or the big pile, which will they choose?</s>
 <p id="p182">
  <s id="182.1">Strangely, not the big pile.</s>
  <s id="182.2">So, I think it's as simple as this.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="183">You know, when you want more, it's because you want to enjoy it.</s>
 <s id="184">When you want less, it's because it's about work.</s>
 <s id="185">And so, to boil it all down, simplicity is about living life with more enjoyment and less pain.</s>
 <s id="186">I think this is sort of simple more versus less.</s>
 <s id="187">Basically, it always depends.</s>
 <s id="188">This book I wrote because I want to figure out life.</s>
 <p id="p189">
  <s id="189.1">I love life.</s>
  <s id="189.2">I love being alive.</s>
  <s id="189.3">I like to see things.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="190">And so life is a big question, I think, in simplicity, because you're trying to simplify your life.</s>
 <p id="p191">
  <s id="191.1">And I just love to see the world.</s>
  <s id="191.2">The world is an amazing place.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="192">By being at TED, we see so many things at one time.</s>
 <s id="193">And I can't help but enjoy looking at everything in the world.</s>
 <s id="194">Like everything you see, every time you wake up.</s>
 <s id="195">It's such a joy to sort of experience everything in the world.</s>
 <s id="196">From everything from a weird hotel lobby, to Saran wrap placed over your window, to this moment where I had my road in front of my house paved dark black, and this white moth was sitting there dying in the sun.</s>
 <s id="197">And so, this whole thing has struck me as exciting to be here, because life is finite.</s>
 <s id="198">This was given to me by the chairman of Shiseido.</s>
 <p id="p199">
  <s id="199.1">He's an expert in aging.</s>
  <s id="199.2">This horizontal axis is how old you are -- twelve years old, twenty-four years old, seventy-four, ninety-six years old -- and this is some medical data.</s>
  <s id="199.3">So, brain strength increases up to 60, and then after 60, it sort of goes down.</s>
  <s id="199.4">Kind of depressing in a way.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="200">Also, if you look at your physical strength.</s>
 <s id="201">You know, I have a lot of cocky freshmen at MIT, so I tell them, "Oh, your bodies are really getting stronger and stronger, but in your late twenties and mid-thirties, cells, they die."</s>
 <p id="p202">
  <s id="202.1">OK.</s>
  <s id="202.2">It gets them to work harder, sometimes.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="203">And if you have your vision, vision is interesting.</s>
 <s id="204">As you age from infant age, your vision gets better, and maybe in your late teens, early twenties, you're looking for a mate, and your vision goes after that.</s>
 <s id="205">(Laughter) Your social responsibility is very interesting.</s>
 <s id="206">So, as you get older, you may, like, have kids, whatever.</s>
 <s id="207">And then the kids graduate, and you have no responsibility any more -- that's very good, too.</s>
 <p id="p208">
  <s id="208.1">But if any of you people ask, "What actually goes up?</s>
  <s id="208.2">Does anything go up?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p209">
  <s id="209.1">What's the positive part of this, you know?"</s>
  <s id="209.2">I think wisdom always goes up.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="210">I love these eighty-year-old, ninety-year-old guys and women.</s>
 <s id="211">They have so many thoughts, and they have so much wisdom, and I think -- you know, this TED thing, I've come here.</s>
 <s id="212">And this is the fourth time, and I come here for this wisdom, I think.</s>
 <s id="213">This whole TED effect, it sort of ups your wisdom, somehow.</s>
 <s id="214">And I'm so glad to be here, and I'm very grateful to be here, Chris.</s>
 <s id="215">And this is an amazing experience for me as well.</s>
</text>
