<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Thirteen years ago, we set ourselves a goal to end poverty.</s>
 <s id="2">After some success, we've hit a big hurdle.</s>
 <s id="3">The aftermath of the financial crisis has begun to hit aid payments, which have fallen for two consecutive years.</s>
 <s id="4">My question is whether the lessons learned from saving the financial system can be used to help us overcome that hurdle and help millions.</s>
 <s id="5">Can we simply print money for aid?</s>
 <s id="6">"Surely not."</s>
 <s id="7">It's a common reaction.</s>
 <s id="8">(Laughter) It's a quick talk.</s>
 <s id="9">Others channel John McEnroe.</s>
 <s id="10">"You cannot be serious!"</s>
 <s id="11">Now, I can't do the accent, but I am serious, thanks to these two children, who, as you'll learn, are very much at the heart of my talk.</s>
 <s id="12">On the left, we have Pia.</s>
 <s id="13">She lives in England.</s>
 <s id="14">She has two loving parents, one of whom is standing right here.</s>
 <s id="15">Dorothy, on the right, lives in rural Kenya.</s>
 <s id="16">She's one of 13,000 orphans and vulnerable children who are assisted by a charity that I support.</s>
 <s id="17">I do that because I believe that Dorothy, like Pia, deserves the best life chances that we can afford to give her.</s>
 <s id="18">You'll all agree with me, I'm sure.</s>
 <s id="19">The U.N. agrees too.</s>
 <s id="20">Their overriding aim for international aid is to strive for a life of dignity for all.</s>
 <s id="21">But -- and here's that hurdle -- can we afford our aid aspirations?</s>
 <s id="22">History suggests not.</s>
 <s id="23">In 1970, governments set themselves a target to increase overseas aid payments to 0.7 percent of their national income.</s>
 <s id="24">As you can see, a big gap opens up between actual aid and that target.</s>
 <s id="25">But then come the Millennium Development Goals, eight ambitious targets to be met by 2015.</s>
 <s id="26">If I tell you that just one of those targets is to eradicate extreme hunger and poverty, you get a sense of the ambition.</s>
 <s id="27">There's also been some success.</s>
 <s id="28">The number of people living on less than $1.25 a day has halved.</s>
 <s id="29">But a lot remains to be done in two years.</s>
 <s id="30">One in eight remain hungry.</s>
 <s id="31">In the context of this auditorium, the front two rows aren't going to get any food.</s>
 <s id="32">We can't settle for that, which is why the concern about the eighth goal, which relates to funding, which I said at the beginning is falling, is so troubling.</s>
 <s id="33">So what can be done?</s>
 <s id="34">Well, I work in financial markets, not development.</s>
 <s id="35">I study the behavior of investors, how they react to policy and the economy.</s>
 <s id="36">It gives me a different angle on the aid issue.</s>
 <s id="37">But it took an innocent question from my then-four-year-old daughter to make me appreciate that.</s>
 <s id="38">Pia and I were on the way to a local cafe and we passed a man collecting for charity.</s>
 <s id="39">I didn't have any change to give him, and she was disappointed.</s>
 <s id="40">Once in the cafe, Pia takes out her coloring book and starts scribbling.</s>
 <s id="41">After a little while, I ask her what she's doing, and she shows me a drawing of a £5 note to give to the man outside.</s>
 <s id="42">It's so sweet, and more generous than Dad would have been.</s>
 <s id="43">But of course I explained to her, "You can't do that; it's not allowed."</s>
 <s id="44">To which I get the classic four-year-old response: "Why not?"</s>
 <s id="45">Now I'm excited, because I actually think I can answer this time.</s>
 <s id="46">So I launch into an explanation of how an unlimited supply of money chasing a limited number of goods sends prices to the moon.</s>
 <s id="47">Something about that exchange stuck with me, not because of the look of relief on Pia's face when I finally finished, but because it related to the sanctity of the money supply, a sanctity that had been challenged and questioned by the reaction of central banks to the financial crisis.</s>
 <s id="48">To reassure investors, central banks began buying assets to try and encourage investors to do the same.</s>
 <s id="49">They funded these purchases with money they created themselves.</s>
 <s id="50">The money wasn't actually physically printed.</s>
 <s id="51">It's still sort of locked away in the banking system today.</s>
 <s id="52">But the amount created was unprecedented.</s>
 <s id="53">Together, the central banks of the U.S., U.K and Japan increased the stock of money in their economies by 3.7 trillion dollars.</s>
 <s id="54">That's three times, in fact that's more than three times, the total physical stock of dollar notes in circulation.</s>
 <s id="55">Three times!</s>
 <s id="56">Before the crisis, this would have been utterly unthinkable, yet it was accepted remarkably quickly.</s>
 <s id="57">The price of gold, an asset thought to protect against inflation, did jump, but investors bought other assets that offered little protection from inflation.</s>
 <s id="58">They bought fixed income securities, bonds.</s>
 <s id="59">They bought equities too.</s>
 <s id="60">For all the scare stories, the actual actions of investors spoke of rapid acceptance and confidence.</s>
 <s id="61">That confidence was based on two pillars.</s>
 <s id="62">The first was that, after years of keeping inflation under control, central banks were trusted to take the money-printing away if inflation became a threat.</s>
 <s id="63">Secondly, inflation simply never became a threat.</s>
 <s id="64">As you can see, in the United States, inflation for most of this period remained below average.</s>
 <s id="65">It was the same elsewhere.</s>
 <s id="66">So how does all this relate to aid?</s>
 <s id="67">Well, this is where Dorothy and the Mango Tree charity that supports her comes in.</s>
 <s id="68">I was at one of their fundraising events earlier this year, and I was inspired to give a one-off donation when I remembered that my firm offers to match the charitable contributions its employees make.</s>
 <s id="69">So think of this: Instead of just being able to help Dorothy and four of her classmates to go through secondary school for a few years, I was able to double my contribution.</s>
 <s id="70">Brilliant.</s>
 <s id="71">So following that conversation with my daughter, and seeing the absence of inflation in the face of money-printing, and knowing that international aid payments were falling at just the wrong time, this made me wonder: Could we match but just on a much grander scale?</s>
 <s id="72">Let's call this scheme "Print Aid."</s>
 <s id="73">And here's how it might work.</s>
 <s id="74">Provided it saw little inflation risk from doing so, the central bank would be mandated to match the government's overseas aid payments up to a certain limit.</s>
 <s id="75">Governments have been aiming to get aid to 0.7 percent for years, so let's set the limit at half of that, 0.35 percent of their income.</s>
 <s id="76">So it would work like this: If in a given year the government gave 0.2 percent of its income to overseas aid, the central bank would simply top it up with a further 0.2 percent.</s>
 <s id="77">So far so good.</s>
 <s id="78">How risky is this?</s>
 <s id="79">Well, this involves the creation of money to buy goods, not assets.</s>
 <s id="80">It sounds more inflationary already, doesn't it.</s>
 <s id="81">But there are two important mitigating factors here.</s>
 <s id="82">The first is that by definition, this money printed would be spent overseas.</s>
 <s id="83">So it's not obvious how it leads to inflation in the country doing the actual printing unless it leads to a currency depreciation of that country.</s>
 <s id="84">That is unlikely for the second reason: the scale of the money that would be printed under this scheme.</s>
 <s id="85">So let's think of an example where Print Aid was in place in the U.S., U.K. and Japan.</s>
 <s id="86">To match the aid payments made by those governments over the last four years, Print Aid would have generated 200 billion dollars' worth of extra aid.</s>
 <s id="87">What would that look like in the context of the increase in the money stock that had already happened in those countries to save the financial system?</s>
 <s id="88">Are you read for this?</s>
 <s id="89">You might struggle to see that at the back, because the gap is quite small.</s>
 <s id="90">So what we're saying here is that we took a $3.7 trillion gamble to save our financial systems, and you know what, it paid off.</s>
 <s id="91">There was no inflation.</s>
 <s id="92">Are we really saying that it's not worth the risk to print an extra 200 billion for aid?</s>
 <s id="93">Would the risks really be that different?</s>
 <s id="94">To me, it's not that clear.</s>
 <s id="95">What is clear is the impact on aid.</s>
 <s id="96">Even though this is the printing of just three central banks, the global aid that's given over this period is up by almost 40 percent.</s>
 <s id="97">Aid as a proportion of national income all of a sudden is at a 40-year high.</s>
 <s id="98">Now, we don't get to 0.7 percent.</s>
 <s id="99">Governments are still incentivized to give.</s>
 <s id="100">But you know what, that's the point of a matching scheme.</s>
 <s id="101">So I think what we've learned is that the risks from this money creation scheme are quite modest, but the benefits are potentially huge.</s>
 <s id="102">Imagine what we could do with 40 percent more funding.</s>
 <s id="103">We might be able to feed the front row.</s>
 <s id="104">The thing that I fear, the only thing that I fear, apart from the fact that I've run out of time, is that the window of opportunity for this idea is a short one.</s>
 <s id="105">Today, money creation by central banks is an accepted policy tool.</s>
 <s id="106">That may not always be the case.</s>
 <s id="107">Today there are universally agreed aims for international aid.</s>
 <s id="108">That may not always be the case.</s>
 <s id="109">Today might be the only time that these two things coincide, such that we can afford the aid that we've always aspired to give.</s>
 <s id="110">So, can we print money for international aid?</s>
 <s id="111">I seriously believe the question should be, why not?</s>
 <s id="112">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="113">(Applause)</s>
</text>
