<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Hi, my name is Marcin -- farmer, technologist.</s>
 <s id="2">I was born in Poland, now in the U.S.</s>
 <s id="3">I started a group called Open Source Ecology.</s>
 <s id="4">We've identified the 50 most important machines that we think it takes for modern life to exist -- things from tractors, bread ovens, circuit makers.</s>
 <s id="5">Then we set out to create an open source, DIY, do it yourself version that anyone can build and maintain at a fraction of the cost.</s>
 <s id="6">We call this the Global Village Construction Set.</s>
 <s id="7">So let me tell you a story.</s>
 <s id="8">So I finished my 20s with a Ph.D. in fusion energy, and I discovered I was useless.</s>
 <s id="9">I had no practical skills.</s>
 <s id="10">The world presented me with options, and I took them.</s>
 <s id="11">I guess you can call it the consumer lifestyle.</s>
 <s id="12">So I started a farm in Missouri and learned about the economics of farming.</s>
 <s id="13">I bought a tractor -- then it broke.</s>
 <s id="14">I paid to get it repaired -- then it broke again.</s>
 <s id="15">Then pretty soon, I was broke too.</s>
 <s id="16">I realized that the truly appropriate, low-cost tools that I needed to start a sustainable farm and settlement just didn't exist yet.</s>
 <s id="17">I needed tools that were robust, modular, highly efficient and optimized, low-cost, made from local and recycled materials that would last a lifetime, not designed for obsolescence.</s>
 <s id="18">I found that I would have to build them myself.</s>
 <s id="19">So I did just that.</s>
 <s id="20">And I tested them.</s>
 <s id="21">And I found that industrial productivity can be achieved on a small scale.</s>
 <s id="22">So then I published the 3D designs, schematics, instructional videos and budgets on a wiki.</s>
 <s id="23">Then contributors from all over the world began showing up, prototyping new machines during dedicated project visits.</s>
 <s id="24">So far, we have prototyped eight of the 50 machines.</s>
 <s id="25">And now the project is beginning to grow on its own.</s>
 <s id="26">We know that open source has succeeded with tools for managing knowledge and creativity.</s>
 <s id="27">And the same is starting to happen with hardware too.</s>
 <s id="28">We're focusing on hardware because it is hardware that can change people's lives in such tangible material ways.</s>
 <s id="29">If we can lower the barriers to farming, building, manufacturing, then we can unleash just massive amounts of human potential.</s>
 <s id="30">That's not only in the developing world.</s>
 <s id="31">Our tools are being made for the American farmer, builder, entrepreneur, maker.</s>
 <s id="32">We've seen lots of excitement from these people, who can now start a construction business, parts manufacturing, organic CSA or just selling power back to the grid.</s>
 <s id="33">Our goal is a repository of published designs so clear, so complete, that a single burned DVD is effectively a civilization starter kit.</s>
 <s id="34">I've planted a hundred trees in a day.</s>
 <s id="35">I've pressed 5,000 bricks in one day from the dirt beneath my feet and built a tractor in six days.</s>
 <s id="36">From what I've seen, this is only the beginning.</s>
 <s id="37">If this idea is truly sound, then the implications are significant.</s>
 <s id="38">A greater distribution of the means of production, environmentally sound supply chains, and a newly relevant DIY maker culture can hope to transcend artificial scarcity.</s>
 <s id="39">We're exploring the limits of what we all can do to make a better world with open hardware technology.</s>
 <s id="40">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="41">(Applause)</s>
</text>
