<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">You don't really look at a toothbrush and say, "I'm great!"</s>
 <s id="2">But when you look at an Afro pick, which is a grooming tool, it can remind you in your subconscious to, like, really be proud and, like, "All right."</s>
 <p id="p3">
  <s id="3.1">[Small thing.]</s>
  <s id="3.2">[Big idea.]</s>
  <s id="3.3">An Afro pick is a utilitarian tool used to maintain the Afro hairstyle.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="4">I think the Afro pick was designed for the ergonomics of creating something that felt like you were running fingers through your hair.</s>
 <s id="5">The shape, even the depth that it goes in -- it's like a hand.</s>
 <s id="6">You have plastic or nylon teeth, and then you have the stainless steel or the nickel teeth.</s>
 <s id="7">I always prefer the metal tooth just 'cause I like the sound and the ones I know have the black power fist on the handle.</s>
 <s id="8">When I think of black hair in America, I think of something that's been policed.</s>
 <s id="9">Back in the days, it was expected for black people to chemically treat their hair.</s>
 <s id="10">Whether that's healthy for them is a secondary thing to blending in.</s>
 <s id="11">In the 50s, dancer Ruth Beckford and a lot of jazz singers were tired of straightening their hair, so they said, all right, we're going to just let it grow naturally and started rocking natural, close-cropped hair.</s>
 <s id="12">And in the 60s, that style evolved with the formation of the Afro, which was the cropped hair, natural, picked out into a more spherical shape.</s>
 <s id="13">You had civil rights leaders, activists, that adopted the hairstyle as a means of rebellion and black pride.</s>
 <s id="14">And then you had musicians like James Brown, who was infamously known for chemically straightening his hair, reject that and go natural.</s>
 <s id="15">It went hand-in-hand with his music, so he had songs like "Say it Loud, I'm Black and I'm Proud."</s>
 <s id="16">The black is beautiful movement is just rejecting the notion that to be black or to have darker skin, to have a curlier grade of hair, was something to be ashamed of.</s>
 <s id="17">I have one of my favorite pictures of my mother and my grandmother, and my grandmother had a small 'fro, and that was in the 60s.</s>
 <s id="18">African hair combs date back to 3500 BCE.</s>
 <s id="19">The oldest African combs are found in ancient Egypt and Sudan, so they were making pyramids and combs.</s>
 <s id="20">The way the ancient African combs were embellished represented status or tribal affiliation.</s>
 <s id="21">It's no coincidence that the fist on the modern Afro pick also sets the tone for affiliation and what set you claim.</s>
 <s id="22">And then there's the Black Power movement.</s>
 <s id="23">Most movements need their icons, right?</s>
 <s id="24">You have the fist, you have the 'fro.</s>
 <s id="25">These things coincide with the Black Panther aesthetic, where you could kind of spot your tribe from afar, because you're not just keeping a pick in, like, your beauty kit.</s>
 <s id="26">It's in your back pocket, purposely with the first outside of it, and in your hair, you'll rock it in your 'fro.</s>
 <s id="27">If I think about iconic Afros, I definitely think about Angela Davis.</s>
 <s id="28">Her 'fro personifies elegance, style, freedom, rebellion.</s>
 <s id="29">You feel all of these feelings at once when you see Angela Davis fighting for her life in federal court.</s>
 <s id="30">By the 80s, the Afro style became less radical.</s>
 <s id="31">The Afro picks are still produced to this day with the clenched fist, so it's the remnants of the movement in the everyday object.</s>
 <s id="32">When I was young, it was just, like, another object.</s>
 <s id="33">It was a comb.</s>
 <s id="34">But as I became more enlightened to really understand the roots and the origin and the intentionality of the design and why the fist and all of these things ...</s>
 <s id="35">I woke up.</s>
</text>
