<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">On a cold winter night in 1916, Felix Yusupov anxiously prepared to pick up his dinner guest.</s>
 <s id="2">If all went as planned, his guest would be dead by morning, though four others had already tried and failed to finish him off.</s>
 <s id="3">The Russian monarchy was on the brink of collapse, and to Yusupov and his fellow aristocrats, the holy man they’d invited to dinner was the single cause of it all.</s>
 <s id="4">But who was he, and how could a single monk be to blame for the fate of an empire?</s>
 <s id="5">Grigori Yefimovich Rasputin began his life in Siberia, born in 1869 to a peasant family.</s>
 <s id="6">He might have lived a life of obscurity in his small village, if not for his conversion to the Russian Orthodox Church in the 1890s.</s>
 <s id="7">Inspired by the humbled monks that wandered endlessly from holy site to holy site, he spent years on pilgrimages across Russia.</s>
 <s id="8">On his travels, strangers were captivated by Rasputin’s magnetic presence.</s>
 <s id="9">Some even believed he had mystical gifts of prediction and healing.</s>
 <s id="10">Despite Rasputin’s heavy drinking, petty theft, and promiscuity, his reputation as a monk quickly spread beyond Siberia and attracted both laypeople and powerful Orthodox clergymen.</s>
 <s id="11">When he finally reached the capital, St. Petersburg, Rasputin used his charisma and connections to win favor with the imperial family’s spiritual advisor.</s>
 <s id="12">In November 1905, Rasputin was finally introduced to Russian Tsar Nicholas II.</s>
 <s id="13">Nicholas and his wife Alexandra devoutly believed in the Orthodox Church, as well as in mysticism and supernatural powers, and this Siberian holy man had them transfixed.</s>
 <s id="14">It was a particularly tumultuous period for Russia and their family.</s>
 <s id="15">The monarchy was barely clinging to control after the Revolution of 1905.</s>
 <s id="16">Their political struggles were only intensified by personal turmoil: Alexei, the heir to the throne, had a life-threatening blood disease called hemophilia.</s>
 <s id="17">When Alexei suffered a severe medical crisis in 1912, Rasputin advised his parents to reject treatment from doctors.</s>
 <s id="18">Alexei’s health improved, cementing the royal family’s belief that Rasputin had magical healing powers, and guaranteeing his privileged place on the royal court.</s>
 <s id="19">Today, we know that the doctors had prescribed aspirin, a drug that worsens hemophilia.</s>
 <s id="20">After this incident, Rasputin made a prophecy: if he died, or the royal family deserted him, both their son and their crown would soon be gone.</s>
 <s id="21">Outside the royal family, people had mixed views on Rasputin.</s>
 <s id="22">On one hand, peasants regarded him as one of their own, amplifying their often-unheard voice to the monarchy.</s>
 <s id="23">But nobles and clergymen came to despise his presence.</s>
 <s id="24">Rasputin never ceased his scandalous behavior, and they were skeptical of his so-called powers and thought he was corrupting the royal family.</s>
 <s id="25">By the end of World War I, they were convinced the only way to maintain order was to eliminate this sham of a holy man.</s>
 <s id="26">With this conviction, Yusupov began to plot Rasputin’s assassination.</s>
 <s id="27">Though the exact details remain mysterious, our best guess at how it all unfolded comes from Yusupov’s memoirs.</s>
 <s id="28">He served Rasputin a number of pastries, believing they contained cyanide.</s>
 <s id="29">But unbeknownst to Yusupov, one of his co-conspirators had a change of heart, and substituted the poison with a harmless substance.</s>
 <s id="30">To Yusupov’s shock, Rasputin ate them without ill effect.</s>
 <s id="31">In desperation, he shot Rasputin at point-blank range.</s>
 <s id="32">But Rasputin recovered, punched his attacker, and fled.</s>
 <s id="33">Yusupov and his accomplices pursued him, finally killing Rasputin with a bullet to the forehead and dumping his body in the Malaya Nevka river.</s>
 <s id="34">But far from stabilizing the monarchy’s authority, Rasputin’s death enraged the peasantry.</s>
 <s id="35">Just as Rasputin prophesied, his murder was swiftly followed by that of the royal family.</s>
 <s id="36">Whether the downfall of the Russian monarchy was a product of the monk’s curse, or the result of political tensions decades in the making, well, we may never know.</s>
</text>
