<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The year was 1776.</s>
 <s id="2">In Bavaria, new ideals of rationalism, religious freedom, and universal human rights competed with the Catholic church’s heavy influence over public affairs.</s>
 <s id="3">Across the Atlantic, a new nation staked its claim for independence on the basis of these ideas.</s>
 <s id="4">But back in Bavaria, law professor Adam Weishaupt’s attempts to teach secular philosophy continued to be frustrated.</s>
 <s id="5">Weishaupt decided to spread his ideas through a secret society that would shine a light on the shortcomings of the Church’s ideology.</s>
 <s id="6">He called his secret society the Illuminati.</s>
 <s id="7">Weishaupt modelled aspects of his secret society off a group called the Freemasons.</s>
 <s id="8">Originally an elite stoneworkers’ guild in the late Middle Ages, the Freemasons had gone from passing down the craft of masonry to more generally promoting ideals of knowledge and reason.</s>
 <s id="9">Over time, they had grown into a semi-secret, exclusive order that included many wealthy and influential individuals, with elaborate, secret initiation rituals.</s>
 <s id="10">Weishaupt created his parallel society while also joining the Freemasons and recruiting from their ranks.</s>
 <s id="11">He adopted the code name Spartacus for himself, after the famed leader of the Roman slave revolt.</s>
 <s id="12">Early members became the Illuminati’s ruling council, or Areopagus.</s>
 <s id="13">One of these members, Baron Adolph Knigge, was also a freemason, and became an influential recruiter.</s>
 <s id="14">With Knigge’s help, the Illuminati expanded their numbers, gained influence within several Masonic chapters, and incorporated Masonic rituals.</s>
 <s id="15">By 1784, there were over 600 members, including influential scholars and politicians.</s>
 <s id="16">As the Illuminati gained members, the American Revolution also gained momentum.</s>
 <s id="17">Thomas Jefferson would later cite Weishaupt as an inspiration.</s>
 <s id="18">European monarchs and clergy were fearful of similar revolts on their home soil.</s>
 <s id="19">Meanwhile, the existence of the Illuminati had become an open secret.</s>
 <s id="20">Both the Illuminati and the Freemasons drew exclusively from society’s wealthy elite, which meant they were constantly rubbing shoulders with members of the religious and political establishment.</s>
 <s id="21">Many in the government and church believed that both groups were determined to undermine the people’s religious faith.</s>
 <s id="22">But these groups didn’t necessarily oppose religion— they just believed it should be kept separate from governance.</s>
 <s id="23">Still, the suspicious Bavarian government started keeping records of alleged members of the Illuminati.</s>
 <s id="24">Just as Illuminati members begun to secure important positions in local governments and universities, a 1784 decree by Duke Karl Theodor of Bavaria banned all secret societies.</s>
 <s id="25">While a public ban on something ostensibly secret might seem difficult to enforce, in this case it worked.</s>
 <s id="26">Only nine years after its founding, the group dissolved, their records were seized, and Weishaupt forced into exile.</s>
 <s id="27">The Illuminati would become more notorious in their afterlife than they had ever been in their brief existence.</s>
 <s id="28">A decade later, in the aftermath of the French Revolution, conservative authors claimed the Illuminati had survived their banishment and orchestrated the overthrow of the monarchy.</s>
 <s id="29">In the United States, preacher Jedidiah Morse promoted similar ideas of an Illuminati conspiracy against the government.</s>
 <s id="30">But though the idea of a secret group orchestrating political upheaval is still alive and well today, there is no evidence that the Illuminati survived, reformed, or went underground.</s>
 <s id="31">Their brief tenure is well-documented in Bavarian government records, the still-active Freemasons’s records, and particularly the overlap between these two sources, without a whisper since.</s>
 <s id="32">In the spirit of rationalism the Illuminati embraced, one must conclude they no longer exist.</s>
 <s id="33">But the ideas that spurred Weishaupt to found the illuminati still spread, becoming the basis for many Western governments today.</s>
 <s id="34">These ideas didn’t start or end with the Illuminati— instead, it was one community that represented a wave of change that was already underway when it was founded and continued long after it ended.</s>
</text>
