<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">A few months ago we posed a challenge to our community.</s>
 <s id="2">We asked everyone: given a range of integers from 0 to 100, guess the whole number closest to 2/3 of the average of all numbers guessed.</s>
 <s id="3">So if the average of all guesses is 60, the correct guess will be 40.</s>
 <s id="4">What number do you think was the correct guess at 2/3 of the average?</s>
 <s id="5">Let’s see if we can try and reason our way to the answer.</s>
 <s id="6">This game is played under conditions known to game theorists as common knowledge.</s>
 <s id="7">Not only does every player have the same information — they also know that everyone else does, and that everyone else knows that everyone else does, and so on, infinitely.</s>
 <s id="8">Now, the highest possible average would occur if every person guessed 100.</s>
 <s id="9">In that case, 2/3 of the average would be 66.66.</s>
 <s id="10">Since everyone can figure this out, it wouldn’t make sense to guess anything higher than 67.</s>
 <s id="11">If everyone playing comes to this same conclusion, no one will guess higher than 67.</s>
 <s id="12">Now 67 is the new highest possible average, so no reasonable guess should be higher than ⅔ of that, which is 44.</s>
 <s id="13">This logic can be extended further and further.</s>
 <s id="14">With each step, the highest possible logical answer keeps getting smaller.</s>
 <s id="15">So it would seem sensible to guess the lowest number possible.</s>
 <s id="16">And indeed, if everyone chose zero, the game would reach what’s known as a Nash Equilibrium.</s>
 <s id="17">This is a state where every player has chosen the best possible strategy for themselves given everyone else playing, and no individual player can benefit by choosing differently.</s>
 <s id="18">But, that’s not what happens in the real world.</s>
 <s id="19">People, as it turns out, either aren’t perfectly rational, or don’t expect each other to be perfectly rational.</s>
 <s id="20">Or, perhaps, it’s some combination of the two.</s>
 <s id="21">When this game is played in real-world settings, the average tends to be somewhere between 20 and 35.</s>
 <s id="22">Danish newspaper Politiken ran the game with over 19,000 readers participating, resulting in an average of roughly 22, making the correct answer 14.</s>
 <s id="23">For our audience, the average was 31.3.</s>
 <s id="24">So if you guessed 21 as 2/3 of the average, well done.</s>
 <s id="25">Economic game theorists have a way of modeling this interplay between rationality and practicality called k-level reasoning.</s>
 <s id="26">K stands for the number of times a cycle of reasoning is repeated.</s>
 <s id="27">A person playing at k-level 0 would approach our game naively, guessing a number at random without thinking about the other players.</s>
 <s id="28">At k-level 1, a player would assume everyone else was playing at level 0, resulting in an average of 50, and thus guess 33.</s>
 <s id="29">At k-level 2, they’d assume that everyone else was playing at level 1, leading them to guess 22.</s>
 <s id="30">It would take 12 k-levels to reach 0.</s>
 <s id="31">The evidence suggests that most people stop at 1 or 2 k-levels.</s>
 <s id="32">And that’s useful to know, because k-level thinking comes into play in high-stakes situations.</s>
 <s id="33">For example, stock traders evaluate stocks not only based on earnings reports, but also on the value that others place on those numbers.</s>
 <s id="34">And during penalty kicks in soccer, both the shooter and the goalie decide whether to go right or left based on what they think the other person is thinking.</s>
 <s id="35">Goalies often memorize the patterns of their opponents ahead of time, but penalty shooters know that and can plan accordingly.</s>
 <s id="36">In each case, participants must weigh their own understanding of the best course of action against how well they think other participants understand the situation.</s>
 <s id="37">But 1 or 2 k-levels is by no means a hard and fast rule— simply being conscious of this tendency can make people adjust their expectations.</s>
 <s id="38">For instance, what would happen if people played the 2/3 game after understanding the difference between the most logical approach and the most common?</s>
 <s id="39">Submit your own guess at what 2/3 of the new average will be by using the form below, and we’ll find out.</s>
</text>
