<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Let's say that it would take you ten minutes to solve this puzzle.</s>
 <s id="2">How long would it take if you received constant electric shocks to your hands?</s>
 <s id="3">Longer, right?</s>
 <s id="4">Because the pain would distract you from the task.</s>
 <s id="5">Well, maybe not; it depends on how you handle pain.</s>
 <s id="6">Some people are distracted by pain.</s>
 <s id="7">It takes them longer to complete a task, and they do it less well.</s>
 <s id="8">Other people use tasks to distract themselves from pain, and those people actually do the task faster and better when they're in pain than when they're not.</s>
 <s id="9">Some people can just send their mind wandering to distract themselves from pain.</s>
 <s id="10">How can different people be subjected to the exact same painful stimulus and yet experience the pain so differently?</s>
 <s id="11">And why does this matter?</s>
 <s id="12">First of all, what is pain?</s>
 <s id="13">Pain is an unpleasant sensory and emotional experience, associated with actual or potential tissue damage.</s>
 <s id="14">Pain is something we experience, so it's best measured by what you say it is.</s>
 <s id="15">Pain has an intensity; you can describe it on a scale from zero, no pain, to ten, the most pain imaginable.</s>
 <s id="16">But pain also has a character, like sharp, dull, burning, or aching.</s>
 <s id="17">What exactly creates these perceptions of pain?</s>
 <s id="18">Well, when you get hurt, special tissue damage-sensing nerve cells, called nociceptors, fire and send signals to the spinal cord and then up to the brain.</s>
 <s id="19">Processing work gets done by cells called neurons and glia.</s>
 <s id="20">This is your Grey matter.</s>
 <s id="21">And brain superhighways carry information as electrical impulses from one area to another.</s>
 <s id="22">This is your white matter.</s>
 <s id="23">The superhighway that carries pain information from the spinal cord to the brain is our sensing pathway that ends in the cortex, a part of the brain that decides what to do with the pain signal.</s>
 <s id="24">Another system of interconnected brain cells called the salience network decides what to pay attention to.</s>
 <s id="25">Since pain can have serious consequences, the pain signal immediately activates the salience network.</s>
 <s id="26">Now, you're paying attention.</s>
 <s id="27">The brain also responds to the pain and has to cope with these pain signals.</s>
 <s id="28">So, motor pathways are activated to take your hand off a hot stove, for example.</s>
 <s id="29">But modulation networks are also activated that deliver endorphins and enkephalins, chemicals released when you're in pain or during extreme exercise, creating the runner's high.</s>
 <s id="30">These chemical systems help regulate and reduce pain.</s>
 <s id="31">All these networks and pathways work together to create your pain experience, to prevent further tissue damage, and help you to cope with pain.</s>
 <s id="32">This system is similar for everyone, but the sensitivity and efficacy of these brain circuits determines how much you feel and cope with pain.</s>
 <s id="33">This is why some people have greater pain than others and why some develop chronic pain that does not respond to treatment, while others respond well.</s>
 <s id="34">Variability in pain sensitivities is not so different than all kinds of variability in responses to other stimuli.</s>
 <s id="35">Like how some people love roller coasters, but other people suffer from terrible motion sickness.</s>
 <s id="36">Why does it matter that there is variability in our pain brain circuits?</s>
 <s id="37">Well, there are many treatments for pain, targeting different systems.</s>
 <s id="38">For mild pain, non-prescription medications can act on cells where the pain signals start.</s>
 <s id="39">Other stronger pain medicines and anesthetics work by reducing the activity in pain-sensing circuits or boosting our coping system, or endorphins.</s>
 <s id="40">Some people can cope with pain using methods that involve distraction, relaxation, meditation, yoga, or strategies that can be taught, like cognitive behavioral therapy.</s>
 <s id="41">For some people who suffer from severe chronic pain, that is pain that doesn't go away months after their injury should have healed, none of the regular treatments work.</s>
 <s id="42">Traditionally, medical science has been about testing treatments on large groups to determine what would help a majority of patients.</s>
 <s id="43">But this has usually left out some who didn't benefit from the treatment or experienced side effects.</s>
 <s id="44">Now, new treatments that directly stimulate or block certain pain-sensing attention or modulation networks are being developed, along with ways to tailor them to individual patients, using tools like magnetic resonance imaging to map brain pathways.</s>
 <s id="45">Figuring out how your brain responds to pain is the key to finding the best treatment for you.</s>
 <s id="46">That's true personalized medicine.</s>
</text>
