<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Metaphor lives a secret life all around us.</s>
 <s id="2">We utter about six metaphors a minute.</s>
 <s id="3">Metaphorical thinking is essential to how we understand ourselves and others, how we communicate, learn, discover and invent.</s>
 <s id="4">But metaphor is a way of thought before it is a way with words.</s>
 <s id="5">Now, to assist me in explaining this, I've enlisted the help of one of our greatest philosophers, the reigning king of the metaphorians, a man whose contributions to the field are so great that he himself has become a metaphor.</s>
 <s id="6">I am, of course, referring to none other than Elvis Presley.</s>
 <s id="7">(Laughter) Now, "All Shook Up" is a great love song.</s>
 <s id="8">It's also a great example of how whenever we deal with anything abstract -- ideas, emotions, feelings, concepts, thoughts -- we inevitably resort to metaphor.</s>
 <s id="9">In "All Shook Up," a touch is not a touch, but a chill.</s>
 <s id="10">Lips are not lips, but volcanoes.</s>
 <s id="11">She is not she, but a buttercup.</s>
 <s id="12">And love is not love, but being all shook up.</s>
 <s id="13">In this, Elvis is following Aristotle's classic definition of metaphor as the process of giving the thing a name that belongs to something else.</s>
 <s id="14">This is the mathematics of metaphor.</s>
 <s id="15">And fortunately it's very simple.</s>
 <s id="16">X equals Y.</s>
 <s id="17">(Laughter) This formula works wherever metaphor is present.</s>
 <s id="18">Elvis uses it, but so does Shakespeare in this famous line from "Romeo and Juliet:" Juliet is the sun.</s>
 <s id="19">Now, here, Shakespeare gives the thing, Juliet, a name that belongs to something else, the sun.</s>
 <s id="20">But whenever we give a thing a name that belongs to something else, we give it a whole network of analogies too.</s>
 <s id="21">We mix and match what we know about the metaphor's source, in this case the sun, with what we know about its target, Juliet.</s>
 <s id="22">And metaphor gives us a much more vivid understanding of Juliet than if Shakespeare had literally described what she looks like.</s>
 <s id="23">So, how do we make and understand metaphors?</s>
 <s id="24">This might look familiar.</s>
 <s id="25">The first step is pattern recognition.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">Look at this image.</s>
  <s id="26.2">What do you see?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">Three wayward Pac-Men, and three pointy brackets are actually present.</s>
 <s id="28">What we see, however, are two overlapping triangles.</s>
 <s id="29">Metaphor is not just the detection of patterns; it is the creation of patterns.</s>
 <s id="30">Second step, conceptual synesthesia.</s>
 <s id="31">Now, synesthesia is the experience of a stimulus in once sense organ in another sense organ as well, such as colored hearing.</s>
 <s id="32">People with colored hearing actually see colors when they hear the sounds of words or letters.</s>
 <s id="33">We all have synesthetic abilities.</s>
 <s id="34">This is the Bouba/Kiki test.</s>
 <s id="35">What you have to do is identify which of these shapes is called Bouba, and which is called Kiki.</s>
 <s id="36">(Laughter) If you are like 98 percent of other people, you will identify the round, amoeboid shape as Bouba, and the sharp, spiky one as Kiki.</s>
 <s id="37">Can we do a quick show of hands?</s>
 <s id="38">Does that correspond?</s>
 <s id="39">Okay, I think 99.9 would about cover it.</s>
 <s id="40">Why do we do that?</s>
 <s id="41">Because we instinctively find, or create, a pattern between the round shape and the round sound of Bouba, and the spiky shape and the spiky sound of Kiki.</s>
 <s id="42">And many of the metaphors we use everyday are synesthetic.</s>
 <s id="43">Silence is sweet.</s>
 <s id="44">Neckties are loud.</s>
 <s id="45">Sexually attractive people are hot.</s>
 <s id="46">Sexually unattractive people leave us cold.</s>
 <s id="47">Metaphor creates a kind of conceptual synesthesia, in which we understand one concept in the context of another.</s>
 <s id="48">Third step is cognitive dissonance.</s>
 <s id="49">This is the Stroop test.</s>
 <s id="50">What you need to do here is identify as quickly as possible the color of the ink in which these words are printed.</s>
 <s id="51">You can take the test now.</s>
 <s id="52">If you're like most people, you will experience a moment of cognitive dissonance when the name of the color is printed in a differently colored ink.</s>
 <s id="53">The test shows that we cannot ignore the literal meaning of words even when the literal meaning gives the wrong answer.</s>
 <s id="54">Stroop tests have been done with metaphor as well.</s>
 <s id="55">The participants had to identify, as quickly as possible, the literally false sentences.</s>
 <s id="56">They took longer to reject metaphors as false than they did to reject literally false sentences.</s>
 <p id="p57">
  <s id="57.1">Why?</s>
  <s id="57.2">Because we cannot ignore the metaphorical meaning of words either.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="58">One of the sentences was, "Some jobs are jails."</s>
 <s id="59">Now, unless you're a prison guard, the sentence "Some jobs are jails" is literally false.</s>
 <s id="60">Sadly, it's metaphorically true.</s>
 <s id="61">And the metaphorical truth interferes with our ability to identify it as literally false.</s>
 <s id="62">Metaphor matters because it's around us every day, all the time.</s>
 <s id="63">Metaphor matters because it creates expectations.</s>
 <s id="64">Pay careful attention the next time you read the financial news.</s>
 <s id="65">Agent metaphors describe price movements as the deliberate action of a living thing, as in, "The NASDAQ climbed higher."</s>
 <s id="66">Object metaphors describe price movements as non-living things, as in, "The Dow fell like a brick."</s>
 <s id="67">Researchers asked a group of people to read a clutch of market commentaries, and then predict the next day's price trend.</s>
 <s id="68">Those exposed to agent metaphors had higher expectations that price trends would continue.</s>
 <s id="69">And they had those expectations because agent metaphors imply the deliberate action of a living thing pursuing a goal.</s>
 <s id="70">If, for example, house prices are routinely described as climbing and climbing, higher and higher, people might naturally assume that that rise is unstoppable.</s>
 <s id="71">They may feel confident, say, in taking out mortgages they really can't afford.</s>
 <s id="72">That's a hypothetical example of course.</s>
 <s id="73">But this is how metaphor misleads.</s>
 <s id="74">Metaphor also matters because it influences decisions by activating analogies.</s>
 <s id="75">A group of students was told that a small democratic country had been invaded and had asked the U.S. for help.</s>
 <s id="76">And they had to make a decision.</s>
 <s id="77">What should they do?</s>
 <s id="78">Intervene, appeal to the U.N., or do nothing?</s>
 <s id="79">They were each then given one of three descriptions of this hypothetical crisis.</s>
 <s id="80">Each of which was designed to trigger a different historical analogy: World War II, Vietnam, and the third was historically neutral.</s>
 <s id="81">Those exposed to the World War II scenario made more interventionist recommendations than the others.</s>
 <s id="82">Just as we cannot ignore the literal meaning of words, we cannot ignore the analogies that are triggered by metaphor.</s>
 <s id="83">Metaphor matters because it opens the door to discovery.</s>
 <s id="84">Whenever we solve a problem, or make a discovery, we compare what we know with what we don't know.</s>
 <s id="85">And the only way to find out about the latter is to investigate the ways it might be like the former.</s>
 <s id="86">Einstein described his scientific method as combinatory play.</s>
 <s id="87">He famously used thought experiments, which are essentially elaborate analogies, to come up with some of his greatest discoveries.</s>
 <s id="88">By bringing together what we know and what we don't know through analogy, metaphorical thinking strikes the spark that ignites discovery.</s>
 <s id="89">Now metaphor is ubiquitous, yet it's hidden.</s>
 <s id="90">But you just have to look at the words around you and you'll find it.</s>
 <s id="91">Ralph Waldo Emerson described language as "fossil poetry."</s>
 <s id="92">But before it was fossil poetry language was fossil metaphor.</s>
 <s id="93">And these fossils still breathe.</s>
 <s id="94">Take the three most famous words in all of Western philosophy: "Cogito ergo sum."</s>
 <s id="95">That's routinely translated as, "I think, therefore I am."</s>
 <s id="96">But there is a better translation.</s>
 <s id="97">The Latin word "cogito" is derived from the prefix "co," meaning "together," and the verb "agitare," meaning "to shake."</s>
 <s id="98">So, the original meaning of "cogito" is to shake together.</s>
 <s id="99">And the proper translation of "cogito ergo sum" is "I shake things up, therefore I am."</s>
 <s id="100">(Laughter) Metaphor shakes things up, giving us everything from Shakespeare to scientific discovery in the process.</s>
 <s id="101">The mind is a plastic snow dome, the most beautiful, most interesting, and most itself, when, as Elvis put it, it's all shook up.</s>
 <s id="102">And metaphor keeps the mind shaking, rattling and rolling, long after Elvis has left the building.</s>
 <s id="103">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="104">(Applause)</s>
</text>
