<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In the middle of the 16th century, a talented young anatomist named Andreas Vesalius made a shocking discovery: the most famous human anatomy texts in the world were wrong.</s>
 <s id="2">They not only failed to account for many details of the human body, they also described the organs of apes and other mammals.</s>
 <s id="3">While Vesalius knew he was right, announcing these errors would mean challenging Galen of Pergamon– the most renowned physician in medical history.</s>
 <s id="4">But who was this towering figure?</s>
 <s id="5">And why did doctors working more than 1,300 years later so revere and fear him?</s>
 <s id="6">Born in 129 CE, Galen left home as a teen to scour the Mediterranean for medical wisdom.</s>
 <s id="7">He returned home a gifted surgeon with a passion for anatomy and a penchant for showmanship.</s>
 <s id="8">He gleefully entered public anatomy contests, eager to show up his fellow physicians.</s>
 <s id="9">In one demonstration, he caused a pig to lose its voice by tying off one of its nerves.</s>
 <s id="10">In another, he disemboweled a monkey and challenged his colleagues to repair it.</s>
 <s id="11">When they couldn’t, he did.</s>
 <s id="12">These grizzly feats won him a position as surgeon to the city’s gladiators.</s>
 <s id="13">Eventually, he would leave the arena to become the personal physician to four Roman Emperors.</s>
 <s id="14">While his peers debated symptoms and their origins, Galen obsessively studied anatomy.</s>
 <s id="15">He was convinced that each organ had a specific function.</s>
 <s id="16">Since the Roman government largely prohibited working with human cadavers, Galen conducted countless dissections of animals instead.</s>
 <s id="17">Even with this constraint, his exhaustive investigations yielded some remarkably accurate conclusions.</s>
 <s id="18">One of Galen’s most important contributions was the insight that the brain, not the heart, controlled the body.</s>
 <s id="19">He confirmed this theory by opening the cranium of a living cow.</s>
 <s id="20">By applying pressure to different parts of the brain, he could link various regions to specific functions.</s>
 <s id="21">Other experiments allowed him to distinguish sensory from motor nerves, establish that urine was made in the kidneys, and deduce that respiration was controlled by muscles and nerves.</s>
 <s id="22">But these wild experiments also produced extraordinary misconceptions.</s>
 <s id="23">Galen never realized that blood cycles continuously throughout the body.</s>
 <s id="24">Instead, he believed the liver constantly produces an endless supply of blood, which gets entirely depleted on its one-way trip to the organs.</s>
 <s id="25">Galen is also credited with solidifying the popular theory of the Four Humours.</s>
 <s id="26">Introduced by Hippocrates centuries earlier, this misguided hypothesis attributed most medical problems to an imbalance in four bodily fluids called humours.</s>
 <s id="27">To correct the balance of these fluids, doctors employed dangerous treatments like bloodletting and purging.</s>
 <s id="28">Informed by his poor understanding of the circulatory system, Galen was a strong proponent of these treatments, despite their sometimes lethal consequences.</s>
 <s id="29">Unfortunately, Galen’s ego drove him to believe that all his discoveries were of the utmost importance.</s>
 <s id="30">He penned treatises on everything from anatomy to nutrition to bedside manner, meticulously cataloguing his writings to ensure their preservation.</s>
 <s id="31">Over the next 13 centuries, Galen’s prolific collection dominated all other schools of medical thought.</s>
 <s id="32">His texts became the standard works taught to new generations of doctors, who in turn, wrote new essays extolling Galen’s ideas.</s>
 <s id="33">Even doctors who actually dissected human cadavers would bafflingly repeat Galen’s mistakes, despite seeing clear evidence to the contrary.</s>
 <s id="34">Meanwhile, the few practitioners bold enough to offer conflicting opinions were either ignored or ridiculed.</s>
 <s id="35">For 1,300 years, Galen’s legacy remained untouchable– until renaissance anatomist Vesalius spoke out against him.</s>
 <s id="36">As a prominent scientist and lecturer, his authority influenced many young doctors of his time.</s>
 <s id="37">But even then, it took another hundred years for an accurate description of blood flow to emerge, and two hundred more for the theory of the Four Humours to fade.</s>
 <s id="38">Hopefully, today we can reap the benefits of Galen’s experiments without attributing equal credence to his less accurate ideas.</s>
 <s id="39">But perhaps just as valuable is the reminder that science is an ever-evolving process, which should always place evidence above ego.</s>
</text>
