<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">A few years ago, my mom developed rheumatoid arthritis.</s>
 <s id="2">Her wrists, knees and toes swelled up, causing crippling, chronic pain.</s>
 <s id="3">She had to file for disability.</s>
 <s id="4">She stopped attending our local mosque.</s>
 <s id="5">Some mornings it was too painful for her to brush her teeth.</s>
 <s id="6">I wanted to help.</s>
 <s id="7">But I didn't know how.</s>
 <s id="8">I'm not a doctor.</s>
 <s id="9">So, what I am is a historian of medicine.</s>
 <s id="10">So I started to research the history of chronic pain.</s>
 <s id="11">Turns out, UCLA has an entire history of pain collection in their archives.</s>
 <s id="12">And I found a story -- a fantastic story -- of a man who saved -- rescued -- millions of people from pain; people like my mom.</s>
 <s id="13">Yet, I had never heard of him.</s>
 <s id="14">There were no biographies of him, no Hollywood movies.</s>
 <s id="15">His name was John J. Bonica.</s>
 <s id="16">But when our story begins, he was better known as Johnny "Bull" Walker.</s>
 <s id="17">It was a summer day in 1941.</s>
 <s id="18">The circus had just arrived in the tiny town of Brookfield, New York.</s>
 <s id="19">Spectators flocked to see the wire-walkers, the tramp clowns -- if they were lucky, the human cannonball.</s>
 <s id="20">They also came to see the strongman, Johnny "Bull" Walker, a brawny bully who'd pin you for a dollar.</s>
 <s id="21">You know, on that particular day, a voice rang out over the circus P.A. system.</s>
 <s id="22">They needed a doctor urgently, in the live animal tent.</s>
 <s id="23">Something had gone wrong with the lion tamer.</s>
 <s id="24">The climax of his act had gone wrong, and his head was stuck inside the lion's mouth.</s>
 <s id="25">He was running out of air; the crowd watched in horror as he struggled and then passed out.</s>
 <s id="26">When the lion finally did relax its jaws, the lion tamer just slumped to the ground, motionless.</s>
 <s id="27">When he came to a few minutes later, he saw a familiar figure hunched over him.</s>
 <s id="28">It was Bull Walker.</s>
 <s id="29">The strongman had given the lion tamer mouth-to-mouth, and saved his life.</s>
 <s id="30">Now, the strongman hadn't told anyone, but he was actually a third-year medical student.</s>
 <s id="31">He toured with the circus during summers to pay tuition, but kept it a secret to protect his persona.</s>
 <s id="32">He was supposed to be a brute, a villain -- not a nerdy do-gooder.</s>
 <s id="33">His medical colleagues didn't know his secret, either.</s>
 <s id="34">As he put it, "If you were an athlete, you were a dumb dodo."</s>
 <s id="35">So he didn't tell them about the circus, or about how he wrestled professionally on evenings and weekends.</s>
 <s id="36">He used a pseudonym like Bull Walker, or later, the Masked Marvel.</s>
 <s id="37">He even kept it a secret that same year, when he was crowned the Light Heavyweight Champion of the world.</s>
 <s id="38">Over the years, John J. Bonica lived these parallel lives.</s>
 <s id="39">He was a wrestler; he was a doctor.</s>
 <s id="40">He was a heel; he was a hero.</s>
 <s id="41">He inflicted pain, and he treated it.</s>
 <s id="42">And he didn’t know it at the time, but over the next five decades, he'd draw on these dueling identities to forge a whole new way to think about pain.</s>
 <s id="43">It'd change modern medicine so much so, that decades later, Time magazine would call him pain relief's founding father.</s>
 <s id="44">But that all happened later.</s>
 <s id="45">In 1942, Bonica graduated medical school and married Emma, his sweetheart, whom he had met at one of his matches years before.</s>
 <s id="46">He still wrestled in secret -- he had to.</s>
 <s id="47">His internship at New York's St. Vincent's Hospital paid nothing.</s>
 <s id="48">With his championship belt, he wrestled in big-ticket venues, like Madison Square Garden, against big-time opponents, like Everett "The Blonde Bear" Marshall, or three-time world champion, Angelo Savoldi.</s>
 <s id="49">The matches took a toll on his body; he tore hip joints, fractured ribs.</s>
 <s id="50">One night, The Terrible Turk's big toe scratched a scar like Capone's down the side of his face.</s>
 <s id="51">The next morning at work, he had to wear a surgical mask to hide it.</s>
 <s id="52">Twice Bonica showed up to the O.R. with one eye so bruised, he couldn't see out of it.</s>
 <s id="53">But worst of all were his mangled cauliflower ears.</s>
 <s id="54">He said they felt like two baseballs on the sides of his head.</s>
 <s id="55">Pain just kept accumulating in his life.</s>
 <s id="56">Next, he watched his wife go into labor at his hospital.</s>
 <s id="57">She heaved and pushed, clearly in anguish.</s>
 <s id="58">Her obstetrician called out to the intern on duty to give her a few drops of ether to ease her pain.</s>
 <s id="59">But the intern was a young guy, just three weeks on the job -- he was jittery, and in applying the ether, irritated Emma's throat.</s>
 <s id="60">She vomited and choked, and started to turn blue.</s>
 <s id="61">Bonica, who was watching all this, pushed the intern out of the way, cleared her airway, and saved his wife and his unborn daughter.</s>
 <s id="62">At that moment, he decided to devote his life to anesthesiology.</s>
 <s id="63">Later, he'd even go on to help develop the epidural, for delivering mothers.</s>
 <s id="64">But before he could focus on obstetrics, Bonica had to report for basic training.</s>
 <s id="65">Right around D-Day, Bonica showed up to Madigan Army Medical Center, near Tacoma.</s>
 <s id="66">At 7,700 beds, it was one of the largest army hospitals in America.</s>
 <s id="67">Bonica was in charge of all pain control there.</s>
 <s id="68">He was only 27.</s>
 <s id="69">Treating so many patients, Bonica started noticing cases that contradicted everything he had learned.</s>
 <s id="70">Pain was supposed to be a kind of alarm bell -- in a good way -- a body's way of signaling an injury, like a broken arm.</s>
 <s id="71">But in some cases, like after a patient had a leg amputated, that patient might still complain of pain in that nonexistent leg.</s>
 <s id="72">But if the injury had been treated, why would the alarm bell keep ringing?</s>
 <s id="73">There were other cases in which there was no evidence of an injury whatsoever, and yet, still the patient hurt.</s>
 <s id="74">Bonica tracked down all the specialists at his hospital -- surgeons, neurologists, psychiatrists, others.</s>
 <s id="75">And he tried to get their opinions on his patients.</s>
 <s id="76">It took too long, so he started organizing group meetings over lunch.</s>
 <s id="77">It would be like a tag team of specialists going up against the patient's pain.</s>
 <s id="78">No one had ever focused on pain this way before.</s>
 <s id="79">After that, he hit the books.</s>
 <s id="80">He read every medical textbook he could get his hands on, carefully noting every mention of the word "pain."</s>
 <s id="81">Out of the 14,000 pages he read, the word "pain" was on 17 and a half of them.</s>
 <s id="82">Seventeen and a half.</s>
 <s id="83">For the most basic, most common, most frustrating part of being a patient.</s>
 <s id="84">Bonica was shocked -- I'm quoting him, he said, "What the hell kind of conclusion can you come to there?</s>
 <s id="85">The most important thing from the patient's perspective, they don't talk about."</s>
 <s id="86">So over the next eight years, Bonica would talk about it.</s>
 <s id="87">He'd write about it; he'd write those missing pages.</s>
 <s id="88">He wrote what would later be known as the Bible of Pain.</s>
 <s id="89">In it he proposed new strategies, new treatments using nerve-block injections.</s>
 <s id="90">He proposed a new institution, the Pain Clinic, based on those lunchtime meetings.</s>
 <s id="91">But the most important thing about his book was that it was kind of an emotional alarm bell for medicine.</s>
 <s id="92">A desperate plea to doctors to take pain seriously in patients' lives.</s>
 <s id="93">He recast the very purpose of medicine.</s>
 <s id="94">The goal wasn't to make patients better; it was to make patients feel better.</s>
 <s id="95">He pushed his pain agenda for decades, before it finally took hold in the mid-'70s.</s>
 <s id="96">Hundreds of pain clinics sprung up all over the world.</s>
 <s id="97">But as they did -- a tragic twist.</s>
 <s id="98">Bonica's years of wrestling caught up to him.</s>
 <s id="99">He had been out of the ring for over 20 years, but those 1,500 professional bouts had left a mark on his body.</s>
 <s id="100">Still in his mid-50s, he suffered severe osteoarthritis.</s>
 <s id="101">Over the next 20 years he'd have 22 surgeries, including four spine operations, and hip replacement after hip replacement.</s>
 <s id="102">He could barely raise his arm, turn his neck.</s>
 <s id="103">He needed aluminum crutches to walk.</s>
 <s id="104">His friends and former students became his doctors.</s>
 <s id="105">One recalled that he probably had more nerve-block injections than anyone else on the planet.</s>
 <s id="106">Already a workaholic, he worked even more -- 15- to 18-hour days.</s>
 <s id="107">Healing others became more than just his job, it was his own most effective form of relief.</s>
 <s id="108">"If I wasn't as busy as I am," he told a reporter at the time, "I would be a completely disabled guy."</s>
 <s id="109">On a business trip to Florida in the early 1980s, Bonica got a former student to drive him to the Hyde Park area in Tampa.</s>
 <s id="110">They drove past palm trees and pulled up to an old mansion, with giant silver howitzer cannons hidden in the garage.</s>
 <s id="111">The house belonged to the Zacchini family, who were something like American circus royalty.</s>
 <s id="112">Decades earlier, Bonica had watched them, clad in silver jumpsuits and goggles, doing the act they pioneered -- the Human Cannonball.</s>
 <s id="113">But now they were like him: retired.</s>
 <s id="114">That generation is all dead now, including Bonica, so there's no way to know exactly what they said that day.</s>
 <s id="115">But still, I love imagining it.</s>
 <s id="116">The strongman and the human cannonballs reunited, showing off old scars, and new ones.</s>
 <s id="117">Maybe Bonica gave them medical advice.</s>
 <s id="118">Maybe he told them what he later said in an oral history, which is that his time in the circus and wrestling deeply molded his life.</s>
 <s id="119">Bonica saw pain close up.</s>
 <p id="p120">
  <s id="120.1">He felt it.</s>
  <s id="120.2">He lived it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="121">And it made it impossible for him to ignore in others.</s>
 <s id="122">Out of that empathy, he spun a whole new field, played a major role in getting medicine to acknowledge pain in and of itself.</s>
 <s id="123">In that same oral history, Bonica claimed that pain is the most complex human experience.</s>
 <s id="124">That it involves your past life, your current life, your interactions, your family.</s>
 <s id="125">That was definitely true for Bonica.</s>
 <s id="126">But it was also true for my mom.</s>
 <s id="127">It's easy for doctors to see my mom as a kind of professional patient, a woman who just spends her days in waiting rooms.</s>
 <s id="128">Sometimes I get stuck seeing her that same way.</s>
 <s id="129">But as I saw Bonica's pain -- a testament to his fully lived life -- I started to remember all the things that my mom's pain holds.</s>
 <s id="130">Before they got swollen and arthritic, my mom's fingers clacked away in the hospital H.R. department where she worked.</s>
 <s id="131">They folded samosas for our entire mosque.</s>
 <s id="132">When I was a kid, they cut my hair, wiped my nose, tied my shoes.</s>
 <s id="133">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="134">(Applause)</s>
</text>
