<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">What's happening to the climate?</s>
 <s id="2">It is unbelievably bad.</s>
 <p id="p3">
  <s id="3.1">This is, obviously, that famous view now of the Arctic, which is likely to be gone at this point in the next three or four or five years.</s>
  <s id="3.2">Very, very, very scary.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="4">So we all look at what we can do.</s>
 <s id="5">And when you look at the worldwide sources of CO2, 52 percent are tied to buildings.</s>
 <s id="6">Only nine percent is passenger cars, interestingly enough.</s>
 <s id="7">So we ran off to a sushi bar.</s>
 <s id="8">And at that sushi bar we came up with a great idea.</s>
 <s id="9">And it was something called EcoRock.</s>
 <s id="10">And we said we could redesign the 115-year-old gypsum drywall process that generates 20 billion pounds of CO2 a year.</s>
 <p id="p11">
  <s id="11.1">So it was a big idea.</s>
  <s id="11.2">We wanted to reduce that by 80 percent, which is exactly what we've done.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="12">We started R&amp;amp;D in 2006.</s>
 <s id="13">Decided to use recycled content from cement and steel manufacturing.</s>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">There is the inside of our lab.</s>
  <s id="14.2">We haven't shown this before.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="15">But our people had to do some 5,000 different mixes to get this right, to hit our targets.</s>
 <s id="16">And they worked absolutely very, very, very hard.</s>
 <s id="17">So then we went forward and built our production line in China.</s>
 <s id="18">We don't build this production equipment any longer in the U.S., unfortunately.</s>
 <s id="19">We did the line install over the summer.</s>
 <s id="20">We started right there, with absolutely nothing.</s>
 <s id="21">You're seeing for the first time, a brand new drywall production line, not made using gypsum at all.</s>
 <s id="22">That's the finished production line there.</s>
 <s id="23">We got our first panel out on December third.</s>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">That is the slurry being poured onto paper, basically.</s>
  <s id="24.2">That's the line running.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="25">The exciting thing is, look at the faces of the people.</s>
 <s id="26">These are people who worked this project for two to three years.</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">And they are so excited.</s>
  <s id="27.2">That's the first board off the line.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">Our Vice President of Operation kissing the board.</s>
  <s id="28.2">Obviously very, very excited.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">But this has a huge, huge impact on the environment.</s>
 <s id="30">We signed the first panel just a few weeks after that, had a great signing ceremony, leading to people hopefully using these products across the world.</s>
 <s id="31">And we've got Cradle-to-Cradle Gold on this thing.</s>
 <s id="32">We happened to win, just recently, the Green Product of the Year for "The Re-Invention of Drywall," from Popular Science.</s>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">Thank you.</s>
  <s id="33.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="34">So here is what we learned: 8,000 gallons of gas equivalent to build one house.</s>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">You probably had no idea.</s>
  <s id="35.2">It's like driving around the world six times.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="36">We must change everything.</s>
 <s id="37">Look around the room: chairs, wood, everything around us has to change or we're not going to lick this problem.</s>
 <s id="38">Don't listen to the people who say you can't do this, because anyone can.</s>
 <s id="39">And these job losses, we can fix them with green-collar jobs.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">We've got four plants.</s>
  <s id="40.2">We're building this stuff around the country.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="41">We're going as fast as we can.</s>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">Two and a half million cars worth of gypsum, you know, CO2 generated.</s>
  <s id="42.2">Right?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">So what will you do?</s>
  <s id="43.2">I'll tell you what I did and why I did it.</s>
  <s id="43.3">And I know my time's up.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">Those are my kids, Natalie and David.</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">When they have their kids, 2050, they'd better look back at Grandpa and say, "Hey, you gave it a good shot.</s>
  <s id="45.2">You did the best you could with the team that you had."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="46">So my hope is that when you leave TED, you will look at reducing your carbon footprint in however you can do it.</s>
 <s id="47">And if you don't know how, please find me -- I will help you.</s>
 <s id="48">Last but not least, Bill Gates, I know you invented Windows.</s>
 <s id="49">Wait till you see, maybe next year, what kind of windows we've invented.</s>
 <s id="50">Thank you so much.</s>
 <s id="51">(Applause)</s>
</text>
