<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I was here about four years ago, talking about the relationship of design and happiness.</s>
 <s id="2">At the very end of it, I showed a list under that title.</s>
 <s id="3">I learned very few things in addition since (Laughter) -- but made a whole number of them into projects since.</s>
 <s id="4">These are inflatable monkeys in every city in Scotland: "Everybody always thinks they are right."</s>
 <s id="5">They were combined in the media.</s>
 <s id="6">"Drugs are fun in the beginning but become a drag later on."</s>
 <s id="7">We're doing changing media.</s>
 <s id="8">This is a projection that can see the viewer as the viewer walks by.</s>
 <s id="9">You can't help but actually ripping that spider web apart.</s>
 <s id="10">All of these things are pieces of graphic design.</s>
 <s id="11">We do them for our clients.</s>
 <s id="12">They are commissioned.</s>
 <s id="13">I would never have the money to actually pay for the installment or pay for all the billboards or the production of these, so there's always a client attached to them.</s>
 <s id="14">These are 65,000 coat hangers in a street that's lined with fashion stores.</s>
 <s id="15">"Worrying solves nothing."</s>
 <s id="16">"Money does not make me happy" appeared first as double-page spreads in a magazine.</s>
 <s id="17">The printer lost the file, didn't tell us.</s>
 <s id="18">When the magazine -- actually, when I got the subscription -- it was 12 following pages.</s>
 <s id="19">It said, "Money does does make me happy."</s>
 <s id="20">And a friend of mine in Austria felt so sorry for me that he talked the largest casino owner in Linz into letting us wrap his building.</s>
 <s id="21">So this is the big pedestrian zone in Linz.</s>
 <s id="22">It just says "Money," and if you look down the side street, it says, "does not make me happy."</s>
 <s id="23">We had a show that just came down last week in New York.</s>
 <s id="24">We steamed up the windows permanently, and every hour we had a different designer come in and write these things that they've learned into the steam in the window.</s>
 <s id="25">Everybody participated -- Milton Glaser, Massimo Vignelli.</s>
 <s id="26">Singapore was quite in discussion.</s>
 <s id="27">This is a little spot that we filmed there that's to be displayed on the large JumboTrons in Singapore.</s>
 <s id="28">And, of course, it's one that's dear to my heart, because all of these sentiments -- some banal, some a bit more profound -- all originally had come out of my diary.</s>
 <s id="29">And I do go often into the diary and check if I wanted to change something about the situation.</s>
 <s id="30">If it's -- see it for a long enough time, I actually do something about it.</s>
 <s id="31">And the very last one is a billboard.</s>
 <s id="32">This is our roof in New York, the roof of the studio.</s>
 <s id="33">This is newsprint plus stencils that lie on the newsprint.</s>
 <s id="34">We let that lie around in the sun.</s>
 <s id="35">As you all know, newsprint yellows significantly in the sun.</s>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">After a week, we took the stencils and the leaves off, shipped the newsprints to Lisbon to a very sunny spot, so on day one the billboard said, "Complaining is silly.</s>
  <s id="36.2">Either act or forget."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="37">Three days later it faded, and a week later, no more complaining anywhere.</s>
 <s id="38">(Laughter) Thank you so much.</s>
 <s id="39">(Applause)</s>
</text>
