<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In the mid-16th century, Italians were captivated by a type of male singer whose incredible range contained notes previously thought impossible for adult men.</s>
 <s id="2">However, this gift came at a high price.</s>
 <s id="3">To prevent their voices from breaking, these singers had been castrated before puberty, halting the hormonal processes that would deepen their voices.</s>
 <s id="4">Known as castrati, their light, angelic voices were renowned throughout Europe, until the cruel procedure that created them was outlawed in the 1800s.</s>
 <s id="5">Though stunting vocal growth can produce an extraordinary musical range, naturally developing voices are already capable of incredible variety.</s>
 <s id="6">And as we age, our bodies undergo two major changes which explore that range.</s>
 <s id="7">So how exactly does our voice box work, and what causes these shifts in speech?</s>
 <s id="8">The specific sound of a speaking voice is the result of many anatomical variables, but it’s mostly determined by the age and health of our vocal cords and the size of our larynxes.</s>
 <s id="9">The larynx is a complex system of muscle and cartilage that supports and moves the vocal cords, or, as they’re more accurately known, the vocal folds.</s>
 <s id="10">Strung between the thyroid and arytenoid cartilages, these two muscles form an elastic curtain that opens and shuts across the trachea, the tube that carries air through the throat.</s>
 <s id="11">The folds are apart when we’re breathing, but when we speak, they slam shut.</s>
 <s id="12">Our lungs push air against the closed folds, blowing them open and vibrating the tissue to produce sound.</s>
 <s id="13">Unlike the deliberate focus required for playing an external instrument, we effortlessly change notes as we speak.</s>
 <s id="14">By pushing air faster or slower, we change the frequency and amplitude of these vibrations, which respectively translate to the pitch and volume of our voices.</s>
 <s id="15">Rapid and small vibrations create high-pitched, quiet tones, while slow, large vibrations produce deep, bellowing rumbles.</s>
 <s id="16">Finally, by moving the laryngeal muscles between the cartilages, we can stretch and contract those folds to intuitively play our internal instruments.</s>
 <s id="17">This process is the same from your first words to your last, but as you age, your larynx ages too.</s>
 <s id="18">During puberty, the first major shift starts, as your voice begins to deepen.</s>
 <s id="19">This happens when your larynx grows in size, elongating the vocal folds and opening up more room for them to vibrate.</s>
 <s id="20">These longer folds have slower, larger vibrations, which result in a lower baseline pitch.</s>
 <s id="21">This growth is especially dramatic in many males, whose high testosterone levels lead first to voice cracks, and then to deeper, more booming voices, and laryngeal protrusions called Adam’s apples.</s>
 <s id="22">Another vocal development during puberty occurs when the homogenous tissue covering the folds specializes into three distinct functional layers: a central muscle, a layer of stiff collagen wrapped in stretchy elastin fibers, and an outer layer of mucus membrane.</s>
 <s id="23">These layers add nuance and depth to the voice, giving it a distinct timbre that sets it apart from its pre-pubescent tones.</s>
 <s id="24">After puberty, most people’s voices remain more or less the same for about 50 years.</s>
 <s id="25">But we all use our voices differently, and eventually we experience the symptoms associated with aging larynxes, known as presbyphonia.</s>
 <s id="26">First, the collagen in our folds stiffens and the surrounding elastin fibers atrophy and decay.</s>
 <s id="27">This decreased flexibility increases the pitch of older voices.</s>
 <s id="28">But for people who have experienced the hormonal effects of menopause, the higher pitch is countered and outweighed by swollen vocal folds.</s>
 <s id="29">The folds' increased mass slows their vibrations, resulting in deeper voices.</s>
 <s id="30">All these symptoms are further complicated by having fewer healthy laryngeal nerve endings, which reduces precise muscle control and causes breathy or rough voices.</s>
 <s id="31">Ultimately, these anatomical changes are just a few of the factors that can affect your voice.</s>
 <s id="32">But when kept in good condition, your voice box is a finely tuned instrument, capable of operatic arias, moody monologues, and stirring speeches.</s>
</text>
