<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm a neuroscientist, a professor at the University of California.</s>
 <s id="2">And over the past 35 years, I've studied behavior on the basis of everything from genes through neurotransmitters, dopamine, things like that, all the way through circuit analysis.</s>
 <s id="3">So that's what I normally do.</s>
 <s id="4">But then, for some reason, I got into something else, just recently.</s>
 <s id="5">And it all grew out of one of my colleagues asking me to analyze a bunch of brains of psychopathic killers.</s>
 <s id="6">And so this would be the typical talk I would give.</s>
 <s id="7">And the question is, "How do you end up with a psychopathic killer?"</s>
 <s id="8">What I mean by psychopathic killer are these people, these types of people.</s>
 <s id="9">And so some of the brains that I've studied are people you know about.</s>
 <s id="10">When I get the brains I don't know what I'm looking at.</s>
 <p id="p11">
  <s id="11.1">It's blind experiments.</s>
  <s id="11.2">They also gave me normal people and everything.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="12">So I've looked at about 70 of these.</s>
 <s id="13">And what came up was a number of pieces of data.</s>
 <s id="14">So we look at these sorts of things theoretically, on the basis of genetics, and brain damage, and interaction with environment, and exactly how that machine works.</s>
 <s id="15">So we're interested in exactly where in the brain, and what's the most important part of the brain.</s>
 <s id="16">So we've been looking at this: the interaction of genes, what's called epigenetic effects, brain damage, and environment, and how these are tied together.</s>
 <s id="17">And how you end up with a psychopath, and a killer, depends on exactly when the damage occurs.</s>
 <s id="18">It's really a very precisely timed thing.</s>
 <s id="19">You get different kinds of psychopaths.</s>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">So we're going along with this.</s>
  <s id="20.2">And here's, just to give you the pattern.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="21">The pattern is that those people, every one of them I looked at, who was a murderer, and was a serial killer, had damage to their orbital cortex, which is right above the eyes, the orbits, and also the interior part of the temporal lobe.</s>
 <s id="22">So there is the pattern that every one of them had, but they all were a little different too.</s>
 <s id="23">They had other sorts of brain damage.</s>
 <s id="24">A key thing is that the major violence genes, it's called the MAO-A gene.</s>
 <s id="25">And there is a variant of this gene that is in the normal population.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">Some of you have this.</s>
  <s id="26.2">And it's sex-linked.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">It's on the X chromosome.</s>
  <s id="27.2">And so in this way you can only get it from your mother.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="28">And in fact this is probably why mostly men, boys, are psychopathic killers, or are very aggressive.</s>
 <s id="29">Because a daughter can get one X from the father, one X from the mother, it's kind of diluted out.</s>
 <s id="30">But for a son, he can only get the X chromosome from his mother.</s>
 <s id="31">So this is how it's passed from mother to son.</s>
 <s id="32">And it has to do with too much brain serotonin during development, which is kind of interesting because serotonin is supposed to make you calm and relaxed.</s>
 <s id="33">But if you have this gene, in utero your brain is bathed in this, so your whole brain becomes insensitive to serotonin, so it doesn't work later on in life.</s>
 <s id="34">And I'd given this one talk in Israel, just this past year.</s>
 <s id="35">And it does have some consequences.</s>
 <s id="36">Theoretically what this means is that in order to express this gene, in a violent way, very early on, before puberty, you have to be involved in something that is really traumatic -- not a little stress, not being spanked or something, but really seeing violence, or being involved in it, in 3D.</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">Right?</s>
  <s id="37.2">That's how the mirror neuron system works.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="38">And so, if you have that gene, and you see a lot of violence in a certain situation, this is the recipe for disaster, absolute disaster.</s>
 <s id="39">And what I think might happen in these areas of the world, where we have constant violence, you end up having generations of kids that are seeing all this violence.</s>
 <s id="40">And if I was a young girl, somewhere in a violent area, you know, a 14 year old, and I want to find a mate, I'd find some tough guy, right, to protect me.</s>
 <s id="41">Well what the problem is this tends to concentrate these genes.</s>
 <s id="42">And now the boys and the girls get them.</s>
 <s id="43">So I think after several generations, and here is the idea, we really have a tinderbox.</s>
 <s id="44">So that was the idea.</s>
 <s id="45">But then my mother said to me, "I hear you've been going around talking about psychopathic killers.</s>
 <s id="46">And you're talking as if you come from a normal family."</s>
 <s id="47">I said, "What the hell are you talking about?"</s>
 <s id="48">She then told me about our own family tree.</s>
 <s id="49">Now she blamed this on my father's side, of course.</s>
 <s id="50">This was one of these cases, because she has no violence in her background, but my father did.</s>
 <s id="51">Well she said, "There is good news and bad news.</s>
 <s id="52">One of your cousins is Ezra Cornell, founder of Cornell university.</s>
 <s id="53">But the bad news is that your cousin is also Lizzie Borden.</s>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">Now I said, "Okay, so what?</s>
  <s id="54.2">We have Lizzie."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">She goes, "No it gets worse, read this book."</s>
 <s id="56">And here is this "Killed Strangely," and it's this historical book.</s>
 <s id="57">And the first murder of a mother by a son was my great-great-great-great-great-great-grandfather.</s>
 <s id="58">Okay, so that's the first case of matricide.</s>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">And that book is very interesting.</s>
  <s id="59.2">Because it's about witch trials, and how people thought back then.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="60">But it doesn't stop there.</s>
 <s id="61">There were seven more men, on my father's side, starting then, Cornells, that were all murderers.</s>
 <s id="62">Okay, now this gives one a little pause.</s>
 <s id="63">(Laughter) Because my father himself, and my three uncles, in World War II, were all conscientious objectors, all pussycats.</s>
 <s id="64">But every once in a while, like Lizzie Borden, like three times a century, and we're kind of due.</s>
 <s id="65">(Laughter) So the moral of the story is: people in glass houses shouldn't throw stones.</s>
 <s id="66">But more likely is this.</s>
 <p id="p67">
  <s id="67.1">(Laughter) And we had to take action.</s>
  <s id="67.2">Now our kids found out about it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="68">And they all seemed to be OK.</s>
 <s id="69">But our grandkids are going to be kind of concerned here.</s>
 <s id="70">So what we've done is I've started to do PET scans of everybody in the family.</s>
 <s id="71">(Laughter) We started to do PET scans, EEGs and genetic analysis to see where the bad news is.</s>
 <s id="72">Now the only person -- it turns out one son and one daughter, siblings, didn't get along and their patterns are exactly the same.</s>
 <s id="73">They have the same brain, and the same EEG.</s>
 <s id="74">And now they are close as can be.</s>
 <s id="75">But there's gonna be bad news somewhere.</s>
 <s id="76">And we don't know where it's going to pop up.</s>
 <s id="77">So that's my talk.</s>
 <s id="78">(Laughter)</s>
</text>
