<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Growing up in Taiwan as the daughter of a calligrapher, one of my most treasured memories was my mother showing me the beauty, the shape and the form of Chinese characters.</s>
 <s id="2">Ever since then, I was fascinated by this incredible language.</s>
 <s id="3">But to an outsider, it seems to be as impenetrable as the Great Wall of China.</s>
 <s id="4">Over the past few years, I've been wondering if I can break down this wall, so anyone who wants to understand and appreciate the beauty of this sophisticated language could do so.</s>
 <s id="5">I started thinking about how a new, fast method of learning Chinese might be useful.</s>
 <s id="6">Since the age of five, I started to learn how to draw every single stroke for each character in the correct sequence.</s>
 <s id="7">I learned new characters every day during the course of the next 15 years.</s>
 <s id="8">Since we only have five minutes, it's better that we have a fast and simpler way.</s>
 <s id="9">A Chinese scholar would understand 20,000 characters.</s>
 <s id="10">You only need 1,000 to understand the basic literacy.</s>
 <s id="11">The top 200 will allow you to comprehend 40 percent of basic literature -- enough to read road signs, restaurant menus, to understand the basic idea of the web pages or the newspapers.</s>
 <s id="12">Today I'm going to start with eight to show you how the method works.</s>
 <s id="13">You are ready?</s>
 <s id="14">Open your mouth as wide as possible until it's square.</s>
 <s id="15">You get a mouth.</s>
 <s id="16">This is a person going for a walk.</s>
 <s id="17">Person.</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">If the shape of the fire is a person with two arms on both sides, as if she was yelling frantically, "Help!</s>
  <s id="18.2">I'm on fire!" -- This symbol actually is originally from the shape of the flame, but I like to think that way.</s>
  <s id="18.3">Whichever works for you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="19">This is a tree.</s>
 <s id="20">Tree.</s>
 <s id="21">This is a mountain.</s>
 <s id="22">The sun.</s>
 <s id="23">The moon.</s>
 <s id="24">The symbol of the door looks like a pair of saloon doors in the wild west.</s>
 <s id="25">I call these eight characters radicals.</s>
 <s id="26">They are the building blocks for you to create lots more characters.</s>
 <s id="27">A person.</s>
 <s id="28">If someone walks behind, that is "to follow."</s>
 <s id="29">As the old saying goes, two is company, three is a crowd.</s>
 <s id="30">If a person stretched their arms wide, this person is saying, "It was this big."</s>
 <s id="31">The person inside the mouth, the person is trapped.</s>
 <s id="32">He's a prisoner, just like Jonah inside the whale.</s>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">One tree is a tree.</s>
  <s id="33.2">Two trees together, we have the woods.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="34">Three trees together, we create the forest.</s>
 <s id="35">Put a plank underneath the tree, we have the foundation.</s>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">Put a mouth on the top of the tree, that's "idiot."</s>
  <s id="36.2">(Laughter) Easy to remember, since a talking tree is pretty idiotic.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="37">Remember fire?</s>
 <s id="38">Two fires together, I get really hot.</s>
 <s id="39">Three fires together, that's a lot of flames.</s>
 <s id="40">Set the fire underneath the two trees, it's burning.</s>
 <s id="41">For us, the sun is the source of prosperity.</s>
 <s id="42">Two suns together, prosperous.</s>
 <s id="43">Three together, that's sparkles.</s>
 <s id="44">Put the sun and the moon shining together, it's brightness.</s>
 <s id="45">It also means tomorrow, after a day and a night.</s>
 <p id="p46">
  <s id="46.1">The sun is coming up above the horizon.</s>
  <s id="46.2">Sunrise.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">A door.</s>
  <s id="47.2">Put a plank inside the door, it's a door bolt.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="48">Put a mouth inside the door, asking questions.</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">Knock knock.</s>
  <s id="49.2">Is anyone home?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">This person is sneaking out of a door, escaping, evading.</s>
 <s id="51">On the left, we have a woman.</s>
 <s id="52">Two women together, they have an argument.</s>
 <s id="53">(Laughter) Three women together, be careful, it's adultery.</s>
 <s id="54">So we have gone through almost 30 characters.</s>
 <s id="55">By using this method, the first eight radicals will allow you to build 32.</s>
 <s id="56">The next group of eight characters will build an extra 32.</s>
 <s id="57">So with very little effort, you will be able to learn a couple hundred characters, which is the same as a Chinese eight-year-old.</s>
 <s id="58">So after we know the characters, we start building phrases.</s>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">For example, the mountain and the fire together, we have fire mountain.</s>
  <s id="59.2">It's a volcano.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="60">We know Japan is the land of the rising sun.</s>
 <s id="61">This is a sun placed with the origin, because Japan lies to the east of China.</s>
 <s id="62">So a sun, origin together, we build Japan.</s>
 <s id="63">A person behind Japan, what do we get?</s>
 <s id="64">A Japanese person.</s>
 <s id="65">The character on the left is two mountains stacked on top of each other.</s>
 <s id="66">In ancient China, that means in exile, because Chinese emperors, they put their political enemies in exile beyond mountains.</s>
 <s id="67">Nowadays, exile has turned into getting out.</s>
 <s id="68">A mouth which tells you where to get out is an exit.</s>
 <p id="p69">
  <s id="69.1">This is a slide to remind me that I should stop talking and get off of the stage.</s>
  <s id="69.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="70">(Applause)</s>
</text>
