<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In an age of global strife and climate change, I'm here to answer the all important question: Why is sex so damn good?</s>
 <s id="2">If you're laughing, you know what I mean.</s>
 <s id="3">Now, before we get to that answer, let me tell you about Chris Hosmer.</s>
 <s id="4">Chris is a great friend of mine from my university days, but secretly, I hate him.</s>
 <p id="p5">
  <s id="5.1">Here's why.</s>
  <s id="5.2">Back in university, we had a quick project to design some solar-powered clocks.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="6">Here's my clock.</s>
 <s id="7">It uses something called the dwarf sunflower, which grows to about 12 inches in height.</s>
 <s id="8">Now, as you know, sunflowers track the sun during the course of the day.</s>
 <s id="9">So in the morning, you see which direction the sunflower is facing, and you mark it on the blank area in the base.</s>
 <s id="10">At noon, you mark the changed position of the sunflower, and in the evening again, and that's your clock.</s>
 <s id="11">Now, I know my clock doesn't tell you the exact time, but it does give you a general idea using a flower.</s>
 <s id="12">So, in my completely unbiased, subjective opinion, it's brilliant.</s>
 <s id="13">However, here's Chris's clock.</s>
 <s id="14">It's five magnifying glasses with a shot glass under each one.</s>
 <s id="15">In each shot glass is a different scented oil.</s>
 <s id="16">In the morning, the sunlight will shine down on the first magnifying glass, focusing a beam of light on the shot glass underneath.</s>
 <s id="17">This will warm up the scented oil inside, and a particular smell will be emitted.</s>
 <s id="18">A couple of hours later, the sun will shine on the next magnifying glass, and a different smell will be emitted.</s>
 <s id="19">So during the course of the day, five different smells are dispersed throughout that environment.</s>
 <s id="20">Anyone living in that house can tell the time just by the smell.</s>
 <s id="21">You can see why I hate Chris.</s>
 <s id="22">I thought my idea was pretty good, but his idea is genius, and at the time, I knew his idea was better than mine, but I just couldn't explain why.</s>
 <s id="23">One thing you have to know about me is I hate to lose.</s>
 <s id="24">This problem's been bugging me for well over a decade.</s>
 <s id="25">All right, let's get back to the question of why sex is so good.</s>
 <s id="26">Many years after the solar powered clocks project, a young lady I knew suggested maybe sex is so good because of the five senses.</s>
 <s id="27">And when she said this, I had an epiphany.</s>
 <s id="28">So I decided to evaluate different experiences I had in my life from the point of view of the five senses.</s>
 <s id="29">To do this, I devised something called the five senses graph.</s>
 <s id="30">Along the y-axis, you have a scale from zero to 10, and along the x-axis, you have, of course, the five senses.</s>
 <s id="31">Anytime I had a memorable experience in my life, I would record it on this graph like a five senses diary.</s>
 <s id="32">Here's a quick video to show you how it works.</s>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">(Video) Jinsop Lee: Hey, my name's Jinsop, and today, I'm going to show you what riding motorbikes is like from the point of view of the five senses.</s>
  <s id="33.2">Hey!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="34">Bike designer: This is [unclear], custom bike designer.</s>
 <s id="35">(Motorcyle revving) [Sound] [Touch] [Sight] [Smell] [Taste] JL: And that's how the five senses graph works.</s>
 <s id="36">Now, for a period of three years, I gathered data, not just me but also some of my friends, and I used to teach in university, so I forced my -- I mean, I asked my students to do this as well.</s>
 <s id="37">So here are some other results.</s>
 <s id="38">The first is for instant noodles.</s>
 <s id="39">Now obviously, taste and smell are quite high, but notice sound is at three.</s>
 <s id="40">Many people told me a big part of the noodle-eating experience is the slurping noise.</s>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">You know.</s>
  <s id="41.2">(Slurps) Needless to say, I no longer dine with these people.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">OK, next, clubbing.</s>
 <s id="43">OK, here what I found interesting was that taste is at four, and many respondents told me it's because of the taste of drinks, but also, in some cases, kissing is a big part of the clubbing experience.</s>
 <s id="44">These people I still do hang out with.</s>
 <s id="45">All right, and smoking.</s>
 <s id="46">Here I found touch is at [six], and one of the reasons is that smokers told me the sensation of holding a cigarette and bringing it up to your lips is a big part of the smoking experience, which shows, it's kind of scary to think how well cigarettes are designed by the manufacturers.</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">OK.</s>
  <s id="47.2">Now, what would the perfect experience look like on the five senses graph?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="48">It would, of course, be a horizontal line along the top.</s>
 <s id="49">Now you can see, not even as intense an experience as riding a motorbike comes close.</s>
 <s id="50">In fact, in the years that I gathered data, only one experience came close to being the perfect one.</s>
 <p id="p51">
  <s id="51.1">That is, of course, sex.</s>
  <s id="51.2">Great sex.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="52">Respondents said that great sex hits all of the five senses at an extreme level.</s>
 <s id="53">Here I'll quote one of my students who said, "Sex is so good, it's good even when it's bad."</s>
 <s id="54">So the five senses theory does help explain why sex is so good.</s>
 <s id="55">Now in the middle of all this five senses work, I suddenly remembered the solar-powered clocks project from my youth.</s>
 <s id="56">And I realized this theory also explains why Chris's clock is so much better than mine.</s>
 <s id="57">You see, my clock only focuses on sight, and a little bit of touch.</s>
 <s id="58">Here's Chris's clock.</s>
 <s id="59">It's the first clock ever that uses smell to tell the time.</s>
 <s id="60">In fact, in terms of the five senses, Chris's clock is a revolution.</s>
 <s id="61">And that's what this theory taught me about my field.</s>
 <s id="62">You see, up till now, us designers, we've mainly focused on making things look very pretty, and a little bit of touch, which means we've ignored the other three senses.</s>
 <s id="63">Chris's clock shows us that even raising just one of those other senses can make for a brilliant product.</s>
 <s id="64">So what if we started using the five senses theory in all of our designs?</s>
 <s id="65">Here's three quick ideas I came up with.</s>
 <s id="66">This is an iron, you know, for your clothes, to which I added a spraying mechanism, so you fill up the vial with your favorite scent, and your clothes will smell nicer, but hopefully it should also make the ironing experience more enjoyable.</s>
 <s id="67">We could call this "the perfumator."</s>
 <s id="68">All right, next.</s>
 <s id="69">So I brush my teeth twice a day, and what if we had a toothbrush that tastes like candy, and when the taste of candy ran out, you'd know it's time to change your toothbrush?</s>
 <s id="70">Finally, I have a thing for the keys on a flute or a clarinet.</s>
 <s id="71">It's not just the way they look, but I love the way they feel when you press down on them.</s>
 <s id="72">Now, I don't play the flute or the clarinet, so I decided to combine these keys with an instrument I do play: the television remote control.</s>
 <s id="73">Now, when we look at these three ideas together, you'll notice that the five senses theory doesn't only change the way we use these products but also the way they look.</s>
 <s id="74">So in conclusion, I've found the five senses theory to be a very useful tool in evaluating different experiences in my life, and then taking those best experiences and hopefully incorporating them into my designs.</s>
 <s id="75">Now, I realize the five senses isn't the only thing that makes life interesting.</s>
 <s id="76">There's also the six emotions and that elusive x-factor.</s>
 <s id="77">Maybe that could be the topic of my next talk.</s>
 <s id="78">Until then, please have fun using the five senses in your own lives and your own designs.</s>
 <s id="79">Oh, one last thing before I leave.</s>
 <s id="80">Here's the experience you all had while listening to the TED Talks.</s>
 <s id="81">However, it would be better if we could boost up a couple of the other senses like smell and taste.</s>
 <s id="82">And the best way to do that is with free candy.</s>
 <s id="83">You guys ready?</s>
 <s id="84">All right.</s>
 <s id="85">(Applause)</s>
</text>
