<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I remember when I first found out I was going to speak at a TED conference.</s>
 <s id="2">I ran across the hall to one of my classrooms to inform my students.</s>
 <s id="3">"Guess what, guys?</s>
 <s id="4">I've been asked to give a TED Talk."</s>
 <s id="5">The reaction wasn't one I quite expected.</s>
 <s id="6">The whole room went silent.</s>
 <p id="p7">
  <s id="7.1">"A TED Talk?</s>
  <s id="7.2">You mean, like the one you made us watch on grit?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="8">Or the one with the scientist that did this really awesome thing with robots?"</s>
 <s id="9">Muhammad asked.</s>
 <s id="10">"Yes, just like that."</s>
 <s id="11">"But Coach, those people are really important and smart."</s>
 <s id="12">(Laughter) "I know that."</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">"But Coach, why are you speaking?</s>
  <s id="13.2">You hate public speaking."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">"I do," I admitted, "But it's important that I speak about us, that I speak about your journeys, about my journey.</s>
 <s id="15">People need to know."</s>
 <s id="16">The students at the all-refugee school that I founded decided to end with some words of encouragement.</s>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">"Cool!</s>
  <s id="17.2">It better be good, Coach."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) There are 65.3 million people who have been forcibly displaced from their homes because of war or persecution.</s>
 <s id="19">The largest number, 11 million, are from Syria.</s>
 <s id="20">33,952 people flee their homes daily.</s>
 <s id="21">The vast majority remain in refugee camps, whose conditions cannot be defined as humane under anyone's definition.</s>
 <s id="22">We are participating in the degradation of humans.</s>
 <s id="23">Never have we had numbers this high.</s>
 <s id="24">This is the highest number of refugees since World War II.</s>
 <s id="25">Now, let me tell you why this issue is so important to me.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">I am an Arab.</s>
  <s id="26.2">I am an immigrant.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">I am a Muslim.</s>
 <s id="28">I've also spent the last 12 years of my life working with refugees.</s>
 <s id="29">Oh -- and I'm also gay.</s>
 <s id="30">It makes me really popular these days.</s>
 <s id="31">(Laughter) But I am the daughter of a refugee.</s>
 <s id="32">My grandmother fled Syria in 1964 during the first Assad regime.</s>
 <s id="33">She was three months pregnant when she packed up a suitcase, piled in her five children and drove to neighboring Jordan, not knowing what the future held for her and her family.</s>
 <s id="34">My grandfather decided to stay, not believing it was that bad.</s>
 <s id="35">He followed her a month later, after his brothers were tortured and his factory was taken over by the government.</s>
 <s id="36">They rebuilt their lives starting from scratch and eventually became independently wealthy Jordanian citizens.</s>
 <s id="37">I was born in Jordan 11 years later.</s>
 <s id="38">It was really important to my grandmother for us to know our history and our journey.</s>
 <s id="39">I was eight years old when she took me to visit my first refugee camp.</s>
 <s id="40">I didn't understand why.</s>
 <s id="41">I didn't know why it was so important to her for us to go.</s>
 <s id="42">I remember walking into the camp holding her hand, and her saying, "Go play with the kids," while she visited with the women in the camp.</s>
 <s id="43">I didn't want to.</s>
 <s id="44">These kids weren't like me.</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">They were poor.</s>
  <s id="45.2">They lived in a camp.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="46">I refused.</s>
 <s id="47">She knelt down beside me and firmly said, "Go.</s>
 <s id="48">And don't come back until you've played.</s>
 <s id="49">Don't ever think people are beneath you or that you have nothing to learn from others."</s>
 <s id="50">I reluctantly went.</s>
 <s id="51">I never wanted to disappoint my grandmother.</s>
 <s id="52">I returned a few hours later, having spent some time playing soccer with the kids in the camp.</s>
 <s id="53">We walked out of the camp, and I was excitedly telling her what a great time I had and how fantastic the kids were.</s>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">"Haram!"</s>
  <s id="54.2">I said in Arabic.</s>
  <s id="54.3">"Poor them."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">"Haram on us," she said, using the word's different meaning, that we were sinning.</s>
 <s id="56">"Don't feel sorry for them; believe in them."</s>
 <s id="57">It wasn't until I left my country of origin for the United States that I realized the impact of her words.</s>
 <s id="58">After my college graduation, I applied for and was granted political asylum, based on being a member of a social group.</s>
 <s id="59">Some people may not realize this, but you can still get the death penalty in some countries for being gay.</s>
 <s id="60">I had to give up my Jordanian citizenship.</s>
 <s id="61">That was the hardest decision I've ever had to make, but I had no other choice.</s>
 <s id="62">The point is, when you find yourself choosing between home and survival, the question "Where are you from?" becomes very loaded.</s>
 <s id="63">A Syrian woman who I recently met at a refugee camp in Greece articulated it best, when she recalled the exact moment she realized she had to flee Aleppo.</s>
 <s id="64">"I looked out the window and there was nothing.</s>
 <s id="65">It was all rubble.</s>
 <p id="p66">
  <s id="66.1">There were no stores, no streets, no schools.</s>
  <s id="66.2">Everything was gone.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="67">I had been in my apartment for months, listening to bombs drop and watching people die.</s>
 <s id="68">But I always thought it would get better, that no one could force me to leave, no one could take my home away from me.</s>
 <s id="69">And I don't know why it was that morning, but when I looked outside, I realized if I didn't leave, my three young children would die.</s>
 <s id="70">And so we left.</s>
 <s id="71">We left because we had to, not because we wanted to.</s>
 <s id="72">There was no choice," she said.</s>
 <s id="73">It's kind of hard to believe that you belong when you don't have a home, when your country of origin rejects you because of fear or persecution, or the city that you grew up in is completely destroyed.</s>
 <s id="74">I didn't feel like I had a home.</s>
 <s id="75">I was no longer a Jordanian citizen, but I wasn't American, either.</s>
 <s id="76">I felt a kind of loneliness that is still hard to put into words today.</s>
 <s id="77">After college, I desperately needed to find a place to call home.</s>
 <s id="78">I bounced around from state to state and eventually ended up in North Carolina.</s>
 <s id="79">Kindhearted people who felt sorry for me offered to pay rent or buy me a meal or a suit for my new interview.</s>
 <s id="80">It just made me feel more isolated and incapable.</s>
 <s id="81">It wasn't until I met Miss Sarah, a Southern Baptist who took me in at my lowest and gave me a job, that I started to believe in myself.</s>
 <s id="82">Miss Sarah owned a diner in the mountains of North Carolina.</s>
 <s id="83">I assumed, because of my privileged upbringing and my Seven Sister education, that she would ask me to manage the restaurant.</s>
 <s id="84">I was wrong.</s>
 <s id="85">I started off washing dishes, cleaning toilets and working the grill.</s>
 <s id="86">I was humbled; I was shown the value of hard work.</s>
 <s id="87">But most importantly, I felt valued and embraced.</s>
 <s id="88">I celebrated Christmas with her family, and she attempted to observe Ramadan with me.</s>
 <s id="89">I remember being very nervous about coming out to her -- after all, she was a Southern Baptist.</s>
 <s id="90">I sat on the couch next to her and I said, "Miss Sarah, you know that I'm gay."</s>
 <s id="91">Her response is one that I will never forget.</s>
 <p id="p92">
  <s id="92.1">"That's fine, honey.</s>
  <s id="92.2">Just don't be a slut."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="93">(Laughter) (Applause) I eventually moved to Atlanta, still trying to find my home.</s>
 <s id="94">My journey took a strange turn three years later, after I met a group of refugee kids playing soccer outside.</s>
 <s id="95">I'd made a wrong turn into this apartment complex, and I saw these kids outside playing soccer.</s>
 <s id="96">They were playing barefoot with a raggedy soccer ball and rocks set up as goals.</s>
 <s id="97">I watched them for about an hour, and after that I was smiling.</s>
 <s id="98">The boys reminded me of home.</s>
 <s id="99">They reminded me of the way I grew up playing soccer in the streets of Jordan, with my brothers and cousins.</s>
 <s id="100">I eventually joined their game.</s>
 <s id="101">They were a little skeptical about letting me join it, because according to them, girls don't know how to play.</s>
 <s id="102">But obviously I did.</s>
 <s id="103">I asked them if they had ever played on a team.</s>
 <s id="104">They said they hadn't, but that they would love to.</s>
 <s id="105">I gradually won them over, and we formed our first team.</s>
 <s id="106">This group of kids would give me a crash course in refugees, poverty and humanity.</s>
 <s id="107">Three brothers from Afghanistan -- Roohullah, Noorullah and Zabiullah -- played a major role in that.</s>
 <s id="108">I showed up late to practice one day to find the field completely deserted.</s>
 <s id="109">I was really worried.</s>
 <s id="110">My team loved to practice.</s>
 <s id="111">It wasn't like them to miss practice.</s>
 <s id="112">I got out of my car, and two kids ran out from behind a dumpster, waving their hands frantically.</s>
 <p id="p113">
  <s id="113.1">"Coach, Rooh got beat up.</s>
  <s id="113.2">He got jumped.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="114">There was blood everywhere."</s>
 <p id="p115">
  <s id="115.1">"What do you mean?</s>
  <s id="115.2">What do you mean he got beat up?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="116">"These bad kids came and beat him up, Coach.</s>
 <p id="p117">
  <s id="117.1">Everybody left.</s>
  <s id="117.2">They were all scared."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="118">We hopped into my car and drove over to Rooh's apartment.</s>
 <s id="119">I knocked on the door, and Noor opened it.</s>
 <p id="p120">
  <s id="120.1">"Where's Rooh?</s>
  <s id="120.2">I need to talk to him, see if he's OK."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p121">
  <s id="121.1">"He's in his room, Coach.</s>
  <s id="121.2">He's refusing to come out."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="122">I knocked on the door.</s>
 <p id="p123">
  <s id="123.1">"Rooh, come on out.</s>
  <s id="123.2">I need to talk to you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="124">I need to see if you're OK or if we need to go to the hospital."</s>
 <s id="125">He came out.</s>
 <s id="126">He had a big gash on his head, a split lip, and he was physically shaken.</s>
 <s id="127">I was looking at him, and I asked the boys to call for their mom, because I needed to go to the hospital with him.</s>
 <s id="128">They called for their mom.</s>
 <s id="129">She came out.</s>
 <s id="130">I had my back turned to her, and she started screaming in Farsi.</s>
 <s id="131">The boys fell to the ground laughing.</s>
 <s id="132">I was very confused, because there was nothing funny about this.</s>
 <s id="133">They explained to me that she said, "You told me your coach was a Muslim and a woman."</s>
 <s id="134">From behind, I didn't appear to be either to her.</s>
 <s id="135">(Laughter) "I am Muslim," I said, turning to her.</s>
 <s id="136">"Ašhadu ʾan lā ʾilāha ʾilla (A)llāh," reciting the Muslim declaration of faith.</s>
 <s id="137">Confused, and perhaps maybe a little bit reassured, she realized that yes, I, this American-acting, shorts-wearing, non-veiled woman, was indeed a Muslim.</s>
 <s id="138">Their family had fled the Taliban.</s>
 <s id="139">Hundreds of people in their village were murdered.</s>
 <s id="140">Their father was taken in by the Taliban, only to return a few months later, a shell of the man he once was.</s>
 <s id="141">The family escaped to Pakistan, and the two older boys, age eight and 10 at the time, wove rugs for 10 hours a day to provide for their family.</s>
 <s id="142">They were so excited when they found out that they had been approved to resettle in the United States, making them the lucky 0.1 percent who get to do that.</s>
 <s id="143">They had hit the jackpot.</s>
 <s id="144">Their story is not unique.</s>
 <s id="145">Every refugee family I have worked with has had some version of this.</s>
 <s id="146">I work with kids who have seen their mothers raped, their fathers' fingers sliced off.</s>
 <s id="147">One kid saw a bullet put in his grandmother's head, because she refused to let the rebels take him to be a child soldier.</s>
 <s id="148">Their journeys are haunting.</s>
 <s id="149">But what I get to see every day is hope, resilience, determination, a love of life and appreciation for being able to rebuild their lives.</s>
 <s id="150">I was at the boys' apartment one night, when the mom came home after cleaning 18 hotel rooms in one day.</s>
 <s id="151">She sat down, and Noor rubbed her feet, saying that he was going to take care of her once he graduated.</s>
 <s id="152">She smiled from exhaustion.</s>
 <p id="p153">
  <s id="153.1">"God is good.</s>
  <s id="153.2">Life is good.</s>
  <s id="153.3">We are lucky to be here."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="154">In the last two years, we have seen an escalating anti-refugee sentiment.</s>
 <s id="155">It's global.</s>
 <s id="156">The numbers continue to grow because we do nothing to prevent it and nothing to stop it.</s>
 <s id="157">The issue shouldn't be stopping refugees from coming into our countries.</s>
 <s id="158">The issue should be not forcing them to leave their own.</s>
 <s id="159">(Applause) Sorry.</s>
 <s id="160">(Applause) How much more suffering, how much more suffering must we take?</s>
 <s id="161">How many more people need to be forced out of their homes before we say, "Enough!"?</s>
 <s id="162">A hundred million?</s>
 <s id="163">Not only do we shame, blame and reject them for atrocities that they had absolutely nothing to do with, we re-traumatize them, when we're supposed to be welcoming them into our countries.</s>
 <s id="164">We strip them of their dignity and treat them like criminals.</s>
 <s id="165">I had a student in my office a couple of weeks ago.</s>
 <s id="166">She's originally from Iraq.</s>
 <s id="167">She broke down crying.</s>
 <s id="168">"Why do they hate us?"</s>
 <s id="169">"Who hates you?"</s>
 <s id="170">"Everyone; everyone hates us because we are refugees, because we are Muslim."</s>
 <s id="171">In the past, I was able to reassure my students that the majority of the world does not hate refugees.</s>
 <s id="172">But this time I couldn't.</s>
 <s id="173">I couldn't explain to her why someone tried to rip off her mother's hijab when they were grocery shopping, or why a player on an opposing team called her a terrorist and told her to go back where she came from.</s>
 <s id="174">I couldn't reassure her that her father's ultimate life sacrifice by serving in the United States military as an interpreter would make her more valued as an American citizen.</s>
 <s id="175">We take in so few refugees worldwide.</s>
 <s id="176">We resettle less than 0.1 percent.</s>
 <s id="177">That 0.1 percent benefits us more than them.</s>
 <s id="178">It dumbfounds me how the word "refugee" is considered something to be dirty, something to be ashamed of.</s>
 <s id="179">They have nothing to be ashamed of.</s>
 <s id="180">We have seen advances in every aspect of our lives -- except our humanity.</s>
 <s id="181">There are 65.3 million people who have been forced out of their homes because of war -- the largest number in history.</s>
 <s id="182">We are the ones who should be ashamed.</s>
 <s id="183">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="184">(Applause)</s>
</text>
