<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">What is love?</s>
 <s id="2">Seriously, though, what is it?</s>
 <s id="3">What is love?</s>
 <s id="4">A verb?</s>
 <s id="5">A noun?</s>
 <s id="6">A universal truth?</s>
 <s id="7">An ideal?</s>
 <s id="8">A common thread of all religions?</s>
 <s id="9">A cult?</s>
 <s id="10">A neurological phenomenon?</s>
 <s id="11">There's no shortage of answers.</s>
 <s id="12">Some are all-encompassing.</s>
 <s id="13">It conquers all.</s>
 <s id="14">It's all you need.</s>
 <s id="15">It's all there is.</s>
 <s id="16">These are all comparisons, though, ways of defining it by contrast, by saying it's more important than all other things, but is it?</s>
 <s id="17">Sure, love matters more than your standard turkey sandwich, but does it matter more than shelter?</s>
 <s id="18">Or sanity?</s>
 <s id="19">Or an exceptional turkey sandwich?</s>
 <s id="20">No matter your answer, you're just ranking it, not defining it.</s>
 <s id="21">Another challenge to defining love is we often try to do so while falling into it or out of it.</s>
 <s id="22">Would you trust someone who just won the lottery to accurately define the concept of currency?</s>
 <s id="23">Or, I don't know, ask a guy to define bears while he's fending them off?</s>
 <s id="24">Or is romance not like winning the lottery?</s>
 <s id="25">Are break ups not like bear attacks?</s>
 <s id="26">Bad comparisons?</s>
 <s id="27">That's my point.</s>
 <s id="28">I'm not thinking right because I'm in love, so ha!</s>
 <s id="29">Taking a step back, or taking a cold shower, whatever, love is potentially the most intensely thought about thing in all of human history.</s>
 <s id="30">And despite centuries upon centuries of obsession, it still overwhelms us.</s>
 <s id="31">Some say it's a feeling, a magical emotion, a feeling for someone like you've never felt before.</s>
 <s id="32">But feelings are fluid, not very concrete foundation for a definition.</s>
 <s id="33">Sometimes you hate the person you love.</s>
 <s id="34">Plus, come on, you've felt feelings like it before, sort of in miniature.</s>
 <s id="35">Your relationships with your family shape your relationships with partners.</s>
 <s id="36">And your love for your partner may be in its own dynamic relationship, healthy or totally weird, with the love of your parents and siblings.</s>
 <s id="37">Love is also a set of behaviors we associate with the feeling: Holding hands, kissing, hugging, public displays of affection, dating, marriage, having kids, or just sex.</s>
 <s id="38">But these loving actions can be subjective or culturally relative.</s>
 <s id="39">You may love or be someone who can't have kids or doesn't want to, who believes in marriage but also in divorce, who's from a culture where people don't really date the way we think of dating, or who just doesn't want to make out on the bus.</s>
 <s id="40">But if love is a thing that we can define, then how can it mean opposite things for so many people?</s>
 <s id="41">So, maybe love's just all in your head, a personal mystery winding through your neural pathways and lighting up pleasing, natural rewards in your nervous system.</s>
 <s id="42">Perhaps these rewards are addictive.</s>
 <s id="43">Perhaps love is a temporary or permanent addiction to a person, just like a person can be addicted to a drug.</s>
 <s id="44">I don't mean to be edgy like some pop song.</s>
 <s id="45">Evidence shows that chemicals in your brain stimulated by another person can make you develop a habit for that person.</s>
 <s id="46">The person comes to satisfy a physiological craving, and you want more.</s>
 <s id="47">But then sometimes, slowly or suddenly, you don't.</s>
 <s id="48">You've fallen out of love, become unaddicted, for a spell.</s>
 <s id="49">What happened?</s>
 <s id="50">Does one develop a tolerance or hit a limit?</s>
 <s id="51">Why do some lovers stay addicted to each other their entire lives?</s>
 <s id="52">Perhaps to create new lives, to proliferate their species?</s>
 <s id="53">Maybe love is just human DNA's optimal method for bringing about its own replication.</s>
 <s id="54">There are evolutionary arguments regarding every human mating behavior, from how we display ourselves to potential mates, to how we treat each other in relationships, to how we raise kids.</s>
 <s id="55">Thus, some argue that the feeling you think you feel in your soul is just biology's way to make you continue our species.</s>
 <s id="56">Nature has selected you to have crushes on hotties, just like it makes monkeys have crushes on hot monkeys, and biology marches on.</s>
 <s id="57">But is that all love is?</s>
 <s id="58">Or, perhaps worse, is it just a construct, some fake concept we all convince each other to try to live up to for a fake sense of purpose?</s>
 <s id="59">Maybe it is a construct, but let's be more precise about what a construct is because love is constructed from reality: Our experiences, feelings, brain chemistry, cultural expectations, our lives.</s>
 <s id="60">And this edifice can be viewed through countless dimensions: scientific, emotional, historical, spiritual, legal, or just personal.</s>
 <s id="61">If no two people are the same, no two people's love is the same either.</s>
 <s id="62">So, in every loving relationship, there's a lot to talk about and partners should be open to that, or the relationship probably won't last.</s>
 <s id="63">Love is always up for discussion and, sure, under construction.</s>
 <s id="64">So, if we can't define it, that's a good sign.</s>
 <s id="65">It means we're all still making it.</s>
 <s id="66">Wait, I didn't mean, you know what I meant.</s>
</text>
