<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">According to legend, once every thousand years a host of sea monsters emerges from the depths to demand tribute from the floating city of Atlantartica.</s>
 <s id="2">As the ruler of the city, you’d always dismissed the stories… until today, when 7 Leviathan Lords rose out of the roiling waters and surrounded your city.</s>
 <s id="3">Each commands 10 giant kraken, and each kraken is accompanied by 12 mermites.</s>
 <s id="4">Your city’s puny army is hopelessly outmatched.</s>
 <s id="5">You think back to the legends.</s>
 <s id="6">In the stories, the ruler of the city saved his people by feeding the creatures a ransom of pearls.</s>
 <s id="7">The pearls would be split equally between the leviathans lords.</s>
 <s id="8">Each leviathan would then divide its share into 11 equal piles, keeping one, and giving the other 10 to their kraken commanders.</s>
 <s id="9">Each kraken would then divide its share into 13 equal piles, keeping one, and distributing the other twelve to their mermite minions.</s>
 <s id="10">If any one of these divisions left an unequal pile or leftover pearl, the monsters would pull everyone to the bottom of the sea.</s>
 <s id="11">Such was the fate of your fabled sister city.</s>
 <s id="12">You rush to the ancient treasure room and find five chests, each containing a precisely counted number of pearls prepared by your ancestors for exactly this purpose.</s>
 <s id="13">Each of the chests bears a number telling how many pearls it contains.</s>
 <s id="14">Unfortunately, the symbols they used to write digits 1,000 years ago have changed with time, and you don’t know how to read the ancient numbers.</s>
 <s id="15">With hundreds of thousands of pearls in each chest, there’s no time to recount.</s>
 <s id="16">One of these chests will save your city and the rest will lead to its certain doom.</s>
 <s id="17">Which do you choose?</s>
 <s id="18">Pause the video to figure it out yourself.</s>
 <s id="19">Answer in 3 Answer in 2 Answer in 1 There isn’t enough information to decode the ancient Atlantartican numeral system.</s>
 <s id="20">But all hope is not lost, because there’s another piece of information those symbols contain: patterns.</s>
 <s id="21">If we can find a matching pattern in arabic numerals, we can still pick the right chest.</s>
 <s id="22">Let’s take stock of what we know.</s>
 <s id="23">A quantity of pearls that can appease the sea monsters must be divisible by 7, 11, and 13.</s>
 <s id="24">Rather than trying out numbers at random, let’s examine ones that have this property and see if there are any patterns that unite them.</s>
 <s id="25">Being divisible by 7, 11, and 13 means that our number must be a multiple of 7, 11, and 13.</s>
 <s id="26">Those three numbers are all prime, so multiplying them together will give us their least common multiple: 1001.</s>
 <s id="27">That’s a useful starting place because we now know that any viable offering to the sea monsters must be a multiple of 1001.</s>
 <s id="28">Let’s try multiplying it by a three digit number, just to get a feel for what we might get.</s>
 <s id="29">If we try 861 times 1001, we get 861,861, and we see something similar with other examples.</s>
 <s id="30">It’s a peculiar pattern.</s>
 <s id="31">Why would multiplying a three-digit number by 1001 end up giving you two copies of that number, written one after the other?</s>
 <s id="32">Breaking down the multiplication problem can give us the answer.</s>
 <s id="33">1001 times any number x is equal to 1000x + x.</s>
 <s id="34">For example, 725 times 1000 is 725,000, and 725 x 1 is 725.</s>
 <s id="35">So 725 x 1001 will be the sum of those two numbers: 725,725.</s>
 <s id="36">And there’s nothing special about 725.</s>
 <s id="37">Pick any three-digit number, and your final product will have that many thousands, plus one more.</s>
 <s id="38">Even though you don’t know how to read the numbers on the chests, you can read which pattern of digits represents a number divisible by 1001.</s>
 <s id="39">As with many problems, trying concrete examples can give you an intuition for behavior that may at first look abstract and mysterious.</s>
 <s id="40">The monsters accept your ransom and swim back down to the depths for another thousand years.</s>
 <s id="41">With the proper planning, that should give you plenty of time to prepare for their inevitable return.</s>
</text>
