<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Sings) Water Boy (Guitar strum) where are you hidin'?</s>
 <s id="2">(Guitar strum) If you don't come right here, I'm gonna tell your pa on you.</s>
 <s id="3">(Guitar strum) There ain't no hammer -- (Guitar strum) that's on this mountain (Guitar strum) That ring like mine, boy -- (Guitar strum) that ring like mine.</s>
 <s id="4">(Guitar strum) I'm gonna bust this rock, boy -- (Guitar strum) from here to Macon.</s>
 <s id="5">(Guitar strum) All the way to the jail, boy -- (Guitar strum) all the way to the jail.</s>
 <s id="6">(Guitar strum) You jack of diamonds -- (Music) you jack of diamonds I know you of old boy, I know you of old.</s>
 <s id="7">You done robbed my pocket, you done robbed my pocket of silver and gold, boy, of silver and gold.</s>
 <s id="8">Water Boy, where are you hidin'?</s>
 <s id="9">If you don't come right here, I'm gonna tell your pa on you.</s>
 <s id="10">There ain't no hammer that's on this mountain that ring like mine, boy, that ring like mine.</s>
 <s id="11">I'm gonna bust this rock, boy, from here to Macon.</s>
 <s id="12">All the way to the jail, boy, all the way to the jail.</s>
 <s id="13">Water Boy (Guitar strum) where are you hidin'?</s>
 <s id="14">(Guitar strum) If you don't come right here, if you don't come right here, if you don't come right here, I'm gonna tell your pa on you.</s>
 <s id="15">(Guitar strum) (Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="16">That was a song based on numerous work songs, and it was arranged by Odetta, a hero of mine.</s>
 <s id="17">And this next song, well, I do a lot of historical music, starting with the Carolina Chocolate Drops and continuing on in my solo endeavors.</s>
 <s id="18">And I believe that knowing your history as a musician is super important -- it's important as a person, it's important as a country, it's important as a people.</s>
 <s id="19">So I read a lot about where the music comes from and where this country comes from.</s>
 <s id="20">I've been reading a lot about the Civil War and about slavery.</s>
 <s id="21">And it's really tough.</s>
 <s id="22">You know?</s>
 <s id="23">It's really tough reading.</s>
 <s id="24">And so as an artist, what I do with all that emotion, reading these people's stories, not just, "Oh, slavery was terrible."</s>
 <s id="25">Yes, it was.</s>
 <s id="26">But it's reading individual narratives of how it was for these people.</s>
 <s id="27">You know?</s>
 <s id="28">Then it's like, "Yeah, that could've been me."</s>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">And it is people now.</s>
  <s id="29.2">You know?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">So what you do with all that emotion is you've got to do something with it.</s>
 <s id="31">As an artist, I write.</s>
 <s id="32">So I wrote a song based on some of those narratives that I read, and it's called, "Come Love Come."</s>
 <s id="33">We're going to do it for you now.</s>
 <s id="34">(Claps) (Sings) Come love come, the road lies low, the way is long and hard, I know.</s>
 <s id="35">Come love come, the road lies free, I'll wait for you in Tennessee.</s>
 <s id="36">(Music) (Sings) When I was four, my loving mam was cornered by the boss's man.</s>
 <s id="37">She turned her head and got struck down, they buried her in the cold, cold ground.</s>
 <s id="38">Come love come, the road lies low, the way is long and hard, I know.</s>
 <s id="39">Come love come, the road lies free, I'll wait for you in Tennessee.</s>
 <s id="40">(Music) When I was 12, my father dear was strong of arm and free of fear until the day he raised his hand, then he was sold to Alabama.</s>
 <s id="41">Come love come, the road lies low, the way is long and hard, I know.</s>
 <s id="42">Come love come, the road lies free, I'll wait for you in Tennessee.</s>
 <s id="43">(Music) When I was 16, found my bloom and found my man, we jumped the broom.</s>
 <s id="44">We pledged each other the rest of our lives and on Saturday nights we were man and wife.</s>
 <s id="45">Come love come, the road lies low, the way is long and hard, I know.</s>
 <s id="46">Come love come, the road lies free, I'll wait for you in Tennessee.</s>
 <s id="47">(Music) When I was 18, bugles called and boys in blue came o'er the wall.</s>
 <s id="48">I took my chance and followed free, they led the way to Tennessee.</s>
 <s id="49">Come love come, the road lies low, the way is long and hard, I know.</s>
 <s id="50">Come love come, the road lies free, I'll wait for you in Tennessee.</s>
 <s id="51">(Music) Now here I sit in a tiny shack with 13 others at my back.</s>
 <s id="52">I've sent you word, so all I can do is wait and wait and wait and wait and wait and wait for you.</s>
 <s id="53">Come love come, the road lies low, the way is long and hard, I know.</s>
 <s id="54">Come love come, the road lies free, I'll wait for you in Tennessee.</s>
 <s id="55">Come love come, the road lies low, the way is long and hard, I know.</s>
 <s id="56">Come love come, the road lies free, I'll wait for you in Tennessee.</s>
 <s id="57">Oh, oh, oh.</s>
 <s id="58">Whoa ... oh I'll wait for you.</s>
 <s id="59">I'll wait for you.</s>
 <s id="60">I'll wait for you I'll wait for you.</s>
 <s id="61">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="62">So, with the dark you have to have the light.</s>
 <s id="63">And in the African-American community, it's been the work of many hundreds of years to find a way to lift ourselves up.</s>
 <s id="64">So I'm going to end with a couple of tunes from Sister Rosetta Tharpe, one of the more influential American music figures that most of you probably never heard of.</s>
 <s id="65">If you have, I'm so happy.</s>
 <s id="66">She's one of the innovators of rock 'n' roll guitar, and one of the first crossover artists from gospel to secular.</s>
 <s id="67">She's an incredibly important figure, and I'm going to talk about her whenever I can.</s>
 <s id="68">So these are a couple of her tunes.</s>
 <s id="69">And don't worry -- you're going to get your chance to sing.</s>
 <s id="70">(Music) (Sings) Look down, look down that lonesome road before you travel on.</s>
 <s id="71">Look up, look up and greet your maker, for Gabriel blows his horn.</s>
 <s id="72">Weary totin' such a load, goin' down that lonesome road.</s>
 <s id="73">Look down that lonesome road, before you travel on.</s>
 <s id="74">Look down, look down that lonesome road before you travel on.</s>
 <s id="75">Look up, look up and greet your maker, for Gabriel blows his horn.</s>
 <s id="76">Weary totin' such a load, goin' down that lonesome road.</s>
 <s id="77">Look down, look down, look down, look down that lonesome road before you travel on.</s>
 <s id="78">Up above my head up above my head I hear music in the air music in the air.</s>
 <s id="79">Up above my head up above my head I hear music in the air I hear music in the air.</s>
 <s id="80">Up above my head up above my head I hear music in the air music in the air and I really do believe I really do believe there's a Heaven somewhere.</s>
 <s id="81">Up above my head up above my head I hear singin' in the air singin' in the air.</s>
 <s id="82">Up above my head up above my head I hear singin' in the air I hear singin' in the air.</s>
 <s id="83">Up above my head up above my head I hear singin' in the air singin' in the air and I really do believe I really do believe there's a Heaven somewhere.</s>
 <s id="84">(Speaks) All right now, guitar man!</s>
 <s id="85">(Guitar music) That's Hubby Jenkins, y'all.</s>
 <s id="86">(Sings) Up above my head up above my head I hear shoutin' in the air shoutin' in the air.</s>
 <s id="87">Up above my head up above my head I hear shoutin' in the air I hear shoutin' in the air.</s>
 <s id="88">Up above my head up above my head I hear shoutin' in the air, that's right, and I really do believe I really do believe there's a heaven somewhere.</s>
 <s id="89">(Speaks) All right now, give me some of that bass.</s>
 <s id="90">(Bass solo) Yeah!</s>
 <s id="91">Woo!</s>
 <s id="92">Jason Sypher on the bass.</s>
 <s id="93">Jamie Dick on those drums.</s>
 <s id="94">All right now, I'm running out of time.</s>
 <s id="95">So it's time for y'all to sing.</s>
 <s id="96">This is the call-and-response.</s>
 <s id="97">I call, you respond.</s>
 <s id="98">There are so many songs like this, y'all know how it goes, don't you?</s>
 <s id="99">You're going to sing along?</s>
 <s id="100">I said, are you going to sing along?</s>
 <s id="101">Audience members: Yes!</s>
 <s id="102">Rhiannon Giddens: Here we go!</s>
 <s id="103">(Sings) Up above my head AM: up above my head RG: music in the air AM: music in the air.</s>
 <s id="104">RG: up above my head AM: up above my head RG: music in the air AM: music in the air RG: up above my head AM: up above my head RG: music in the air AM: music in the air RG: and I really do believe I really do believe there's a heaven somewhere.</s>
 <s id="105">One more time!</s>
 <s id="106">Up above my head AM: up above my head RG: I hear music in the air AM: music in the air.</s>
 <s id="107">RG: Up above my head AM: up above my head RG: I hear music in the air AM: music in the air.</s>
 <s id="108">RG: Up above my head AM: up above my head RG: I hear music in the air AM: music in the air RG: and I really do believe I really do believe there's a heaven somewhere.</s>
 <s id="109">I said I really do believe I really do believe there's a heaven somewhere.</s>
 <s id="110">Heaven somewhere.</s>
 <s id="111">(Holds note) (Applause and cheers) (Music ends) (Applause)</s>
</text>
