<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Now, since this is TEDGlobal, who can tell me what this is called in French?</s>
 <s id="2">I see you're all up on the history of hurdy-gurdy -- "vielle à roue."</s>
 <s id="3">And in Spanish, "zanfona."</s>
 <s id="4">And in Italian, "ghironda," okay?</s>
 <s id="5">Hurdy-gurdy, or wheel fiddle.</s>
 <s id="6">So, these are the different kinds and shapes of the hurdy-gurdy.</s>
 <s id="7">The hurdy-gurdy is the only musical instrument that uses a crank to turn a wheel to rub strings, like the bow of a violin, to produce music.</s>
 <s id="8">It has three different kinds of strings.</s>
 <s id="9">The first string is the drone string, which plays a continuous sound like the bagpipe.</s>
 <s id="10">The second string is a melody string, which is played with a wooden keyboard tuned like a piano.</s>
 <s id="11">And the third string is pretty innovative.</s>
 <s id="12">It's also the only instrument that uses this kind of technique.</s>
 <s id="13">It activates what's called the buzzing bridge, or the dog.</s>
 <s id="14">When I turn the crank and I apply pressure, it makes a sound like a barking dog.</s>
 <s id="15">So all of this is pretty innovative, if you consider that the hurdy-gurdy appeared about a thousand years ago and it took two people to play it; one to turn the crank, and another person -- yes -- to play the melody by physically pulling up large wooden pegs.</s>
 <s id="16">Luckily, all of this changed a couple of centuries later.</s>
 <s id="17">So, one person could actually play and almost -- this is pretty heavy -- carry the hurdy-gurdy.</s>
 <s id="18">The hurdy-gurdy has been used, historically, through the centuries in mostly dance music because of the uniqueness of the melody combined with the acoustic boombox here.</s>
 <s id="19">And today, the hurdy-gurdy is used in all sorts of music -- traditional folk music, dance, contemporary and world music -- in the U.K., in France, in Spain and in Italy.</s>
 <s id="20">And this kind of hurdy-gurdy takes anywhere from three to five years [to order and receive it].</s>
 <s id="21">It's made by specialized luthiers, also in Europe.</s>
 <s id="22">And it's very difficult to tune.</s>
 <s id="23">So without further ado, would you like to hear it?</s>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">(Audience: Yes.)</s>
  <s id="24.2">Caroline Phillips: I didn't hear you.</s>
  <s id="24.3">Would you like to hear it?</s>
  <s id="24.4">(Audience: Yes!)</s>
  <s id="24.5">CP: Okay.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="25">There I go.</s>
 <s id="26">I'd like to sing in Basque, which is the language spoken in the Basque Country where I live, in the region in France and Spain.</s>
 <s id="27">(Music) [Basque] (Music) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="28">(Applause) This is a song that I wrote based on traditional Basque rhythms.</s>
 <s id="29">And this is a song that has a kind of a Celtic feel.</s>
 <p id="p30">
  <s id="30.1">(Music) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="30.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="31">(Applause)</s>
</text>
