<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In 2008, archeologists uncovered two 9,000-year old skeletons.</s>
 <s id="2">There’s no definitive way of knowing what killed these ancient people, but we do know their bones were infected by an all too familiar bacterium.</s>
 <s id="3">The ancient Greeks knew its consumptive effects as phthisis; the Incans called it chaky oncay; and the English called it tuberculosis.</s>
 <s id="4">Today, tuberculosis, or TB, is still one of the world’s biggest infectious killers, causing more deaths than malaria or even HIV and AIDS.</s>
 <s id="5">But what exactly is this disease, and how has this pathogen persisted for so long?</s>
 <s id="6">Typically, TB bacteria called mycobacterium tuberculosis, are airborne.</s>
 <s id="7">They travel into our airways and infect our lungs.</s>
 <s id="8">Here, immune cells called macrophages rush to the infection site, attempting to absorb and break down the bacterial invaders.</s>
 <s id="9">In many cases, this response is enough to remove the bacteria.</s>
 <s id="10">But in individuals with other medical conditions– ranging from malnutrition and HIV to diabetes and pregnancy –the immune response may not be strong enough to destroy the intruder.</s>
 <s id="11">If so, mycobacterium tuberculosis will reproduce inside those macrophages, and form colonies in the surrounding lung tissue.</s>
 <s id="12">As they infect more cells, the bacteria employ cell-degrading enzymes that destroy the infected tissue, triggering chest pain, and causing patients to cough up blood.</s>
 <s id="13">The damage to the lungs leads to oxygen deprivation.</s>
 <s id="14">This begins a flood of hormonal changes– including a decrease in appetite and iron production.</s>
 <s id="15">From here, microbes can spread to the skeletal system, causing back pain and difficulty moving; to the kidneys and intestines, causing abdominal pain; and to the brain, causing headaches and even impaired consciousness.</s>
 <s id="16">These symptoms produce the classic image of TB: weight loss, a hacking, bloody cough, and ashen skin.</s>
 <s id="17">This ghostly appearance earned TB the title of the ‘White Plague’ in Victorian-era England.</s>
 <s id="18">During this period, tuberculosis was considered a ‘romantic disease,' because it tended to affect poverty- stricken artists and poets– those with weaker immune systems.</s>
 <s id="19">TB’s outward symptoms even helped fuel the popular myth of vampirism.</s>
 <s id="20">In spite of– or perhaps because of these less than scientific concerns, this period also marked the first strides toward curing TB.</s>
 <s id="21">In 1882, the German physician Robert Koch identified the disease’s bacterial origins.</s>
 <s id="22">13 years later, physicist Wilhelm Roentgen  discovered the X-ray, enabling physicians to diagnose and track its progression through the body.</s>
 <s id="23">These techniques allowed researchers to develop reliable and effective vaccines– first for smallpox, and again in 1921, when scientists developed the BCG vaccine to battle TB.</s>
 <s id="24">These developments laid the groundwork for the modern field of antibiotics– currently home to our most effective TB treatments.</s>
 <s id="25">But, antibiotics fail to address a major diagnostic complication: about 90% of people infected with TB don’t show any symptoms.</s>
 <s id="26">In these latent infections, the TB bacterium may be dormant, only activating when someone’s immune system is too weak to mount a defense.</s>
 <s id="27">This makes TB much harder to diagnose.</s>
 <s id="28">And even when properly identified, traditional treatments can take up to 9 months, requiring multiple drugs and a high potential for side effects.</s>
 <s id="29">This discourages people from finishing the full course, and partial treatment enables bacteria to develop resistance to these drugs.</s>
 <s id="30">Today, the disease is still prevalent in 30 countries, most of which face other health crises that exacerbate TB and trigger latent cases.</s>
 <s id="31">Worse still, accessing treatment can be difficult in many of these countries, and the stigma towards TB can discourage people from getting the help they need.</s>
 <s id="32">Health experts agree we need to develop better diagnostics, faster acting antibiotics, and more effective vaccines.</s>
 <s id="33">Researchers have already developed a urine test that yields results in 12 hours, as well as a new oral treatment that could cut treatment time by 75%.</s>
 <s id="34">Hopefully, with advancements like these, we’ll finally be able to make TB exclusively a thing of the past.</s>
</text>
