<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Music) Rainn Wilson: It takes its toll, being alone.</s>
 <s id="2">I'm a little bit lost, and it's finally time to make a real connection.</s>
 <s id="3">Who am I?</s>
 <s id="4">(Drums) I'm a single white male, 45 years of age.</s>
 <s id="5">I love animals.</s>
 <s id="6">Gainfully employed.</s>
 <s id="7">I'm a people person.</s>
 <s id="8">I keep fit.</s>
 <s id="9">Who am I looking for?</s>
 <s id="10">I'm looking for my idea mate.</s>
 <s id="11">Are you that idea that matches with who I really am?</s>
 <s id="12">(Video) Ron Finley: How would you feel if you had no access to healthy food?</s>
 <s id="13">Gardening is the most therapeutic and defiant act you can do.</s>
 <s id="14">RW: Wow, we sure are getting our fingers dirty for a first date, huh?</s>
 <s id="15">RF: Gardening is the most therapeutic and defiant act you can do.</s>
 <s id="16">People in these areas -- they're exposed to crappy food.</s>
 <s id="17">I want people to know that growing your own food is like printing your own money.</s>
 <s id="18">RW: You're like a food superhero!</s>
 <s id="19">RF: Food is the problem and food is the solution.</s>
 <s id="20">(Music) Erin McKean: I'm a lexicographer.</s>
 <s id="21">My job is to put every word possible into the dictionary.</s>
 <s id="22">RW: I love words, too -- just as much as any lexi-ta-tographer.</s>
 <s id="23">What if you love a word that you've just made up, like -- I don't know -- "scuberfinkles"?</s>
 <s id="24">Beau Lotto: Do you think you see reality?</s>
 <s id="25">RW: Well, I'm a little nearsighted, but yeah.</s>
 <s id="26">BL: Well, you can't -- I mean, your brain has no access to this world.</s>
 <s id="27">In fact, even the sensory information that your eyes are receiving, your ears are receiving, is completely meaningless because it could mean anything.</s>
 <s id="28">That tree could be a large object far away or a small object up close, and your brain has no way of knowing.</s>
 <s id="29">RW: Once I thought I saw Bigfoot but it was just a German shepherd.</s>
 <s id="30">Isabel Behncke Izquierdo: Bonobos are, together with chimpanzees, your closest living relatives.</s>
 <s id="31">Bonobos have frequent and promiscuous sex to manage conflict and solve social issues.</s>
 <s id="32">RW: I'm just curious: Do we have any conflict that needs managing or social issues to resolve?</s>
 <s id="33">IBI: Remember -- you're on a date with my idea, not me.</s>
 <s id="34">Jane McGonigal: This is the face of someone who, against all odds, is on the verge of an epic win.</s>
 <s id="35">RW: An epic win?</s>
 <s id="36">JM: An epic win is an outcome so extraordinarily positive, you didn't even know it was possible until you achieved it.</s>
 <s id="37">You're not making the face.</s>
 <s id="38">You're making the "I'm not good at life" face.</s>
 <s id="39">RW: Arthur, I want to be really honest with you.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">I am seeing other ideas.</s>
  <s id="40.2">OK?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="41">I'm dating around.</s>
 <s id="42">That's the situation.</s>
 <s id="43">Arthur Benjamin: I'd say this: Mathematics is not just solving for x, it's also figuring out why.</s>
 <s id="44">RW: Do you want to get some pie?</s>
 <s id="45">AB: Pi?</s>
 <s id="46">3.14159265358979 -- Reggie Watts: If we're going to do something, we've got to just make a decision.</s>
 <s id="47">Because without a decision we're left powerless.</s>
 <s id="48">Without power, we have nothing to supply the chain of those who are truly curious to solve all of our current conditions.</s>
 <s id="49">RW: And, "If you choose not to decide, you still have made a choice" -- Rush.</s>
 <s id="50">JM: Yes!</s>
 <s id="51">This is the face we need to see on millions of problem solvers worldwide, as we try to tackle the challenges of the next century.</s>
 <s id="52">RW: So, are we going Dutch?</s>
 <s id="53">AB: 3846264338327950 28841...</s>
 <s id="54">971?</s>
 <s id="55">RW: One night, want to go to a movie or something?</s>
 <p id="p56">
  <s id="56.1">RF: Hell, no!</s>
  <s id="56.2">Let's go plant some shit!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="57">RW: Let's plant some shit!</s>
 <s id="58">Good, now what is this that I'm planting?</s>
 <s id="59">Bonobos!</s>
 <p id="p60">
  <s id="60.1">IBI: Bonobos!</s>
  <s id="60.2">(Laughs) Bonobos.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="61">RWatts: Um, interested much?</s>
 <s id="62">RW: I want to have your idea baby.</s>
 <s id="63">RWatts: Well, you know what they say in Russia.</s>
 <s id="64">RW: Hm?</s>
 <s id="65">RWatts: "scuberfinckle."</s>
 <s id="66">(Bottles clink)</s>
</text>
