<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm going to speak about a tiny, little idea.</s>
 <s id="2">And this is about shifting baseline.</s>
 <s id="3">And because the idea can be explained in one minute, I will tell you three stories before to fill in the time.</s>
 <s id="4">And the first story is about Charles Darwin, one of my heroes.</s>
 <s id="5">And he was here, as you well know, in '35.</s>
 <s id="6">And you'd think he was chasing finches, but he wasn't.</s>
 <s id="7">He was actually collecting fish.</s>
 <s id="8">And he described one of them as very "common."</s>
 <s id="9">This was the sailfin grouper.</s>
 <s id="10">A big fishery was run on it until the '80s.</s>
 <s id="11">Now the fish is on the IUCN Red List.</s>
 <s id="12">Now this story, we have heard it lots of times on Galapagos and other places, so there is nothing particular about it.</s>
 <s id="13">But the point is, we still come to Galapagos.</s>
 <s id="14">We still think it is pristine.</s>
 <s id="15">The brochures still say it is untouched.</s>
 <s id="16">So what happens here?</s>
 <s id="17">The second story, also to illustrate another concept, is called shifting waistline.</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) Because I was there in '71, studying a lagoon in West Africa.</s>
 <s id="19">I was there because I grew up in Europe and I wanted later to work in Africa.</s>
 <s id="20">And I thought I could blend in.</s>
 <s id="21">And I got a big sunburn, and I was convinced that I was really not from there.</s>
 <s id="22">This was my first sunburn.</s>
 <s id="23">And the lagoon was surrounded by palm trees, as you can see, and a few mangrove.</s>
 <s id="24">And it had tilapia about 20 centimeters, a species of tilapia called blackchin tilapia.</s>
 <s id="25">And the fisheries for this tilapia sustained lots of fish and they had a good time and they earned more than average in Ghana.</s>
 <s id="26">When I went there 27 years later, the fish had shrunk to half of their size.</s>
 <s id="27">They were maturing at five centimeters.</s>
 <s id="28">They had been pushed genetically.</s>
 <s id="29">There were still fishes.</s>
 <s id="30">They were still kind of happy.</s>
 <s id="31">And the fish also were happy to be there.</s>
 <s id="32">So nothing has changed, but everything has changed.</s>
 <s id="33">My third little story is that I was an accomplice in the introduction of trawling in Southeast Asia.</s>
 <s id="34">In the '70s -- well, beginning in the '60s -- Europe did lots of development projects.</s>
 <s id="35">Fish development meant imposing on countries that had already 100,000 fishers to impose on them industrial fishing.</s>
 <s id="36">And this boat, quite ugly, is called the Mutiara 4.</s>
 <s id="37">And I went sailing on it, and we did surveys throughout the southern South China sea and especially the Java Sea.</s>
 <s id="38">And what we caught, we didn't have words for it.</s>
 <s id="39">What we caught, I know now, is the bottom of the sea.</s>
 <s id="40">And 90 percent of our catch were sponges, other animals that are fixed on the bottom.</s>
 <s id="41">And actually most of the fish, they are a little spot on the debris, the piles of debris, were coral reef fish.</s>
 <s id="42">Essentially the bottom of the sea came onto the deck and then was thrown down.</s>
 <s id="43">And these pictures are extraordinary because this transition is very rapid.</s>
 <s id="44">Within a year, you do a survey and then commercial fishing begins.</s>
 <s id="45">The bottom is transformed from, in this case, a hard bottom or soft coral into a muddy mess.</s>
 <s id="46">This is a dead turtle.</s>
 <s id="47">They were not eaten, they were thrown away because they were dead.</s>
 <s id="48">And one time we caught a live one.</s>
 <s id="49">It was not drowned yet.</s>
 <s id="50">And then they wanted to kill it because it was good to eat.</s>
 <s id="51">This mountain of debris is actually collected by fishers every time they go into an area that's never been fished.</s>
 <s id="52">But it's not documented.</s>
 <s id="53">We transform the world, but we don't remember it.</s>
 <s id="54">We adjust our baseline to the new level, and we don't recall what was there.</s>
 <s id="55">If you generalize this, something like this happens.</s>
 <s id="56">You have on the y axis some good thing: biodiversity, numbers of orca, the greenness of your country, the water supply.</s>
 <s id="57">And over time it changes -- it changes because people do things, or naturally.</s>
 <s id="58">Every generation will use the images that they got at the beginning of their conscious lives as a standard and will extrapolate forward.</s>
 <s id="59">And the difference then, they perceive as a loss.</s>
 <s id="60">But they don't perceive what happened before as a loss.</s>
 <s id="61">You can have a succession of changes.</s>
 <s id="62">At the end you want to sustain miserable leftovers.</s>
 <s id="63">And that, to a large extent, is what we want to do now.</s>
 <s id="64">We want to sustain things that are gone or things that are not the way they were.</s>
 <s id="65">Now one should think this problem affected people certainly when in predatory societies, they killed animals and they didn't know they had done so after a few generations.</s>
 <s id="66">Because, obviously, an animal that is very abundant, before it gets extinct, it becomes rare.</s>
 <s id="67">So you don't lose abundant animals.</s>
 <s id="68">You always lose rare animals.</s>
 <s id="69">And therefore they're not perceived as a big loss.</s>
 <s id="70">Over time, we concentrate on large animals, and in a sea that means the big fish.</s>
 <s id="71">They become rarer because we fish them.</s>
 <s id="72">Over time we have a few fish left and we think this is the baseline.</s>
 <s id="73">And the question is, why do people accept this?</s>
 <s id="74">Well because they don't know that it was different.</s>
 <s id="75">And in fact, lots of people, scientists, will contest that it was really different.</s>
 <s id="76">And they will contest this because the evidence presented in an earlier mode is not in the way they would like the evidence presented.</s>
 <s id="77">For example, the anecdote that some present, as Captain so-and-so observed lots of fish in this area cannot be used or is usually not utilized by fishery scientists, because it's not "scientific."</s>
 <s id="78">So you have a situation where people don't know the past, even though we live in literate societies, because they don't trust the sources of the past.</s>
 <s id="79">And hence, the enormous role that a marine protected area can play.</s>
 <s id="80">Because with marine protected areas, we actually recreate the past.</s>
 <s id="81">We recreate the past that people cannot conceive because the baseline has shifted and is extremely low.</s>
 <s id="82">That is for people who can see a marine protected area and who can benefit from the insight that it provides, which enables them to reset their baseline.</s>
 <s id="83">How about the people who can't do that because they have no access -- the people in the Midwest for example?</s>
 <s id="84">There I think that the arts and film can perhaps fill the gap, and simulation.</s>
 <s id="85">This is a simulation of Chesapeake Bay.</s>
 <s id="86">There were gray whales in Chesapeake Bay a long time ago -- 500 years ago.</s>
 <s id="87">And you will have noticed that the hues and tones are like "Avatar."</s>
 <s id="88">(Laughter) And if you think about "Avatar," if you think of why people were so touched by it -- never mind the Pocahontas story -- why so touched by the imagery?</s>
 <s id="89">Because it evokes something that in a sense has been lost.</s>
 <s id="90">And so my recommendation, it's the only one I will provide, is for Cameron to do "Avatar II" underwater.</s>
 <s id="91">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="92">(Applause)</s>
</text>
