<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">After years of experiments, you’ve finally created the pets of the future– nano-rabbits!</s>
 <s id="2">They’re tiny, they’re fuzzy… and they multiply faster than the eye can see.</s>
 <s id="3">In your lab there are 36 habitat cells, arranged in an inverted pyramid, with 8 cells in the top row.</s>
 <s id="4">The first has one rabbit, the second has two, and so on, with eight rabbits in the last one.</s>
 <s id="5">The other rows of cells are empty… for now.</s>
 <s id="6">The rabbits are hermaphroditic, and each rabbit in a given cell will breed once with every rabbit in the horizontally adjacent cells, producing exactly one offspring each time.</s>
 <s id="7">The newborn rabbits will drop into the cell directly below the two cells of its parents, and within minutes will mature and reproduce in turn.</s>
 <s id="8">Each cell can hold 10^80 nano-rabbits – that’s a 1 followed by 80 zeros – before they break free and overrun the world.</s>
 <s id="9">Your calculations have given you a 46-digit number for the count of rabbits in the bottom cell– plenty of room to spare.</s>
 <s id="10">But just as you pull the lever to start the experiment, your assistant runs in with terrible news.</s>
 <s id="11">A rival lab has sabotaged your code so that all the zeros at the end of your results got cut off.</s>
 <s id="12">That means you don’t actually know if the bottom cell will be able to hold all the rabbits – and the reproduction is already underway!</s>
 <s id="13">To make matters worse, your devices and calculators are all malfunctioning, so you only have a few minutes to work it out by hand.</s>
 <s id="14">How many trailing zeros should there be at the end of the count of rabbits in the bottom habitat?</s>
 <s id="15">And do you need to pull the emergency shut-down lever?</s>
 <s id="16">Pause the video now if you want to figure it out for yourself.</s>
 <s id="17">Answer in 3 Answer in 2 Answer in 1 There isn’t enough time to calculate the exact number of rabbits in the final cell.</s>
 <s id="18">The good news is we don’t need to.</s>
 <s id="19">All we need to figure out is how many trailing zeros it has.</s>
 <s id="20">But how can we know how many trailing zeros a number has without calculating the number itself?</s>
 <s id="21">What we do know is that we arrive at the number of rabbits in the bottom cell through a process of multiplication – literally.</s>
 <s id="22">The number of rabbits in each cell is the product of the number of rabbits in each of the two cells above it.</s>
 <s id="23">And there are only two ways to get numbers with trailing zeros through multiplication: either multiplying a number ending in 5 by any even number, or by multiplying numbers that have trailing zeroes themselves.</s>
 <s id="24">Let’s calculate the number of rabbits in the second row and see what patterns emerge.</s>
 <s id="25">Two of the numbers have trailing zeros – 20 rabbits in the fourth cell and 30 in the fifth cell.</s>
 <s id="26">But there are no numbers ending in 5.</s>
 <s id="27">And since the only way to get a number ending in 5 through multiplication is by starting with a number ending in 5, there won’t be any more down the line either.</s>
 <s id="28">That means we only need to worry about the numbers that have trailing zeros themselves.</s>
 <s id="29">And a neat trick to figure out the amount of trailing zeros in a product is to count and add the trailing zeros in each of the factors – for example, 10 x 100 = 1,000.</s>
 <s id="30">So let’s take the numbers in the fourth and fifth cells and multiply down from there.</s>
 <s id="31">20 and 30 each have one zero, so the product of both cells will have two trailing zeros, while the product of either cell and an adjacent non-zero-ending cell will have only one.</s>
 <s id="32">When we continue all the way down, we end up with 35 zeros in the bottom cell.</s>
 <s id="33">And if you’re not too stressed about the potential nano-rabbit apocalypse, you might notice that counting the zeros this way forms part of Pascal’s triangle.</s>
 <s id="34">Adding those 35 zeros to the 46 digit number we had before yields an 81 digit number – too big for the habitat to contain!</s>
 <s id="35">You rush over and pull the emergency switch just as the seventh generation of rabbits was about to mature – hare-raisingly close to disaster.</s>
</text>
