<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Roald Amundsen had spent nearly two years preparing his Arctic expedition.</s>
 <s id="2">He had secured funding from the Norwegian Crown and hand-picked a trusted crew.</s>
 <s id="3">He’d even received the blessing of the famed explorer Fridtjof Nansen, along with the use of his ship, Fram, specially constructed to withstand the ice.</s>
 <s id="4">Now, with the voyage departing, he had one final announcement to his shipmates: They were going to head in the opposite direction.</s>
 <s id="5">By the early 20th century, nearly every region of the globe had been visited and mapped, with only two key locations remaining: the North Pole, deep in the frozen waters of the Arctic region, and the South Pole, nestled within a recently discovered icy continent in the vast Antarctic Ocean.</s>
 <s id="6">A veteran of several expeditions, Amundsen had long dreamed of reaching the North Pole.</s>
 <s id="7">But in 1909, amidst his preparations, news came that the American explorers Frederick Cook and Robert Peary had staked rival claims to the achievement.</s>
 <p id="p8">
  <s id="8.1">Instead of abandoning the planned voyage, Amundsen decided to alter its course to what he called “the last great problem.”</s>
  <s id="8.2">But Amundsen’s crew weren’t the only ones kept in the dark.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="9">British naval officer Robert F. Scott had already visited the Antarctic, and was leading his own South Pole expedition.</s>
 <s id="10">Now, as Scott’s ship Terra Nova reached Melbourne in 1910, he was greeted with the news that Amundsen was also heading south.</s>
 <p id="p11">
  <s id="11.1">Reluctantly, Scott found himself pitted against the Norwegian in what the newspapers called a ‘race to the Pole.’</s>
  <s id="11.2">Yet if it was a race, it was a strange one.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="12">The expeditions left at different times from different locations, and they had very different plans for the journey.</s>
 <s id="13">Amundsen was focused solely on reaching the Pole.</s>
 <s id="14">Informed by his Arctic exploration, he drew on both Inuit and Norwegian experience, arriving with a small team of men and more than a hundred dogs.</s>
 <s id="15">His explorers were clothed in sealskin and furs, as well as specially designed skis and boots.</s>
 <s id="16">But Scott's venture was more complicated.</s>
 <s id="17">Launching an extensive scientific research expedition, he traveled with over three times more men than Amundsen, alongside over 30 dogs, 19 Siberian ponies, and three state-of-the-art motorized sledges.</s>
 <s id="18">But these additional tools and bodies weighed down the ship as it battled the storms of the southern ocean.</s>
 <s id="19">And as they finally began to lay supplies, they found both their ponies and motor-sledges ineffective in the harsh ice and snow.</s>
 <s id="20">In the spring of 1911, after waiting out the long polar night, both parties began the journey south.</s>
 <s id="21">Scott’s team traveled over the Beardmore Glacier, following the path of Ernest Shackleton's earlier attempt to reach the pole.</s>
 <s id="22">But although this course had been documented, it proved slow and laborious.</s>
 <s id="23">Meanwhile, despite an initial false start, Amundsen’s five-man team made good time using a previously uncharted route through the same Transantarctic Mountains.</s>
 <s id="24">They stayed ahead of Scott’s team, and on December 14, arrived first at their desolate destination.</s>
 <s id="25">To avoid the ambiguity that surrounded Cook and Peary’s North Pole claims, Amundsen’s team traversed the area in a grid to make sure they covered the Pole’s location.</s>
 <s id="26">Along with flags and a tent marker, they left a letter for Scott, which would not be found until over a month later.</s>
 <s id="27">But when Scott’s party finally reached the pole, losing the ‘race’ was the least of their problems.</s>
 <s id="28">On the way back towards the camp, two of the five men succumbed to frostbite starvation, and exhaustion.</s>
 <s id="29">The remaining explorers hoped for a prearranged rendezvous with a team sent from their base, but due to a series of mishaps, misjudgements and miscommunications, their rescue never arrived.</s>
 <s id="30">Their remains, along with Scott’s diary, would not be found until spring.</s>
 <s id="31">Today, scientists from various countries live and work at Antarctic research stations.</s>
 <s id="32">But the journeys of these early explorers are not forgotten.</s>
 <s id="33">Despite their divergent fates, they are forever joined in history, and in the name of the research base that marks the South Pole.</s>
</text>
