<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I used to be a Malthusian.</s>
 <s id="2">This was my mental model of the world: exploding population, small planet; it's going to lead to ugly things.</s>
 <s id="3">But I'm moving past Malthus, because I think that we just might be about 150 years from a kind of new enlightenment.</s>
 <s id="4">Here's why.</s>
 <s id="5">This is the U.N.'s population data, you may have seen, for the world.</s>
 <s id="6">And the world's population expected to top out at something hopefully a bit less than 10 billion, late this century.</s>
 <s id="7">And after that, most likely it's going to begin to decline.</s>
 <s id="8">So what then?</s>
 <s id="9">Most of the economic models are built around scarcity and growth.</s>
 <s id="10">So a lot of economists look at declining population and expect to see stagnation, maybe depression.</s>
 <s id="11">But a declining population is going to have at least two very beneficial economic effects.</s>
 <s id="12">One: fewer people on a fixed amount of land make investing in property a bad bet.</s>
 <s id="13">In the cities, a lot of the cost of property is actually wrapped up in its speculative value.</s>
 <s id="14">Take away land speculation, price of land drops.</s>
 <s id="15">And that begins to lift a heavy burden off the world's poor.</s>
 <s id="16">Number two: a declining population means scarce labor.</s>
 <s id="17">Scarce labor drives wages.</s>
 <s id="18">As wages increase that also lifts the burden on the poor and the working class.</s>
 <s id="19">Now I'm not talking about a radical drop in population like we saw in the Black Death.</s>
 <s id="20">But look what happened in Europe after the plague: rising wages, land reform, technological innovation, birth of the middle class; and after that, forward-looking social movements like the Renaissance, and later the Enlightenment.</s>
 <s id="21">Most of our cultural heritage has tended to look backward, romanticizing the past.</s>
 <s id="22">All of the Western religions begin with the notion of Eden, and descend through a kind of profligate present to a very ugly future.</s>
 <s id="23">So human history is viewed as sort of this downhill slide from the good old days.</s>
 <s id="24">But I think we're in for another change, about two generations after the top of that curve, once the effects of a declining population start to settle in.</s>
 <s id="25">At that point, we'll start romanticizing the future again, instead of the nasty, brutish past.</s>
 <s id="26">So why does this matter?</s>
 <s id="27">Why talk about social-economic movements that may be more than a century away?</s>
 <s id="28">Because transitions are dangerous times.</s>
 <s id="29">When land owners start to lose money, and labor demands more pay, there are some powerful interests that are going to fear for the future.</s>
 <s id="30">Fear for the future leads to some rash decisions.</s>
 <s id="31">If we have a positive view about the future then we may be able to accelerate through that turn, instead of careening off a cliff.</s>
 <s id="32">If we can make it through the next 150 years, I think that your great great grandchildren will forget all about Malthus.</s>
 <s id="33">And instead, they'll be planning for the future and starting to build the 22nd Century Enlightenment.</s>
 <s id="34">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="35">(Applause)</s>
</text>
