<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <p id="p1">
  <s id="1.1">Hi.</s>
  <s id="1.2">This is my mobile phone.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="2">A mobile phone can change your life, and a mobile phone gives you individual freedom.</s>
 <s id="3">With a mobile phone, you can shoot a crime against humanity in Syria.</s>
 <s id="4">With a mobile phone, you can tweet a message and start a protest in Egypt.</s>
 <s id="5">And with a mobile phone, you can record a song, load it up to SoundCloud and become famous.</s>
 <s id="6">All this is possible with your mobile phone.</s>
 <s id="7">I'm a child of 1984, and I live in the city of Berlin.</s>
 <s id="8">Let's go back to that time, to this city.</s>
 <s id="9">Here you can see how hundreds of thousands of people stood up and protested for change.</s>
 <s id="10">This is autumn 1989, and imagine that all those people standing up and protesting for change had a mobile phone in their pocket.</s>
 <s id="11">Who in the room has a mobile phone with you?</s>
 <s id="12">Hold it up.</s>
 <s id="13">Hold your phones up, hold your phones up!</s>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">Hold it up.</s>
  <s id="14.2">An Android, a Blackberry, wow.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p15">
  <s id="15.1">That's a lot.</s>
  <s id="15.2">Almost everybody today has a mobile phone.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="16">But today I will talk about me and my mobile phone, and how it changed my life.</s>
 <s id="17">And I will talk about this.</s>
 <s id="18">These are 35,830 lines of information.</s>
 <s id="19">Raw data.</s>
 <s id="20">And why are these informations there?</s>
 <s id="21">Because in the summer of 2006, the E.U. Commission tabled a directive.</s>
 <s id="22">This directive [is] called Data Retention Directive.</s>
 <s id="23">This directive says that each phone company in Europe, each Internet service company all over Europe, has to store a wide range of information about the users.</s>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">Who calls whom?</s>
  <s id="24.2">Who sends whom an email?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="25">Who sends whom a text message?</s>
 <s id="26">And if you use your mobile phone, where you are.</s>
 <s id="27">All this information is stored for at least six months, up to two years by your phone company or your Internet service provider.</s>
 <s id="28">And all over Europe, people stood up and said, "We don't want this."</s>
 <s id="29">They said, we don't want this data retention.</s>
 <s id="30">We want self-determination in the digital age, and we don't want that phone companies and Internet companies have to store all this information about us.</s>
 <s id="31">They were lawyers, journalists, priests, they all said: "We don't want this."</s>
 <s id="32">And here you can see, like 10 thousands of people went out on the streets of Berlin and said, "Freedom, not fear."</s>
 <s id="33">And some even said, this would be Stasi 2.0.</s>
 <s id="34">Stasi was the secret police in East Germany.</s>
 <s id="35">And I also ask myself, does it really work?</s>
 <s id="36">Can they really store all this information about us?</s>
 <s id="37">Every time I use my mobile phone?</s>
 <s id="38">So I asked my phone company, Deutsche Telekom, which was at that time the largest phone company in Germany, and I asked them, please, send me all the information you have stored about me.</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">And I asked them once, and I asked them again, and I got no real answer.</s>
  <s id="39.2">It was only blah blah answers.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">But then I said, I want to have this information, because this is my life you are protocoling.</s>
 <s id="41">So I decided to start a lawsuit against them, because I wanted to have this information.</s>
 <s id="42">But Deutsche Telekom said, no, we will not give you this information.</s>
 <s id="43">So at the end, I had a settlement with them.</s>
 <s id="44">I'll put down the lawsuit and they will send me all the information I ask for.</s>
 <s id="45">Because in the mean time, the German Constitutional Court ruled that the implementation of this E.U. directive into German law was unconstitutional.</s>
 <s id="46">So I got this ugly brown envelope with a C.D. inside.</s>
 <s id="47">And on the C.D., this was on.</s>
 <s id="48">Thirty-five thousand eight hundred thirty lines of information.</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">At first I saw it, and I said, okay, it's a huge file.</s>
  <s id="49.2">Okay.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">But then after a while I realized, this is my life.</s>
 <s id="51">This is six months of my life, into this file.</s>
 <s id="52">So I was a little bit skeptical, what should I do with it?</s>
 <s id="53">Because you can see where I am, where I sleep at night, what I am doing.</s>
 <s id="54">But then I said, I want to go out with this information.</s>
 <s id="55">I want to make them public.</s>
 <s id="56">Because I want to show the people what does data retention mean.</s>
 <s id="57">So together with Zeit Online and Open Data City, I did this.</s>
 <s id="58">This is a visualization of six months of my life.</s>
 <s id="59">You can zoom in and zoom out, you can wind back and fast forward.</s>
 <s id="60">You can see every step I take.</s>
 <s id="61">And you can even see how I go from Frankfurt by train to Cologne, and how often I call in between.</s>
 <s id="62">All this is possible with this information.</s>
 <s id="63">That's a little bit scary.</s>
 <s id="64">But it is not only about me.</s>
 <s id="65">It's about all of us.</s>
 <s id="66">First, it's only like, I call my wife and she calls me, and we talk to each other a couple of times.</s>
 <s id="67">And then there are some friends calling me, and they call each other.</s>
 <s id="68">And after a while you are calling you, and you are calling you, and you have this great communication network.</s>
 <s id="69">But you can see how your people are communicating with each other, what times they call each other, when they go to bed.</s>
 <s id="70">You can see all of this.</s>
 <s id="71">You can see the hubs, like who are the leaders in the group.</s>
 <s id="72">If you have access to this information, you can see what your society is doing.</s>
 <s id="73">If you have access to this information, you can control your society.</s>
 <s id="74">This is a blueprint for countries like China and Iran.</s>
 <s id="75">This is a blueprint how to survey your society, because you know who talks to whom, who sends whom an email, all this is possible if you have access to this information.</s>
 <s id="76">And this information is stored for at least six months in Europe, up to two years.</s>
 <s id="77">Like I said at the beginning, imagine that all those people on the streets of Berlin in autumn of 1989 had a mobile phone in their pocket.</s>
 <s id="78">And the Stasi would have known who took part at this protest, and if the Stasi would have known who are the leaders behind it, this may never have happened.</s>
 <s id="79">The fall of the Berlin Wall would maybe not [have been] there.</s>
 <s id="80">And in the aftermath, also not the fall of the Iron Curtain.</s>
 <s id="81">Because today, state agencies and companies want to store as much information as they can get about us, online and offline.</s>
 <s id="82">They want to have the possibility to track our lives, and they want to store them for all time.</s>
 <s id="83">But self-determination and living in the digital age is no contradiction.</s>
 <s id="84">But you have to fight for your self-determination today.</s>
 <s id="85">You have to fight for it every day.</s>
 <s id="86">So, when you go home, tell your friends that privacy is a value of the 21st century, and it's not outdated.</s>
 <s id="87">When you go home, tell your representative only because companies and state agencies have the possibility to store certain information, they don't have to do it.</s>
 <s id="88">And if you don't believe me, ask your phone company what information they store about you.</s>
 <s id="89">So, in the future, every time you use your mobile phone, let it be a reminder to you that you have to fight for self-determination in the digital age.</s>
 <s id="90">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="91">(Applause)</s>
</text>
