<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Imagine you're asked to invent something new.</s>
 <s id="2">It could be whatever you want made from anything you choose in any shape or size.</s>
 <s id="3">That kind of creative freedom sounds so liberating, doesn't it?</s>
 <s id="4">Or does it?</s>
 <s id="5">If you're like most people, you'd probably be paralyzed by this task.</s>
 <s id="6">Without more guidance, where would you even begin?</s>
 <s id="7">As it turns out, boundless freedom isn't always helpful.</s>
 <s id="8">In reality, any project is restricted by many factors, such as the cost, what materials you have at your disposal, and unbreakable laws of physics.</s>
 <s id="9">These factors are called creative constraints, and they're the requirements and limitations we have to address in order to accomplish a goal.</s>
 <s id="10">Creative constraints apply across professions, to architects and artists, writers, engineers, and scientists.</s>
 <s id="11">In many fields, constraints play a special role as drivers of discovery and invention.</s>
 <s id="12">During the scientific process in particular, constraints are an essential part of experimental design.</s>
 <s id="13">For instance, a scientist studying a new virus would consider, "How can I use the tools and techniques at hand to create an experiment that tells me how this virus infects the body's cells?</s>
 <s id="14">And what are the limits of my knowledge that prevent me from understanding this new viral pathway?"</s>
 <s id="15">In engineering, constraints have us apply our scientific discoveries to invent something new and useful.</s>
 <s id="16">Take, for example, the landers Viking 1 and 2, which relied on thrusters to arrive safely on the surface of Mars.</s>
 <s id="17">The problem?</s>
 <s id="18">Those thrusters left foreign chemicals on the ground, contaminating soil samples.</s>
 <s id="19">So a new constraint was introduced.</s>
 <s id="20">How can we land a probe on Mars without introducing chemicals from Earth?</s>
 <s id="21">The next Pathfinder mission used an airbag system to allow the rover to bounce and roll to a halt without burning contaminating fuel.</s>
 <s id="22">Years later, we wanted to send a much larger rover: Curiosity.</s>
 <s id="23">However, it was too large for the airbag design, so another constraint was defined.</s>
 <s id="24">How can we land a large rover while still keeping rocket fuel away from the Martian soil?</s>
 <s id="25">In response, engineers had a wild idea.</s>
 <s id="26">They designed a skycrane.</s>
 <s id="27">Similar to the claw machine at toy stores, it would lower the rover from high above the surface.</s>
 <s id="28">With each invention, the engineers demonstrated an essential habit of scientific thinking - that solutions must recognize the limitations of current technology in order to advance it.</s>
 <s id="29">Sometimes this progress is iterative, as in, "How can I make a better parachute to land my rover?"</s>
 <s id="30">And sometimes, it's innovative, like how to reach our goal when the best possible parachute isn't going to work.</s>
 <s id="31">In both cases, the constraints guide decision-making to ensure we reach each objective.</s>
 <s id="32">Here's another Mars problem yet to be solved.</s>
 <s id="33">Say we want to send astronauts who will need water.</s>
 <s id="34">They'd rely on a filtration system that keeps the water very clean and enables 100% recovery.</s>
 <s id="35">Those are some pretty tough constraints, and we may not have the technology for it now.</s>
 <s id="36">But in the process of trying to meet these objectives, we might discover other applications of any inventions that result.</s>
 <s id="37">Building an innovative water filtration system could provide a solution for farmers working in drought-stricken regions, or a way to clean municipal water in polluted cities.</s>
 <s id="38">In fact, many scientific advances have occurred when serendipitous failures in one field address the constraints of another.</s>
 <s id="39">When scientist Alexander Fleming mistakenly contaminated a Petri dish in the lab, it led to the discovery of the first antibiotic, penicillin.</s>
 <s id="40">The same is true of synthetic dye, plastic, and gunpowder.</s>
 <s id="41">All were created mistakenly, but went on to address the constraints of other problems.</s>
 <s id="42">Understanding constraints guides scientific progress, and what's true in science is also true in many other fields.</s>
 <s id="43">Constraints aren't the boundaries of creativity, but the foundation of it.</s>
</text>
