<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Well, there's lots to talk about, but I think I'm just going to play to start off.</s>
 <s id="2">(Music) ♫ When I wake up ♫ ♫ in the morning ♫ ♫ I pour the coffee ♫ ♫ I read the paper ♫ ♫ And then I slowly ♫ ♫ and so softly ♫ ♫ do the dishes ♫ ♫ So feed the fishes ♫ ♫ You sing me happy birthday ♫ ♫ Like it's gonna be ♫ ♫ your last day ♫ ♫ here on Earth ♫ (Applause) All right.</s>
 <s id="3">So, I wanted to do something special today.</s>
 <s id="4">I want to debut a new song that I've been working on in the last five or six months.</s>
 <s id="5">And there's few things more thrilling than playing a song for the first time in front of an audience, especially when it's half-finished.</s>
 <s id="6">(Laughter) I'm kind of hoping some conversations here might help me finish it.</s>
 <s id="7">Because it gets into all sorts of crazy realms.</s>
 <s id="8">And so this is basically a song about loops, but not the kind of loops that I make up here.</s>
 <s id="9">They're feedback loops.</s>
 <s id="10">And in the audio world that's when the microphone gets too close to its sound source, and then it gets in this self-destructive loop that creates a very unpleasant sound.</s>
 <s id="11">And I'm going to demonstrate for you.</s>
 <p id="p12">
  <s id="12.1">(Laughter) I'm not going to hurt you.</s>
  <s id="12.2">Don't worry.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">♫ This is a loop, feedback loop ♫ ♫ This is a loop, feedback loop ♫ ♫ This is a loop, feedback loop ♫ ♫ This is a loop, feedback loop ♫ ♫ This is a loop, feedback loop ♫ ♫ This is a loop, feedback loop ♫ ♫ This is a -- (Feedback) All right.</s>
  <s id="13.2">I don't know if that was necessary to demonstrate -- (Laughter) -- but my point is it's the sound of self-destruction.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">And I've been thinking about how that applies across a whole spectrum of realms, from, say, the ecological, okay.</s>
 <s id="15">There seems to be a rule in nature that if you get too close to where you came from, it gets ugly.</s>
 <s id="16">So like, you can't feed cows their own brains or you get mad cow disease, and inbreeding and incest and, let's see, what's the other one?</s>
 <s id="17">Biological -- there's autoimmune diseases, where the body attacks itself a little too overzealously and destroys the host, or the person.</s>
 <s id="18">And then -- okay, this is where we get to the song -- kind of bridges the gap to the emotional.</s>
 <s id="19">Because although I've used scientific terms in songs, it's very difficult sometimes to make them lyrical.</s>
 <s id="20">And there's some things you just don't need to have in songs.</s>
 <s id="21">So I'm trying to bridge this gap between this idea and this melody.</s>
 <s id="22">And so, I don't know if you've ever had this, but when I close my eyes sometimes and try to sleep, I can't stop thinking about my own eyes.</s>
 <s id="23">And it's like your eyes start straining to see themselves.</s>
 <s id="24">That's what it feels like to me.</s>
 <s id="25">It's not pleasant.</s>
 <s id="26">I'm sorry if I put that idea in your head.</s>
 <s id="27">(Laughter) It's impossible, of course, for your eyes to see themselves, but they seem to be trying.</s>
 <s id="28">So that's getting a little more closer to a personal experience.</s>
 <s id="29">Or ears being able to hear themselves -- it's just impossible.</s>
 <s id="30">That's the thing.</s>
 <s id="31">So, I've been working on this song that mentions these things and then also imagines a person who's been so successful at defending themselves from heartbreak that they're left to do the deed themselves, if that's possible.</s>
 <s id="32">And that's what the song is asking.</s>
 <s id="33">All right.</s>
 <s id="34">It doesn't have a name yet.</s>
 <s id="35">(Music) ♫ Go ahead and congratulate yourself ♫ ♫ Give yourself a hand, the hand is your hand ♫ ♫ And the eye that eyes itself is your eye ♫ ♫ And the ear that hears itself is near ♫ ♫ 'Cause it's your ear, oh oh ♫ ♫ You've done the impossible now ♫ ♫ Took yourself apart ♫ ♫ You made yourself invulnerable ♫ ♫ No one can break your heart ♫ ♫ So you wear it out ♫ ♫ And you wring it out ♫ ♫ And you wear it out ♫ ♫ And you break it yourself ♫ ♫ Breaking your own, break it yourself ♫ ♫ Breaking your own, break it yourself ♫ ♫ Breaking your own ♫ (Applause) Thanks.</s>
 <s id="36">(Applause) All right.</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">It's kind of cool.</s>
  <s id="37.2">Songwriters can sort of get away with murder.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="38">You can throw out crazy theories and not have to back it up with data or graphs or research.</s>
 <s id="39">But, you know, I think reckless curiosity would be what the world needs now, just a little bit.</s>
 <s id="40">(Applause) I'm going to finish up with a song of mine called "Weather Systems."</s>
 <s id="41">(Music) ♫ Quiet ♫ ♫ Quiet down, she said ♫ ♫ Speak into the back of his head ♫ ♫ On the edge of the bed, I can see your blood flow ♫ ♫ I can see your ♫ ♫ cells grow ♫ ♫ Hold still awhile ♫ ♫ Don't spill the wine ♫ ♫ I can see it all from here ♫ ♫ I can see ♫ ♫ oh, I ♫ ♫ I can see ♫ ♫ weather systems ♫ ♫ of the world ♫ ♫ Weather systems ♫ ♫ of the world ♫ ♫ Some things you say ♫ ♫ are not for sale ♫ ♫ I would hold it where ♫ ♫ our free agents of some substance are ♫ ♫ scared ♫ ♫ Hold still a while ♫ ♫ Don't spill the wine ♫ ♫ I can see it all from here ♫ ♫ I can see ♫ ♫ oh, I ♫ ♫ I can see ♫ ♫ weather systems of the world ♫ ♫ Weather systems ♫ ♫ of the world ♫ Thanks.</s>
 <s id="42">(Applause)</s>
</text>
