<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <p id="p1">
  <s id="1.1">Good morning.</s>
  <s id="1.2">So magic is an excellent way for staying ahead of the reality curve, to make possible today what science will make a reality tomorrow.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="2">As a cyber-magician, I combine elements of illusion and science to give us a feel of how future technologies might be experienced.</s>
 <s id="3">You've probably all heard of Google's Project Glass.</s>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">It's new technology.</s>
  <s id="4.2">You look through them and the world you see is augmented with data: names of places, monuments, buildings, maybe one day even the names of the strangers that pass you on the street.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="5">So these are my illusion glasses.</s>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">They're a little bigger.</s>
  <s id="6.2">They're a prototype.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="7">And when you look through them, you get a glimpse into the mind of the cyber-illusionist.</s>
 <s id="8">Let me show you what I mean.</s>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">All we need is a playing card.</s>
  <s id="9.2">Any card will do.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p10">
  <s id="10.1">Like this.</s>
  <s id="10.2">And let me mark it so we can recognize it when we see it again.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p11">
  <s id="11.1">All right.</s>
  <s id="11.2">Very significant mark.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="12">And let's put it back into the deck, somewhere in the middle, and let's get started.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">(Music) Voice: System ready.</s>
  <s id="13.2">Acquiring image.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">Marco Tempest: For those of you who don't play cards, a deck of cards is made up of four different suits: hearts, clubs, diamonds and spades.</s>
 <s id="15">The cards are amongst the oldest of symbols, and have been interpreted in many different ways.</s>
 <s id="16">Now, some say that the four suits represent the four seasons.</s>
 <s id="17">There's spring, summer, autumn and — Voice: My favorite season is winter.MT: Well yeah, mine too.</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">Winter is like magic.</s>
  <s id="18.2">It's a time of change, when warmth turns to cold, water turns to snow, and then it all disappears.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">There are 13 cards in each suit.</s>
  <s id="19.2">(Music) Voice: Each card represents a phase of the 13 lunar cycles.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">MT: So over here is low tide, and over here is high tide, and in the middle is the moon.</s>
 <s id="21">Voice: The moon is one of the most potent symbols of magic.</s>
 <s id="22">MT: There are two colors in a deck of cards.</s>
 <s id="23">There is the color red and the color black, representing the constant change from day to night.</s>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">Voice: Marco, I did not know you could do that.</s>
  <s id="24.2">(Laughter) MT: And is it a coincidence that there are 52 cards in a deck of cards, just as there are 52 weeks in a year?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="25">(Music) Voice: If you total all the spots on a deck of cards, the result is 365.</s>
 <s id="26">MT: Oh, 365, the number of days in a year, the number of days between each birthday.</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">Make a wish.</s>
  <s id="27.2">(Blowing noise) Voice: Don't tell, or it won't come true.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">MT: Well, as a matter of fact, it was on my sixth birthday that I received my first deck of cards, and ever since that day, I have traveled around the world performing magic for boys and girls, men and women, husbands and wives, even kings and queens.</s>
  <s id="28.2">(Applause) Voice: And who are these?MT: Ah, mischief-makers.</s>
  <s id="28.3">Watch.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">Wake up.</s>
 <s id="30">Joker: Whoa.MT: Are you ready for your party piece?</s>
 <s id="31">Joker: Ready!MT: Let me see what you've got.</s>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">Joker: Presenting my pogo stick.MT: Ah.</s>
  <s id="32.2">Watch out.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">Joker: Whoa, whoa, whoa, oh!</s>
  <s id="33.2">(Music) MT: But today, I am performing for a different kind of audience.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="34">I'm performing for you.</s>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">Voice: Signed card detected.MT: Well, sometimes people ask me how do you become a magician?</s>
  <s id="35.2">Is it a 9-to-5 job?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">Of course not!</s>
  <s id="36.2">You've got to practice 24/7.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="37">I don't literally mean 24 hours, seven days a week.</s>
 <p id="p38">
  <s id="38.1">24/7 is a little bit of an exaggeration, but it does take practice.</s>
  <s id="38.2">Now, some people will say, well, magic, that must be the work of some evil supernatural force.</s>
  <s id="38.3">(Laughter) (Applause) (Music) Whoa.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="39">Well, to this, I just say, no no.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">Actually, in German, it's nein nein.</s>
  <s id="40.2">(Laughter) Magic isn't that intense.</s>
  <s id="40.3">I have to warn you, though, if you ever play with someone who deals cards like this, don't play for money.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">(Music) Voice: Why not?</s>
  <s id="41.2">That's a very good hand.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">The odds of getting it are 4,165 to one.</s>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">MT: Yeah, but I guess my hand is better.</s>
  <s id="43.2">We beat the odds.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">Voice: I think you got your birthday wish.MT: And that actually leaves me with the last, and most important card of all: the one with this very significant mark on it.</s>
 <s id="45">And unlike anything else we've just seen, virtual or not.Voice: Signed card detected.</s>
 <s id="46">Digital MT: This is without a question the real thing.</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">MT: Bye bye.</s>
  <s id="47.2">(Music) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="47.3">(Applause) (Applause) Thank you very much.</s>
  <s id="47.4">(Applause) (Applause)</s>
 </p>
</text>
