<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">There are more than a trillion galaxies in the universe.</s>
 <s id="2">And my team discovered an extremely rare one, a galaxy that doesn't look quite like anything observed before.</s>
 <s id="3">This galaxy is so peculiar, that it challenges our theories and our assumptions about how the universe works.</s>
 <s id="4">The majority of the galaxies are spiral, similar to our own Milky Way.</s>
 <s id="5">We have strong theories about how these common galaxies form and evolve.</s>
 <s id="6">But we don't understand how rare galaxies form and evolve.</s>
 <s id="7">An especially puzzling rare case is Hoag's Object.</s>
 <s id="8">It has a very symmetric central body surrounded by a circular outer ring, with nothing visible connecting them.</s>
 <s id="9">Hoag-type galaxies are among the rarest types of galaxies currently known.</s>
 <s id="10">There are fewer than one in 1,000 galaxies.</s>
 <s id="11">It's a mystery how the stars in the outer ring are just floating there in such an orderly manner.</s>
 <s id="12">That's interesting, right?</s>
 <s id="13">Hold on.</s>
 <s id="14">Things are about to get more mysterious.</s>
 <s id="15">The galaxy that my team discovered is even rarer and much more complex than that.</s>
 <s id="16">You know, sometimes, you search and search for these objects, and you find nothing.</s>
 <s id="17">But sometimes, it just appears in the background, when you are not even looking for it.</s>
 <s id="18">This system looks very similar to Hoag's Object, with its central body and circular outer ring.</s>
 <s id="19">We got very excited and thought we discovered another Hoag's Object.</s>
 <s id="20">But my research showed this is an entirely new galaxy type, now commonly referred to as "Burçin's Galaxy."</s>
 <s id="21">(Laughs) (Cheers) (Applause) We will not be visiting this galaxy anytime soon.</s>
 <s id="22">It is approximately 359 million light years away from Earth.</s>
 <s id="23">You may think this is far.</s>
 <s id="24">Well, actually, this is one of the nearby galaxies.</s>
 <s id="25">I study this object in different light -- in ultraviolet, optical and near-infrared.</s>
 <s id="26">Small details on our body, like a scar or wrinkles, tell the story of our lives.</s>
 <s id="27">Similarly, a galaxy's structure in different light can help us trace back their origin and evolution.</s>
 <s id="28">How do I look for these details?</s>
 <s id="29">I model the bright central body and remove my model from the image to check for any hidden features, because a bright structure in a galaxy may blind our views of faint features, just like using sunglasses when you are blinded by the intense light.</s>
 <s id="30">The result was a big surprise.</s>
 <s id="31">This galaxy doesn't just have an outer ring, it has an additional, diffused inner ring.</s>
 <s id="32">We were having a hard time explaining the origin of the outer ring in Hoag-type galaxies.</s>
 <s id="33">Now we also need to explain this mysterious second ring.</s>
 <s id="34">There is currently no known mechanism that can explain the existence of an inner ring in such a peculiar galaxy.</s>
 <s id="35">So the discovery of Burçin's Galaxy clearly highlights the gap in our knowledge of galaxy evolution.</s>
 <s id="36">Further research into how this extremely rare galaxy was formed can provide us with new clues on how the universe works.</s>
 <s id="37">This discovery tells us that we still have a lot to learn, and we should keep looking deeper and deeper in space and keep searching for the unknown.</s>
 <s id="38">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="39">(Applause)</s>
</text>
