<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Music: "East Virginia") (Banjo) (Singing) I'm from old East Virginia.</s>
 <s id="2">North Carolina I did go.</s>
 <s id="3">I met a fair, young maiden.</s>
 <s id="4">Her name I did not know.</s>
 <s id="5">(Banjo) Don't that road look rough and rocky?</s>
 <s id="6">Don't that sea look wide and deep?</s>
 <s id="7">Don't my darlin' look the sweetest ...</s>
 <s id="8">When she's in my arms asleep?</s>
 <s id="9">(Banjo) Her hair was a dark-brown curly.</s>
 <s id="10">Her cheeks were chestnut red.</s>
 <s id="11">On her breast she wore a white lilly.</s>
 <s id="12">Through the night, the tears she shed.</s>
 <s id="13">(Banjo) Captain, Captain, I am dyin'.</s>
 <s id="14">Won't you take these words for me?</s>
 <s id="15">Take them back to old East Virginia.</s>
 <s id="16">Tell my darlin' she is free.</s>
 <s id="17">(Banjo) (Music ends) (Applause and cheers) That was a song called "East Virginia" I learned from a man named Clifton Hicks who lives down in Georgia.</s>
 <s id="18">The next song ...</s>
 <s id="19">I have for you is called "John Brown's Dream."</s>
 <s id="20">It's an old dance tune.</s>
 <s id="21">And you may notice that the banjo that I'm holding looks a little different than banjos you might be used to seeing or the one I just played, for example.</s>
 <s id="22">And this banjo is sort of an earlier model.</s>
 <s id="23">Banjos kind of evolved like a human has.</s>
 <s id="24">And I like to say that the sound that comes out of this banjo is a sound that was just a little closer to the source, which is Africa, and some people forget that, so, yeah ...</s>
 <s id="25">(Banjo tuning) (Music: "John Brown's Dream") (Banjo) (Banjo continues) (Singing) John Brown's dream, John Brown's dream the devil was dead.</s>
 <s id="26">I'm gonna get that, get that, get that, I'm gonna get that pretty little girl.</s>
 <s id="27">(Banjo) John Brown's dream, John Brown's dream the devil was dead.</s>
 <s id="28">(Banjo) Come on, Liza, Liza, Liza.</s>
 <s id="29">Come on, Liza we'll be pickin' it again.</s>
 <s id="30">I'm gonna get that, get that, get that, I'm gonna get that pretty little girl.</s>
 <s id="31">(Banjo) (Music ends) (Applause and cheers) Thank you very much.</s>
</text>
