<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">"Listen.</s>
 <s id="2">Do you hear that?"</s>
 <s id="3">my grandmother asked me.</s>
 <s id="4">"Listen.</s>
 <s id="5">Listen to what the beetle is saying."</s>
 <s id="6">I would spend hours and hours listening to the little beetle rolling a huge ball of dung, and while at it, I heard a variety of environmental sounds.</s>
 <s id="7">With the keenest of ears, I would hear family chatter, laughter, the wind howling and even crickets chirping.</s>
 <s id="8">All these sounds crisscrossed into each other, and I would hear rhythm in between.</s>
 <s id="9">Then I would beat my plate with a spoon and my chest with my tiny hands trying to recreate what I was hearing.</s>
 <s id="10">I have been beating the same plates, shakers, drums, pans and so much more ever since to become a professional drummer and percussionist.</s>
 <s id="11">(Applause) As I grew up, subconsciously, I felt a strong urge to hide my newfound hobby.</s>
 <s id="12">Even without it being said out loud, I knew that somehow it was wrong to do what I was doing.</s>
 <s id="13">In most of the ceremonies, I noticed that most of the women and girls were not in sight, but when they were, I noticed that they would wear their dancing skirts and shake their waists off, singing, clapping, ululating, while the men filled up the rhythm section.</s>
 <s id="14">A few years later, I came to understand what tradition and culture meant, and what was considered taboo or otherwise.</s>
 <s id="15">In the majority of African cultures, women have been forbidden to play drums and percussion for a very long time.</s>
 <s id="16">I believe this taboo stems from the psychological and traditional belief that the woman is an inferior being.</s>
 <s id="17">I grew up hearing that the place of the woman is in the kitchen or in the other room.</s>
 <s id="18">Mhm?</s>
 <s id="19">(Laughter) Women had been brainwashed and led on for so long until we had fallen victim and actually started believing in this ourselves.</s>
 <s id="20">This, coupled with the lack of interest to educate women, played a major, major role in etching this into our minds.</s>
 <s id="21">The sounds of the drum provoke emotion and movement.</s>
 <s id="22">Essentially, the drum is a very sensual instrument.</s>
 <s id="23">Once at a festival, a man asked me how I dared put a drum in between my legs.</s>
 <s id="24">I have been considered loose and dirty for playing an instrument.</s>
 <s id="25">I have repeatedly been questioned why I would choose to play drums instead of practicing journalism, which I studied for my undergraduate, which has been termed "more decent."</s>
 <s id="26">The sight of a woman playing drums enfeebles her, makes her less feminine, less desirable, but all this optimally puts her on a lower social stand.</s>
 <s id="27">Drumming has essentially represented the strong African heritage, and its importance can be seen in the many aspects of the African tradition.</s>
 <s id="28">Many communities encompass drumming in their day-to-day activities, and still do up to date, from childbirths to initiation ceremonies, welcoming ceremonies, marriages and even burials.</s>
 <s id="29">However, this same drum is disappearing very fast from the music scene, and the traditional genre is losing its popularity very quickly amongst the people.</s>
 <s id="30">Inspired by the need to preserve this culture, I am teaching the significance and the importance of the drum to young boys, women and girls.</s>
 <s id="31">In my journey as a percussion teacher, I have realized that very many women actually want to play the drum, but at the same time, they fear it.</s>
 <s id="32">Some fear how society will perceive them.</s>
 <s id="33">Others fear the physical pain that comes with playing.</s>
 <s id="34">Oh yes, it's not that easy.</s>
 <s id="35">Some, because their spouses don't approve of them, and others generally fear the responsibility of being a bearer of culture.</s>
 <s id="36">I believe, or I think that all these fears are etched in the collective feminine cautiousness because when we learn of the atrocities that have happened to women, continentally especially, it serves as a constant reminder that one step out of our designated place may end up in very serious consequences.</s>
 <s id="37">Well, I use my drum to tell my story and my people's stories.</s>
 <s id="38">My roots shaped me and my culture is here to stay with me.</s>
 <s id="39">Women can be custodians of culture, too.</s>
 <s id="40">We are born to bring forth life, to nurture it.</s>
 <s id="41">We can definitely preserve our traditions very, very excellently.</s>
 <s id="42">My drum and I, we are here to stay.</s>
 <s id="43">(Applause) We are definitely here to stay.</s>
 <s id="44">If women have led countries, women have gone to space, women have won Grammys, then the same, same women can play the drum and play it -- to a five-star rating?</s>
 <s id="45">No, to a million-star rating.</s>
 <s id="46">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="47">(Applause) (Chiming) (Metallic drumming) (Chiming) (Rattling) (Drumming) (Applause)</s>
</text>
