<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">What does it mean to be a witness?</s>
 <s id="2">Why is it important to bear witness to people's suffering, especially when those people are isolated from us?</s>
 <s id="3">And what happens when we turn away?</s>
 <s id="4">Three years ago, I traveled to the Central African Republic to report on its ongoing war.</s>
 <s id="5">I'd heard warnings of massacres in the country's jungles and deserts, but no one could locate these massacres or tell me who was killed, or when.</s>
 <s id="6">I drove into this war with little information.</s>
 <s id="7">I witnessed scenes that were tragic and unreal, and only at the end did I realize that I had witnessed the slow preparation of ethnic cleansing.</s>
 <s id="8">The Central African Republic is a country of about five million people the size of Texas in the center of Africa.</s>
 <s id="9">The country has known chronic violence since French colonial rule ended in 1960.</s>
 <s id="10">The war I reported on was between the minority Muslim government, called the Seleka, and citizen militias, mostly Christian, called the anti-balaka.</s>
 <s id="11">The first sign of the impending cleansing was the breakdown of trust within communities.</s>
 <s id="12">Three days after I arrived in the country, I watched the small city of Gaga be abandoned.</s>
 <s id="13">A battle was about to break out.</s>
 <s id="14">And to save themselves, many people were working as government spies, identifying friends and neighbors to be killed.</s>
 <s id="15">Cities and towns, any place with humans, had become unsafe.</s>
 <s id="16">So people moved to the jungle.</s>
 <s id="17">I felt strangely isolated as pigs and livestock moved into the empty homes.</s>
 <s id="18">In a war zone, you know that you are near the killing when people have left.</s>
 <s id="19">The war moved across the jungle and reached Gaga, and I was surrounded by the thunder of bombs.</s>
 <s id="20">Government forces drove into the jungle to attack a town sheltering a militia.</s>
 <s id="21">I rode on motorcycle for hours, crossing jungle streams and tall elephant grass, but I only got to the town after the government had burned it and its people were gone.</s>
 <s id="22">To see if I could speak to someone, I shouted out that I was a friend, that I would not hurt them.</s>
 <s id="23">A woman in a red shirt ran out of the forest.</s>
 <s id="24">Others cautiously emerged from the trees and asked, "Est-ce les gens savent?"</s>
 <s id="25">"Do people know?"</s>
 <s id="26">The question surprised me.</s>
 <s id="27">Their children were hungry and sick, but they didn't ask for food or medicine.</s>
 <s id="28">They asked me, "Do people know what is happening to us?"</s>
 <s id="29">I felt helpless as I wrote down their question.</s>
 <s id="30">And I became determined that this moment in their lives should not be forgotten.</s>
 <s id="31">In bearing witness to their crisis, I felt a small communion with these people.</s>
 <s id="32">From far away, this war had felt like a footnote in world news.</s>
 <s id="33">As a witness, the war felt like history unfolding.</s>
 <s id="34">The government denied that it was committing any violence, but I continually drove through towns where people described government massacres from a day or a week before.</s>
 <s id="35">I felt overwhelmed and tried to calm myself.</s>
 <s id="36">As I reported on these massacres, I bought and ate little sweets, seeking the familiar comfort of their taste.</s>
 <s id="37">Central Africans ate these sweets to ease their hunger, leaving a trail of thousands of plastic wrappers as they fled.</s>
 <s id="38">On the few radio stations still operating in the country, I mostly heard pop music.</s>
 <s id="39">As the war mounted, we received less information about the massacres.</s>
 <s id="40">It became easier to feel a sense of normalcy.</s>
 <s id="41">I witnessed the effect of this missing information.</s>
 <s id="42">Two weeks later, I slowly and anxiously drove into an isolated militia headquarters, a town called PK100.</s>
 <s id="43">Here, Christian fighters told me that all Muslims were foreigners, evil and allied with the government.</s>
 <s id="44">They likened Muslims to animals.</s>
 <s id="45">Without neutral observers or media to counter this absurd narrative, it became the single narrative in these camps.</s>
 <s id="46">The militias began to hunt down Muslims, and emptied the capital, Bangui, of nearly 140,000 Muslims in just a few months.</s>
 <s id="47">Most of the killing and fleeing of Muslims went unrecorded by witnesses.</s>
 <s id="48">I'm telling you about my reporting in the Central African Republic, but I still ask myself why I went there.</s>
 <s id="49">Why put myself at risk?</s>
 <s id="50">I do this work because I feel that ignored people in all our communities tell us something important about who we are.</s>
 <s id="51">When information is missing, people have the power to manipulate reality.</s>
 <s id="52">Without witnesses, we would believe that those thousands of massacred people are still alive, that those hundreds of burned homes are still standing.</s>
 <s id="53">A war zone can pass for a mostly peaceful place when no one is watching.</s>
 <s id="54">And a witness can become precious, and their gaze most necessary, when violence passes silently, unseen and unheard.</s>
 <s id="55">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="56">(Applause)</s>
</text>
