<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Two years ago, after having served four years in the United States Marine Corps and deployments to both Iraq and Afghanistan, I found myself in Port-au-Prince, leading a team of veterans and medical professionals in some of the hardest-hit areas of that city, three days after the earthquake.</s>
 <p id="p2">
  <s id="2.1">We were going to the places that nobody else wanted to go, the places nobody else could go, and after three weeks, we realized something.</s>
  <s id="2.2">Military veterans are very, very good at disaster response.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="3">And coming home, my cofounder and I, we looked at it, and we said, there are two problems.</s>
 <s id="4">The first problem is there's inadequate disaster response.</s>
 <p id="p5">
  <s id="5.1">It's slow.</s>
  <s id="5.2">It's antiquated.</s>
  <s id="5.3">It's not using the best technology, and it's not using the best people.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="6">The second problem that we became aware of was a very inadequate veteran reintegration, and this is a topic that is front page news right now as veterans are coming home from Iraq and Afghanistan, and they're struggling to reintegrate into civilian life.</s>
 <p id="p7">
  <s id="7.1">And we sat here and we looked at these two problems, and finally we came to a realization.</s>
  <s id="7.2">These aren't problems.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p8">
  <s id="8.1">These are actually solutions.</s>
  <s id="8.2">And what do I mean by that?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="9">Well, we can use disaster response as an opportunity for service for the veterans coming home.</s>
 <s id="10">Recent surveys show that 92 percent of veterans want to continue their service when they take off their uniform.</s>
 <s id="11">And we can use veterans to improve disaster response.</s>
 <s id="12">Now on the surface, this makes a lot of sense, and in 2010, we responded to the tsunami in Chile, the floods in Pakistan, we sent training teams to the Thai-Burma border.</s>
 <s id="13">But it was earlier this year, when one of our original members caused us to shift focus in the organization.</s>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">This is Clay Hunt.</s>
  <s id="14.2">Clay was a Marine with me.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="15">We served together in Iraq and Afghanistan.</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">Clay was with us in Port-au-Prince.</s>
  <s id="16.2">He was also with us in Chile.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="17">Earlier this year, in March, Clay took his own life.</s>
 <s id="18">This was a tragedy, but it really forced us to refocus what it is that we were doing.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">You know, Clay didn't kill himself because of what happened in Iraq and Afghanistan.</s>
  <s id="19.2">Clay killed himself because of what he lost when he came home.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">He lost purpose.</s>
  <s id="20.2">He lost his community.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="21">And perhaps most tragically, he lost his self-worth.</s>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">And so, as we evaluated, and as the dust settled from this tragedy, we realized that, of those two problems -- in the initial iteration of our organization, we were a disaster response organization that was using veteran service.</s>
  <s id="22.2">We had a lot of success, and we really felt like we were changing the disaster response paradigm.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">But after Clay, we shifted that focus, and suddenly, now moving forward, we see ourselves as a veteran service organization that's using disaster response.</s>
 <s id="24">Because we think that we can give that purpose and that community and that self-worth back to the veteran.</s>
 <s id="25">And tornadoes in Tuscaloosa and Joplin, and then later Hurricane Irene, gave us an opportunity to look at that.</s>
 <s id="26">Now I want you to imagine for a second an 18-year-old boy who graduates from high school in Kansas City, Missouri.</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">He joins the Army.</s>
  <s id="27.2">The Army gives him a rifle.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="28">They send him to Iraq.</s>
 <s id="29">Every day he leaves the wire with a mission.</s>
 <s id="30">That mission is to defend the freedom of the family that he left at home.</s>
 <s id="31">It's to keep the men around him alive.</s>
 <s id="32">It's to pacify the village that he works in.</s>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">He's got a purpose.</s>
  <s id="33.2">But he comes home [to] Kansas City, Missouri, maybe he goes to college, maybe he's got a job, but he doesn't have that same sense of purpose.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">You give him a chainsaw.</s>
  <s id="34.2">You send him to Joplin, Missouri after a tornado, he regains that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="35">Going back, that same 18-year-old boy graduates from high school in Kansas City, Missouri, joins the Army, the Army gives him a rifle, they send him to Iraq.</s>
 <s id="36">Every day he looks into the same sets of eyes around him.</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">He leaves the wire.</s>
  <s id="37.2">He knows that those people have his back.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p38">
  <s id="38.1">He's slept in the same sand.</s>
  <s id="38.2">They've lived together.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">They've eaten together.</s>
  <s id="39.2">They've bled together.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">He goes home to Kansas City, Missouri.</s>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">He gets out of the military.</s>
  <s id="41.2">He takes his uniform off.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">He doesn't have that community anymore.</s>
 <s id="43">But you drop 25 of those veterans in Joplin, Missouri, they get that sense of community back.</s>
 <s id="44">Again, you have an 18-year-old boy who graduates high school in Kansas City.</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">He joins the Army.</s>
  <s id="45.2">The Army gives him a rifle.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="46">They send him to Iraq.</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">They pin a medal on his chest.</s>
  <s id="47.2">He goes home to a ticker tape parade.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">He takes the uniform off.</s>
  <s id="48.2">He's no longer Sergeant Jones in his community.</s>
  <s id="48.3">He's now Dave from Kansas City.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="49">He doesn't have that same self-worth.</s>
 <s id="50">But you send him to Joplin after a tornado, and somebody once again is walking up to him and shaking their hand and thanking them for their service, now they have self-worth again.</s>
 <s id="51">I think it's very important, because right now somebody needs to step up, and this generation of veterans has the opportunity to do that if they are given the chance.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">Thank you very much.</s>
  <s id="52.2">(Applause)</s>
 </p>
</text>
