<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Joe Kowan: I have stage fright.</s>
 <s id="2">I've always had stage fright, and not just a little bit, it's a big bit.</s>
 <s id="3">And it didn't even matter until I was 27.</s>
 <s id="4">That's when I started writing songs, and even then I only played them for myself.</s>
 <s id="5">Just knowing my roommates were in the same house made me uncomfortable.</s>
 <s id="6">But after a couple of years, just writing songs wasn't enough.</s>
 <s id="7">I had all these stories and ideas, and I wanted to share them with people, but physiologically, I couldn't do it.</s>
 <s id="8">I had this irrational fear.</s>
 <s id="9">But the more I wrote, and the more I practiced, the more I wanted to perform.</s>
 <s id="10">So on the week of my 30th birthday, I decided I was going to go to this local open mic, and put this fear behind me.</s>
 <s id="11">Well, when I got there, it was packed.</s>
 <s id="12">There were like 20 people there.</s>
 <s id="13">(Laughter) And they all looked angry.</s>
 <s id="14">But I took a deep breath, and I signed up to play, and I felt pretty good.</s>
 <s id="15">Pretty good, until about 10 minutes before my turn, when my whole body rebelled, and this wave of anxiety just washed over me.</s>
 <s id="16">Now, when you experience fear, your sympathetic nervous system kicks in.</s>
 <s id="17">So you have a rush of adrenaline, your heart rate increases, your breathing gets faster.</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">Next your non-essential systems start to shut down, like digestion.</s>
  <s id="18.2">(Laughter) So your mouth gets dry, and blood is routed away from your extremities, so your fingers don't work anymore.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">Your pupils dilate, your muscles contract, your Spidey sense tingles, basically your whole body is trigger-happy.</s>
  <s id="19.2">(Laughter) That condition is not conducive to performing folk music.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">(Laughter) I mean, your nervous system is an idiot.</s>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">Really?</s>
  <s id="21.2">Two hundred thousand years of human evolution, and it still can't tell the difference between a saber tooth tiger and 20 folksingers on a Tuesday night open mic?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="22">(Laughter) I have never been more terrified -- until now.</s>
 <s id="23">(Laughter and cheers) So then it was my turn, and somehow, I get myself onto the stage, I start my song, I open my mouth to sing the first line, and this completely horrible vibrato -- you know, when your voice wavers -- comes streaming out.</s>
 <s id="24">And this is not the good kind of vibrato, like an opera singer has, this is my whole body just convulsing with fear.</s>
 <s id="25">I mean, it's a nightmare.</s>
 <s id="26">I'm embarrassed, the audience is clearly uncomfortable, they're focused on my discomfort.</s>
 <s id="27">It was so bad.</s>
 <s id="28">But that was my first real experience as a solo singer-songwriter.</s>
 <s id="29">And something good did happen -- I had the tiniest little glimpse of that audience connection that I was hoping for.</s>
 <p id="p30">
  <s id="30.1">And I wanted more.</s>
  <s id="30.2">But I knew I had to get past this nervousness.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="31">That night I promised myself: I would go back every week until I wasn't nervous anymore.</s>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">And I did.</s>
  <s id="32.2">I went back every single week, and sure enough, week after week, it didn't get any better.</s>
  <s id="32.3">The same thing happened every week.</s>
  <s id="32.4">(Laughter) I couldn't shake it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="33">And that's when I had an epiphany.</s>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">And I remember it really well, because I don't have a lot of epiphanies.</s>
  <s id="34.2">(Laughter) All I had to do was write a song that exploits my nervousness.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">That only seems authentic when I have stage fright, and the more nervous I was, the better the song would be.</s>
  <s id="35.2">Easy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="36">So I started writing a song about having stage fright.</s>
 <s id="37">First, fessing up to the problem, the physical manifestations, how I would feel, how the listener might feel.</s>
 <s id="38">And then accounting for things like my shaky voice, and I knew I would be singing about a half-octave higher than normal, because I was nervous.</s>
 <s id="39">By having a song that explained what was happening to me, while it was happening, that gave the audience permission to think about it.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">They didn't have to feel bad for me because I was nervous, they could experience that with me, and we were all one big happy, nervous, uncomfortable family.</s>
  <s id="40.2">(Laughter) By thinking about my audience, by embracing and exploiting my problem, I was able to take something that was blocking my progress, and turn it into something that was essential for my success.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="41">And having the stage fright song let me get past that biggest issue right in the beginning of a performance.</s>
 <s id="42">And then I could move on, and play the rest of my songs with just a little bit more ease.</s>
 <s id="43">And eventually, over time, I didn't have to play the stage fright song at all.</s>
 <p id="p44">
  <s id="44.1">Except for when I was really nervous, like now.</s>
  <s id="44.2">(Laughter) Would it be okay if I played the stage fright song for you?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="45">(Applause) Can I have a sip of water?</s>
 <s id="46">(Music) Thank you.</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">♫ I'm not joking, you know, ♫ ♫ this stage fright is real. ♫ ♫ And if I'm up here trembling and singing, ♫ ♫ well, you'll know how I feel. ♫ ♫ And the mistake I'd be making, ♫ ♫ the tremolo caused by my whole body shaking. ♫ ♫ As you sit there feeling embarrassed for me, ♫ ♫ well, you don't have to be. ♫ ♫ Well, maybe just a little bit. ♫ (Laughter) ♫ And maybe I'll try to imagine you all without clothes. ♫ ♫ But singing in front of all naked strangers scares me more than anyone knows. ♫ ♫ Not to discuss this at length, ♫ ♫ but my body image was never my strength. ♫ ♫ So frankly, I wish that you all would get dressed, ♫ ♫ I mean, you're not even really naked. ♫ ♫ And I'm the one with the problem. ♫ ♫ And you tell me, don't worry so much, you'll be great. ♫ ♫ But I'm the one living with me ♫ ♫ and I know how I get. ♫ ♫ Your advice is gentle but late. ♫ ♫ If not just a bit patronizing. ♫ ♫ And that sarcastic tone doesn't help me when I sing. ♫ ♫ But we shouldn't talk about these things right now, ♫ ♫ really, I'm up on stage, and you're in the crowd.</s>
  <s id="47.2">Hi. ♫ ♫ And I'm not making fun of unnurtured, irrational fear, ♫ ♫ and if I wasn't ready to face this, ♫ ♫ I sure as hell wouldn't be here. ♫ ♫ But if I belt one note out clearly, ♫ ♫ you'll know I'm recovering slowly but surely. ♫ ♫ And maybe next week, I'll set my guitar ringin' ♫ ♫ my voice clear as water, and everyone singin'. ♫ ♫ But probably I'll just get up and start groovin', ♫ ♫ my vocal cords movin', ♫ ♫ at speeds slightly faster than sound. ♫ (Applause)</s>
 </p>
</text>
