<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">It was a night like any other night, except here I was climbing the platonic peaks like Romeo on a second date.</s>
 <s id="2">(ugh) I was there for the dame.</s>
 <s id="3">She had eyes like imaginary numbers and curves that went on forever.</s>
 <s id="4">Said she wanted to go home.</s>
 <s id="5">Said I could help.</s>
 <s id="6">Said the pay was good.</s>
 <s id="7">Didn't say anything about climbing a...</s>
 <s id="8">Voice: "Who's there?"</s>
 <s id="9">Manny Brot: "Manny Brot, private eye."</s>
 <s id="10">Voice: "What are you doing here?"</s>
 <s id="11">"A pretty number sent me to find a stolen dingus."</s>
 <s id="12">Voice: "Well, to enter the cave, you must answer my riddles three."</s>
 <s id="13">What was it with riddles, and why do they always come in threes?</s>
 <s id="14">"Is it an egg?"</s>
 <p id="p15">
  <s id="15.1">"No.</s>
  <s id="15.2">Why would it be an egg?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="16">"It's usually an egg."</s>
 <s id="17">"What can I hold in my hand, but has zero area?"</s>
 <s id="18">"Is it a dodo egg?"</s>
 <s id="19">"It's not an egg!"</s>
 <s id="20">I took out the rock that had nearly brained me before and gave it a hard ponder.</s>
 <s id="21">The size of the rising bump on my conk said to me that this thing had area, and a lot of it.</s>
 <s id="22">But what if I carved out a triangle from this side here?</s>
 <s id="23">As any mook could see, this triangle had a quarter of the area of the full triangle.</s>
 <s id="24">I did the same thing again with each of the smaller triangles.</s>
 <s id="25">Again, a quarter of the remaining area -- gone.</s>
 <s id="26">And I just kept going.</s>
 <s id="27">After an infinite number of cuts, I was satisfied that my triangle had zero area.</s>
 <s id="28">A bounded shape with zero area.</s>
 <s id="29">Now, it's not often that I surprise myself, but my own two mitts had created something crazy, and new.</s>
 <s id="30">"Very good. (ahem) Now, show me a shape with finite area, but an infinitely long perimeter."</s>
 <s id="31">"Let me get this straight.</s>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">If I want to make a snip in the border of this shape, smooth it out, and lay it on the ground ... "</s>
  <s id="32.2">"It would go on for ... "</s>
  <s id="32.3">"Wait 'til I'm through, and then you can talk.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="33">It would go on forever."</s>
 <s id="34">"Are you through?"</s>
 <s id="35">"Yeah."</s>
 <s id="36">"So show me that shape then."</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">Mmm ...</s>
  <s id="37.2">I hadn't been this stuck since the Rubik's Cube fiasco of '58.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="38">All the shapes I knew had perimeters.</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">Circles: 2πr.</s>
  <s id="39.2">Triangles: sum of their sides.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">What's this?</s>
 <s id="41">An angle.</s>
 <s id="42">An angle from heaven.</s>
 <s id="43">What if I were to pinch each side, like so.</s>
 <s id="44">A third of the way through, just so.</s>
 <s id="45">And do it again, and again, and again.</s>
 <s id="46">After each pinch, the perimeter got a third longer because where there had been three line segments, now there were four.</s>
 <s id="47">As for the area, every pinch made more triangles, that's true.</s>
 <s id="48">But those triangles were getting smaller and smaller.</s>
 <s id="49">You could say that the area was converging, approaching a fixed number, while the perimeter was just getting bigger and bigger, uncontrollably ballooning like an overindulgent birthday clown.</s>
 <s id="50">After infinity pinches, flimflam, there it was: Finite area, but infinite perimeter.</s>
 <s id="51">Now that is a piece of work.</s>
 <s id="52">"Oh, you're good. (ahem) Riddle three: Show me a picture that if I magnify it under my microscope, I'll keep seeing the original picture, no matter how much I zoom in."</s>
 <s id="53">"You're a strange little man."</s>
 <s id="54">"Thank you."</s>
 <s id="55">I was out of ideas, so I looked at my muse, my complex Dora.</s>
 <s id="56">Voice: "Who's the dame?"</s>
 <s id="57">And then it hit me.</s>
 <s id="58">"She's a heart breaker, my fractal femme fatale.</s>
 <s id="59">Will she do?"</s>
 <s id="60">"Yes, she'll do just fine."</s>
 <s id="61">(lightning) It was dark, and at first I thought the cave was empty, but then I noticed: the box.</s>
 <s id="62">The dame had played me like a triangle.</s>
 <s id="63">She had told me she wanted to go home.</s>
 <s id="64">(Lightning) What she really wanted was to bring her home here.</s>
 <s id="65">The fractals spread everywhere.</s>
 <s id="66">Most of them the same no matter how deep you looked at them, like Dora's mugshot.</s>
 <s id="67">Some had infinitely long perimeters, others were objects with no area or volume, all of them created through infinite repetition.</s>
 <s id="68">So, you wanted to know what fractals are?</s>
 <s id="69">Well, kid, they're the stuff that dreams are made of.</s>
 <s id="70">(Music)</s>
</text>
