<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Tashka Yawanawá (Sharp exhale) (Sharp exhale) (Sharp exhale) (Sharp exhale) (Singing) (Singing ends) (Sharp exhale) I'm Tashka Yawanawá.</s>
 <s id="2">I'm here with my wife.</s>
 <s id="3">I come from the Yawanawá community, which is located in the state of Acre in the Brazilian Amazon.</s>
 <s id="4">Takes some days to arrive here.</s>
 <s id="5">I just did the song to reconnect us to the spirit of the rainforest.</s>
 <s id="6">From immemorial time, my people live in the Yawanawá territory.</s>
 <s id="7">We see this holistic way of how nature is.</s>
 <s id="8">Nature, to us, belongs to the whole of humanity.</s>
 <s id="9">And we Yawanawá see the environment, the forest, as alive.</s>
 <s id="10">But everything is always a challenge.</s>
 <s id="11">Mostly now, because I think many of you know that the Amazon now is on fire.</s>
 <s id="12">That affects all of us.</s>
 <s id="13">Destroying the Amazon does not affect just the indigenous people, because we are all connected.</s>
 <s id="14">Whatever we do in my community, if I burn everything, it's going to affect it here, when the snow comes here at Christmas.</s>
 <s id="15">If you pollute here, it's going to affect it when the rain comes to my country.</s>
 <s id="16">I used to say we all belong to the global village.</s>
 <s id="17">I used to say, Amazon belongs to humanity, and also that humanity needs to take care as the indigenous do in the world.</s>
 <s id="18">And for this reason, today is a time to wake, unite us.</s>
 <s id="19">We Yawanawá are doing our part.</s>
 <s id="20">We take care of Mother Earth.</s>
 <s id="21">And now, I will give to my wife.</s>
 <s id="22">Laura Yawanawá: We are here with our hearts crying.</s>
 <s id="23">I am smiling here, but my heart is crying, because a lot of our forests are being destroyed.</s>
 <s id="24">And I just want to give you a message.</s>
 <s id="25">This crisis is giving humanity two options.</s>
 <s id="26">One option is you help to end, to destroy and exterminate all our forests and all our cultures that go with it.</s>
 <s id="27">Or, we transform this crisis into an opportunity to empower indigenous people, to support indigenous people and to save the rainforest and their cultures.</s>
 <s id="28">And how can you do that?</s>
 <s id="29">We have, the Yawanawá, we created a life plan, which is our strategic planning that tells us the steps of how we want to secure our territory.</s>
 <s id="30">We take care of about 200,000 hectares of rainforest.</s>
 <s id="31">But now it's under threat.</s>
 <s id="32">So this life plan shows the steps for us to secure our land, our biodiversity, our culture, our education.</s>
 <s id="33">I invite you all, I invite all companies, I invite all governments, all civil society, to listen to indigenous peoples, to go back to our roots.</s>
 <s id="34">We have been here for many, many ... for centuries.</s>
 <s id="35">And we have been trying to scream to the world that we need to protect our territory, our nature.</s>
 <s id="36">And you never listen to us.</s>
 <s id="37">Never.</s>
 <s id="38">I guess this crisis is teaching humanity that now you need to listen to us and to support indigenous peoples directly, to support their initiatives directly.</s>
 <s id="39">So that's the message that I would love to leave to you.</s>
 <s id="40">That indigenous people have the answer, and if you want to save the Amazon, we have to take action now.</s>
 <s id="41">TY: (Sharp exhale) (Applause)</s>
</text>
