<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So when I do my job, people hate me.</s>
 <s id="2">In fact, the better I do my job, the more people hate me.</s>
 <s id="3">And no, I'm not a meter maid, and I'm not an undertaker.</s>
 <s id="4">I am a progressive, lesbian talking head on Fox News.</s>
 <p id="p5">
  <s id="5.1">(Applause) So y'all heard that, right?</s>
  <s id="5.2">Just to make sure, right?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="6">I am a gay talking head on Fox News.</s>
 <s id="7">I am going to tell you how I do it, and the most important thing I've learned.</s>
 <s id="8">So I go on television.</s>
 <s id="9">I debate people who literally want to obliterate everything I believe in -- in some cases, who don't want me and people like me to even exist.</s>
 <s id="10">It's sort of like Thanksgiving with your conservative uncle on steroids, with a live television audience of millions.</s>
 <s id="11">It's totally almost just like that.</s>
 <s id="12">And that's just on air.</s>
 <s id="13">The hate mail I get is unbelievable.</s>
 <s id="14">Last week alone, I got 238 pieces of nasty email and more hate tweets than I can even count.</s>
 <s id="15">I was called an idiot, a traitor, a scourge, a cunt and an ugly man, and that was just in one email.</s>
 <s id="16">(Laughter) So what have I realized, being on the receiving end of all this ugliness?</s>
 <s id="17">Well, my biggest takeaway is that for decades, we've been focused on political correctness, but what matters more is emotional correctness.</s>
 <s id="18">Let me give you a small example.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">I don't care if you call me a dyke.</s>
  <s id="19.2">I really don't.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">I care about two things.</s>
 <s id="21">One, I care that you spell it right.</s>
 <s id="22">(Laughter) (Applause) Just quick refresher, it's D-Y-K-E.</s>
 <s id="23">You'd totally be surprised.</s>
 <s id="24">And second, I don't care about the word, I care about how you use it.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">Are you being friendly?</s>
  <s id="25.2">Are you just being naive?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">Or do you really want to hurt me personally?</s>
 <s id="27">Emotional correctness is the tone, the feeling, how we say what we say, the respect and compassion we show one another.</s>
 <s id="28">And what I've realized is that political persuasion doesn't begin with ideas or facts or data.</s>
 <s id="29">Political persuasion begins with being emotionally correct.</s>
 <s id="30">So when I first went to go work at Fox News, true confession, I expected there to be marks in the carpet from all the knuckle-dragging.</s>
 <s id="31">That, by the way, in case you're paying attention, is not emotionally correct.</s>
 <s id="32">But liberals on my side, we can be self-righteous, we can be condescending, we can be dismissive of anyone who doesn't agree with us.</s>
 <s id="33">In other words, we can be politically right but emotionally wrong.</s>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">And incidentally, that means that people don't like us.</s>
  <s id="34.2">Right?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="35">Now here's the kicker.</s>
 <s id="36">Conservatives are really nice.</s>
 <s id="37">I mean, not all of them, and not the ones who send me hate mail, but you would be surprised.</s>
 <s id="38">Sean Hannity is one of the sweetest guys I've ever met.</s>
 <s id="39">He spends his free time trying to fix up his staff on blind dates, and I know that if I ever had a problem, he would do anything he could to help.</s>
 <s id="40">Now, I think Sean Hannity is 99 percent politically wrong, but his emotional correctness is strikingly impressive.</s>
 <s id="41">And that's why people listen to him.</s>
 <s id="42">Because you can't get anyone to agree with you if they don't even listen to you first.</s>
 <s id="43">We spend so much time talking past each other and not enough time talking through our disagreements.</s>
 <s id="44">And if we can start to find compassion for one another, then we have a shot at building common ground.</s>
 <s id="45">It actually sounds really hokey to say it standing up here, but when you try to put it in practice, it's really powerful.</s>
 <s id="46">So someone who says they hate immigrants, I try to imagine how scared they must be that their community is changing from what they've always known.</s>
 <s id="47">Or someone who says they don't like teachers' unions, I bet they're really devastated to see their kid's school going into the gutter, and they're just looking for someone to blame.</s>
 <s id="48">Our challenge is to find the compassion for others that we want them to have for us.</s>
 <s id="49">That is emotional correctness.</s>
 <s id="50">I'm not saying it's easy.</s>
 <s id="51">An average of, like, 5.6 times per day I have to stop myself from responding to all of my hate mail with a flurry of vile profanities.</s>
 <s id="52">This whole finding compassion and common ground with your enemies thing is kind of like a political-spiritual practice for me, and I ain't the Dalai Lama.</s>
 <s id="53">I'm not perfect, but what I am is optimistic.</s>
 <s id="54">Because I don't just get hate mail.</s>
 <s id="55">I get a lot of really nice letters, lots of them.</s>
 <s id="56">And one of my all-time favorites begins: "I am not a big fan of your political leanings or your sometimes tortured logic, (Laughter) but I'm a big fan of you as a person."</s>
 <s id="57">Now this guy doesn't agree with me -- yet.</s>
 <s id="58">(Laughter) But he's listening -- not because of what I said, but because of how I said it.</s>
 <s id="59">And somehow, even though we've never met, we've managed to form a connection.</s>
 <s id="60">That's emotional correctness, and that's how we start the conversations that really lead to change.</s>
 <s id="61">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="62">(Applause)</s>
</text>
