<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I am no designer, nope, no way.</s>
 <s id="2">My dad was, which is kind of an interesting way to grow up.</s>
 <s id="3">I had to figure out what it is my dad did and why it was important.</s>
 <s id="4">Dad talked a lot about bad design when we were growing up, you know, "Bad design is just people not thinking, John," he would say whenever a kid would be injured by a rotary lawn mower or, say, a typewriter ribbon would get tangled or an eggbeater would get jammed in the kitchen.</s>
 <s id="5">You know, "Design -- bad design, there's just no excuse for it.</s>
 <s id="6">It's letting stuff happen without thinking about it.</s>
 <s id="7">Every object should be about something, John.</s>
 <s id="8">It should imagine a user.</s>
 <s id="9">It should cast that user in a story starring the user and the object.</s>
 <s id="10">Good design," my dad said, "is about supplying intent."</s>
 <s id="11">That's what he said.</s>
 <s id="12">Dad helped design the control panels for the IBM 360 computer.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">That was a big deal; that was important.</s>
  <s id="13.2">He worked for Kodak for a while; that was important.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">He designed chairs and desks and other office equipment for Steelcase; that was important.</s>
 <s id="15">I knew design was important in my house because, for heaven's sake, it put food on our table, right?</s>
 <s id="16">And design was in everything my dad did.</s>
 <s id="17">He had a Dixieland jazz band when we were growing up, and he would always cover Louis Armstrong tunes.</s>
 <s id="18">And I would ask him every once in a while, "Dad, do you want it to sound like the record?"</s>
 <s id="19">We had lots of old jazz records lying around the house.</s>
 <s id="20">And he said, "No, never, John, never.</s>
 <s id="21">The song is just a given, that's how you have to think about it.</s>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">You gotta make it your own.</s>
  <s id="22.2">You gotta design it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">Show everyone what you intend," is what he said.</s>
 <s id="24">"Doing that, acting by design, is what we all should be doing.</s>
 <s id="25">It's where we all belong."</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">All of us?</s>
  <s id="26.2">Designers?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">Oh, oh, Dad.</s>
  <s id="27.2">Oh, Dad.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="28">The song is just a given.</s>
 <s id="29">It's how you cover it that matters.</s>
 <s id="30">Well, let's hold on to that thought for just a minute.</s>
 <s id="31">It's kind of like this wheelchair I'm in, right?</s>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">The original tune?</s>
  <s id="32.2">It's a little scary.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="33">"Ooh, what happened to that dude?</s>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">He can't walk.</s>
  <s id="34.2">Anybody know the story?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="35">Anybody?"</s>
 <s id="36">I don't like to talk about this very much, but I'll tell you guys the story today.</s>
 <s id="37">All right, exactly 36 years ago this week, that's right, I was in a poorly designed automobile that hit a poorly designed guardrail on a poorly designed road in Pennsylvania, and plummeted down a 200-foot embankment and killed two people in the car.</s>
 <s id="38">But ever since then, the wheelchair has been a given in my life.</s>
 <s id="39">My life, at the mercy of good design and bad design.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">Think about it.</s>
  <s id="40.2">Now, in design terms, a wheelchair is a very difficult object.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="41">It mostly projects tragedy and fear and misfortune, and it projects that message, that story, so strongly that it almost blots out anything else.</s>
 <s id="42">I roll swiftly through an airport, right?</s>
 <s id="43">And moms grab their kids out of the way and say, "Don't stare!"</s>
 <s id="44">The poor kid, you know, has this terrified look on his face, God knows what they think.</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">And for decades, I'm going, why does this happen?</s>
  <s id="45.2">What can I do about it?</s>
  <s id="45.3">How can I change this?</s>
  <s id="45.4">I mean there must be something.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="46">So I would roll, I'd make no eye contact -- just kinda frown, right?</s>
 <s id="47">Or I'd dress up really, really sharply or something.</s>
 <s id="48">Or I'd make eye contact with everyone -- that was really creepy; that didn't work at all.</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">(Laughter) You know anything, I'd try.</s>
  <s id="49.2">I wouldn't shower for a week -- nothing worked.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p50">
  <s id="50.1">Nothing whatsoever worked until a few years ago, my six-year-old daughters were looking at this wheelchair catalog that I had, and they said, "Oh, Dad!</s>
  <s id="50.2">Dad!</s>
  <s id="50.3">Look, you gotta get these, these flashy wheels -- you gotta get 'em!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="51">And I said, "Oh, girls, Dad is a very important journalist, that just wouldn't do at all."</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">And of course, they immediately concluded, "Oh, what a bummer, Dad.</s>
  <s id="52.2">Journalists aren't allowed to have flashy wheels.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="53">I mean, how important could you be then?" they said.</s>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">I went, "Wait a minute, all right, right -- I'll get the wheels."</s>
  <s id="54.2">Purely out of protest, I got the flashy wheels, and I installed them and -- check this out.</s>
  <s id="54.3">Could I have my special light cue please?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">(Laughter) Look at that!</s>
 <p id="p56">
  <s id="56.1">Now ... look at, look at this!</s>
  <s id="56.2">Look at this!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="57">So what you are looking at here has completely changed my life, I mean totally changed my life.</s>
 <s id="58">Instead of blank stares and awkwardness, now it is pointing and smiling!</s>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">People going, "Awesome wheels, dude!</s>
  <s id="59.2">Those are awesome!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p60">
  <s id="60.1">I mean, I want some of those wheels!"</s>
  <s id="60.2">Little kids say, "Can I have a ride?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="61">(Laughter) And of course there's the occasional person -- usually a middle-aged male who will say, "Oh, those wheels are great!</s>
 <s id="62">I guess they're for safety, right?"</s>
 <p id="p63">
  <s id="63.1">(Laughter) No!</s>
  <s id="63.2">They're not for safety.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="64">No, no, no, no, no.</s>
 <s id="65">What's the difference here, the wheelchair with no lights and the wheelchair with lights?</s>
 <s id="66">The difference is intent.</s>
 <s id="67">That's right, that's right; I'm no longer a victim.</s>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">I chose to change the situation -- I'm the Commander of the Starship Wheelchair with the phaser wheels in the front.</s>
  <s id="68.2">Right?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="69">Intent changes the picture completely.</s>
 <s id="70">I choose to enhance this rolling experience with a simple design element.</s>
 <s id="71">Acting with intent.</s>
 <s id="72">It conveys authorship.</s>
 <s id="73">It suggests that someone is driving.</s>
 <s id="74">It's reassuring; people are drawn to it.</s>
 <s id="75">Someone making the experience their own.</s>
 <s id="76">Covering the tragic tune with something different, something radically different.</s>
 <s id="77">People respond to that.</s>
 <s id="78">Now it seems simple, but actually I think in our society and culture in general, we have a huge problem with intent.</s>
 <p id="p79">
  <s id="79.1">Now go with me here.</s>
  <s id="79.2">Look at this guy.</s>
  <s id="79.3">You know who this is?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p80">
  <s id="80.1">It's Anders Breivik.</s>
  <s id="80.2">Now, if he intended to kill in Olso, Norway last year, dozens and dozens of young people -- if he intended to do that, he's a vicious criminal.</s>
  <s id="80.3">We punish him.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p81">
  <s id="81.1">Life in prison.</s>
  <s id="81.2">Death penalty in the United States, not so much in Norway.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="82">But, if he instead acted out of a delusional fantasy, if he was motivated by some random mental illness, he's in a completely different category.</s>
 <s id="83">We may put him away for life, but we watch him clinically.</s>
 <s id="84">It's a completely different domain.</s>
 <s id="85">As an intentional murderer, Anders Breivik is merely evil.</s>
 <s id="86">But as a dysfunctional, as a dysfunctional murderer/psychotic, he's something much more complicated.</s>
 <s id="87">He's the breath of some primitive, ancient chaos.</s>
 <s id="88">He's the random state of nature we emerged from.</s>
 <s id="89">He's something very, very different.</s>
 <s id="90">It's as though intent is an essential component for humanity.</s>
 <s id="91">It's what we're supposed to do somehow.</s>
 <s id="92">We're supposed to act with intent.</s>
 <s id="93">We're supposed to do things by design.</s>
 <s id="94">Intent is a marker for civilization.</s>
 <s id="95">Now here's an example a little closer to home: My family is all about intent.</s>
 <s id="96">You can probably tell there are two sets of twins, the result of IVF technology, in vitro fertilization technology, due to some physical limitations I won't go into.</s>
 <s id="97">Anyway, in vitro technology, IVF, is about as intentional as agriculture.</s>
 <s id="98">Let me tell you, some of you may have the experience.</s>
 <s id="99">In fact, the whole technology of sperm extraction for spinal cord-injured males was invented by a veterinarian.</s>
 <p id="p100">
  <s id="100.1">I met the dude.</s>
  <s id="100.2">He's a great guy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="101">He carried this big leather bag full of sperm probes for all of the animals that he'd worked with, all the different animals.</s>
 <s id="102">Probes he designed, and in fact, he was really, really proud of these probes.</s>
 <s id="103">He would say, "You're right between horse and squirrel, John."</s>
 <s id="104">(Laughter) But anyway, so when my wife and I decided to upgrade our early middle age -- we had four kids, after all -- with a little different technology that I won't explain in too much detail here -- my urologist assured me I had nothing whatsoever to worry about.</s>
 <s id="105">"No need for birth control, Doc, are you sure about that?"</s>
 <s id="106">"John, John, I looked at your chart.</s>
 <s id="107">From your sperm tests we can confidently say that you're basically a form of birth control."</s>
 <s id="108">Well!</s>
 <p id="p109">
  <s id="109.1">(Laughter) What a liberating thought!</s>
  <s id="109.2">Yes!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="110">And after a couple very liberating weekends, my wife and I, utilizing some cutting-edge erectile technology that is certainly worthy of a TEDTalk someday but I won't get into it now, we noticed some familiar, if unexpected, symptoms.</s>
 <s id="111">I wasn't exactly a form of birth control.</s>
 <p id="p112">
  <s id="112.1">Look at that font there.</s>
  <s id="112.2">My wife was so pissed.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="113">I mean, did a designer come up with that?</s>
 <s id="114">No, I don't think a designer did come up with that.</s>
 <s id="115">In fact, maybe that's the problem.</s>
 <s id="116">And so, little Ajax was born.</s>
 <s id="117">He's like our other children, but the experience is completely different.</s>
 <s id="118">It's something like my accident, right?</s>
 <s id="119">He came out of nowhere.</s>
 <s id="120">But we all had to change, but not just react to the given; we bend to this new experience with intent.</s>
 <p id="p121">
  <s id="121.1">We're five now.</s>
  <s id="121.2">Five.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p122">
  <s id="122.1">Facing the given with intent.</s>
  <s id="122.2">Doing things by design.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="123">Hey, the name Ajax -- you can't get much more intentional than that, right?</s>
 <s id="124">We're really hoping he thanks us for that later on.</s>
 <p id="p125">
  <s id="125.1">(Laughter) But I never became a designer.</s>
  <s id="125.2">No, no, no, no.</s>
  <s id="125.3">Never attempted.</s>
  <s id="125.4">Never even close.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p126">
  <s id="126.1">I did love some great designs as I was growing up: The HP 35S calculator -- God, I loved that thing.</s>
  <s id="126.2">Oh God, I wish I had one.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="127">Man, I love that thing.</s>
 <s id="128">I could afford that.</s>
 <s id="129">Other designs I really couldn't afford, like the 1974 911 Targa.</s>
 <s id="130">In school, I studied nothing close to design or engineering; I studied useless things like the Classics, but there were some lessons even there -- this guy, Plato, it turns out he's a designer.</s>
 <s id="131">He designed a state in "The Republic," a design never implemented.</s>
 <s id="132">Listen to one of the design features of Plato's Government 4.0: "The State in which the rulers are most reluctant to govern is always the best and most quietly governed, and the State in which they are most eager, the worst."</s>
 <s id="133">Well, got that wrong, didn't we?</s>
 <p id="p134">
  <s id="134.1">But look at that statement; it's all about intent.</s>
  <s id="134.2">That's what I love about it.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p135">
  <s id="135.1">But consider what Plato is doing here.</s>
  <s id="135.2">What is he doing?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="136">It's a grand idea of design -- a huge idea of design, common to all of the voices of religion and philosophy that emerged in the Classical period.</s>
 <s id="137">What was going on then?</s>
 <s id="138">They were trying to answer the question of what would human beings do now that they were no longer simply trying to survive?</s>
 <s id="139">As the human race emerged from a prehistoric chaos, a confrontation with random, brutal nature, they suddenly had a moment to think -- and there was a lot to think about.</s>
 <s id="140">All of a sudden, human existence needed an intent.</s>
 <s id="141">Human life needed a reason.</s>
 <s id="142">Reality itself needed a designer.</s>
 <s id="143">The given was replaced by various aspects of intent, by various designs, by various gods.</s>
 <p id="p144">
  <s id="144.1">Gods we're still fighting about.</s>
  <s id="144.2">Oh yeah.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="145">Today we don't confront the chaos of nature.</s>
 <s id="146">Today it is the chaos of humanity's impact on the Earth itself that we confront.</s>
 <s id="147">This young discipline called design, I think, is in fact the emerging ethos formulating and then answering a very new question: What shall we do now in the face of the chaos that we have created?</s>
 <s id="148">What shall we do?</s>
 <s id="149">How shall we inscribe intent on all the objects we create, on all the circumstances we create, on all the places we change?</s>
 <s id="150">The consequences of a planet with 7 billion people and counting.</s>
 <s id="151">That's the tune we're all covering today, all of us.</s>
 <p id="p152">
  <s id="152.1">And we can't just imitate the past.</s>
  <s id="152.2">No.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="153">That won't do.</s>
 <s id="154">That won't do at all.</s>
 <s id="155">Here's my favorite design moment: In the city of Kinshasa in Zaire in the 1990s, I was working for ABC News, and I was reporting on the fall of Mobutu Sese Seko, the dictator, the brutal dictator in Zaire, who raped and pillaged that country.</s>
 <s id="156">There was rioting in the middle of Kinshasa.</s>
 <s id="157">The place was falling apart; it was a horrible, horrible place, and I needed to go and explore the center of Kinshasa to report on the rioting and the looting.</s>
 <s id="158">People were carrying off vehicles, carrying off pieces of buildings.</s>
 <s id="159">Soldiers were in the streets shooting at looters and herding some in mass arrests.</s>
 <p id="p160">
  <s id="160.1">In the middle of this chaos, I'm rolling around in a wheelchair, and I was completely invisible.</s>
  <s id="160.2">Completely.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="161">I was in a wheelchair; I didn't look like a looter.</s>
 <s id="162">I was in a wheelchair; I didn't look like a journalist, particularly, at least from their perspective.</s>
 <s id="163">And I didn't look like a soldier, that's for sure.</s>
 <s id="164">I was part of this sort of background noise of the misery of Zaire, completely invisible.</s>
 <s id="165">And all of a sudden, from around a corner, comes this young man, paralyzed, just like me, in this metal and wood and leather pedal, three-wheel tricycle-wheelchair device, and he pedals up to me as fast as he can.</s>
 <p id="p166">
  <s id="166.1">He goes, "Hey, mister!</s>
  <s id="166.2">Mister!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="167">And I looked at him -- he didn't know any other English than that, but we didn't need English, no, no, no, no, no.</s>
 <s id="168">We sat there and compared wheels and tires and spokes and tubes.</s>
 <s id="169">And I looked at his whacky pedal mechanism; he was full of pride over his design.</s>
 <s id="170">I wish I could show you that contraption.</s>
 <s id="171">His smile, our glow as we talked a universal language of design, invisible to the chaos around us.</s>
 <s id="172">His machine: homemade, bolted, rusty, comical.</s>
 <s id="173">My machine: American-made, confident, sleek.</s>
 <s id="174">He was particularly proud of the comfortable seat, really comfortable seat he had made in his chariot and its beautiful fabric fringe around the edge.</s>
 <s id="175">Oh, I wish I'd had those sparkly wheels back then to have shown him, man!</s>
 <p id="p176">
  <s id="176.1">He would have loved those!</s>
  <s id="176.2">Oh yeah.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="177">He would have understood those; a chariot of pure intent -- think about it -- in a city out of control.</s>
 <s id="178">Design blew it all away for a moment.</s>
 <s id="179">We spoke for a few minutes and then each of us vanished back into the chaos.</s>
 <p id="p180">
  <s id="180.1">He went back to the streets of Kinshasa; I went to my hotel.</s>
  <s id="180.2">And I think of him now, now ...</s>
 </p>
 <s id="181">And I pose this question.</s>
 <s id="182">An object imbued with intent -- it has power, it's treasure, we're drawn to it.</s>
 <p id="p183">
  <s id="183.1">An object devoid of intent -- it's random, it's imitative, it repels us.</s>
  <s id="183.2">It's like a piece of junk mail to be thrown away.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="184">This is what we must demand of our lives, of our objects, of our things, of our circumstances: living with intent.</s>
 <s id="185">And I have to say that on that score, I have a very unfair advantage over all of you.</s>
 <s id="186">And I want to explain it to you now because this is a very special day.</s>
 <s id="187">Thirty-six years ago at nearly this moment, a 19-year-old boy awoke from a coma to ask a nurse a question, but the nurse was already there with an answer.</s>
 <p id="p188">
  <s id="188.1">"You've had a terrible accident, young man.</s>
  <s id="188.2">You've broken your back.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="189">You'll never walk again."</s>
 <s id="190">I said, "I know all that -- what day is it?"</s>
 <s id="191">You see, I knew that the car had gone over the guardrail on the 28th of February, and I knew that 1976 was a leap year.</s>
 <p id="p192">
  <s id="192.1">"Nurse!</s>
  <s id="192.2">Is this the 28th or the 29th?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="193">And she looked at me and said, "It's March 1st."</s>
 <s id="194">And I went, "Oh my God.</s>
 <s id="195">I've got some catching up to do!"</s>
 <s id="196">And from that moment, I knew the given was that accident; I had no option but to make up this new life without walking.</s>
 <s id="197">Intent -- a life with intent -- lived by design, covering the original with something better.</s>
 <s id="198">It's something for all of us to do or find a way to do in these times.</s>
 <s id="199">To get back to this, to get back to design, and as my daddy suggested a long time ago, "Make the song your own, John.</s>
 <s id="200">Show everybody what you intend."</s>
 <s id="201">Daddy, this one's for you.</s>
 <s id="202">(Music) ♫ Jo Jo was a man who thought he was a loner ♫ ♫ but he was another man. ♫ ♫ Jo Jo left his home in Tucson, Arizona to attend a California bash. ♫ ♫ Get back, get back, ♫ ♫ get back to where you once belonged. ♫ ♫ Get back, get back, ♫ ♫ get back to where you once belonged. ♫ (Applause)</s>
</text>
