<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I would like to tell you about a project which I started about 16 years ago.</s>
 <s id="2">It's about making new forms of life.</s>
 <s id="3">And these are made of this kind of tube -- electricity tube, we call it in Holland.</s>
 <s id="4">And we can start a film about that, and we can see a little bit backwards in time.</s>
 <s id="5">(Video) Narrator: Eventually, these beasts are going to live in herds on the beaches.</s>
 <s id="6">Theo Jansen is working hard on this evolution.</s>
 <s id="7">Theo Jansen: I want to put these forms of life on the beaches.</s>
 <s id="8">And they should survive over there, on their own, in the future.</s>
 <s id="9">Learning to live on their own -- and it'll take couple of more years to let them walk on their own.</s>
 <s id="10">Narrator: The mechanical beasts will not get their energy from food, but from the wind.</s>
 <s id="11">The wind will move feathers on their back, which will drive their feet.</s>
 <s id="12">The beast walks sideways on the wet sand of the beach, with its nose pointed into the wind.</s>
 <s id="13">As soon as it walks into either the rolling surf or the dry sand, it stops, and walks in the opposite direction.</s>
 <s id="14">Evolution has generated many species.</s>
 <s id="15">(Music) This is the Animaris Currens Ventosa.</s>
 <s id="16">(Music) (Laughter) (Applause) TJ: This is a herd, and it is built according to genetic codes.</s>
 <s id="17">And it is a sort of race, and each and every animal is different, and the winning codes will multiply.</s>
 <s id="18">This is the wave, going from left to right.</s>
 <s id="19">You can see this one.</s>
 <s id="20">Yes, and now it goes from left to right.</s>
 <s id="21">This is a new generation, a new family, which is able to store the wind.</s>
 <s id="22">So, the wings pump up air in lemonade bottles, which are on top of that.</s>
 <s id="23">And they can use that energy in case the wind falls away, and the tide is coming up, and there is still a little bit of energy to reach the dunes and save their lives, because they are drowned very easily.</s>
 <s id="24">(Laughter) I could show you this animal.</s>
 <s id="25">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="26">(Applause) So, the proportion of the tubes in this animal is very important for the walking.</s>
 <s id="27">There are 11 numbers, which I call The 11 Holy Numbers.</s>
 <s id="28">These are the distances of the tubes which make it walk that way.</s>
 <s id="29">In fact, it's a new invention of the wheel.</s>
 <s id="30">It works the same as a wheel.</s>
 <s id="31">The axis of a wheel stays on the same level, and this hip is staying on the same level as well.</s>
 <s id="32">In fact, this is better than a wheel, because when you try to drive your bicycle on the beach, you will notice it's very hard to do.</s>
 <s id="33">And the feet just step over the sand, and the wheel has to touch every piece of the ground in-between.</s>
 <s id="34">So 5,000 years after the invention of the wheel, we have a new wheel.</s>
 <s id="35">I will show you, in the next video -- can you start it, please? -- that very heavy loads can be moved.</s>
 <s id="36">There's a guy pushing there, behind, but it can also walk on the wind very well.</s>
 <s id="37">It's 3.2 tons.</s>
 <s id="38">This is working on the stored wind in the bottles.</s>
 <s id="39">It has a feeler, where it can feel obstacles and turn around.</s>
 <s id="40">You see, it's going the other way.</s>
 <s id="41">Can I have the feeler here?</s>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">OK.</s>
  <s id="42.2">Good.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="43">So, they have to survive all the dangers of the beach, and one of the big dangers is the sea.</s>
 <s id="44">This is the sea.</s>
 <s id="45">And it must feel the water of the sea.</s>
 <s id="46">And this is the water feeler, and what's very important is this tube.</s>
 <s id="47">It sucks in air normally, but when it swallows water, it feels the resistance of it.</s>
 <s id="48">So, imagine that the animal is walking towards the sea.</s>
 <s id="49">As soon as it touches the water -- you should hear a sound of running air.</s>
 <s id="50">(Sound of running air) Yes!</s>
 <s id="51">So if it doesn't feel, it will be drowned, OK?</s>
 <s id="52">Here we have the brain of the animal.</s>
 <s id="53">In fact, it is a step counter, and it counts the steps.</s>
 <s id="54">It's a binary step counter.</s>
 <s id="55">So as soon it has been to the sea, it changes the pattern of zeroes and ones here.</s>
 <s id="56">And it always knows where it is on the beach.</s>
 <s id="57">So it's very simple brain.</s>
 <s id="58">It says, well, there's the sea, there are dunes, and I'm here.</s>
 <s id="59">So it's a sort of imagination of the simple world of the beach animal.</s>
 <s id="60">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="61">One of the biggest enemies are the storms.</s>
 <s id="62">This is a part of the nose of the Animaris Percipiere.</s>
 <s id="63">When the nose of the animal is fixed, the whole animal is fixed.</s>
 <s id="64">So when the storm is coming up, it drives a pin into the ground.</s>
 <s id="65">(Laughter) Audience member: Wow!</s>
 <s id="66">The nose is fixed, the whole animal is fixed.</s>
 <s id="67">The wind may turn, but the animal will always turn its nose into the wind.</s>
 <s id="68">Now, another couple of years, and these animals will survive on their own.</s>
 <s id="69">I still have to help them a lot.</s>
 <s id="70">Thank you very much, ladies and gentlemen.</s>
 <s id="71">(Applause)</s>
</text>
