<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Dialogue gives a story color, makes it exciting and moves it forward.</s>
 <s id="2">Romeo: O, wilt thou leave me so unsatisfied?</s>
 <s id="3">Juliet: What satisfaction canst thou have tonight?</s>
 <s id="4">Romeo: The exchange of thy love's faithful vows for mine.</s>
 <s id="5">Without dialogue: (cricket sounds) So what goes into writing effective dialogue?</s>
 <s id="6">Well, there are social skills: making friends, solving conflicts, being pleasant and polite.</s>
 <s id="7">We won't be using any of those today.</s>
 <s id="8">Instead, we'll be working on -- let's call them "anti-social skills."</s>
 <s id="9">If you're a writer, you may already have a few of these.</s>
 <s id="10">The first is eavesdropping.</s>
 <s id="11">If you're riding a bus and hear an interesting conversation, you could write it all down.</s>
 <s id="12">Of course, when you write fiction, you're not describing real people, you're making up characters.</s>
 <s id="13">But sometimes the words you overhear can give you ideas.</s>
 <s id="14">"I did not," says one person.</s>
 <s id="15">"I saw you," the other replies.</s>
 <s id="16">Who might be saying those words?</s>
 <s id="17">Maybe it's two kids in a class, and the boy thinks the girl pushed him.</s>
 <s id="18">Maybe it's a couple, but one of them is a vampire, and the woman vampire saw the man flirting with a zombie.</s>
 <s id="19">Or maybe not.</s>
 <s id="20">Maybe the characters are a teenager and his mother, and they're supposed to be vegetarians, but the mother saw him eating a burger.</s>
 <s id="21">So let's say you've decided on some characters.</s>
 <s id="22">This is anti-social skill number two: start pretending they're real.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">What are they like?</s>
  <s id="23.2">Where are they from?</s>
  <s id="23.3">What music do they listen to?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="24">Spend some time with them.</s>
 <s id="25">If you're on a bus, think about what they might be doing if they were there too.</s>
 <s id="26">Would they talk on the phone, listen to music, draw pictures, sleep?</s>
 <s id="27">What we say depends on who we are.</s>
 <s id="28">An older person might speak differently than a younger person.</s>
 <s id="29">Someone from the south might speak differently than someone from the north.</s>
 <s id="30">Once you know your characters, you can figure out how they talk.</s>
 <s id="31">At this stage, it's helpful to use anti-social skill number three: muttering to yourself.</s>
 <s id="32">When you speak your character's words, you can hear whether they sound natural, and fix them if necessary.</s>
 <s id="33">Remember, most people are usually pretty informal when they speak.</s>
 <s id="34">They use simple language and contractions.</s>
 <s id="35">So, "Do not attempt to lie to me" sounds more natural as "Don't try to lie to me."</s>
 <s id="36">Also keep it short.</s>
 <s id="37">People tend to speak in short bursts, not lengthy speeches.</s>
 <s id="38">And let the dialogue do the work.</s>
 <s id="39">Ask yourself: do I really need that adverb?</s>
 <s id="40">For instance, "'Your money or your life,' she said threateningly."</s>
 <s id="41">Here, "threateningly" is redundant, so you can get rid of it.</s>
 <s id="42">But if the words and the actions don't match, an adverb can be helpful.</s>
 <s id="43">"'Your money or your life,' she said lovingly."</s>
 <p id="p44">
  <s id="44.1">So, to recap: First, eavesdrop.</s>
  <s id="44.2">Next, pretend imaginary people are real.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="45">Finally, mutter to yourself, and write it all down.</s>
 <s id="46">You already have everything you need.</s>
 <s id="47">This is fictional dialogue, or "How to Hear Voices in Your Head."</s>
</text>
