<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm used to thinking of the TED audience as a wonderful collection of some of the most effective, intelligent, intellectual, savvy, worldly and innovative people in the world.</s>
 <s id="2">And I think that's true.</s>
 <s id="3">However, I also have reason to believe that many, if not most, of you are actually tying your shoes incorrectly.</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) Now I know that seems ludicrous.</s>
 <s id="5">I know that seems ludicrous.</s>
 <s id="6">And believe me, I lived the same sad life until about three years ago.</s>
 <s id="7">And what happened to me was I bought, what was for me, a very expensive pair of shoes.</s>
 <s id="8">But those shoes came with round nylon laces, and I couldn't keep them tied.</s>
 <s id="9">So I went back to the store and said to the owner, "I love the shoes, but I hate the laces."</s>
 <s id="10">He took a look and said, "Oh, you're tying them wrong."</s>
 <s id="11">Now up until that moment, I would have thought that, by age 50, one of the life skills that I had really nailed was tying my shoes.</s>
 <s id="12">(Laughter) But not so -- let me demonstrate.</s>
 <s id="13">This is the way that most of us were taught to tie our shoes.</s>
 <s id="14">Now as it turns out -- thank you.</s>
 <s id="15">(Applause) Wait, there's more.</s>
 <s id="16">As it turns out -- (Laughter) there's a strong form and a weak form of this knot, and we were taught the weak form.</s>
 <s id="17">And here's how to tell.</s>
 <s id="18">If you pull the strands at the base of the knot, you will see that the bow will orient itself down the long axis of the shoe.</s>
 <s id="19">That's the weak form of the knot.</s>
 <s id="20">But not to worry.</s>
 <s id="21">If we start over and simply go the other direction around the bow, we get this, the strong form of the knot.</s>
 <s id="22">And if you pull the cords under the knot, you will see that the bow orients itself along the transverse axis of the shoe.</s>
 <s id="23">This is a stronger knot.</s>
 <s id="24">It will come untied less often.</s>
 <s id="25">It will let you down less, and not only that, it looks better.</s>
 <s id="26">We're going to do this one more time.</s>
 <s id="27">(Applause) Start as usual -- (Applause) go the other way around the loop.</s>
 <s id="28">This is a little hard for children, but I think you can handle it.</s>
 <s id="29">Pull the knot.</s>
 <s id="30">There it is: the strong form of the shoe knot.</s>
 <s id="31">Now, in keeping with today's theme, I'd like to point out -- something you already know -- that sometimes a small advantage someplace in life can yield tremendous results someplace else.</s>
 <s id="32">(Laughter) Live long and prosper.</s>
 <s id="33">(Applause)</s>
</text>
