<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Joseph Keller used to jog around the Stanford campus, and he was struck by all the women jogging there as well.</s>
 <s id="2">Why did their ponytails swing from side to side like that?</s>
 <s id="3">Being a mathematician, he set out to understand why.</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) Professor Keller was curious about many things: why teapots dribble or how earthworms wriggle.</s>
 <s id="5">Until a few months ago, I hadn't heard of Joseph Keller.</s>
 <s id="6">I read about him in the New York Times, in the obituaries.</s>
 <s id="7">The Times had half a page of editorial dedicated to him, which you can imagine is premium space for a newspaper of their stature.</s>
 <s id="8">I read the obituaries almost every day.</s>
 <s id="9">My wife understandably thinks I'm rather morbid to begin my day with scrambled eggs and a "Let's see who died today."</s>
 <s id="10">(Laughter) But if you think about it, the front page of the newspaper is usually bad news, and cues man's failures.</s>
 <s id="11">An instance where bad news cues accomplishment is at the end of the paper, in the obituaries.</s>
 <s id="12">In my day job, I run a company that focuses on future insights that marketers can derive from past data -- a kind of rearview-mirror analysis.</s>
 <s id="13">And we began to think: What if we held a rearview mirror to obituaries from the New York Times?</s>
 <s id="14">Were there lessons on how you could get your obituary featured -- even if you aren't around to enjoy it?</s>
 <s id="15">(Laughter) Would this go better with scrambled eggs?</s>
 <s id="16">(Laughter) And so, we looked at the data.</s>
 <s id="17">2,000 editorial, non-paid obituaries over a 20-month period between 2015 and 2016.</s>
 <s id="18">What did these 2,000 deaths -- rather, lives -- teach us?</s>
 <s id="19">Well, first we looked at words.</s>
 <s id="20">This here is an obituary headline.</s>
 <s id="21">This one is of the amazing Lee Kuan Yew.</s>
 <s id="22">If you remove the beginning and the end, you're left with a beautifully worded descriptor that tries to, in just a few words, capture an achievement or a lifetime.</s>
 <s id="23">Just looking at these is fascinating.</s>
 <s id="24">Here are a few famous ones, people who died in the last two years.</s>
 <s id="25">Try and guess who they are.</s>
 <s id="26">[An Artist who Defied Genre] That's Prince.</s>
 <s id="27">[Titan of Boxing and the 20th Century] Oh, yes.</s>
 <s id="28">[Muhammad Ali] [Groundbreaking Architect] Zaha Hadid.</s>
 <s id="29">So we took these descriptors and did what's called natural language processing, where you feed these into a program, it throws out the superfluous words -- "the," "and," -- the kind of words you can mime easily in "Charades," -- and leaves you with the most significant words.</s>
 <s id="30">And we did it not just for these four, but for all 2,000 descriptors.</s>
 <s id="31">And this is what it looks like.</s>
 <s id="32">Film, theatre, music, dance and of course, art, are huge.</s>
 <s id="33">Over 40 percent.</s>
 <s id="34">You have to wonder why in so many societies we insist that our kids pursue engineering or medicine or business or law to be construed as successful.</s>
 <s id="35">And while we're talking profession, let's look at age -- the average age at which they achieved things.</s>
 <s id="36">That number is 37.</s>
 <s id="37">What that means is, you've got to wait 37 years ...</s>
 <s id="38">before your first significant achievement that you're remembered for -- on average -- 44 years later, when you die at the age of 81 -- on average.</s>
 <s id="39">(Laughter) Talk about having to be patient.</s>
 <s id="40">(Laughter) Of course, it varies by profession.</s>
 <s id="41">If you're a sports star, you'll probably hit your stride in your 20s.</s>
 <s id="42">And if you're in your 40s like me, you can join the fun world of politics.</s>
 <s id="43">(Laughter) Politicians do their first and sometimes only commendable act in their mid-40s.</s>
 <s id="44">(Laughter) If you're wondering what "others" are, here are some examples.</s>
 <s id="45">Isn't it fascinating, the things people do and the things they're remembered for?</s>
 <s id="46">(Laughter) Our curiosity was in overdrive, and we desired to analyze more than just a descriptor.</s>
 <s id="47">So, we ingested the entire first paragraph of all 2,000 obituaries, but we did this separately for two groups of people: people that are famous and people that are not famous.</s>
 <s id="48">Famous people -- Prince, Ali, Zaha Hadid -- people who are not famous are people like Jocelyn Cooper, Reverend Curry or Lorna Kelly.</s>
 <s id="49">I'm willing to bet you haven't heard of most of their names.</s>
 <s id="50">Amazing people, fantastic achievements, but they're not famous.</s>
 <s id="51">So what if we analyze these two groups separately -- the famous and the non-famous?</s>
 <s id="52">What might that tell us?</s>
 <s id="53">Take a look.</s>
 <s id="54">Two things leap out at me.</s>
 <s id="55">First: "John."</s>
 <s id="56">(Laughter) Anyone here named John should thank your parents -- (Laughter) and remind your kids to cut out your obituary when you're gone.</s>
 <s id="57">And second: "help."</s>
 <s id="58">We uncovered, many lessons from lives well-led, and what those people immortalized in print could teach us.</s>
 <s id="59">The exercise was a fascinating testament to the kaleidoscope that is life, and even more fascinating was the fact that the overwhelming majority of obituaries featured people famous and non-famous, who did seemingly extraordinary things.</s>
 <s id="60">They made a positive dent in the fabric of life.</s>
 <s id="61">They helped.</s>
 <s id="62">So ask yourselves as you go back to your daily lives: How am I using my talents to help society?</s>
 <s id="63">Because the most powerful lesson here is, if more people lived their lives trying to be famous in death, the world would be a much better place.</s>
 <s id="64">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="65">(Applause)</s>
</text>
