<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">It's the Second World War.</s>
 <s id="2">A German prison camp.</s>
 <s id="3">And this man, Archie Cochrane, is a prisoner of war and a doctor, and he has a problem.</s>
 <s id="4">The problem is that the men under his care are suffering from an excruciating and debilitating condition that Archie doesn't really understand.</s>
 <s id="5">The symptoms are this horrible swelling up of fluids under the skin.</s>
 <s id="6">But he doesn't know whether it's an infection, whether it's to do with malnutrition.</s>
 <s id="7">He doesn't know how to cure it.</s>
 <s id="8">And he's operating in a hostile environment.</s>
 <s id="9">And people do terrible things in wars.</s>
 <s id="10">The German camp guards, they've got bored.</s>
 <s id="11">They've taken to just firing into the prison camp at random for fun.</s>
 <s id="12">On one particular occasion, one of the guards threw a grenade into the prisoners' lavatory while it was full of prisoners.</s>
 <s id="13">He said he heard suspicious laughter.</s>
 <s id="14">And Archie Cochrane, as the camp doctor, was one of the first men in to clear up the mess.</s>
 <s id="15">And one more thing: Archie was suffering from this illness himself.</s>
 <s id="16">So the situation seemed pretty desperate.</s>
 <s id="17">But Archie Cochrane was a resourceful person.</s>
 <s id="18">He'd already smuggled vitamin C into the camp, and now he managed to get hold of supplies of marmite on the black market.</s>
 <s id="19">Now some of you will be wondering what marmite is.</s>
 <s id="20">Marmite is a breakfast spread beloved of the British.</s>
 <s id="21">It looks like crude oil.</s>
 <s id="22">It tastes ...</s>
 <s id="23">zesty.</s>
 <s id="24">And importantly, it's a rich source of vitamin B12.</s>
 <s id="25">So Archie splits the men under his care as best he can into two equal groups.</s>
 <s id="26">He gives half of them vitamin C.</s>
 <s id="27">He gives half of them vitamin B12.</s>
 <s id="28">He very carefully and meticulously notes his results in an exercise book.</s>
 <s id="29">And after just a few days, it becomes clear that whatever is causing this illness, marmite is the cure.</s>
 <s id="30">So Cochrane then goes to the Germans who are running the prison camp.</s>
 <s id="31">Now you've got to imagine at the moment -- forget this photo, imagine this guy with this long ginger beard and this shock of red hair.</s>
 <s id="32">He hasn't been able to shave -- a sort of Billy Connolly figure.</s>
 <s id="33">Cochrane, he starts ranting at these Germans in this Scottish accent -- in fluent German, by the way, but in a Scottish accent -- and explains to them how German culture was the culture that gave Schiller and Goethe to the world.</s>
 <s id="34">And he can't understand how this barbarism can be tolerated, and he vents his frustrations.</s>
 <s id="35">And then he goes back to his quarters, breaks down and weeps because he's convinced that the situation is hopeless.</s>
 <s id="36">But a young German doctor picks up Archie Cochrane's exercise book and says to his colleagues, "This evidence is incontrovertible.</s>
 <s id="37">If we don't supply vitamins to the prisoners, it's a war crime."</s>
 <s id="38">And the next morning, supplies of vitamin B12 are delivered to the camp, and the prisoners begin to recover.</s>
 <s id="39">Now I'm not telling you this story because I think Archie Cochrane is a dude, although Archie Cochrane is a dude.</s>
 <s id="40">I'm not even telling you the story because I think we should be running more carefully controlled randomized trials in all aspects of public policy, although I think that would also be completely awesome.</s>
 <s id="41">I'm telling you this story because Archie Cochrane, all his life, fought against a terrible affliction, and he realized it was debilitating to individuals and it was corrosive to societies.</s>
 <s id="42">And he had a name for it.</s>
 <s id="43">He called it the God complex.</s>
 <s id="44">Now I can describe the symptoms of the God complex very, very easily.</s>
 <s id="45">So the symptoms of the complex are, no matter how complicated the problem, you have an absolutely overwhelming belief that you are infallibly right in your solution.</s>
 <s id="46">Now Archie was a doctor, so he hung around with doctors a lot.</s>
 <s id="47">And doctors suffer from the God complex a lot.</s>
 <s id="48">Now I'm an economist, I'm not a doctor, but I see the God complex around me all the time in my fellow economists.</s>
 <s id="49">I see it in our business leaders.</s>
 <s id="50">I see it in the politicians we vote for -- people who, in the face of an incredibly complicated world, are nevertheless absolutely convinced that they understand the way that the world works.</s>
 <s id="51">And you know, with the future billions that we've been hearing about, the world is simply far too complex to understand in that way.</s>
 <s id="52">Well let me give you an example.</s>
 <s id="53">Imagine for a moment that, instead of Tim Harford in front of you, there was Hans Rosling presenting his graphs.</s>
 <s id="54">You know Hans: the Mick Jagger of TED.</s>
 <s id="55">(Laughter) And he'd be showing you these amazing statistics, these amazing animations.</s>
 <s id="56">And they are brilliant; it's wonderful work.</s>
 <s id="57">But a typical Hans Rosling graph: think for a moment, not what it shows, but think instead about what it leaves out.</s>
 <s id="58">So it'll show you GDP per capita, population, longevity, that's about it.</s>
 <s id="59">So three pieces of data for each country -- three pieces of data.</s>
 <s id="60">Three pieces of data is nothing.</s>
 <s id="61">I mean, have a look at this graph.</s>
 <s id="62">This is produced by the physicist Cesar Hidalgo.</s>
 <s id="63">He's at MIT.</s>
 <s id="64">Now you won't be able to understand a word of it, but this is what it looks like.</s>
 <s id="65">Cesar has trolled the database of over 5,000 different products, and he's used techniques of network analysis to interrogate this database and to graph relationships between the different products.</s>
 <s id="66">And it's wonderful, wonderful work.</s>
 <s id="67">You show all these interconnections, all these interrelations.</s>
 <s id="68">And I think it'll be profoundly useful in understanding how it is that economies grow.</s>
 <s id="69">Brilliant work.</s>
 <s id="70">Cesar and I tried to write a piece for The New York Times Magazine explaining how this works.</s>
 <s id="71">And what we learned is Cesar's work is far too good to explain in The New York Times Magazine.</s>
 <s id="72">Five thousand products -- that's still nothing.</s>
 <s id="73">Five thousand products -- imagine counting every product category in Cesar Hidalgo's data.</s>
 <s id="74">Imagine you had one second per product category.</s>
 <s id="75">In about the length of this session, you would have counted all 5,000.</s>
 <s id="76">Now imagine doing the same thing for every different type of product on sale in Walmart.</s>
 <p id="p77">
  <s id="77.1">There are 100,000 there.</s>
  <s id="77.2">It would take you all day.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="78">Now imagine trying to count every different specific product and service on sale in a major economy such as Tokyo, London or New York.</s>
 <s id="79">It's even more difficult in Edinburgh because you have to count all the whisky and the tartan.</s>
 <s id="80">If you wanted to count every product and service on offer in New York -- there are 10 billion of them -- it would take you 317 years.</s>
 <s id="81">This is how complex the economy we've created is.</s>
 <s id="82">And I'm just counting toasters here.</s>
 <s id="83">I'm not trying to solve the Middle East problem.</s>
 <s id="84">The complexity here is unbelievable.</s>
 <s id="85">And just a piece of context -- the societies in which our brains evolved had about 300 products and services.</s>
 <s id="86">You could count them in five minutes.</s>
 <s id="87">So this is the complexity of the world that surrounds us.</s>
 <s id="88">This perhaps is why we find the God complex so tempting.</s>
 <s id="89">We tend to retreat and say, "We can draw a picture, we can post some graphs, we get it, we understand how this works."</s>
 <s id="90">And we don't.</s>
 <s id="91">We never do.</s>
 <s id="92">Now I'm not trying to deliver a nihilistic message here.</s>
 <s id="93">I'm not trying to say we can't solve complicated problems in a complicated world.</s>
 <s id="94">We clearly can.</s>
 <s id="95">But the way we solve them is with humility -- to abandon the God complex and to actually use a problem-solving technique that works.</s>
 <s id="96">And we have a problem-solving technique that works.</s>
 <s id="97">Now you show me a successful complex system, and I will show you a system that has evolved through trial and error.</s>
 <s id="98">Here's an example.</s>
 <s id="99">This baby was produced through trial and error.</s>
 <s id="100">I realize that's an ambiguous statement.</s>
 <s id="101">Maybe I should clarify it.</s>
 <s id="102">This baby is a human body: it evolved.</s>
 <s id="103">What is evolution?</s>
 <s id="104">Over millions of years, variation and selection, variation and selection -- trial and error, trial and error.</s>
 <s id="105">And it's not just biological systems that produce miracles through trial and error.</s>
 <s id="106">You could use it in an industrial context.</s>
 <s id="107">So let's say you wanted to make detergent.</s>
 <s id="108">Let's say you're Unilever and you want to make detergent in a factory near Liverpool.</s>
 <s id="109">How do you do it?</s>
 <s id="110">Well you have this great big tank full of liquid detergent.</s>
 <s id="111">You pump it at a high pressure through a nozzle.</s>
 <s id="112">You create a spray of detergent.</s>
 <p id="p113">
  <s id="113.1">Then the spray dries.</s>
  <s id="113.2">It turns into powder.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="114">It falls to the floor.</s>
 <p id="p115">
  <s id="115.1">You scoop it up.</s>
  <s id="115.2">You put it in cardboard boxes.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="116">You sell it at a supermarket.</s>
 <s id="117">You make lots of money.</s>
 <s id="118">How do you design that nozzle?</s>
 <s id="119">It turns out to be very important.</s>
 <s id="120">Now if you ascribe to the God complex, what you do is you find yourself a little God.</s>
 <s id="121">You find yourself a mathematician; you find yourself a physicist -- somebody who understands the dynamics of this fluid.</s>
 <s id="122">And he will, or she will, calculate the optimal design of the nozzle.</s>
 <s id="123">Now Unilever did this and it didn't work -- too complicated.</s>
 <s id="124">Even this problem, too complicated.</s>
 <s id="125">But the geneticist Professor Steve Jones describes how Unilever actually did solve this problem -- trial and error, variation and selection.</s>
 <s id="126">You take a nozzle and you create 10 random variations on the nozzle.</s>
 <s id="127">You try out all 10; you keep the one that works best.</s>
 <s id="128">You create 10 variations on that one.</s>
 <p id="p129">
  <s id="129.1">You try out all 10.</s>
  <s id="129.2">You keep the one that works best.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="130">You try out 10 variations on that one.</s>
 <s id="131">You see how this works, right?</s>
 <s id="132">And after 45 generations, you have this incredible nozzle.</s>
 <s id="133">It looks a bit like a chess piece -- functions absolutely brilliantly.</s>
 <s id="134">We have no idea why it works, no idea at all.</s>
 <s id="135">And the moment you step back from the God complex -- let's just try to have a bunch of stuff; let's have a systematic way of determining what's working and what's not -- you can solve your problem.</s>
 <s id="136">Now this process of trial and error is actually far more common in successful institutions than we care to recognize.</s>
 <s id="137">And we've heard a lot about how economies function.</s>
 <s id="138">The U.S. economy is still the world's greatest economy.</s>
 <s id="139">How did it become the world's greatest economy?</s>
 <s id="140">I could give you all kinds of facts and figures about the U.S. economy, but I think the most salient one is this: ten percent of American businesses disappear every year.</s>
 <s id="141">That is a huge failure rate.</s>
 <s id="142">It's far higher than the failure rate of, say, Americans.</s>
 <s id="143">Ten percent of Americans don't disappear every year.</s>
 <s id="144">Which leads us to conclude American businesses fail faster than Americans, and therefore American businesses are evolving faster than Americans.</s>
 <s id="145">And eventually, they'll have evolved to such a high peak of perfection that they will make us all their pets -- (Laughter) if, of course, they haven't already done so.</s>
 <s id="146">I sometimes wonder.</s>
 <s id="147">But it's this process of trial and error that explains this great divergence, this incredible performance of Western economies.</s>
 <s id="148">It didn't come because you put some incredibly smart person in charge.</s>
 <s id="149">It's come through trial and error.</s>
 <s id="150">Now I've been sort of banging on about this for the last couple of months, and people sometimes say to me, "Well Tim, it's kind of obvious.</s>
 <s id="151">Obviously trial and error is very important.</s>
 <s id="152">Obviously experimentation is very important.</s>
 <s id="153">Now why are you just wandering around saying this obvious thing?"</s>
 <s id="154">So I say, okay, fine.</s>
 <s id="155">You think it's obvious?</s>
 <s id="156">I will admit it's obvious when schools start teaching children that there are some problems that don't have a correct answer.</s>
 <s id="157">Stop giving them lists of questions every single one of which has an answer.</s>
 <s id="158">And there's an authority figure in the corner behind the teacher's desk who knows all the answers.</s>
 <s id="159">And if you can't find the answers, you must be lazy or stupid.</s>
 <s id="160">When schools stop doing that all the time, I will admit that, yes, it's obvious that trial and error is a good thing.</s>
 <s id="161">When a politician stands up campaigning for elected office and says, "I want to fix our health system.</s>
 <s id="162">I want to fix our education system.</s>
 <s id="163">I have no idea how to do it.</s>
 <s id="164">I have half a dozen ideas.</s>
 <p id="p165">
  <s id="165.1">We're going to test them out.</s>
  <s id="165.2">They'll probably all fail.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="166">Then we'll test some other ideas out.</s>
 <p id="p167">
  <s id="167.1">We'll find some that work.</s>
  <s id="167.2">We'll build on those.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="168">We'll get rid of the ones that don't." -- when a politician campaigns on that platform, and more importantly, when voters like you and me are willing to vote for that kind of politician, then I will admit that it is obvious that trial and error works, and that -- thank you.</s>
 <s id="169">(Applause) Until then, until then I'm going to keep banging on about trial and error and why we should abandon the God complex.</s>
 <s id="170">Because it's so hard to admit our own fallibility.</s>
 <s id="171">It's so uncomfortable.</s>
 <s id="172">And Archie Cochrane understood this as well as anybody.</s>
 <s id="173">There's this one trial he ran many years after World War II.</s>
 <s id="174">He wanted to test out the question of, where is it that patients should recover from heart attacks?</s>
 <s id="175">Should they recover in a specialized cardiac unit in hospital, or should they recover at home?</s>
 <s id="176">All the cardiac doctors tried to shut him down.</s>
 <s id="177">They had the God complex in spades.</s>
 <s id="178">They knew that their hospitals were the right place for patients, and they knew it was very unethical to run any kind of trial or experiment.</s>
 <s id="179">Nevertheless, Archie managed to get permission to do this.</s>
 <s id="180">He ran his trial.</s>
 <s id="181">And after the trial had been running for a little while, he gathered together all his colleagues around his table, and he said, "Well, gentlemen, we have some preliminary results.</s>
 <s id="182">They're not statistically significant.</s>
 <s id="183">But we have something.</s>
 <s id="184">And it turns out that you're right and I'm wrong.</s>
 <s id="185">It is dangerous for patients to recover from heart attacks at home.</s>
 <s id="186">They should be in hospital."</s>
 <s id="187">And there's this uproar, and all the doctors start pounding the table and saying, "We always said you were unethical, Archie.</s>
 <p id="p188">
  <s id="188.1">You're killing people with your clinical trials.</s>
  <s id="188.2">You need to shut it down now.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="189">Shut it down at once."</s>
 <s id="190">And there's this huge hubbub.</s>
 <s id="191">Archie lets it die down.</s>
 <s id="192">And then he says, "Well that's very interesting, gentlemen, because when I gave you the table of results, I swapped the two columns around.</s>
 <s id="193">It turns out your hospitals are killing people, and they should be at home.</s>
 <s id="194">Would you like to close down the trial now, or should we wait until we have robust results?"</s>
 <s id="195">Tumbleweed rolls through the meeting room.</s>
 <s id="196">But Cochrane would do that kind of thing.</s>
 <s id="197">And the reason he would do that kind of thing is because he understood it feels so much better to stand there and say, "Here in my own little world, I am a god, I understand everything.</s>
 <s id="198">I do not want to have my opinions challenged.</s>
 <s id="199">I do not want to have my conclusions tested."</s>
 <s id="200">It feels so much more comfortable simply to lay down the law.</s>
 <s id="201">Cochrane understood that uncertainty, that fallibility, that being challenged, they hurt.</s>
 <s id="202">And you sometimes need to be shocked out of that.</s>
 <s id="203">Now I'm not going to pretend that this is easy.</s>
 <s id="204">It isn't easy.</s>
 <s id="205">It's incredibly painful.</s>
 <s id="206">And since I started talking about this subject and researching this subject, I've been really haunted by something a Japanese mathematician said on the subject.</s>
 <s id="207">So shortly after the war, this young man, Yutaka Taniyama, developed this amazing conjecture called the Taniyama-Shimura Conjecture.</s>
 <s id="208">It turned out to be absolutely instrumental many decades later in proving Fermat's Last Theorem.</s>
 <s id="209">In fact, it turns out it's equivalent to proving Fermat's Last Theorem.</s>
 <s id="210">You prove one, you prove the other.</s>
 <s id="211">But it was always a conjecture.</s>
 <s id="212">Taniyama tried and tried and tried and he could never prove that it was true.</s>
 <s id="213">And shortly before his 30th birthday in 1958, Yutaka Taniyama killed himself.</s>
 <s id="214">His friend, Goro Shimura -- who worked on the mathematics with him -- many decades later, reflected on Taniyama's life.</s>
 <s id="215">He said, "He was not a very careful person as a mathematician.</s>
 <s id="216">He made a lot of mistakes.</s>
 <s id="217">But he made mistakes in a good direction.</s>
 <s id="218">I tried to emulate him, but I realized it is very difficult to make good mistakes."</s>
 <s id="219">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="220">(Applause)</s>
</text>
