<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm a designer and an educator.</s>
 <s id="2">I'm a multitasking person, and I push my students to fly through a very creative, multitasking design process.</s>
 <s id="3">But how efficient is, really, this multitasking?</s>
 <s id="4">Let's consider for a while the option of monotasking.</s>
 <s id="5">A couple of examples.</s>
 <s id="6">Look at that.</s>
 <p id="p7">
  <s id="7.1">This is my multitasking activity result.</s>
  <s id="7.2">(Laughter) So trying to cook, answering the phone, writing SMS, and maybe uploading some pictures about this awesome barbecue.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="8">So someone tells us the story about supertaskers, so this two percent of people who are able to control multitasking environment.</s>
 <s id="9">But what about ourselves, and what about our reality?</s>
 <s id="10">When's the last time you really enjoyed just the voice of your friend?</s>
 <s id="11">So this is a project I'm working on, and this is a series of front covers to downgrade our super, hyper — (Laughter) (Applause) to downgrade our super, hyper-mobile phones into the essence of their function.</s>
 <s id="12">Another example: Have you ever been to Venice?</s>
 <s id="13">How beautiful it is to lose ourselves in these little streets on the island.</s>
 <s id="14">But our multitasking reality is pretty different, and full of tons of information.</s>
 <s id="15">So what about something like that to rediscover our sense of adventure?</s>
 <s id="16">I know that it could sound pretty weird to speak about mono when the number of possibilities is so huge, but I push you to consider the option of focusing on just one task, or maybe turning your digital senses totally off.</s>
 <s id="17">So nowadays, everyone could produce his mono product.</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">Why not?</s>
  <s id="18.2">So find your monotask spot within the multitasking world.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="19">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="20">(Applause)</s>
</text>
