<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Two years ago, I was invited as an artist to participate in an exhibition commemorating 100 years of Islamic art in Europe.</s>
 <s id="2">The curator had only one condition: I had to use the Arabic script for my artwork.</s>
 <s id="3">Now, as an artist, a woman, an Arab, or a human being living in the world in 2010, I only had one thing to say: I wanted to say no.</s>
 <s id="4">And in Arabic, to say "no," we say "no, and a thousand times no."</s>
 <s id="5">So I decided to look for a thousand different noes.</s>
 <s id="6">on everything ever produced under Islamic or Arab patronage in the past 1,400 years, from Spain to the borders of China.</s>
 <s id="7">I collected my findings in a book, placed them chronologically, stating the name, the patron, the medium and the date.</s>
 <s id="8">Now, the book sat on a small shelf next to the installation, which stood three by seven meters, in Munich, Germany, in September of 2010.</s>
 <s id="9">Now, in January, 2011, the revolution started, and life stopped for 18 days, and on the 12th of February, we naively celebrated on the streets of Cairo, believing that the revolution had succeeded.</s>
 <p id="p10">
  <s id="10.1">Nine months later I found myself spraying messages in Tahrir Square.</s>
  <s id="10.2">The reason for this act was this image that I saw in my newsfeed.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="11">I did not feel that I could live in a city where people were being killed and thrown like garbage on the street.</s>
 <s id="12">So I took one "no" off a tombstone from the Islamic Museum in Cairo, and I added a message to it: "no to military rule."</s>
 <s id="13">And I started spraying that on the streets in Cairo.</s>
 <s id="14">But that led to a series of no, coming out of the book like ammunition, and adding messages to them, and I started spraying them on the walls.</s>
 <s id="15">So I'll be sharing some of these noes with you.</s>
 <s id="16">No to a new Pharaoh, because whoever comes next should understand that we will never be ruled by another dictator.</s>
 <s id="17">No to violence: Ramy Essam came to Tahrir on the second day of the revolution, and he sat there with this guitar, singing.</s>
 <s id="18">One month after Mubarak stepped down, this was his reward.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">No to blinding heroes.</s>
  <s id="19.2">Ahmed Harara lost his right eye on the 28th of January, and he lost his left eye on the 19th of November, by two different snipers.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">No to killing, in this case no to killing men of religion, because Sheikh Ahmed Adina Refaat was shot on December 16th, during a demonstration, leaving behind three orphans and a widow.</s>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">No to burning books.</s>
  <s id="21.2">The Institute of Egypt was burned on December 17th, a huge cultural loss.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="22">No to stripping the people, and the blue bra is to remind us of our shame as a nation when we allow a veiled woman to be stripped and beaten on the street, and the footprint reads, "Long live a peaceful revolution," because we will never retaliate with violence.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">No to barrier walls.</s>
  <s id="23.2">On February 5th, concrete roadblocks were set up in Cairo to protect the Ministry of Defense from protesters.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="24">Now, speaking of walls, I want to share with you the story of one wall in Cairo.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">A group of artists decided to paint a life-size tank on a wall.</s>
  <s id="25.2">It's one to one.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">In front of this tank there's a man on a bicycle with a breadbasket on his head.</s>
  <s id="26.2">To any passerby, there's no problem with this visual.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">After acts of violence, another artist came, painted blood, protesters being run over by the tank, demonstrators, and a message that read, "Starting tomorrow, I wear the new face, the face of every martyr.</s>
  <s id="27.2">I exist."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">Authority comes, paints the wall white, leaves the tank and adds a message: "Army and people, one hand.</s>
  <s id="28.2">Egypt for Egyptians."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">Another artist comes, paints the head of the military as a monster eating a maiden in a river of blood in front of the tank.</s>
 <s id="30">Authority comes, paints the wall white, leaves the tank, leaves the suit, and throws a bucket of black paint just to hide the face of the monster.</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">So I come with my stencils, and I spray them on the suit, on the tank, and on the whole wall, and this is how it stands today until further notice.</s>
  <s id="31.2">(Laughter) Now, I want to leave you with a final no.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">I found Neruda scribbled on a piece of paper in a field hospital in Tahrir, and I decided to take a no of Mamluk Mausoleum in Cairo.</s>
 <s id="33">The message reads, [Arabic] "You can crush the flowers, but you can't delay spring."</s>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">Thank you.</s>
  <s id="34.2">(Applause) (Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="34.3">Shukran.</s>
  <s id="34.4">(Applause)</s>
 </p>
</text>
