<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Music) (Singing) It was a teenage wedding and the old folks wished them well.</s>
 <s id="2">You could see that Pierre did truly love the mademoiselle.</s>
 <s id="3">Oh, and now the young monsieur and madame have rung the chapel bell.</s>
 <s id="4">C'est la vie, say the old folks, it goes to show you never can tell.</s>
 <s id="5">No, no.</s>
 <s id="6">They furnished off an apartment with a two-room Roebuck sale.</s>
 <s id="7">The coolerator was crammed with TV dinners and ginger ale.</s>
 <s id="8">Oh, but when Pierre found work, the little money comin' worked out well .</s>
 <s id="9">C'est la vie, say the old folks, it goes to show you never can tell.</s>
 <s id="10">You never can tell.</s>
 <s id="11">They bought a souped-up jitney, was a cherry red '53.</s>
 <s id="12">They drove it down to New Orleans to celebrate their anniversary.</s>
 <s id="13">Oh, it was there where Pierre was wedded to the lovely mademoiselle.</s>
 <s id="14">C'est la vie, say the old folks, it goes to show you never can tell.</s>
 <s id="15">No, no, you never can tell.</s>
 <s id="16">No, no, you never can tell.</s>
 <s id="17">You never can tell.</s>
 <s id="18">You never can tell.</s>
 <s id="19">No, no, you never can tell.</s>
 <s id="20">(Applause and cheers) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="21">I recently had the tremendous opportunity of searching for gold in the vast mine of songs released by Chess Records, a Chicago-based label that was really very active in the '50s and '60s in the US and that music spread all over the world.</s>
 <s id="22">And the songs that I'm singing tonight are from an album that I just put out called, "Playing Chess," that pays homage to those songs.</s>
 <s id="23">And these guys were really the innovators of rock 'n' roll and soul and R&amp;amp;B as we now know it.</s>
 <s id="24">(Applause) (Music) (Singing) Over the mountain, across the sea, there's a girl waiting, she's waiting for ...</s>
 <s id="25">me.</s>
 <s id="26">(Music) Over the river, beyond every cloud, she's passed the wind blowin' loud.</s>
 <s id="27">Over the mountain, a girl waits for me.</s>
 <s id="28">(Music) Tell the sands, every blade of grass, please tell the wind to let my love pass.</s>
 <s id="29">Over the mountain, a girl waits for me.</s>
 <s id="30">Tell the moon up -- up in the sky.</s>
 <s id="31">Tell all the birds that fly on by that over and over the mountain ...</s>
 <s id="32">my love waits for me.</s>
 <s id="33">Oh, into each dark, starry night, oh, what a mystery that's sealed so tight.</s>
 <s id="34">Over the mountain, a girl waits for me.</s>
 <s id="35">Tell the moon up -- up in the sky.</s>
 <s id="36">Tell the birds that fly by that over and over the mountain my love waits for me.</s>
 <s id="37">Into each dark and starry night, oh, what a mystery that's sealed so tight.</s>
 <s id="38">Over the mountains, a girl waits for me.</s>
 <s id="39">She waits for me.</s>
 <s id="40">Oh, she waits for me.</s>
 <s id="41">I know, I know, I know, I know, I know.</s>
 <s id="42">Oh, I know, I know, I know, I know, I know.</s>
 <s id="43">Oh, I know, I know, I know, I know, I know, oh oh, oh oh.</s>
 <s id="44">(Applause and cheers)</s>
</text>
