<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In 1944, 11 years before her fateful decision on a Montgomery Bus, Rosa Parks was investigating a vicious crime.</s>
 <s id="2">As an emissary for the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, she had traveled to rural Alabama to meet with Recy Taylor, a young woman who had been sexually assaulted by six white men.</s>
 <s id="3">It would be difficult enough to convince an Alabama court that even one of these men was guilty, but Rosa was undeterred.</s>
 <s id="4">She formed a committee to defend Recy in court, flooding the media with testimony and sparking protests throughout the South.</s>
 <s id="5">When a jury failed to indict the attackers, Parks demanded the governor assemble a new grand jury.</s>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">She wrote, “I know that you will not fail to let the people of Alabama know that there is equal justice for all of our citizens.”</s>
  <s id="6.2">Throughout her life, Parks repeatedly challenged racial violence and the prejudiced systems protecting its perpetrators.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="7">But this work came at an enormous risk— and a personal price.</s>
 <s id="8">Born in 1913, Rosa was raised by her mother and grandparents in rural Alabama.</s>
 <s id="9">But outside this loving home, the fear of racial violence cast a long shadow.</s>
 <s id="10">The Ku Klux Klan frequently drove past their home, and Jim Crow laws segregated public spaces.</s>
 <s id="11">At 19 she settled in Montgomery and married Raymond Parks, a barber who shared her growing fury at racial injustice.</s>
 <s id="12">He was involved with the local chapter of the NAACP; a role many avoided for fear of persecution.</s>
 <s id="13">At first Raymond was eager to keep Rosa safe from the potential dangers of activism.</s>
 <s id="14">But as she grew more incensed at the limitations imposed on African Americans, she could no longer stand by.</s>
 <s id="15">When she officially joined the NAACP in 1943, Parks and Johnnie Rebecca Carr were the only women in the Montgomery chapter.</s>
 <s id="16">She began keeping minutes for their meetings, and soon found herself elected secretary of the chapter— formally beginning her secret double life.</s>
 <s id="17">By day, Rosa worked as a seamstress to support her mother and husband.</s>
 <s id="18">By night, she researched and documented numerous civil rights cases, from local policy disputes to high-profile murder cases and hate crimes.</s>
 <s id="19">As secretary, she prepared public responses on behalf of the Montgomery chapter, battling the harsh sentencing, false accusation and smear campaigns frequently used against African Americans.</s>
 <s id="20">In addition to her legal work, Parks was a brilliant local strategist.</s>
 <s id="21">As advisor to the NAACP youth group council, she helped young people navigate segregated systems including voter registration and whites-only libraries.</s>
 <s id="22">Through the cover of the NAACP, Parks strived to bring clandestine civil rights activities into the open.</s>
 <s id="23">She advocated for civil disobedience training and spoke out against racial violence, particularly the murder of Emmet Till.</s>
 <s id="24">In 1955, her refusal to move to the back of a segregated bus helped ignite the grassroots movement she had hoped for.</s>
 <s id="25">Parks was arrested and jailed for her one-woman protest, where she was visited by local activists.</s>
 <s id="26">Together they planned a twenty-four hour bus boycott.</s>
 <s id="27">It lasted for three hundred and eighty-one days.</s>
 <s id="28">Park’s simple act had transformed nascent civil rights activism into a national movement.</s>
 <s id="29">In 1956, the boycott ended when the Supreme Court ruled in favor of desegregating public transport.</s>
 <s id="30">But this victory for the movement had come at a great cost.</s>
 <s id="31">Rosa had been receiving vicious death threats throughout the campaign, and was unable to find work in Montgomery because of her political reputation.</s>
 <s id="32">In 1957, she moved to Detroit to continue working as a seamstress, until being hired by Congressman John Conyers to help support his burgeoning civil rights campaigns.</s>
 <s id="33">Ever vigilant in the fight against racial inequality, Parks remained active for the next 40 years.</s>
 <s id="34">She wrote several books, traveled across the country giving talks to support other activists, and established an institute for the education of young people in her late husband’s memory.</s>
 <s id="35">Today, Rosa Parks is remembered as a radical spirit who railed against the most powerful people and policies.</s>
 <s id="36">Her call to action continues to resound: “knowing what must be done does away with fear.”</s>
</text>
