<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Imagine a world in which you see numbers and letters as colored even though they're printed in black, in which music or voices trigger a swirl of moving, colored shapes, in which words and names fill your mouth with unusual flavors.</s>
 <s id="2">Jail tastes like cold, hard bacon while Derek tastes like earwax.</s>
 <s id="3">Welcome to synesthesia, the neurological phenomenon that couples two or more senses in 4% of the population.</s>
 <s id="4">A synesthete might not only hear my voice, but also see it, taste it, or feel it as a physical touch.</s>
 <s id="5">Sharing the same root with anesthesia, meaning no sensation, synesthesia means joined sensation.</s>
 <s id="6">Having one type, such as colored hearing, gives you a 50% chance of having a second, third, or fourth type.</s>
 <s id="7">One in 90 among us experience graphemes, the written elements of language, like letters, numerals, and punctuation marks, as saturated with color.</s>
 <s id="8">Some even have gender or personality.</s>
 <s id="9">For Gail, 3 is athletic and sporty, 9 is a vain, elitist girl.</s>
 <s id="10">By contrast, the sound units of language, or phonemes, trigger synestetic tastes.</s>
 <s id="11">For James, college tastes like sausage, as does message and similar words with the -age ending.</s>
 <s id="12">Synesthesia is a trait, like having blue eyes, rather than a disorder because there's nothing wrong.</s>
 <s id="13">In fact, all the extra hooks endow synesthetes with superior memories.</s>
 <s id="14">For example, a girl runs into someone she met long ago.</s>
 <s id="15">"Let's see, she had a green name.</s>
 <s id="16">D's are green: Debra, Darby, Dorothy, Denise.</s>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">Yes!</s>
  <s id="17.2">Her name is Denise!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="18">Once established in childhood, pairings remain fixed for life.</s>
 <s id="19">Synesthetes inherit a biological propensity for hyperconnecting brain neurons, but then must be exposed to cultural artifacts, such as calendars, food names, and alphabets.</s>
 <s id="20">The amazing thing is that a single nucleotide change in the sequence of one's DNA alters perception.</s>
 <s id="21">In this way, synesthesia provides a path to understanding subjective differences, how two people can see the same thing differently.</s>
 <s id="22">Take Sean, who prefers blue tasting food, such as milk, oranges, and spinach.</s>
 <s id="23">The gene heightens normally occurring connections between the taste area in his frontal lobe and the color area further back.</s>
 <s id="24">But suppose in someone else that the gene acted in non-sensory areas.</s>
 <s id="25">You would then have the ability to link seemingly unrelated things, which is the definition of metaphor, seeing the similar in the dissimilar.</s>
 <s id="26">Not surprisingly, synesthesia is more common in artists who excel at making metaphors, like novelist Vladimir Nabokov, painter David Hockney, and composers Billy Joel and Lady Gaga.</s>
 <s id="27">But why do the rest of us non-synesthetes understand metaphors like "sharp cheese" or "sweet person"?</s>
 <s id="28">It so happens that sight, sound, and movement already map to one another so closely, that even bad ventriloquists convince us that the dummy is talking.</s>
 <s id="29">Movies, likewise, can convince us that the sound is coming from the actors' mouths rather than surrounding speakers.</s>
 <s id="30">So, inwardly, we're all synesthetes, outwardly unaware of the perceptual couplings happening all the time.</s>
 <s id="31">Cross-talk in the brain is the rule, not the exception.</s>
 <s id="32">And that sounds like a sweet deal to me!</s>
</text>
