<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Behold the human brain, it's lumpy landscape visibly split into a left and right side.</s>
 <s id="2">This structure has inspired one of the most pervasive ideas about the brain, that the left side controls logic and the right, creativity.</s>
 <s id="3">And yet, this is a myth unsupported by scientific evidence.</s>
 <s id="4">So how did this misleading idea come about, and what does it get wrong?</s>
 <s id="5">It's true that the brain has a right and a left side.</s>
 <s id="6">This is most apparent with the outer layer, or the cortex.</s>
 <s id="7">Internal regions, like the striatum, hypothalamus, thalamus, and brain stem appear to be made from continuous tissue, but in fact, they're also organized with left and right sides.</s>
 <s id="8">The left and the right sides of the brain do control different body functions, such as movement and sight.</s>
 <s id="9">The brain's right side controls the motion of the left arm and leg and vice versa.</s>
 <s id="10">The visual system is even more complex.</s>
 <s id="11">Each eye has a left and right visual field.</s>
 <s id="12">Both left visual fields are sent to the right side of the brain, and both right fields are sent to the left side.</s>
 <s id="13">So the brain uses both sides to make a complete image of the world.</s>
 <s id="14">Scientists don't know for sure why we have that crossing over.</s>
 <s id="15">One theory is it began soon after animals developed more complex nervous systems because it gave the survival advantage of quicker reflexes.</s>
 <s id="16">If an animal sees a predator coming from its left side, it's best off escaping to the right.</s>
 <s id="17">So we can say that vision and movement control are two systems that rely on this left-right structure, but problems arise when we over-extend that idea to logic and creativity.</s>
 <s id="18">This misconception began in the mid-1800s when two neurologists, Broca and Wernicke, examined patients who had problems communicating due to injuries.</s>
 <s id="19">The researchers found damage to the patients' left temporal lobes, so they suggested that language is controlled by the left side of the brain.</s>
 <s id="20">That captured the popular imagination.</s>
 <s id="21">Author Robert Louis Stevenson then introduced the idea of a logical left hemisphere competing with an emotional right hemisphere represented by his characters Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde.</s>
 <s id="22">But this idea didn't hold up when doctors and scientists examined patients who were missing a hemisphere or had their two hemispheres separated.</s>
 <s id="23">These patients showed a complete range of behaviors, both logical and creative.</s>
 <s id="24">Later research showed that one side of the brain is more active than the other for some functions.</s>
 <s id="25">Language is more localized to the left and attention to the right.</s>
 <s id="26">So one side of the brain may do more work, but this varies by system rather than by person.</s>
 <s id="27">There isn't any evidence to suggest that individuals have dominant sides of the brain, or to support the idea of a left-right split between logic and creativity.</s>
 <s id="28">Some people may be particularly logical or creative, but that has nothing to do with the sides of their brains.</s>
 <s id="29">And even the idea of logic and creativity being at odds with each other doesn't hold up well.</s>
 <s id="30">Solving complex math problems requires inspired creativity and many vibrant works of art have intricate logical frameworks.</s>
 <s id="31">Almost every feat of creativity and logic carries the mark of the whole brain functioning as one.</s>
</text>
