<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Hi.</s>
 <s id="2">I've received hate online.</s>
 <s id="3">A lot of it.</s>
 <s id="4">And it comes with the territory of my work.</s>
 <s id="5">I'm a digital creator, I make things specifically for the internet.</s>
 <s id="6">Like, a few years ago, I made a video series called "Every Single Word" where I edited down popular films to only the words spoken by people of color, as a way to empirically and accessibly talk about the issue of representation in Hollywood.</s>
 <s id="7">Then, later, as transphobic bathroom bill started gaining media attention around the United States, I hosted and produced an interview series called "Sitting in Bathrooms with Trans People" where I did exactly that.</s>
 <s id="8">(Laughter) And then -- Sure, I'll take applause.</s>
 <s id="9">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="10">And then, are you familiar with those unboxing videos on YouTube where YouTubers open up the latest electronic gadgets?</s>
 <s id="11">Great, so I satirized those in a weekly series, where instead I unboxed intangible ideologies like police brutality, masculinity and the mistreatment of Native Americans.</s>
 <s id="12">(Laughter) My work -- Thanks.</s>
 <s id="13">One person applauding, God bless.</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) Mom, hi.</s>
 <s id="15">(Laughter) So, my work became popular.</s>
 <s id="16">Very popular.</s>
 <s id="17">I got millions of views, a ton of great press and a slew of new followers.</s>
 <s id="18">But the flip side of success on the internet is internet hate.</s>
 <s id="19">I was called everything.</s>
 <s id="20">From "beta" to "snowflake" and, of course, the ever-popular "cuck."</s>
 <s id="21">Don't worry, I will break these terms down for you.</s>
 <s id="22">(Laughter) So, "beta," for those of you unfamiliar, is shorthand online lingo for "beta male."</s>
 <s id="23">But let's be real, I wear pearl earrings and my fashion aesthetic is rich-white-woman-running-errands, so I'm not angling to be an alpha.</s>
 <s id="24">(Applause) Doesn't totally work.</s>
 <s id="25">(Laughter) Now, "snowflake" is a put-down for people who are sensitive and believe themselves to be unique, and I'm a millennial and an only child, so, duh!</s>
 <s id="26">(Laughter) But my favorite, favorite, favorite is "cuck."</s>
 <s id="27">It's a slur, short for "cuckold," for men who have been cheated on by their wives.</s>
 <s id="28">But friends, I am so gay, that if I had a wife, I would encourage her to cheat on me.</s>
 <s id="29">(Laughter) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="30">Let's take a look at some of this negativity in action.</s>
 <s id="31">Sometimes it's direct.</s>
 <s id="32">Like Marcos, who wrote, "You're everything I hate in a human being."</s>
 <s id="33">Thank you, Marcos.</s>
 <s id="34">Others are more concise.</s>
 <s id="35">Like Donovan, who wrote, "gaywad fagggggg."</s>
 <s id="36">Now, I do need to point out, Donovan is not wrong, OK?</s>
 <s id="37">In fact, he's right on both counts, so credit where credit is due.</s>
 <s id="38">Thank you, Donovan.</s>
 <s id="39">Others write to me with questions, like Brian, who asked, "Were you born a bitch or did you just learn to be one over time?"</s>
 <s id="40">But my favorite thing about this is that once Brian was done typing, his finger must have slipped because then he sent me the thumbs-up emoji.</s>
 <s id="41">(Laughter) So, babe, thumbs up to you, too.</s>
 <s id="42">(Laughter) It's fun to talk about these messages now.</s>
 <s id="43">Right?</s>
 <s id="44">And it's cathartic to laugh at them.</s>
 <s id="45">But I can tell you that it really does not feel good to receive them.</s>
 <s id="46">At first, I would screenshot their comments and make fun of their typos, but this soon felt elitist and ultimately unhelpful.</s>
 <s id="47">So over time, I developed an unexpected coping mechanism.</s>
 <s id="48">Because most of these messages I received were through social media, I could often click on the profile picture of the person who sent them and learn everything about them.</s>
 <s id="49">I could see pictures they were tagged in, posts they'd written, memes they'd shared, and somehow, seeing that it was a human on the other side of the screen made me feel a little better.</s>
 <s id="50">Not to justify what they wrote, right?</s>
 <s id="51">But just to provide context.</s>
 <s id="52">Still, that didn't feel like enough.</s>
 <s id="53">So, I called some of them -- only the ones I felt safe talking to -- with a simple opening question: "Why did you write that?"</s>
 <s id="54">The first person I spoke to was Josh.</s>
 <s id="55">He had written to tell me that I was a moron, I was a reason this country was dividing itself, and he added at the end that being gay was a sin.</s>
 <s id="56">I was so nervous for our first conversation.</s>
 <s id="57">This wasn't a comments section.</s>
 <s id="58">So I couldn't use tools like muting or blocking.</s>
 <s id="59">Of course, I guess, I could have hung up on him.</s>
 <s id="60">But I didn't want to.</s>
 <s id="61">Because I liked talking to him.</s>
 <s id="62">Because I liked him.</s>
 <s id="63">Here's a clip of one of our conversations.</s>
 <s id="64">(Audio) Dylan Marron: Josh, you said you're about to graduate high school, right?</s>
 <s id="65">Josh: Mmm-hmm.</s>
 <s id="66">DM: How is high school for you?</s>
 <s id="67">Josh: Am I allowed to use the H-E-double-hockey-stick word?</s>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">DM: Oh, yeah.</s>
  <s id="68.2">You're allowed to.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="69">Josh: It was hell.</s>
 <s id="70">DM: Really?</s>
 <s id="71">Josh: And it's still hell right now, even though it's only two weeks left.</s>
 <s id="72">I'm a little bit bigger -- I don't like to use the word "fat," but I am a little bit bigger than a lot of my classmates and they seem to judge me before they even got to know me.</s>
 <s id="73">DM: That's awful.</s>
 <s id="74">I mean, I also just want to let you know, Josh, I was bullied in high school, too.</s>
 <s id="75">So did our common ground of being bullied in high school erase what he wrote me?</s>
 <s id="76">No.</s>
 <s id="77">And did our single phone conversation radically heal a politically divided country and cure systemic injustice?</s>
 <s id="78">No, absolutely not, right?</s>
 <s id="79">But did our conversation humanize us to each other more than profile pictures and posts ever could?</s>
 <s id="80">Absolutely.</s>
 <s id="81">I didn't stop there.</s>
 <s id="82">Because some of the hate I received was from "my side."</s>
 <s id="83">So when Matthew, a queer liberal artist like me publicly wrote that I represented some of the worst aspects of liberalism, I wanted to ask him this.</s>
 <s id="84">DM: You tagged me in this post.</s>
 <s id="85">Did you want me to see it?</s>
 <s id="86">Matthew (Laughing): I honestly didn't think that you would.</s>
 <s id="87">DM: Have you ever been publicly dragged?</s>
 <s id="88">Matthew: I have been.</s>
 <s id="89">And I just said, "No, I don't care."</s>
 <s id="90">DM: And did you not care?</s>
 <s id="91">Matthew: But it was hard.</s>
 <s id="92">DM: Did you not care?</s>
 <s id="93">Matthew: Oh, I cared, yes.</s>
 <s id="94">DM: At the end of these conversations, there's often a moment of reflection.</s>
 <s id="95">A reconsideration.</s>
 <s id="96">And that's exactly what happened at the end of my call with a guy named Doug who had written that I was a talentless propaganda hack.</s>
 <s id="97">(Audio) Did the conversation we just had -- does it, like, make you feel differently about how you write online?</s>
 <p id="p98">
  <s id="98.1">Doug: Yeah!</s>
  <s id="98.2">You know, when I said this to you, when I said you were a "talentless hack," I had never conversed with you in my life, really.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="99">I didn't really know anything really about you.</s>
 <s id="100">And I think that a lot of times, that's what the comment sections really are, it's really a way to get your anger at the world out on random profiles of strangers, pretty much.</s>
 <s id="101">DM (Laughing): Yeah, right.</s>
 <s id="102">Doug: But it definitely has made me rethink the way that I interact with people online.</s>
 <s id="103">DM: So I've collected these conversations and many others for my podcast "Conversations with People Who Hate Me."</s>
 <s id="104">(Laughter) Before I started this project, I thought that the real way to bring about change was to shut down opposing viewpoints through epically worded video essays and comments and posts, but I soon learned those were only cheered on by the people who already agreed with me.</s>
 <s id="105">Sometimes -- bless you.</s>
 <s id="106">Sometimes, the most subversive thing you could do -- yeah, clap for him.</s>
 <s id="107">(Laughter) Sometimes, the most subversive thing you could do was to actually speak with the people you disagreed with, and not simply at them.</s>
 <s id="108">Now in every one of my calls, I always ask my guests to tell me about themselves.</s>
 <s id="109">And it's their answer to this question that allows me to empathize with them.</s>
 <s id="110">And empathy, it turns out, is a key ingredient in getting these conversations off the ground, but it can feel very vulnerable to be empathizing with someone you profoundly disagree with.</s>
 <s id="111">So I established a helpful mantra for myself.</s>
 <s id="112">Empathy is not endorsement.</s>
 <s id="113">Empathizing with someone you profoundly disagree with does not suddenly compromise your own deeply held beliefs and endorse theirs.</s>
 <s id="114">Empathizing with someone who, for example, believes that being gay is a sin doesn't mean that I'm suddenly going to drop everything, pack my bags and grab my one-way ticket to hell, right?</s>
 <s id="115">It just means that I'm acknowledging the humanity of someone who was raised to think very differently from me.</s>
 <s id="116">I also want to be super clear about something.</s>
 <s id="117">This is not a prescription for activism.</s>
 <s id="118">I understand that some people don't feel safe talking to their detractors and others feel so marginalized that they justifiably don't feel that they have any empathy to give.</s>
 <s id="119">I totally get that.</s>
 <s id="120">This is just what I feel well-suited to do.</s>
 <s id="121">You know, I've reached out to a lot of people for this podcast.</s>
 <s id="122">And some have politely declined, others have read my message and ignored it, some have blocked me automatically when I sent the invitation and one guy actually agreed to do it and then, five minutes into the call, hung up on me.</s>
 <s id="123">I'm also aware that this talk will appear on the internet.</s>
 <s id="124">And with the internet comes comment sections, and with comment sections inevitably comes hate.</s>
 <s id="125">So as you are watching this talk, you can feel free to call me whatever you'd like.</s>
 <s id="126">You can call me a "gaywad," a "snowflake," a "cuck," a "beta," or "everything wrong with liberalism."</s>
 <s id="127">But just know that if you do, I may ask you to talk.</s>
 <s id="128">And if you refuse or block me automatically or agree and hang up on me, then maybe, babe, the snowflake is you.</s>
 <s id="129">Thank you so much.</s>
 <s id="130">(Applause) (Cheering) (Applause)</s>
</text>
