<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The most romantic thing to ever happen to me online started out the way most things do: without me, and not online.</s>
 <s id="2">On December 10, 1896, the man on the medal, Alfred Nobel, died.</s>
 <s id="3">One hundred years later, exactly, actually, December 10, 1996, this charming lady, Wislawa Szymborska, won the Nobel Prize for literature.</s>
 <s id="4">She's a Polish poet.</s>
 <s id="5">She's a big deal, obviously, but back in '96, I thought I had never heard of her, and when I checked out her work, I found this sweet little poem, "Four in the Morning."</s>
 <s id="6">"The hour from night to day.</s>
 <s id="7">The hour from side to side.</s>
 <s id="8">The hour for those past thirty..."</s>
 <s id="9">And it goes on, but as soon as I read this poem, I fell for it hard, so hard, I suspected we must have met somewhere before.</s>
 <s id="10">Had I shared an elevator ride with this poem?</s>
 <s id="11">Did I flirt with this poem in a coffee shop somewhere?</s>
 <s id="12">I could not place it, and it bugged me, and then in the coming week or two, I would just be watching an old movie, and this would happen.</s>
 <s id="13">(Video) Groucho Marx: Charlie, you should have come to the first party.</s>
 <s id="14">We didn't get home till around four in the morning.</s>
 <s id="15">Rives: My roommates would have the TV on, and this would happen.</s>
 <s id="16">(Music: Seinfeld theme) (Video) George Costanza: Oh boy, I was up til four in the morning watching that Omen trilogy.</s>
 <s id="17">Rives: I would be listening to music, and this would happen.</s>
 <s id="18">(Video) Elton John: ♪ It's four o'clock in the morning, damn it. ♪ Rives: So you can see what was going on, right?</s>
 <s id="19">Obviously, the demigods of coincidence were just messing with me.</s>
 <s id="20">Some people get a number stuck in their head, you may recognize a certain name or a tune, some people get nothing, but four in the morning was in me now, but mildly, like a groin injury.</s>
 <s id="21">I always assumed it would just go away on its own eventually, and I never talked about it with anybody, but it did not, and I totally did.</s>
 <s id="22">In 2007, I was invited to speak at TED for the second time, and since I was still an authority on nothing, I thought, what if I made a multimedia presentation on a topic so niche it is actually inconsequential or actually cockamamie.</s>
 <s id="23">So my talk had some of my four in the morning examples, but it also had examples from my fellow TED speakers that year.</s>
 <s id="24">I found four in the morning in a novel by Isabel Allende.</s>
 <s id="25">I found a really great one in the autobiography of Bill Clinton.</s>
 <s id="26">I found a couple in the work of Matt Groening, although Matt Groening told me later that he could not make my talk because it was a morning session and I gather that he is not an early riser.</s>
 <s id="27">However, had Matt been there, he would have seen this mock conspiracy theory that was un-freaking-canny for me to assemble.</s>
 <s id="28">It was totally contrived just for that room, just for that moment.</s>
 <s id="29">That's how we did it in the pre-TED.com days.</s>
 <p id="p30">
  <s id="30.1">It was fun.</s>
  <s id="30.2">That was pretty much it.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">When I got home, though, the emails started coming in from people who had seen the talk live, beginning with, and this is still my favorite, "Here's another one for your collection: 'It's the friends you can call up at 4 a.m. that matter.'"</s>
  <s id="31.2">The sentiment is Marlene Dietrich.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">The email itself was from another very sexy European type, TED Curator Chris Anderson.</s>
 <s id="33">(Laughter) Chris found this quote on a coffee cup or something, and I'm thinking, this man is the Typhoid Mary of ideas worth spreading, and I have infected him.</s>
 <s id="34">I am contagious, which was confirmed less than a week later when a Hallmark employee scanned and sent an actual greeting card with that same quotation.</s>
 <s id="35">As a bonus, she hooked me up with a second one they make.</s>
 <s id="36">It says, "Just knowing I can call you at four in the morning if I need to makes me not really need to," which I love, because together these are like, "Hallmark: When you care enough to send the very best twice, phrased slightly differently."</s>
 <s id="37">I was not surprised at the TEDster and New Yorker magazine overlap.</s>
 <s id="38">A bunch of people sent me this when it came out.</s>
 <s id="39">"It's 4 a.m.—maybe you'd sleep better if you bought some crap."</s>
 <s id="40">I was surprised at the TEDster/"Rugrats" overlap.</s>
 <s id="41">More than one person sent me this.</s>
 <s id="42">(Video) Didi Pickles: It's four o'clock in the morning.</s>
 <s id="43">Why on Earth are you making chocolate pudding?</s>
 <s id="44">Stu Pickles: Because I've lost control of my life.</s>
 <s id="45">(Laughter) Rives: And then there was the lone TEDster who was disgruntled I had overlooked what he considers to be a classic.</s>
 <p id="p46">
  <s id="46.1">(Video) Roy Neary: Get up, get up!</s>
  <s id="46.2">I'm not kidding.</s>
  <s id="46.3">Ronnie Neary: Is there an accident?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">Roy: No, it's not an accident.</s>
  <s id="47.2">You wanted to get out of the house anyway, right?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="48">Ronnie: Not at four o'clock in the morning.</s>
 <s id="49">Rives: So that's "Close Encounters," and the main character is all worked up because aliens, momentously, have chosen to show themselves to earthlings at four in the morning, which does make that a very solid example.</s>
 <s id="50">Those were all really solid examples.</s>
 <s id="51">They did not get me any closer to understanding why I thought I recognized this one particular poem.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">But they followed the pattern.</s>
  <s id="52.2">They played along.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p53">
  <s id="53.1">Right?</s>
  <s id="53.2">Four in the morning as this scapegoat hour when all these dramatic occurrences allegedly occur.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="54">Maybe this was some kind of cliche that had never been taxonomized before.</s>
 <s id="55">Maybe I was on the trail of a new meme or something.</s>
 <s id="56">Just when things were getting pretty interesting, things got really interesting.</s>
 <s id="57">TED.com launched, later that year, with a bunch of videos from past talks, including mine, and I started receiving "four in the morning" citations from what seemed like every time zone on the planet.</s>
 <s id="58">Much of it was content I never would have found on my own if I was looking for it, and I was not.</s>
 <s id="59">I don't know anybody with juvenile diabetes.</s>
 <s id="60">I probably would have missed the booklet, "Grilled Cheese at Four O'Clock in the Morning."</s>
 <p id="p61">
  <s id="61.1">(Laughter) I do not subscribe to Crochet Today! magazine, although it looks delightful.</s>
  <s id="61.2">(Laughter) Take note of those clock ends.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="62">This is a college student's suggestion for what a "four in the morning" gang sign should look like.</s>
 <s id="63">People sent me magazine ads.</s>
 <s id="64">They took photographs in grocery stores.</s>
 <s id="65">I got a ton of graphic novels and comics.</s>
 <s id="66">A lot of good quality work, too: "The Sandman," "Watchmen."</s>
 <s id="67">There's a very cute example here from "Calvin and Hobbes."</s>
 <s id="68">In fact, the oldest citation anybody sent in was from a cartoon from the Stone Age.</s>
 <s id="69">Take a look.</s>
 <s id="70">(Video) Wilma Flintstone: Like how early?</s>
 <s id="71">Fred Flintstone: Like at 4 a.m., that's how early.</s>
 <s id="72">Rives: And the flip side of the timeline, this is from the 31st century.</s>
 <s id="73">A thousand years from now, people are still doing this.</s>
 <s id="74">(Video): Announcer: The time is 4 a.m.</s>
 <s id="75">(Laughter) Rives: It shows the spectrum.</s>
 <s id="76">I received so many songs, TV shows, movies, like from dismal to famous, I could give you a four-hour playlist.</s>
 <s id="77">If I just stick to modern male movie stars, I keep it to the length of about a commercial.</s>
 <s id="78">Here's your sampler.</s>
 <p id="p79">
  <s id="79.1">(Movie montage of "It's 4 a.m.")</s>
  <s id="79.2">(Laughter) Rives: So somewhere along the line, I realized I have a hobby I didn't know I wanted, and it is crowdsourced.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="80">But I was also thinking what you might be thinking, which is really, couldn't you do this with any hour of the day?</s>
 <s id="81">First of all, you are not getting clips like that about four in the afternoon.</s>
 <s id="82">Secondly, I did a little research.</s>
 <s id="83">You know, I was kind of interested.</s>
 <s id="84">If this is confirmation bias, there is so much confirmation, I am biased.</s>
 <s id="85">Literature probably shows it best.</s>
 <s id="86">There are a couple three in the mornings in Shakespeare.</s>
 <s id="87">There's a five in the morning.</s>
 <s id="88">There are seven four in the mornings, and they're all very dire.</s>
 <s id="89">In "Measure for Measure," it's the call time for the executioner.</s>
 <s id="90">Tolstoy gives Napoleon insomnia at four in the morning right before battle in "War and Peace."</s>
 <s id="91">Charlotte Brontë's "Jane Eyre" has got kind of a pivotal four in the morning, as does Emily Brontë's "Wuthering Heights."</s>
 <s id="92">"Lolita" has as a creepy four in the morning.</s>
 <s id="93">"Huckleberry Finn" has one in dialect.</s>
 <s id="94">Someone sent in H.G. Wells' "The Invisible Man."</s>
 <s id="95">Someone else sent in Ralph Ellison's "Invisible Man."</s>
 <s id="96">"The Great Gatsby" spends the last four in the morning of his life waiting for a lover who never shows, and the most famous wake-up in literature, perhaps, "The Metamorphosis."</s>
 <s id="97">First paragraph, the main character wakes up transformed into a giant cockroach, but we already know, cockroach notwithstanding, something is up with this guy.</s>
 <p id="p98">
  <s id="98.1">Why?</s>
  <s id="98.2">His alarm is set for four o'clock in the morning.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="99">What kind of person would do that?</s>
 <s id="100">This kind of person would do that.</s>
 <p id="p101">
  <s id="101.1">(Music) (4 a.m. alarm clock montage) (Video) Newcaster: Top of the hour.</s>
  <s id="101.2">Time for the morning news.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="102">But of course, there is no news yet.</s>
 <s id="103">Everyone's still asleep in their comfy, comfy beds.</s>
 <s id="104">Rives: Exactly.</s>
 <s id="105">So that's Lucy from the Peanuts, "Mommie Dearest", Rocky, first day of training, Nelson Mandela, first day in office, and Bart Simpson, which combined with a cockroach would give you one hell of a dinner party and gives me yet another category, people waking up, in my big old database.</s>
 <s id="106">Just imagine that your friends and your family have heard that you collect, say, stuffed polar bears, and they send them to you.</s>
 <s id="107">Even if you don't really, at a certain point, you totally collect stuffed polar bears, and your collection is probably pretty kick-ass.</s>
 <s id="108">And when I got to that point, I embraced it.</s>
 <p id="p109">
  <s id="109.1">I got my curator on.</s>
  <s id="109.2">I started fact checking, downloading, illegally screen-grabbing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="110">I started archiving.</s>
 <s id="111">My hobby had become a habit, and my habit gave me possibly the world's most eclectic Netflix queue.</s>
 <s id="112">At one point, it went, "Guys and Dolls: The Musical," "Last Tango in Paris," "Diary of a Wimpy Kid," "Porn Star: Legend of Ron Jeremy."</s>
 <s id="113">Why "Porn Star: Legend of Ron Jeremy"?</s>
 <s id="114">Because someone told me I would find this clip in there.</s>
 <s id="115">(Video) Ron Jeremy: I was born in Flushing, Queens on March, 12, 1953, at four o'clock in the morning.</s>
 <p id="p116">
  <s id="116.1">Rives: Of course he was.</s>
  <s id="116.2">(Laughter) (Applause) Yeah.</s>
  <s id="116.3">Not only does it seem to make sense, it also answers the question, "What do Ron Jeremy and Simone de Beauvoir have in common?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="117">Simone de Beauvoir begins her entire autobiography with the sentence, "I was born at four o'clock in the morning," which I had because someone else had emailed it to me, and when they did, I had another bump up in my entry for this, because porn star Ron Jeremy and feminist Simone de Beauvoir are not just different people.</s>
 <s id="118">They are different people that have this thing connecting them, and I did not know if that is trivia or knowledge or inadvertent expertise, but I did wonder, is there maybe a cooler way to do this?</s>
 <s id="119">So last October, in gentleman scholar tradition, I put the entire collection online as "Museum of Four in the Morning."</s>
 <s id="120">You can click on that red "refresh" button.</s>
 <s id="121">It will take you at random to one of hundreds of snippets that are in the collection.</s>
 <s id="122">Here is a knockout poem by Billy Collins called "Forgetfulness."</s>
 <s id="123">(Video) Billy Collins: No wonder you rise in the middle of the night to look up the date of a famous battle in a book on war.</s>
 <s id="124">No wonder the moon in the window seems to have drifted out of a love poem that you used to know by heart.</s>
 <s id="125">Rives: So the first hour of this project was satisfying.</s>
 <s id="126">A Bollywood actor sang a line on a DVD in a cafe.</s>
 <s id="127">Half a globe away, a teenager made an Instagram video of it and sent it to me, a stranger.</s>
 <s id="128">Less than a week later, though, I received a little bit of grace.</s>
 <s id="129">I received a poignant tweet.</s>
 <s id="130">It was brief.</s>
 <s id="131">It just said, "Reminds me of an ancient mix tape."</s>
 <s id="132">The name was a pseudonym, actually, or a pseudo-pseudonym.</s>
 <s id="133">As soon as I saw the initials, and the profile pic, I knew immediately, my whole body knew immediately who this was, and I knew immediately what mix tape she was talking about.</s>
 <s id="134">(Music) L.D. was my college romance.</s>
 <p id="p135">
  <s id="135.1">This is in the early '90s.</s>
  <s id="135.2">I was an undegrad.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="136">She was a grad student in the library sciences department.</s>
 <s id="137">Not the kind of librarian that takes her glasses off, lets her hair down, suddenly she's smoking hot.</s>
 <s id="138">She was already smoking hot, she was super dorky, and we had a December-May romance, meaning we started dating in December, and by May, she had graduated and became my one that got away.</s>
 <s id="139">But her mix tape did not get away.</s>
 <s id="140">I have kept this mix tape in a box with notes and postcards, not just from L.D., from my life, but for decades.</s>
 <s id="141">It's the kind of box where, if I have a girlfriend, I tend to hide it from her, and if I had a wife, I'm sure I would share it with her, but the story — (Laughter) — with this mix tape is there are seven songs per side, but no song titles.</s>
 <s id="142">Instead, L.D. has used the U.S. Library of Congress classification system, including page numbers, to leave me clues.</s>
 <s id="143">When I got this mix tape, I put it in my cassette player, I took it to the campus library, her library, I found 14 books on the shelves.</s>
 <s id="144">I remember bringing them all to my favorite corner table, and I read poems paired to songs like food to wine, paired, I can tell you, like saddle shoes to a cobalt blue vintage cotton dress.</s>
 <s id="145">I did this again last October.</s>
 <s id="146">I'm sitting there, I got new earbuds, old Walkman, I realize this is just the kind of extravagance I used to take for granted even when I was extravagant.</s>
 <s id="147">And then I thought, "Good for him."</s>
 <s id="148">"PG" is Slavic literature.</s>
 <s id="149">"7000" series Polish literature.</s>
 <s id="150">Z9A24 is a collection of 70 poems.</s>
 <s id="151">Page 31 is Wislawa Szymborska's poem paired with Paul Simon's "Peace Like a River."</s>
 <p id="p152">
  <s id="152.1">(Music: Paul Simon, "Peace Like a River") (Video) Paul Simon: ♪ Oh, four in the morning ♪ ♪ I woke up from out of my dream ♪ Rives: Thank you.</s>
  <s id="152.2">Appreciate it.</s>
  <s id="152.3">(Applause)</s>
 </p>
</text>
