<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Consider the claw.</s>
 <s id="2">Frequently found on four-limbed animals around the world, it’s one of nature’s most versatile tools.</s>
 <s id="3">Bears use claws for digging as well as defense.</s>
 <s id="4">An eagle’s needle-like talons can pierce the skulls of their prey.</s>
 <s id="5">And lions can retract their massive claws for easy movement, before flicking them out to hunt.</s>
 <s id="6">Even the ancestors of primates used to wield these impressive appendages, until their claws evolved into nails.</s>
 <s id="7">So what in our evolutionary past led to this manicured adaptation, and what can nails do that their sharper cousins can’t?</s>
 <s id="8">When nails first appeared in the fossil record around 55.8 million years ago, claws had already been present for over 260 million years in the ancestors of mammals and reptiles.</s>
 <s id="9">But despite the gulf of time between their emergence, these adaptations are both part of the same evolutionary story.</s>
 <s id="10">Both nails and claws are made of keratin— a tough, fibrous protein also found in horns, scales, hooves and hair.</s>
 <s id="11">This protein is produced by a wedge of tissue called the keratin matrix.</s>
 <s id="12">Rich in blood vessels and nutrients, this protein factory produces an endless stream of keratin, which is tightly packed into cells called keratinocytes.</s>
 <s id="13">These high-density cells give nails and claws their trademark toughness.</s>
 <s id="14">Since nails evolved from claws, both adaptations produce keratinocytes in the same way.</s>
 <s id="15">The cells grow out from the matrix, emerging from the skin where they die and harden into a water-resistant sheath.</s>
 <s id="16">The primary difference between the two keratin coverings is really just their shape, which depends on the shape of the bone at the end of the animal’s digits.</s>
 <s id="17">In claws, the bed of keratinocytes conforms to a narrow finger bone, wrapping around the end of the digit and radiating outwards to form a cone-shaped structure.</s>
 <s id="18">Animals with nails, on the other hand, have much broader digits, and keratinocytes only cover the top surface of their wide bones.</s>
 <s id="19">It’s possible that nails have simply persisted as a side effect of primates evolving wider, more dexterous fingers.</s>
 <s id="20">But given what we know about the habitats of our primate ancestors, it’s more likely that nails came with their own powerful advantages.</s>
 <s id="21">High in the forest canopy where these primates lived, wide finger bones and expansive finger pads were ideal for gripping narrow branches.</s>
 <s id="22">And nails improved that grip even further.</s>
 <s id="23">By providing a rigid surface to press against, primates could splay out their pads to create even more contact with the trees.</s>
 <s id="24">Additionally, nails improved the sensitivity of their digits by providing an extra surface to detect changes in pressure while climbing.</s>
 <s id="25">This combination of sensitivity and dexterity gave our ancestors the precise motor control needed to snatch up insects, pinch berries and seeds, and keep a firm grip on slim branches.</s>
 <s id="26">The evolution of nails and the evolution of opposable thumbs and toes are closely linked.</s>
 <s id="27">And when our ancestors moved down from the trees, this flexible grasp enabled them to create and wield complex tools.</s>
 <s id="28">Even if it was possible for wide fingers to sport claws, their sharp points would’ve likely interfered with these primates’ regular tasks.</s>
 <s id="29">Claws are ideal for piercing, puncturing, and hooking, but their points make grabbing difficult, and potentially dangerous.</s>
 <s id="30">However, both claws and nails are used in some unexpected ways.</s>
 <s id="31">Manatees use nails to grasp their food, and researchers think elephant toenails may sense vibrations in the ground to help them hear.</s>
 <s id="32">Meanwhile, some primates, like the aye-ayes of Madagascar, have re-acquired claws.</s>
 <s id="33">They use these extra-long appendages to tap branches and trunks, while listening for hollow sections with their bat-like ears.</s>
 <s id="34">When they hear an opening, they burrow into the tree and skewer grubs with their needle-like middle finger.</s>
 <s id="35">We’ve only scratched the surface of all the incredible ways nails and claws are used throughout the animal kingdom.</s>
 <s id="36">But as for which of these adaptations is better?</s>
 <s id="37">That’s an answer we may never nail down.</s>
</text>
