<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">When a new pathogen emerges, our bodies and healthcare systems are left vulnerable.</s>
 <s id="2">In times like these, there’s an urgent need for a vaccine to create widespread immunity with minimal loss of life.</s>
 <s id="3">So how quickly can we develop vaccines when we need them most?</s>
 <s id="4">Vaccine development can generally be split into three phases.</s>
 <s id="5">In exploratory research, scientists experiment with different approaches to find safe and replicable vaccine designs.</s>
 <s id="6">Once these are vetted in the lab, they enter clinical testing, where vaccines are evaluated for safety, efficacy, and side effects across a variety of populations.</s>
 <s id="7">Finally, there’s manufacturing, where vaccines are produced and distributed for public use.</s>
 <s id="8">Under regular circumstances, this process takes an average of 15 to 20 years.</s>
 <s id="9">But during a pandemic, researchers employ numerous strategies to move through each stage as quickly as possible.</s>
 <s id="10">Exploratory research is perhaps the most flexible.</s>
 <s id="11">The goal of this stage is to find a safe way to introduce our immune system to the virus or bacteria.</s>
 <s id="12">This gives our body the information it needs to create antibodies capable of fighting a real infection.</s>
 <s id="13">There are many ways to safely trigger this immune response, but generally, the most effective designs are also the slowest to produce.</s>
 <s id="14">Traditional attenuated vaccines create long lasting resilience.</s>
 <s id="15">But they rely on weakened viral strains that must be cultivated in non-human tissue over long periods of time.</s>
 <s id="16">Inactivated vaccines take a much faster approach, directly applying heat, acid, or radiation to weaken the pathogen.</s>
 <s id="17">Sub-unit vaccines, that inject harmless fragments of viral proteins, can also be created quickly.</s>
 <s id="18">But these faster techniques produce less robust resilience.</s>
 <s id="19">These are just three of many vaccine designs, each with their own pros and cons.</s>
 <s id="20">No single approach is guaranteed to work, and all of them require time-consuming research.</s>
 <s id="21">So the best way to speed things up is for many labs to work on different models simultaneously.</s>
 <s id="22">This race-to-the-finish strategy produced the first testable Zika vaccine in 7 months, and the first testable COVID-19 vaccine in just 42 days.</s>
 <s id="23">Being testable doesn’t mean these vaccines will be successful.</s>
 <s id="24">But models that are deemed safe and easily replicable can move into clinical testing while other labs continue exploring alternatives.</s>
 <s id="25">Whether a testable vaccine is produced in four months or four years, the next stage is often the longest and most unpredictable stage of development.</s>
 <s id="26">Clinical testing consists of three phases, each containing multiple trials.</s>
 <s id="27">Phase I trials focus on the intensity of the triggered immune response, and try to establish that the vaccine is safe and effective.</s>
 <s id="28">Phase II trials focus on determining the right dosage and delivery schedule across a wider population.</s>
 <s id="29">And Phase III trials determine safety across the vaccine’s primary use population, while also identifying rare side effects and negative reactions.</s>
 <s id="30">Given the number of variables and the focus on long-term safety, it’s incredibly difficult to speed up clinical testing.</s>
 <s id="31">In extreme circumstances, researchers run multiple trials within one phase at the same time.</s>
 <s id="32">But they still need to meet strict safety criteria before moving on.</s>
 <s id="33">Occasionally, labs can expedite this process by leveraging previously approved treatments.</s>
 <s id="34">In 2009, researchers adapted the seasonal flu vaccine to treat H1N1— producing a widely available vaccine in just six months.</s>
 <s id="35">However, this technique only works when dealing with familiar pathogens that have well-established vaccine designs.</s>
 <s id="36">After a successful Phase III trial, a national regulatory authority reviews the results and approves safe vaccines for manufacturing.</s>
 <s id="37">Every vaccine has a unique blend of biological and chemical components that require a specialized pipeline to produce.</s>
 <s id="38">To start production as soon as the vaccine is approved, manufacturing plans must be designed in parallel to research and testing.</s>
 <s id="39">This requires constant coordination between labs and manufacturers, as well as the resources to adapt to sudden changes in vaccine design— even if that means scrapping months of work.</s>
 <s id="40">Over time, advances in exploratory research and manufacturing should make this process faster.</s>
 <s id="41">Preliminary studies suggest that future researchers may be able to swap genetic material from different viruses into the same vaccine design.</s>
 <s id="42">These DNA and mRNA based vaccines could dramatically expedite all three stages of vaccine production.</s>
 <s id="43">But until such breakthroughs arrive, our best strategy is for labs around the world to cooperate and work in parallel on different approaches.</s>
 <s id="44">By sharing knowledge and resources, scientists can divide and conquer any pathogen.</s>
</text>
