<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">This is the exact moment that I started creating something called Tinkering School.</s>
 <s id="2">Tinkering School is a place where kids can pick up sticks and hammers and other dangerous objects, and be trusted.</s>
 <s id="3">Trusted not to hurt themselves, and trusted not to hurt others.</s>
 <s id="4">Tinkering School doesn't follow a set curriculum, and there are no tests.</s>
 <s id="5">We're not trying to teach anybody any specific thing.</s>
 <s id="6">When the kids arrive they're confronted with lots of stuff: wood and nails and rope and wheels, and lots of tools, real tools.</s>
 <s id="7">It's a six-day immersive experience for the kids.</s>
 <s id="8">And within that context, we can offer the kids time -- something that seems in short supply in their over-scheduled lives.</s>
 <s id="9">Our goal is to ensure that they leave with a better sense of how to make things than when they arrived, and the deep internal realization that you can figure things out by fooling around.</s>
 <s id="10">Nothing ever turns out as planned ... ever.</s>
 <s id="11">(Laughter) And the kids soon learn that all projects go awry -- (Laughter) and become at ease with the idea that every step in a project is a step closer to sweet success, or gleeful calamity.</s>
 <s id="12">We start from doodles and sketches.</s>
 <s id="13">And sometimes we make real plans.</s>
 <s id="14">And sometimes we just start building.</s>
 <s id="15">Building is at the heart of the experience: hands on, deeply immersed and fully committed to the problem at hand.</s>
 <s id="16">Robin and I, acting as collaborators, keep the landscape of the projects tilted towards completion.</s>
 <s id="17">Success is in the doing, and failures are celebrated and analyzed.</s>
 <s id="18">Problems become puzzles and obstacles disappear.</s>
 <s id="19">When faced with particularly difficult setbacks or complexities, a really interesting behavior emerges: decoration.</s>
 <s id="20">(Laughter) Decoration of the unfinished project is a kind of conceptual incubation.</s>
 <s id="21">From these interludes come deep insights and amazing new approaches to solving the problems that had them frustrated just moments before.</s>
 <s id="22">All materials are available for use.</s>
 <s id="23">Even those mundane, hateful, plastic grocery bags can become a bridge stronger than anyone imagined.</s>
 <s id="24">And the things that they build amaze even themselves.</s>
 <s id="25">Video: Three, two, one, go!</s>
 <s id="26">Gever Tulley: A rollercoaster built by seven-year-olds.</s>
 <s id="27">Video: Yay!</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">(Applause) GT: Thank you.</s>
  <s id="28.2">It's been a great pleasure.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">(Applause)</s>
</text>
