<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Have you ever been floating in a swimming pool, all comfy and warm, thinking, "Man, it'd be cool to be an astronaut!</s>
 <s id="2">You could float out in outer space, look down at the Earth and everything.</s>
 <s id="3">It'd be so neat!"</s>
 <s id="4">Only that's not how it is at all.</s>
 <s id="5">If you are in outer space, you are orbiting the Earth: it's called free fall.</s>
 <s id="6">You're actually falling towards the Earth.</s>
 <s id="7">Think about this for a moment: that's the feeling you get if you're going over the top of a roller coaster, going, like, "Whoa!"</s>
 <s id="8">Only you're doing this the whole time you're orbiting the Earth, for two, three, four hours, days.</s>
 <s id="9">Whatever it takes, right?</s>
 <s id="10">So, how does orbiting work?</s>
 <s id="11">Let's take a page from Isaac Newton.</s>
 <s id="12">He had this idea, a little mental experiment: You take a cannon, you put it on top of a hill.</s>
 <s id="13">If you shoot the cannonball, it goes a little bit away.</s>
 <s id="14">But if you shoot it harder, it goes far enough so that it lands a little bit past the curvature of Earth.</s>
 <s id="15">Well, you can imagine if you shot it really, really, hard, it would go all the way around the Earth and come back -- boom! -- and hit you in the backside or something.</s>
 <s id="16">Let's zoom way back and put you in a little satellite over the North Pole of the Earth and consider north to be up.</s>
 <s id="17">You're going to fall down and hit the Earth.</s>
 <s id="18">But you are actually moving sideways really fast.</s>
 <s id="19">So when you fall down, you're going to miss.</s>
 <s id="20">You're going to end up on the side of the Earth, falling down, and now the Earth is pulling you back in sideways.</s>
 <s id="21">So it's pulling you back in and you fall down, and so you miss the Earth again, and now you're under the Earth.</s>
 <s id="22">The Earth is going to pull you up, but you're moving sideways still.</s>
 <s id="23">So you're going to miss the Earth again.</s>
 <s id="24">Now you're on the other side of the Earth, moving upward, and the Earth's pulling you sideways.</s>
 <s id="25">So you're going to fall sideways, but you're going to be moving up and so you'll miss.</s>
 <s id="26">Now you're back on top of the Earth again, over the North Pole, going sideways and falling down, and yep -- you guessed it.</s>
 <s id="27">You'll keep missing because you're moving so fast.</s>
 <s id="28">In this way, astronauts orbit the Earth.</s>
 <s id="29">They're always falling towards the Earth, but they're always missing, and therefore, they're falling all the time.</s>
 <s id="30">They feel like they're falling, so you just have to get over it.</s>
 <s id="31">So technically, if you ran fast enough and tripped, you could miss the Earth.</s>
 <s id="32">But there's a big problem.</s>
 <s id="33">First, you have to be going eight kilometers a second.</s>
 <s id="34">That's 18,000 miles an hour, just over Mach 23!</s>
 <s id="35">The second problem: If you're going that fast, yes, you would orbit the Earth and come back where you came from, but there's a lot of air in the way, much less people and things.</s>
 <s id="36">So you would burn up due to atmospheric friction.</s>
 <s id="37">So, I do not recommend this.</s>
</text>
