<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Video) Announcer: 10 seconds.</s>
 <s id="2">Five, four, three, two, one.</s>
 <s id="3">Official top.</s>
 <s id="4">Plus one, two, three, four, five six, seven, eight, nine, ten.</s>
 <s id="5">Guillaume Néry, France.</s>
 <s id="6">Constant weight, 123 meters, three minutes and 25 seconds.</s>
 <s id="7">National record attempt.</s>
 <s id="8">70 meters.</s>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">[123 meters] (Applause) (Video) Judge: White card.</s>
  <s id="9.2">Guillaume Néry!</s>
  <s id="9.3">National record!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="10">Guillaume Néry: Thank you.</s>
 <s id="11">(Applause) Thank you very much, thanks for the warm welcome.</s>
 <s id="12">That dive you just watched is a journey -- a journey between two breaths.</s>
 <s id="13">A journey that takes place between two breaths -- the last one before diving into the water, and the first one, coming back to the surface.</s>
 <s id="14">That dive is a journey to the very limits of human possibility, a journey into the unknown.</s>
 <s id="15">But it's also, and above all, an inner journey, where a number of things happen, physiologically as well as mentally.</s>
 <s id="16">And that's why I'm here today, to share my journey with you and to take you along with me.</s>
 <s id="17">So, we start with the last breath.</s>
 <s id="18">(Breathing in) (Breathing out) As you noticed, that last breath in is slow, deep and intense.</s>
 <s id="19">It ends with a special technique called the carp, which allows me to store one to two extra liters of air in my lungs by compressing it.</s>
 <s id="20">When I leave the surface, I have about 10 liters of air in my lungs.</s>
 <s id="21">As soon as I leave the surface the first mechanism kicks in: the diving reflex.</s>
 <s id="22">The first thing the diving reflex does is make your heart rate drop.</s>
 <s id="23">My heart beat will drop from about 60-70 per minute to about 30-40 beats per minute in a matter of seconds; almost immediately.</s>
 <s id="24">Next, the diving reflex causes peripheral vasoconstriction, which means that the blood flow will leave the body's extremities to feed the most important organs: the lungs, the heart and the brain.</s>
 <s id="25">This mechanism is innate.</s>
 <s id="26">I cannot control it.</s>
 <s id="27">If you go underwater, even if you've never done it before, you'll experience the exact same effects.</s>
 <s id="28">All human beings share this characteristic.</s>
 <s id="29">And what's extraordinary is that we share this instinct with marine mammals -- all marine mammals: dolphins, whales, sea lions, etc.</s>
 <s id="30">When they dive deep into the ocean, these mechanisms become activated, but to a greater extent.</s>
 <s id="31">And, of course, it works much better for them.</s>
 <s id="32">It's absolutely fascinating.</s>
 <s id="33">Right as I leave the surface, nature gives me a push in the right direction, allowing me to descend with confidence.</s>
 <s id="34">So as I dive deeper into the blue, the pressure slowly starts to squeeze my lungs.</s>
 <s id="35">And since it's the amount of air in my lungs that makes me float, the farther down I go, the more pressure there is on my lungs, the less air they contain and the easier it is for my body to fall.</s>
 <s id="36">And at one point, around 35 or 40 meters down, I don't even need to swim.</s>
 <s id="37">My body is dense and heavy enough to fall into the depths by itself, and I enter what's called the free fall phase.</s>
 <s id="38">The free fall phase is the best part of the dive.</s>
 <s id="39">It's the reason I still dive.</s>
 <s id="40">Because it feels like you're being pulled down and you don't need to do anything.</s>
 <s id="41">I can go from 35 meters to 123 meters without making a single movement.</s>
 <s id="42">I let myself be pulled by the depths, and it feels like I'm flying underwater.</s>
 <s id="43">It's truly an amazing feeling -- an extraordinary feeling of freedom.</s>
 <s id="44">And so I slowly continue sliding to the bottom.</s>
 <s id="45">40 meters down, 50 meters down, and between 50 and 60 meters, a second physiological response kicks in.</s>
 <s id="46">My lungs reach residual volume, below which they're not supposed to be compressed, in theory.</s>
 <s id="47">And this second response is called blood shift, or "pulmonary erection" in French.</s>
 <s id="48">I prefer "blood shift."</s>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) So blood shift -- how does it work?</s>
 <s id="50">The capillaries in the lungs become engorged with blood -- which is caused by the suction -- so the lungs can harden and protect the whole chest cavity from being crushed.</s>
 <s id="51">It prevents the two walls of the lungs from collapsing, from sticking together and caving in.</s>
 <s id="52">Thanks to this phenomenon, which we also share with marine mammals, I'm able to continue with my dive.</s>
 <s id="53">60, 70 meters down, I keep falling, faster and faster, because the pressure is crushing my body more and more.</s>
 <s id="54">Below 80 meters, the pressure becomes a lot stronger, and I start to feel it physically.</s>
 <s id="55">I really start to feel the suffocation.</s>
 <s id="56">You can see what it looks like -- not pretty at all.</s>
 <s id="57">The diaphragm is completely collapsed, the rib cage is squeezed in, and mentally, there is something going on as well.</s>
 <s id="58">You may be thinking, "This doesn't look enjoyable.</s>
 <s id="59">How do you do it?"</s>
 <s id="60">If I relied on my earthly reflexes -- what do we do above water when there's a problem?</s>
 <s id="61">We resist, we go against it.</s>
 <s id="62">We fight.</s>
 <s id="63">Underwater, that doesn't work.</s>
 <s id="64">If you try that underwater, you might tear your lungs, spit up blood, develop an edema and you'll have to stop diving for a good amount of time.</s>
 <s id="65">So what you need to do, mentally, is to tell yourself that nature and the elements are stronger than you.</s>
 <s id="66">And so I let the water crush me.</s>
 <s id="67">I accept the pressure and go with it.</s>
 <s id="68">At this point, my body receives this information, and my lungs start relaxing.</s>
 <s id="69">I relinquish all control, and relax completely.</s>
 <s id="70">The pressure starts crushing me, and it doesn't feel bad at all.</s>
 <s id="71">I even feel like I'm in a cocoon, protected.</s>
 <s id="72">And the dive continues.</s>
 <s id="73">80, 85 meters down, 90, 100.</s>
 <s id="74">100 meters -- the magic number.</s>
 <s id="75">In every sport, it's a magic number.</s>
 <s id="76">For swimmers and athletes and also for us, free divers, it's a number everyone dreams of.</s>
 <s id="77">Everyone wishes one day to be able to get to 100 meters.</s>
 <s id="78">And it's a symbolic number for us, because in the 1970s, doctors and physiologists did their math, and predicted that the human body would not be able to go below 100 meters.</s>
 <s id="79">Below that, they said, the human body would implode.</s>
 <s id="80">And then the Frenchman, Jacques Mayol -- you all know him as the hero in "The Big Blue" -- came along and dived down to 100 meters.</s>
 <s id="81">He even reached 105 meters.</s>
 <s id="82">At that time, he was doing "no limits."</s>
 <s id="83">He'd use weights to descend faster and come back up with a balloon, just like in the movie.</s>
 <s id="84">Today, we go down 200 meters in no limit free diving.</s>
 <s id="85">I can do 123 meters by simply using muscle strength.</s>
 <s id="86">And in a way, it's all thanks to him, because he challenged known facts, and with a sweep of his hand, got rid of the theoretical beliefs and all the mental limits that we like to impose on ourselves.</s>
 <s id="87">He showed us that the human body has an infinite ability to adapt.</s>
 <s id="88">So I carry on with my dive.</s>
 <s id="89">105, 110, 115.</s>
 <s id="90">The bottom is getting closer.</s>
 <s id="91">120, 123 meters.</s>
 <s id="92">I'm at the bottom.</s>
 <s id="93">And now, I'd like to ask you to join me and put yourself in my place.</s>
 <s id="94">Close your eyes.</s>
 <s id="95">Imagine you get to 123 meters.</s>
 <s id="96">The surface is far, far away.</s>
 <s id="97">You're alone.</s>
 <s id="98">There's hardly any light.</s>
 <s id="99">It's cold -- freezing cold.</s>
 <s id="100">The pressure is crushing you completely -- 13 times stronger than on the surface.</s>
 <s id="101">And I know what you're thinking: "This is horrible.</s>
 <s id="102">What the hell am I doing here?</s>
 <s id="103">He's insane."</s>
 <s id="104">But no.</s>
 <s id="105">That's not what I think when I'm down there.</s>
 <s id="106">When I'm at the bottom, I feel good.</s>
 <s id="107">I get this extraordinary feeling of well-being.</s>
 <s id="108">Maybe it's because I've completely released all tensions and let myself go.</s>
 <s id="109">I feel great, without the need to breathe.</s>
 <s id="110">Although, you'd agree, I should be worried.</s>
 <s id="111">I feel like a tiny dot, a little drop of water, floating in the middle of the ocean.</s>
 <s id="112">And each time, I picture the same image.</s>
 <s id="113">[The Pale Blue Dot] It's that small dot the arrow is pointing to.</s>
 <s id="114">Do you know what it is?</s>
 <s id="115">It's planet Earth.</s>
 <s id="116">Planet Earth, photographed by the Voyager probe, from 4 billion kilometers away.</s>
 <s id="117">And it shows that our home is that small dot over there, floating in the middle of nothing.</s>
 <s id="118">That's how I feel when I'm at the bottom, at 123 meters.</s>
 <s id="119">I feel like a small dot, a speck of dust, stardust, floating in the middle of the cosmos, in the middle of nothing, in the immensity of space.</s>
 <s id="120">It's a fascinating sensation, because when I look up, down, left, right, in front, behind, I see the same thing: the infinite deep blue.</s>
 <s id="121">Nowhere else on Earth you can experience this -- looking all around you, and seeing the same thing.</s>
 <s id="122">It's extraordinary.</s>
 <s id="123">And at that moment, I still get that feeling each time, building up inside of me -- the feeling of humility.</s>
 <s id="124">Looking at this picture, I feel very humble -- just like when I'm all the way down at the bottom -- because I'm nothing, I'm a little speck of nothingness lost in all of time and space.</s>
 <s id="125">And it still is absolutely fascinating.</s>
 <s id="126">I decide to go back to the surface, because this is not where I belong.</s>
 <s id="127">I belong up there, on the surface.</s>
 <s id="128">So I start heading back up.</s>
 <s id="129">I get something of a shock at the very moment when I decide to go up.</s>
 <s id="130">First, because it takes a huge effort to tear yourself away from the bottom.</s>
 <s id="131">It pulled you down on the way in, and will do the same on the way up.</s>
 <s id="132">You have to swim twice as hard.</s>
 <s id="133">Then, I'm hit with another phenomenon known as narcosis.</s>
 <s id="134">I don't know if you've heard of that.</s>
 <s id="135">It's called nitrogen narcosis.</s>
 <s id="136">It's something that happens to scuba divers, but it can happen to free divers.</s>
 <s id="137">It's caused by nitrogen dissolving in the blood, which causes confusion between the conscious and unconscious mind.</s>
 <s id="138">A flurry of thoughts goes spinning through your head.</s>
 <s id="139">You can't control them, and you shouldn't try to -- you have to let it happen.</s>
 <s id="140">The more you try to control it, the harder it is to manage.</s>
 <s id="141">Then, a third thing happens: the desire to breathe.</s>
 <s id="142">I'm not a fish, I'm a human being, and the desire to breathe reminds me of that fact.</s>
 <s id="143">Around 60, 70 meters, you start to feel the need to breathe.</s>
 <s id="144">And with everything else that's going on, you can very easily lose your ground and start to panic.</s>
 <s id="145">When that happens, you think, "Where's the surface?</s>
 <p id="p146">
  <s id="146.1">I want to go up.</s>
  <s id="146.2">I want to breathe now."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="147">You should not do that.</s>
 <s id="148">Never look up to the surface -- not with your eyes, or your mind.</s>
 <s id="149">You should never picture yourself up there.</s>
 <s id="150">You have to stay in the present.</s>
 <s id="151">I look at the rope right in front of me, leading me back to the surface.</s>
 <s id="152">And I focus on that, on the present moment.</s>
 <s id="153">Because if I think about the surface, I panic.</s>
 <s id="154">And if I panic, it's over.</s>
 <s id="155">Time goes faster this way.</s>
 <s id="156">And at 30 meters: deliverance.</s>
 <s id="157">I'm not alone any more.</s>
 <s id="158">The safety divers, my guardian angels, join me.</s>
 <s id="159">They leave the surface, we meet at 30 meters, and they escort me for the final few meters, where potential problems could arise.</s>
 <s id="160">Every time I see them, I think to myself, "It's thanks to you."</s>
 <s id="161">It's thanks to them, my team, that I'm here.</s>
 <s id="162">It brings back the sense of humility.</s>
 <s id="163">Without my team, without all the people around me, the adventure into the deep would be impossible.</s>
 <s id="164">A journey into the deep is above all a group effort.</s>
 <s id="165">So I'm happy to finish my journey with them, because I wouldn't be here if it weren't for them.</s>
 <s id="166">20 meters, 10 meters, my lungs slowly return to their normal volume.</s>
 <s id="167">Buoyancy pushes me up to the surface.</s>
 <s id="168">Five meters below the surface, I start to breathe out, so that as soon as I get to the surface all I do is breathe in.</s>
 <s id="169">And so I arrive at the surface.</s>
 <s id="170">(Breathing in) Air floods into my lungs.</s>
 <s id="171">It's like being born again, a relief.</s>
 <s id="172">It feels good.</s>
 <s id="173">Though the journey was extraordinary, I do need to feel those small oxygen molecules fueling my body.</s>
 <s id="174">It's an extraordinary sensation, but at the same time it's traumatizing.</s>
 <s id="175">It's a shock to the system, as you can you imagine.</s>
 <s id="176">I go from complete darkness to the light of day, from the near-silence of the depths to the commotion up top.</s>
 <s id="177">In terms of touch, I go from the soft, velvety feeling of the water, to air rubbing across my face.</s>
 <s id="178">In terms of smell, there is air rushing into my lungs.</s>
 <s id="179">And in return, my lungs open up.</s>
 <s id="180">They were completely squashed just 90 seconds ago, and now, they've opened up again.</s>
 <s id="181">So all of this affects quite a lot of things.</s>
 <s id="182">I need a few seconds to come back, and to feel "all there" again.</s>
 <s id="183">But that needs to happen quickly, because the judges are there to verify my performance; I need to show them I'm in perfect physical condition.</s>
 <s id="184">You saw in the video, I was doing a so-called exit protocol.</s>
 <s id="185">Once at the surface, I have 15 seconds to take off my nose clip, give this signal and say (English) "I am OK."</s>
 <s id="186">Plus, you need to be bilingual.</s>
 <s id="187">(Laughter) On top of everything -- that's not very nice.</s>
 <s id="188">Once the protocol is completed, the judges show me a white card, and that's when the joy starts.</s>
 <s id="189">I can finally celebrate what has just happened.</s>
 <s id="190">So, the journey I've just described to you is a more extreme version of free diving.</s>
 <s id="191">Luckily, it's far from just that.</s>
 <s id="192">For the past few years, I've been trying to show another side of free diving, because the media mainly talks about competitions and records.</s>
 <s id="193">But free diving is more than just that.</s>
 <s id="194">It's about being at ease in the water.</s>
 <s id="195">It's extremely beautiful, very poetic and artistic.</s>
 <s id="196">So my wife and I decided to film it and try to show another side of it, mostly to make people want to go into the water.</s>
 <s id="197">Let me show you some images to finish my story.</s>
 <s id="198">It's a mix of beautiful underwater photos.</s>
 <s id="199">(Music) I'd like you to know that if one day you try to stop breathing, you'll realize that when you stop breathing, you stop thinking, too.</s>
 <s id="200">It calms your mind.</s>
 <s id="201">Today, in the 21st century, we're under so much pressure.</s>
 <s id="202">Our minds are overworked, we think at a million miles an hour, we're always stressed.</s>
 <s id="203">Being able to free dive lets you, just for a moment, relax your mind.</s>
 <s id="204">Holding your breath underwater means giving yourself the chance to experience weightlessness.</s>
 <s id="205">It means being underwater, floating, with your body completely relaxed, letting go of all your tensions.</s>
 <s id="206">This is our plight in the 21st century: our backs hurt, our necks hurt, everything hurts, because we're stressed and tense all the time.</s>
 <s id="207">But when you're in the water, you let yourself float, as if you were in space.</s>
 <s id="208">You let yourself go completely.</s>
 <s id="209">It's an extraordinary feeling.</s>
 <s id="210">You can finally get in touch with your body, mind and spirit.</s>
 <s id="211">Everything feels better, all at once.</s>
 <s id="212">Learning how to free dive is also about learning to breathe correctly.</s>
 <s id="213">We breathe with our first breath at birth, up until our last one.</s>
 <s id="214">Breathing gives rhythm to our lives.</s>
 <s id="215">Learning how to breathe better is learning how to live better.</s>
 <s id="216">Holding your breath in the sea, not necessarily at 100 meters, but maybe at two or three, putting on your goggles, a pair of flippers, means you can go see another world, another universe, completely magical.</s>
 <s id="217">You can see little fish, seaweed, the flora and fauna, you can watch it all discreetly, sliding underwater, looking around, and coming back to the surface, leaving no trace.</s>
 <s id="218">It's an amazing feeling to become one with nature like that.</s>
 <s id="219">And if I may say one more thing, holding your breath, being in the water, finding this underwater world -- it's all about connecting with yourself.</s>
 <s id="220">You heard me talk a lot about the body's memory that dates back millions of years, to our marine origins.</s>
 <s id="221">The day you get back into the water, when you hold your breath for a few seconds, you will reconnect with those origins.</s>
 <s id="222">And I guarantee it's absolute magic.</s>
 <s id="223">I encourage you to try it out.</s>
 <s id="224">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="225">(Applause)</s>
</text>
