<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I was asked to come here and speak about creation.</s>
 <s id="2">And I only have 15 minutes, and I see they're counting already.</s>
 <s id="3">And I can -- in 15 minutes, I think I can touch only a very rather janitorial branch of creation, which I call "creativity."</s>
 <s id="4">Creativity is how we cope with creation.</s>
 <s id="5">While creation sometimes seems a bit un-graspable, or even pointless, creativity is always meaningful.</s>
 <s id="6">See, for instance, in this picture.</s>
 <s id="7">You know, creation is what put that dog in that picture, and creativity is what makes us see a chicken on his hindquarters.</s>
 <s id="8">When you think about -- you know, creativity has a lot to do with causality too.</s>
 <s id="9">You know, when I was a teenager, I was a creator.</s>
 <s id="10">I just did things.</s>
 <s id="11">Then I became an adult and started knowing who I was, and tried to maintain that persona -- I became creative.</s>
 <s id="12">It wasn't until I actually did a book and a retrospective exhibition, that I could track exactly -- looks like all the craziest things that I had done, all my drinking, all my parties -- they followed a straight line that brings me to the point that actually I'm talking to you at this moment.</s>
 <s id="13">Though it's actually true, you know, the reason I'm talking to you right now is because I was born in Brazil.</s>
 <s id="14">If I was born in Monterey, probably would be in Brazil.</s>
 <s id="15">You know, I was born in Brazil and grew up in the '70s under a climate of political distress, and I was forced to learn to communicate in a very specific way -- in a sort of a semiotic black market.</s>
 <s id="16">You couldn't really say what you wanted to say; you had to invent ways of doing it.</s>
 <s id="17">You didn't trust information very much.</s>
 <s id="18">That led me to another step of why I'm here today, is because I really liked media of all kinds.</s>
 <s id="19">I was a media junkie, and eventually got involved with advertising.</s>
 <s id="20">My first job in Brazil was actually to develop a way to improve the readability of billboards, and based on speed, angle of approach and actually blocks of text.</s>
 <s id="21">It was very -- actually, it was a very good study, and got me a job in an ad agency.</s>
 <s id="22">And they also decided that I had to -- to give me a very ugly Plexiglas trophy for it.</s>
 <s id="23">And another point -- why I'm here -- is that the day I went to pick up the Plexiglas trophy, I rented a tuxedo for the first time in my life, picked the thing -- didn't have any friends.</s>
 <s id="24">On my way out, I had to break a fight apart.</s>
 <s id="25">Somebody was hitting somebody else with brass knuckles.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">They were in tuxedos, and fighting.</s>
  <s id="26.2">It was very ugly.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">And also -- advertising people do that all the time -- (Laughter) -- and I -- well, what happened is when I went back, it was on the way back to my car, the guy who got hit decided to grab a gun -- I don't know why he had a gun -- and shoot the first person he decided to be his aggressor.</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">The first person was wearing a black tie, a tuxedo.</s>
  <s id="28.2">It was me.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">Luckily, it wasn't fatal, as you can all see.</s>
 <s id="30">And, even more luckily, the guy said that he was sorry and I bribed him for compensation money, otherwise I press charges.</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">And that's how -- with this money I paid for a ticket to come to the United States in 1983, and that's very -- the basic reason I'm talking to you here today: because I got shot.</s>
  <s id="31.2">(Laughter) (Applause) Well, when I started working with my own work, I decided that I shouldn't do images.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">You know, I became -- I took this very iconoclastic approach.</s>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">Because when I decided to go into advertising, I wanted to do -- I wanted to airbrush naked people on ice, for whiskey commercials, that's what I really wanted to do.</s>
  <s id="33.2">(Laughter) But I -- they didn't let me do it, so I just -- you know, they would only let me do other things.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="34">But I wasn't into selling whiskey; I was into selling ice.</s>
 <s id="35">The first works were actually objects.</s>
 <s id="36">It was kind of a mixture of found object, product design and advertising.</s>
 <s id="37">And I called them relics.</s>
 <s id="38">They were displayed first at Stux Gallery in 1983.</s>
 <s id="39">This is the clown skull.</s>
 <s id="40">Is a remnant of a race of -- a very evolved race of entertainers.</s>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">They lived in Brazil, long time ago.</s>
  <s id="41.2">(Laughter) This is the Ashanti joystick.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">Unfortunately, it has become obsolete because it was designed for Atari platform.</s>
 <s id="43">A Playstation II is in the works, maybe for the next TED I'll bring it.</s>
 <p id="p44">
  <s id="44.1">The rocking podium.</s>
  <s id="44.2">(Laughter) This is the pre-Columbian coffeemaker.</s>
  <s id="44.3">(Laughter) Actually, the idea came out of an argument that I had at Starbucks, that I insisted that I wasn't having Colombian coffee; the coffee was actually pre-Columbian.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="45">The Bonsai table.</s>
 <s id="46">The entire Encyclopedia Britannica bound in a single volume, for travel purposes.</s>
 <s id="47">And the half tombstone, for people who are not dead yet.</s>
 <s id="48">I wanted to take that into the realm of images, and I decided to make things that had the same identity conflicts.</s>
 <s id="49">So I decided to do work with clouds.</s>
 <s id="50">Because clouds can mean anything you want.</s>
 <s id="51">But now I wanted to work in a very low-tech way, so something that would mean at the same time a lump of cotton, a cloud and Durer's praying hands -- although this looks a lot more like Mickey Mouse's praying hands.</s>
 <s id="52">But I was still, you know -- this is a kitty cloud.</s>
 <s id="53">They're called "Equivalents," after Alfred Stieglitz's work.</s>
 <s id="54">"The Snail."</s>
 <s id="55">But I was still working with sculpture, and I was really trying to go flatter and flatter.</s>
 <s id="56">"The Teapot."</s>
 <s id="57">I had a chance to go to Florence, in -- I think it was '94, and I saw Ghiberti's "Door of Paradise."</s>
 <s id="58">And he did something that was very tricky.</s>
 <s id="59">He put together two different media from different periods of time.</s>
 <s id="60">First, he got an age-old way of making it, which was relief, and he worked this with three-point perspective, which was brand-new technology at the time.</s>
 <s id="61">And it's totally overkill.</s>
 <s id="62">And your eye doesn't know which level to read.</s>
 <s id="63">And you become trapped into this kind of representation.</s>
 <s id="64">So I decided to make these very simple renderings, that at first they are taken as a line drawing -- you know, something that's very -- and then I did it with wire.</s>
 <s id="65">The idea was to -- because everybody overlooks white -- like pencil drawings, you know?</s>
 <s id="66">And they would look at it -- "Ah, it's a pencil drawing."</s>
 <s id="67">Then you have this double take and see that it's actually something that existed in time.</s>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">It had a physicality, and you start going deeper and deeper into sort of narrative that goes this way, towards the image.</s>
  <s id="68.2">So this is "Monkey with Leica."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="69">"Relaxation."</s>
 <s id="70">"Fiat Lux."</s>
 <s id="71">And the same way the history of representation evolved from line drawings to shaded drawings.</s>
 <s id="72">And I wanted to deal with other subjects.</s>
 <s id="73">I started taking that into the realm of landscape, which is something that's almost a picture of nothing.</s>
 <s id="74">I made these pictures called "Pictures of Thread," and I named them after the amount of yards that I used to represent each picture.</s>
 <s id="75">These always end up being a photograph at the end, or more like an etching in this case.</s>
 <s id="76">So this is a lighthouse.</s>
 <p id="p77">
  <s id="77.1">This is "6,500 Yards," after Corot.</s>
  <s id="77.2">"9,000 Yards," after Gerhard Richter.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="78">And I don't know how many yards, after John Constable.</s>
 <s id="79">Departing from the lines, I decided to tackle the idea of points, like which is more similar to the type of representation that we find in photographs themselves.</s>
 <s id="80">I had met a group of children in the Caribbean island of Saint Kitts, and I did work and play with them.</s>
 <s id="81">I got some photographs from them.</s>
 <s id="82">Upon my arrival in New York, I decided -- they were children of sugar plantation workers.</s>
 <s id="83">And by manipulating sugar over a black paper, I made portraits of them.</s>
 <p id="p84">
  <s id="84.1">These are -- (Applause) -- Thank you.</s>
  <s id="84.2">This is "Valentina, the Fastest."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="85">It was just the name of the child, with the little thing you get to know of somebody that you meet very briefly.</s>
 <s id="86">"Valicia."</s>
 <s id="87">"Jacynthe."</s>
 <s id="88">But another layer of representation was still introduced.</s>
 <s id="89">Because I was doing this while I was making these pictures, I realized that I could add still another thing I was trying to make a subject -- something that would interfere with the themes, so chocolate is very good, because it has -- it brings to mind ideas that go from scatology to romance.</s>
 <s id="90">And so I decided to make these pictures, and they were very large, so you had to walk away from it to be able to see them.</s>
 <s id="91">So they're called "Pictures of Chocolate."</s>
 <s id="92">Freud probably could explain chocolate better than I. He was the first subject.</s>
 <s id="93">And Jackson Pollock also.</s>
 <s id="94">Pictures of crowds are particularly interesting, because, you know, you go to that -- you try to figure out the threshold with something you can define very easily, like a face, goes into becoming just a texture.</s>
 <s id="95">"Paparazzi."</s>
 <s id="96">I used the dust at the Whitney Museum to render some pieces of their collection.</s>
 <s id="97">And I picked minimalist pieces because they're about specificity.</s>
 <s id="98">And you render this with the most non-specific material, which is dust itself.</s>
 <s id="99">Like, you know, you have the skin particles of every single museum visitor.</s>
 <s id="100">They do a DNA scan of this, they will come up with a great mailing list.</s>
 <s id="101">This is Richard Serra.</s>
 <s id="102">I bought a computer, and [they] told me it had millions of colors in it.</s>
 <p id="p103">
  <s id="103.1">You know an artist's first response to this is, who counted it?</s>
  <s id="103.2">You know?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="104">And I realized that I never worked with color, because I had a hard time controlling the idea of single colors.</s>
 <s id="105">But once they're applied to numeric structure, then you can feel more comfortable.</s>
 <s id="106">So the first time I worked with colors was by making these mosaics of Pantone swatches.</s>
 <s id="107">They end up being very large pictures, and I photographed with a very large camera -- an 8x10 camera.</s>
 <s id="108">So you can see the surface of every single swatch -- like in this picture of Chuck Close.</s>
 <s id="109">And you have to walk very far to be able to see it.</s>
 <s id="110">Also, the reference to Gerhard Richter's use of color charts -- and the idea also entering another realm of representation that's very common to us today, which is the bit map.</s>
 <s id="111">I ended up narrowing the subject to Monet's "Haystacks."</s>
 <s id="112">This is something I used to do as a joke -- you know, make -- the same like -- Robert Smithson's "Spiral Jetty" -- and then leaving traces, as if it was done on a tabletop.</s>
 <s id="113">I tried to prove that he didn't do that thing in the Salt Lake.</s>
 <s id="114">But then, just doing the models, I was trying to explore the relationship between the model and the original.</s>
 <s id="115">And I felt that I would have to actually go there and make some earthworks myself.</s>
 <s id="116">I opt for very simple line drawings -- kind of stupid looking.</s>
 <s id="117">And at the same time, I was doing these very large constructions, being 150 meters away.</s>
 <s id="118">Now I would do very small ones, which would be like -- but under the same light, and I would show them together, so the viewer would have to really figure it out what one he was looking.</s>
 <s id="119">I wasn't interested in the very large things, or in the small things.</s>
 <s id="120">I was more interested in the things in between, you know, because you can leave an enormous range for ambiguity there.</s>
 <s id="121">This is like you see -- the size of a person over there.</s>
 <s id="122">This is a pipe.</s>
 <s id="123">A hanger.</s>
 <s id="124">And this is another thing that I did -- you know working -- everybody loves to watch somebody draw, but not many people have a chance to watch somebody draw in -- a lot of people at the same time, to evidence a single drawing.</s>
 <s id="125">And I love this work, because I did these cartoonish clouds over Manhattan for a period of two months.</s>
 <s id="126">And it was quite wonderful, because I had an interest -- an early interest -- in theater, that's justified on this thing.</s>
 <s id="127">In theater, you have the character and the actor in the same place, trying to negotiate each other in front of an audience.</s>
 <s id="128">And in this, you'd have like a -- something that looks like a cloud, and it is a cloud at the same time.</s>
 <s id="129">So they're like perfect actors.</s>
 <s id="130">My interest in acting, especially bad acting, goes a long way.</s>
 <s id="131">Actually, I once paid like 60 dollars to see a very great actor to do a version of "King Lear," and I felt really robbed, because by the time the actor started being King Lear, he stopped being the great actor that I had paid money to see.</s>
 <s id="132">On the other hand, you know, I paid like three dollars, I think -- and I went to a warehouse in Queens to see a version of "Othello" by an amateur group.</s>
 <s id="133">And it was quite fascinating, because you know the guy -- his name was Joey Grimaldi -- he impersonated the Moorish general -- you know, for the first three minutes he was really that general, and then he went back into plumber, he worked as a plumber, so -- plumber, general, plumber, general -- so for three dollars, I saw two tragedies for the price of one.</s>
 <s id="134">See, I think it's not really about impression, making people fall for a really perfect illusion, as much as it is to make -- I usually work at the lowest threshold of visual illusion.</s>
 <s id="135">Because it's not about fooling somebody, it's actually giving somebody a measure of their own belief: how much you want to be fooled.</s>
 <s id="136">That's why we pay to go to magic shows and things like that.</s>
 <s id="137">Well, I think that's it.</s>
 <s id="138">My time is nearly up.</s>
 <s id="139">Thank you very much.</s>
</text>
