<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The decorative use of wire in southern Africa dates back hundreds of years.</s>
 <s id="2">But modernization actually brought communication and a whole new material, in the form of telephone wire.</s>
 <s id="3">Rural to urban migration meant that newfound industrial materials started to replace hard-to-come-by natural grasses.</s>
 <s id="4">So, here you can see the change from use -- starting to use contemporary materials.</s>
 <s id="5">These pieces date back from the '40s to the late '50s.</s>
 <s id="6">In the '90s, my interest and passion for transitional art forms led me to a new form, which came from a squatter camp outside Durban.</s>
 <s id="7">And I got the opportunity to start working with this community at that point, and started developing, really, and mentoring them in terms of scale, in terms of the design.</s>
 <s id="8">And the project soon grew from five to 50 weavers in about a year.</s>
 <s id="9">Soon we had outgrown the scrap yards, what they could provide, so we coerced a wire manufacturer to help us, and not only to supply the materials on bobbins, but to produce to our color specifications.</s>
 <s id="10">At the same time, I was thinking, well, there's lots of possibility here to produce contemporary products, away from the ethnic, a little bit more contemporary.</s>
 <s id="11">So I developed a whole range around -- mass-produced range -- that obviously fitted into a much higher-end decor market that could be exported and also service our local market.</s>
 <p id="p12">
  <s id="12.1">We started experimenting, as you can see, in terms of shapes, forms.</s>
  <s id="12.2">The scale became very important, and it's become our pet project.</s>
  <s id="12.3">It's successful, it's been running for 12 years.</s>
  <s id="12.4">And we supply the Conran shops, and Donna Karan, and so it's kind of great.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="13">This is our group, our main group of weavers.</s>
 <s id="14">They come on a weekly basis to Durban.</s>
 <s id="15">They all have bank accounts.</s>
 <s id="16">They've all moved back to the rural area where they came from.</s>
 <s id="17">It's a weekly turnaround of production.</s>
 <s id="18">This is the community that I originally showed you the slide of.</s>
 <s id="19">And that's also modernized today, and it's supporting work for 300 weavers.</s>
 <s id="20">And the rest says it all.</s>
 <s id="21">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="22">(Applause)</s>
</text>
