<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Nicole Paris: TEDYouth, make some noise!</s>
 <s id="2">(Beatboxing) TEDYouth, make some -- (Beatboxing) (Beatboxing ends) Are you ready?</s>
 <s id="3">(Cheers and applause) Are you ready?</s>
 <s id="4">Ed Cage: Yeah, yeah, yeah!</s>
 <p id="p5">
  <s id="5.1">(Beatboxing) (Laughter) EC: Y'all like that?</s>
  <s id="5.2">Let me show you how we used to do it -- NP: Get it pops, go ahead.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="6">EC: ... when I was growing up in the '90s.</s>
 <s id="7">(Beatboxing) (Beatboxing ends) (Laughter) (Beatboxing) NP: Pops, pops, pops, pops, pops, pops, hold up, hold up, hold up, hold up!</s>
 <s id="8">Oh my God.</s>
 <s id="9">OK, he's trying to battle me.</s>
 <s id="10">Hold on, right now, hold on.</s>
 <s id="11">Do you remember when you used to beatbox me to sleep?</s>
 <s id="12">EC: Yeah, yeah, I remember.</s>
 <s id="13">That's when she was a little baby.</s>
 <s id="14">We would do something like this.</s>
 <s id="15">(Beatboxing) NP: I remember that.</s>
 <s id="16">(Beatboxing) NP: All right, pops, pops, pops, chill out, chill out.</s>
 <s id="17">Hold up, hold up, hold up.</s>
 <s id="18">EC: Y'all remember the video.</s>
 <s id="19">This is like a little payback or something for 50 million people calling me the loser.</s>
 <s id="20">NP: Hold up, hold up.</s>
 <s id="21">But a lot of people out there don't really know what beatboxing is, where it started from.</s>
 <s id="22">EC: Right, right.</s>
 <s id="23">NP: Where it came from.</s>
 <s id="24">So why don't you give them a little history -- just a tickle -- a bit of history of where it comes from.</s>
 <s id="25">EC: Beatbox started here in New York.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">(Cheers) That's right, that's right.</s>
  <s id="26.2">New York, New York!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">Everybody like, "Yeah!"</s>
 <s id="28">Well, we from St. Louis.</s>
 <s id="29">(Laughter) NP: Now you can put y'all hands down.</s>
 <s id="30">(Laughter) EC: But beatbox started here in New York.</s>
 <s id="31">What you would have is that, when we would go to parties, you would have the DJ and you would have the rapper.</s>
 <s id="32">But because I don't have electricity coming out of me, we had to emulate what the beats was doing.</s>
 <s id="33">So when you would see the beatboxer, you would see us over to the side.</s>
 <s id="34">Then you would see a rapper, and when the rapper began to rap, we would do a simple beat, because back then the beats were simple -- (Beatboxing) or -- (Beatboxing) Those were simple beats.</s>
 <s id="35">But now, you got folks that want to do all type of stuff with their beats now, and they want to humiliate their father, which is not right when you want to humiliate the person that take care of you, pay all your tuition, (Nicole laughs) especially when you have 50 million people that just go around and call you "the loser."</s>
 <s id="36">Well, I'm taking that to heart.</s>
 <s id="37">But now we do something different in our house, so we have these jam sessions, and our jam sessions consist of us jamming in church.</s>
 <s id="38">You know, in church, we'll look at each other like, (Beatboxing) (Laughter) and we'll text the beat to each other.</s>
 <s id="39">Or we'll be in the kitchen cooking, road trips, airports.</s>
 <s id="40">NP: Standing right there in the corner, "Aw, Dad -- listen to that."</s>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">(Beatboxing) Naw, I'm kidding.</s>
  <s id="41.2">But you know what?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">We're talking all about this jam session and everything.</s>
 <s id="43">EC: Yeah.</s>
 <s id="44">NP: Why don't we give them a little peek, just a tiny bit of our jam session?</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">NP: Y'all want to hear some jam session?</s>
  <s id="45.2">EC: Y'all ready for a jam session?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p46">
  <s id="46.1">(Cheers) NP: Sorry?</s>
  <s id="46.2">I can't hear you.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">(Cheers) Yeah!</s>
  <s id="47.2">Kick it, pops!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="48">(Beatboxing) (Applause) (Beatboxing) (Beatboxing ends) (Applause) NP: I'm getting ready to go!</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">EC: Y'all ready?</s>
  <s id="49.2">Everybody stand up!</s>
  <s id="49.3">Come on, everybody stand up!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p50">
  <s id="50.1">Get on up!</s>
  <s id="50.2">Come on, stretch!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="51">(Beatboxing) (Beatboxing ends) NP: That's it.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">(Cheers and applause) Thank you!</s>
  <s id="52.2">Make some noise!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="53">EG: Thank you, everybody!</s>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">NP: Make some noise!</s>
  <s id="54.2">Make some noise!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">Thank you!</s>
</text>
