<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">How many of you are tired of seeing celebrities adopting kids from the African continent?</s>
 <s id="2">(Laughter) Well, it's not all that bad.</s>
 <s id="3">I was adopted.</s>
 <s id="4">I grew up in rural Uganda, lost both my parents when I was very, very young.</s>
 <s id="5">And when my parents passed, I experienced all the negative effects of poverty, from homelessness, eating out of trash piles, you name it.</s>
 <s id="6">But my life changed when I got accepted into an orphanage.</s>
 <s id="7">Through one of those sponsor-an-orphan programs, I was sponsored and given an opportunity to acquire an education.</s>
 <s id="8">I started off in Uganda.</s>
 <s id="9">I went through school, and the way this particular program worked, you finished high school and after high school, you go learn a trade -- to become a carpenter, a mechanic or something along those lines.</s>
 <s id="10">My case was a little different.</s>
 <s id="11">The sponsor family that was sending these 25 dollars a month to this orphanage to sponsor me, which -- I had never met them -- said, "Well ...</s>
 <s id="12">we would like to send you to college instead."</s>
 <s id="13">Oh -- it gets better.</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) And they said, "If you get the paperwork, we'll send you to school in America instead."</s>
 <s id="15">So with their help, I went to the embassy and applied for the visa.</s>
 <s id="16">I got the visa.</s>
 <s id="17">I remember this day like it was yesterday.</s>
 <s id="18">I walked out of the embassy with this piece of paper in my hand, a hop in my step, smile on my face, knowing that my life is about to change.</s>
 <s id="19">I went home that night, and I slept with my passport, because I was afraid that someone might steal it.</s>
 <s id="20">(Laughter) I couldn't fall asleep.</s>
 <s id="21">I kept feeling it.</s>
 <s id="22">I had a good idea for security.</s>
 <s id="23">I was like, "OK, I'm going to put it in a plastic bag, and take it outside and dig a hole, and put it in there."</s>
 <s id="24">I did that, went back in the house.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">I could not fall asleep.</s>
  <s id="25.2">I was like, "Maybe someone saw me."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">I went back -- (Laughter) I pulled it out, and I put it with me the entire night -- all to say that it was an anxiety-filled night.</s>
 <s id="27">(Laughter) Going to the US was, just like another speaker said, was my first time to see a plane, be on one, let alone sit on it to fly to another country.</s>
 <s id="28">December 15, 2006.</s>
 <s id="29">7:08pm.</s>
 <s id="30">I sat in seat 7A.</s>
 <s id="31">Fly Emirates.</s>
 <s id="32">One of the most gorgeous, beautiful women I've ever seen walked up, red little hat with a white veil.</s>
 <s id="33">I'm looking terrified, I have no idea what I'm doing.</s>
 <s id="34">She hands me this warm towel -- warm, steamy, snow white.</s>
 <s id="35">I'm looking at this warm towel; I don't know what to do with my life, let alone with this damn towel -- (Laughter) (Applause) I did one of the -- you know, anything anyone could do in that situation: look around, see what everyone else is doing.</s>
 <s id="36">I did the same.</s>
 <s id="37">Mind you, I drove about seven hours from my village to the airport that day.</s>
 <s id="38">So I grab this warm towel, wipe my face just like everyone else is doing, I look at it -- damn.</s>
 <s id="39">(Laughter) It was all dirt brown.</s>
 <s id="40">(Laughter) I remember being so embarrassed that when she came by to pick it up, I didn't give mine.</s>
 <s id="41">(Laughter) I still have it.</s>
 <s id="42">(Laughter) (Applause) Going to America opened doors for me to live up to my full God-given potential.</s>
 <s id="43">I remember when I arrived, the sponsor family embraced me, and they literally had to teach me everything from scratch: this is a microwave, that's a refrigerator -- things I'd never seen before.</s>
 <s id="44">And it was also the first time I got immersed into a new and different culture.</s>
 <s id="45">These strangers showed me true love.</s>
 <s id="46">These strangers showed me that I mattered, that my dreams mattered.</s>
 <s id="47">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="48">These individuals had two of their own biological children.</s>
 <s id="49">And when I came in, I had needs.</s>
 <s id="50">They had to teach me English, teach me literally everything, which resulted in them spending a lot of time with me.</s>
 <s id="51">And that created a little bit of jealousy with their children.</s>
 <s id="52">So, if you're a parent in this room, and you have those teenager children who don't want anything to do with your love and affection -- in fact, they find it repulsive -- I got a solution: adopt a child.</s>
 <s id="53">(Laughter) It will solve the problem.</s>
 <s id="54">(Applause) I went on to acquire two engineering degrees from one of the best institutions in the world.</s>
 <s id="55">I've got to tell you: talent is universal, but opportunities are not.</s>
 <s id="56">And I credit this to the individuals who embrace multiculturalism, love, empathy and compassion for others.</s>
 <s id="57">We live in a world filled with hate: building walls, Brexit, xenophobia here on the African continent.</s>
 <s id="58">Multiculturalism can be an answer to many of these worst human qualities.</s>
 <s id="59">Today, I challenge you to help a young child experience multiculturalism.</s>
 <s id="60">I guarantee you that will enrich their life, and in turn, it will enrich yours.</s>
 <s id="61">And as a bonus, one of them may even give a TED Talk.</s>
 <s id="62">(Laughter) (Applause) We may not be able to solve the bigotry and the racism of this world today, but certainly we can raise children to create a positive, inclusive, connected world full of empathy, love and compassion.</s>
 <s id="63">Love wins.</s>
 <s id="64">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="65">(Applause)</s>
</text>
