<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">As an artist, connection is very important to me.</s>
 <s id="2">Through my work I'm trying to articulate that humans are not separate from nature and that everything is interconnected.</s>
 <s id="3">I first went to Antarctica almost 10 years ago, where I saw my first icebergs.</s>
 <s id="4">I was in awe.</s>
 <s id="5">My heart beat fast, my head was dizzy, trying to comprehend what it was that stood in front of me.</s>
 <s id="6">The icebergs around me were almost 200 feet out of the water, and I could only help but wonder that this was one snowflake on top of another snowflake, year after year.</s>
 <s id="7">Icebergs are born when they calve off of glaciers or break off of ice shelves.</s>
 <s id="8">Each iceberg has its own individual personality.</s>
 <s id="9">They have a distinct way of interacting with their environment and their experiences.</s>
 <s id="10">Some refuse to give up and hold on to the bitter end, while others can't take it anymore and crumble in a fit of dramatic passion.</s>
 <s id="11">It's easy to think, when you look at an iceberg, that they're isolated, that they're separate and alone, much like we as humans sometimes view ourselves.</s>
 <s id="12">But the reality is far from it.</s>
 <s id="13">As an iceberg melts, I am breathing in its ancient atmosphere.</s>
 <s id="14">As the iceberg melts, it is releasing mineral-rich fresh water that nourishes many forms of life.</s>
 <s id="15">I approach photographing these icebergs as if I'm making portraits of my ancestors, knowing that in these individual moments they exist in that way and will never exist that way again.</s>
 <s id="16">It is not a death when they melt; it is not an end, but a continuation of their path through the cycle of life.</s>
 <s id="17">Some of the ice in the icebergs that I photograph is very young -- a couple thousand years old.</s>
 <s id="18">And some of the ice is over 100,000 years old.</s>
 <s id="19">The last pictures I'd like to show you are of an iceberg that I photographed in Qeqetarsuaq, Greenland.</s>
 <s id="20">It's a very rare occasion that you get to actually witness an iceberg rolling.</s>
 <s id="21">So here it is.</s>
 <s id="22">You can see on the left side a small boat.</s>
 <s id="23">That's about a 15-foot boat.</s>
 <s id="24">And I'd like you to pay attention to the shape of the iceberg and where it is at the waterline.</s>
 <s id="25">You can see here, it begins to roll, and the boat has moved to the other side, and the man is standing there.</s>
 <s id="26">This is an average-size Greenlandic iceberg.</s>
 <s id="27">It's about 120 feet above the water, or 40 meters.</s>
 <s id="28">And this video is real time.</s>
 <s id="29">(Music) And just like that, the iceberg shows you a different side of its personality.</s>
 <s id="30">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="31">(Applause)</s>
</text>
