<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm Jessi, and this is my suitcase.</s>
 <s id="2">But before I show you what I've got inside, I'm going to make a very public confession, and that is, I'm outfit-obsessed.</s>
 <s id="3">I love finding, wearing, and more recently, photographing and blogging a different, colorful, crazy outfit for every single occasion.</s>
 <s id="4">But I don't buy anything new.</s>
 <s id="5">I get all my clothes secondhand from flea markets and thrift stores.</s>
 <s id="6">Aww, thank you.</s>
 <s id="7">Secondhand shopping allows me to reduce the impact my wardrobe has on the environment and on my wallet.</s>
 <s id="8">I get to meet all kinds of great people; my dollars usually go to a good cause; I look pretty unique; and it makes shopping like my own personal treasure hunt.</s>
 <s id="9">I mean, what am I going to find today?</s>
 <s id="10">Is it going to be my size?</s>
 <s id="11">Will I like the color?</s>
 <s id="12">Will it be under $20?</s>
 <s id="13">If all the answers are yes, I feel as though I've won.</s>
 <s id="14">I want to get back to my suitcase and tell you what I packed for this exciting week here at TED.</s>
 <s id="15">I mean, what does somebody with all these outfits bring with her?</s>
 <s id="16">So I'm going to show you exactly what I brought.</s>
 <s id="17">I brought seven pairs of underpants and that's it.</s>
 <s id="18">Exactly one week's worth of undies is all I put in my suitcase.</s>
 <s id="19">I was betting that I'd be able to find everything else I could possible want to wear once I got here to Palm Springs.</s>
 <s id="20">And since you don't know me as the woman walking around TED in her underwear -- (Laughter) that means I found a few things.</s>
 <s id="21">And I'd really love to show you my week's worth of outfits right now.</s>
 <s id="22">Does that sound good?</s>
 <s id="23">(Applause) So as I do this, I'm also going to tell you a few of the life lessons that, believe it or not, I have picked up in these adventures wearing nothing new.</s>
 <s id="24">So let's start with Sunday.</s>
 <s id="25">I call this "Shiny Tiger."</s>
 <s id="26">You do not have to spend a lot of money to look great.</s>
 <s id="27">You can almost always look phenomenal for under $50.</s>
 <s id="28">This whole outfit, including the jacket, cost me $55, and it was the most expensive thing that I wore the entire week.</s>
 <s id="29">Monday: Color is powerful.</s>
 <s id="30">It is almost physiologically impossible to be in a bad mood when you're wearing bright red pants.</s>
 <s id="31">(Laughter) If you are happy, you are going to attract other happy people to you.</s>
 <s id="32">Tuesday: Fitting in is way overrated.</s>
 <s id="33">I've spent a whole lot of my life trying to be myself and at the same time fit in.</s>
 <s id="34">Just be who you are.</s>
 <s id="35">If you are surrounding yourself with the right people, they will not only get it, they will appreciate it.</s>
 <s id="36">Wednesday: Embrace your inner child.</s>
 <s id="37">Sometimes people tell me that I look like I'm playing dress-up, or that I remind them of their seven-year-old.</s>
 <s id="38">I like to smile and say, "Thank you."</s>
 <s id="39">Thursday: Confidence is key.</s>
 <s id="40">If you think you look good in something, you almost certainly do.</s>
 <s id="41">And if you don't think you look good in something, you're also probably right.</s>
 <s id="42">I grew up with a mom who taught me this day-in and day-out.</s>
 <s id="43">But it wasn't until I turned 30 that I really got what this meant.</s>
 <s id="44">And I'm going to break it down for you for just a second.</s>
 <s id="45">If you believe you're a beautiful person inside and out, there is no look that you can't pull off.</s>
 <s id="46">So there is no excuse for any of us here in this audience.</s>
 <s id="47">We should be able to rock anything we want to rock.</s>
 <s id="48">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="49">(Applause) Friday: A universal truth -- five words for you: Gold sequins go with everything.</s>
 <s id="50">And finally, Saturday: Developing your own unique personal style is a really great way to tell the world something about you without having to say a word.</s>
 <s id="51">It's been proven to me time and time again as people have walked up to me this week simply because of what I'm wearing, and we've had great conversations.</s>
 <s id="52">So obviously this is not all going to fit back in my tiny suitcase.</s>
 <s id="53">So before I go home to Brooklyn, I'm going to donate everything back.</s>
 <s id="54">Because the lesson I'm trying to learn myself this week is that it's okay to let go.</s>
 <s id="55">I don't need to get emotionally attached to these things because around the corner, there is always going to be another crazy, colorful, shiny outfit just waiting for me, if I put a little love in my heart and look.</s>
 <s id="56">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="57">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="58">(Applause)</s>
</text>
