<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Architecture is amazing, for sure.</s>
 <s id="2">It's amazing because it's art.</s>
 <s id="3">But you know, it's a very funny kind of art.</s>
 <s id="4">It's an art at the frontier between art and science.</s>
 <s id="5">It's fed by ...</s>
 <s id="6">by real life, every day.</s>
 <s id="7">It's driven by force of necessity.</s>
 <s id="8">Quite amazing, quite amazing.</s>
 <s id="9">And the life of the architect is also amazing.</s>
 <s id="10">You know, as an architect, at 10 o’clock in the morning, you need to be a poet, for sure.</s>
 <s id="11">But at 11, you must become a humanist, otherwise you'd lose your direction.</s>
 <s id="12">And at noon, you absolutely need to be a builder.</s>
 <s id="13">You need to be able to make a building, because architecture, at the end, is the art of making buildings.</s>
 <s id="14">Architecture is the art of making shelter for human beings.</s>
 <s id="15">Period.</s>
 <s id="16">And this is not easy at all.</s>
 <s id="17">It's amazing.</s>
 <s id="18">Look at this.</s>
 <s id="19">Here we are in London, at the top of the Shard of Glass.</s>
 <s id="20">This is a building we completed a few years ago.</s>
 <s id="21">Those people are well-trained workers, and they are assembling the top piece of the tower.</s>
 <s id="22">Well, they look like rock climbers.</s>
 <s id="23">They are.</s>
 <s id="24">I mean, they are defying the force of gravity, like building does, by the way.</s>
 <s id="25">We got 30 of those people -- actually, on that site, we got more than 1,400 people, coming from 60 different nationalities.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">You know, this is a miracle.</s>
  <s id="26.2">It's a miracle.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">To put together 1,400 people, coming from such different places, is a miracle.</s>
 <s id="28">Sites are miracles.</s>
 <s id="29">This is another one.</s>
 <s id="30">Let's talk about construction.</s>
 <s id="31">Adventure, it's adventure in real life, not adventure in spirit.</s>
 <s id="32">This guy there is a deepwater diver.</s>
 <s id="33">From rock climbers to deepwater divers.</s>
 <s id="34">This is in Berlin.</s>
 <s id="35">After the fall of the Wall in '89, we built this building, connecting East Berlin to West Berlin, in Potsdamer Platz.</s>
 <s id="36">We got on that project almost 5,000 people.</s>
 <s id="37">Almost 5,000 people.</s>
 <s id="38">And this is another site in Japan, building the Kansai Airport.</s>
 <s id="39">Again, all the rock climbers, Japanese ones.</s>
 <s id="40">You know, making buildings together is the best way to create a sense of cooperation.</s>
 <s id="41">The sense of pride -- pride is essential.</s>
 <s id="42">But, you know, construction, of course, is one of the reasons why architecture is amazing.</s>
 <s id="43">But there is another one, that is maybe even more amazing.</s>
 <s id="44">Because architecture is the art of making shelter for communities, not just for individuals -- communities and society at large.</s>
 <s id="45">And society is never the same.</s>
 <s id="46">The world keeps changing.</s>
 <s id="47">And changes are difficult to swallow by people.</s>
 <s id="48">And architecture is a mirror of those changes.</s>
 <s id="49">Architecture is the built expression of those changes.</s>
 <s id="50">So, this is why it is so difficult, because those changes create adventure.</s>
 <s id="51">They create adventure, and architecture is adventure.</s>
 <s id="52">This is the Centre Georges Pompidou in Paris, a long time ago.</s>
 <s id="53">That was back in time, '77.</s>
 <s id="54">This was a spaceship landing in the middle of Paris.</s>
 <s id="55">Together with my friend in adventure, Richard Rogers, we were, at the time, young bad boys.</s>
 <s id="56">Young, bad boys.</s>
 <s id="57">(Laughter) It was really only a few years after May '68.</s>
 <s id="58">So it was a rebellion, pure rebellion.</s>
 <s id="59">The idea was to make the proof that cultural buildings should not be intimidating.</s>
 <s id="60">They should create a sense of curiosity.</s>
 <s id="61">This is the way to create a cultural place.</s>
 <s id="62">Curiosity is the beginning of a cultural attitude.</s>
 <s id="63">And there's a piazza there, you can see that piazza.</s>
 <s id="64">And a piazza is the beginning of urban life.</s>
 <s id="65">A piazza is the place where people meet.</s>
 <s id="66">And they mix experience.</s>
 <s id="67">And they mix ages.</s>
 <s id="68">And, you know, in some way, you create the essence of the city.</s>
 <s id="69">And since then, we made, in the office, so many other places for people.</s>
 <s id="70">Here, in Rome, is a concert hall.</s>
 <s id="71">Another place for people.</s>
 <s id="72">This building inside is actually designed by the sound, you can see.</s>
 <s id="73">It's flirting with sound.</s>
 <s id="74">And this is the Kansai Airport, in Japan.</s>
 <s id="75">To make a building, sometimes you need to make an island, and we made the island.</s>
 <s id="76">The building is more than one mile long.</s>
 <s id="77">It looks like an immense glider, landing on the ground.</s>
 <s id="78">And this is in San Francisco.</s>
 <s id="79">Another place for people.</s>
 <s id="80">This building is the California Academy of Sciences.</s>
 <s id="81">And we planted on that roof -- thousands and thousands of plants that use the humidity of the air, instead of pumping water from the water table.</s>
 <s id="82">The roof is a living roof, actually.</s>
 <s id="83">And this building was made Platinum LEED.</s>
 <s id="84">The LEED is the system to measure, of course, the sustainability of a building.</s>
 <s id="85">So this was also a place for people that will stay a long time.</s>
 <s id="86">And this is actually New York.</s>
 <s id="87">This is the new Whitney, in the Meatpacking District in New York.</s>
 <s id="88">Well, another flying vessel.</s>
 <s id="89">Another place for people.</s>
 <s id="90">Here we are in Athens, the Niarchos Foundation.</s>
 <s id="91">It's a library, it's an open house, a concert hall and a big park.</s>
 <s id="92">This building is also a Platinum LEED building.</s>
 <s id="93">This building actually captures the sun's energy with that roof.</s>
 <s id="94">But, you know, making a building a place for people is good.</s>
 <s id="95">Making libraries, making concert halls, making universities, making museums is good, because you create a place that's open, accessible.</s>
 <s id="96">You create a building for a better world, for sure.</s>
 <s id="97">But there is something else that makes architecture amazing, even more.</s>
 <s id="98">And this is the fact that architecture doesn't just answer to need and necessity, but also to desires -- yes, desires -- dreams, aspirations.</s>
 <s id="99">This is what architecture does.</s>
 <s id="100">Even the most modest hut on earth is not just a roof.</s>
 <s id="101">It's more than a roof.</s>
 <s id="102">It's telling a story; it's telling a story about the identity of the people living in that hut.</s>
 <s id="103">Individuals.</s>
 <s id="104">Architecture is the art of telling stories.</s>
 <s id="105">Like this one.</s>
 <s id="106">In London: the Shard of Glass.</s>
 <s id="107">Well, this building is the tallest building in Western Europe.</s>
 <s id="108">It goes up more than 300 meters in the air, to breathe fresh air.</s>
 <s id="109">The facets of this building are inclined, and they reflect the sky of London, that is never the same.</s>
 <s id="110">After rain, everything becomes bluish.</s>
 <s id="111">In the sunny evening, everything is red.</s>
 <s id="112">It's something that is difficult to explain.</s>
 <s id="113">It's what we call the soul of a building.</s>
 <s id="114">On this picture on the left, you have the Menil Collection, used a long time ago.</s>
 <s id="115">It's a museum.</s>
 <s id="116">On the right is the Harvard Art Museum.</s>
 <s id="117">Both those two buildings flirt with light.</s>
 <s id="118">Light is probably one of the most essential materials in architecture.</s>
 <s id="119">And this is in Amsterdam.</s>
 <s id="120">This building is flirting with water.</s>
 <s id="121">And this is my office, on the sea.</s>
 <s id="122">Well, this is flirting with work.</s>
 <s id="123">Actually, we enjoy working there.</s>
 <s id="124">And that cable car is the little cable car that goes up to there.</s>
 <s id="125">That's "The New York Times" in New York.</s>
 <s id="126">Well, this is playing with transparency.</s>
 <s id="127">Again, the sense of light, the sense of transparency.</s>
 <s id="128">On the left here, you have the Magic Lantern in Japan, in Ginza, in Tokyo.</s>
 <s id="129">And in the center is a monastery in the forest.</s>
 <s id="130">This monastery is playing with the silence and the forest.</s>
 <s id="131">And a museum, a science museum.</s>
 <s id="132">This is about levitation.</s>
 <s id="133">And this is in the center of Paris, in the belly of the whale.</s>
 <s id="134">This is the Pathé Foundation in Paris.</s>
 <s id="135">All those buildings have something in common: it's that something is searching for desire, for dreams.</s>
 <s id="136">And that's me.</s>
 <s id="137">(Laughter) Well, it's me on my sailing boat.</s>
 <s id="138">Flirting with breeze.</s>
 <s id="139">Well, there's not a very good reason to show you this picture.</s>
 <s id="140">(Laughter) I'm trying, I'm trying.</s>
 <s id="141">You know, one thing is clear: I love sailing, for sure.</s>
 <s id="142">I actually also love designing sailing boats.</s>
 <s id="143">But I love sailing, because sailing is associated with slowness.</s>
 <s id="144">And ...</s>
 <s id="145">and silence.</s>
 <s id="146">And the sense of suspension.</s>
 <s id="147">And there is another thing that this picture says.</s>
 <s id="148">It says that I'm Italian.</s>
 <s id="149">(Laughter) Well, there is very little I can do about that.</s>
 <s id="150">(Laughter) I'm Italian, and I love beauty.</s>
 <s id="151">I love beauty.</s>
 <s id="152">Well, let's go sailing, I want to take you sailing here, to this place, in the middle of the Pacific Ocean.</s>
 <s id="153">This is the Jean-Marie Tjibaou Center.</s>
 <s id="154">It's for the Kanaky ethnic group.</s>
 <s id="155">It's in Nouméa, New Caledonia.</s>
 <s id="156">This place is for art.</s>
 <s id="157">Art and nature.</s>
 <s id="158">And those buildings actually flirt with the wind, with the trade winds.</s>
 <s id="159">They have a sound, they have a voice, those buildings.</s>
 <s id="160">I'm showing this because it's about beauty.</s>
 <s id="161">It's about pure beauty.</s>
 <s id="162">And let's talk about beauty for a moment.</s>
 <s id="163">Beauty is like the bird of paradise: the very moment you try to catch it, it flies away.</s>
 <s id="164">Your arm is too short.</s>
 <s id="165">But beauty is not a frivolous idea.</s>
 <s id="166">It's the opposite.</s>
 <s id="167">In my native language, that is Italian, "beautiful" is "bello."</s>
 <s id="168">In Spanish, "beauty" is "belleza."</s>
 <s id="169">In Greek, "beautiful" is "kalos."</s>
 <s id="170">When you add "agathos," that means "beautiful and good."</s>
 <s id="171">In no one of those languages, "beautiful" just means "beautiful."</s>
 <s id="172">It also means "good."</s>
 <s id="173">Real beauty is when the invisible joins the visible, coming on surface.</s>
 <s id="174">And this doesn't apply only to art or nature.</s>
 <s id="175">This applies to science, human curiosity, solidarity -- that's the reason why you may say, "This is a beautiful person," "That's a beautiful mind."</s>
 <s id="176">This, this is the beauty that can change people into better people, by switching a special light in their eyes.</s>
 <s id="177">And making buildings for this beauty makes cities better places to live.</s>
 <s id="178">And better cities make better citizens.</s>
 <s id="179">Well, this beauty -- this universal beauty, I should say -- is one of the few things that can change the world.</s>
 <s id="180">Believe me, this beauty will save the world.</s>
 <s id="181">One person at a time, but it will do it.</s>
 <s id="182">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="183">(Applause)</s>
</text>
