<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">[Stories from the Sea] [Fish Tale My Secret Life as Plankton] How did I get here?</s>
 <s id="2">Well, it's a stranger story than you might think.</s>
 <s id="3">I came from a world of drifters, a place few humans have ever seen.</s>
 <s id="4">The world of plankton.</s>
 <s id="5">I came from a batch of a million eggs, and only a few of us survived.</s>
 <s id="6">When I became a larva, I moved among other drifters.</s>
 <s id="7">["Plankton" comes from the Greek "planktos" for wandering] My fellow plankton came in all sizes, from tiny algae and bacteria to animals longer than a blue whale.</s>
 <s id="8">I shared my nursery with other embryos and juveniles, from clams and crabs to sea urchins and anemones.</s>
 <s id="9">(High pitch sound) We drifting animals are called zooplankton.</s>
 <s id="10">The most common animals here are copepods and krill.</s>
 <s id="11">(Buzzing) You could search the world over, but you'd never find a place more diverse than my childhood home.</s>
 <s id="12">A teaspoon of seawater can contain more than a million living creatures.</s>
 <s id="13">It can be a pretty tough existence, though.</s>
 <s id="14">Trillions are born here, but only a few make it to adulthood.</s>
 <s id="15">He may be no larger than a pin head, but this crab larva is an arrow worm's worst nightmare.</s>
 <s id="16">(Bumping noises) (Buzzing) Epic battles between carnivores like these are just one way to get food.</s>
 <s id="17">But the real powers of this place come from phytoplankton.</s>
 <s id="18">Single-celled life that transforms sunlight and carbon dioxide into edible gold.</s>
 <s id="19">Phytoplankton are the base for the largest food web in the world.</s>
 <s id="20">During the night, many animals like me would rise up from the depths to feed on this sun-powered feast.</s>
 <s id="21">(Maraca sound) I was part of the largest daily migration of life on Earth.</s>
 <s id="22">During the day, I'd return to the darkness, where I'd join my bizarre companions.</s>
 <s id="23">(High pitch buzz) (Flapping noises) Cannibals, like this sea butterfly mollusk, that eats its next of kin.</s>
 <s id="24">And comb jellies, that beat cilia like rainbowed eyelashes.</s>
 <s id="25">Some of these snare their prey with sticky tentacles, while others just take a bite out of their cousins.</s>
 <s id="26">And siphonophores that catch prey with toxic fishing lures.</s>
 <s id="27">But my favorite would have to be the crustacean Phronima.</s>
 <s id="28">Its monstrous looks inspired the movie "Aliens."</s>
 <s id="29">It can catch tiny bits in its bristles, but prefers larger prey like salps.</s>
 <s id="30">With two sets of eyes, this female prowls the deeper water.</s>
 <s id="31">Prey in hand, she performs one of the strangest behaviors in the entire animal kingdom.</s>
 <s id="32">With body parts from her victims, she delicately assembles a barrel-like home feeding her young until they can drift off and survive on their own.</s>
 <s id="33">Best of all, they make the perfect snack for a small fish like me.</s>
 <s id="34">Here among the plankton, the food web is so tangled and complex, even scientists don't know who eats whom.</s>
 <s id="35">But I do.</s>
 <s id="36">At least now you know a bit of my story.</s>
 <s id="37">There's so much more to me than just a tasty meal.</s>
</text>
