<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In the sun-dappled streets of a small town, a proud mother showed off her newborn son.</s>
 <s id="2">Upon noticing his lucky birthmark, townsfolk predicted he would marry a princess.</s>
 <s id="3">But soon, these rumors reached the ears of the wicked king.</s>
 <s id="4">Enraged, the king stole the child away, and sent him hurtling down the river.</s>
 <s id="5">But the infant’s luck proved greater than the king’s plan.</s>
 <s id="6">Years later, the king was traveling his realm, when he spotted a strapping young man with an uncanny birthmark.</s>
 <s id="7">After confirming the child’s origins, the sly king entrusted the boy with a letter for the queen.</s>
 <s id="8">The youth eagerly set out to deliver the message— not knowing he was carrying his own death sentence.</s>
 <s id="9">That night, roaming bandits stumbled upon his camp.</s>
 <s id="10">Yet when they read the brutal letter, they were filled with pity.</s>
 <s id="11">Deciding to make trouble for the king instead, they scribbled a new note.</s>
 <s id="12">As soon as the youth arrived at the palace, he locked eyes with the princess.</s>
 <s id="13">The two felt destined for each other.</s>
 <s id="14">And when the queen read that the king approved this union, she joyfully organized a whirlwind wedding.</s>
 <s id="15">When the king returned, he was furious.</s>
 <s id="16">But he couldn’t execute his daughter’s beloved without reason.</s>
 <s id="17">So he devised a diabolical trial.</s>
 <s id="18">He ordered the youth to travel to Hell itself, and return with three golden hairs freshly plucked from the Devil’s head.</s>
 <s id="19">Only upon succeeding could he return to his bride.</s>
 <s id="20">The youth searched across the land for the entrance to Hell, until he finally reached an eerie village.</s>
 <s id="21">Here, he saw some villagers gathered around a well.</s>
 <s id="22">They closed in on the youth, refusing to let him pass until he answered their question: why was the well dry?</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">The youth replied, “I will answer when I return.”</s>
  <s id="23.2">They directed him further into town, where he came across another set of villagers contemplating a gnarled tree.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="24">They refused to let him pass until he answered their question: why was the tree barren?</s>
 <s id="25">Again, the youth responded, “I will answer when I return."</s>
 <s id="26">These villagers guided him to the dock, where an elderly ferryman awaited.</s>
 <s id="27">As he paddled through the black water, the ferryman rasped a third question: how can I escape my interminable task?</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">Once more, the youth promised, “I will answer when I return.”</s>
  <s id="28.2">At last, they reached a hut sinking into the swampy banks of Hell.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">Reluctantly, the youth knocked on the rotting door.</s>
 <s id="30">The devil’s grandmother answered his call.</s>
 <s id="31">She was known to help some visiting souls, and harm others.</s>
 <s id="32">The youth had just finished his story when they heard the devil’s footsteps.</s>
 <s id="33">Without warning, the boy’s world appeared to shrink.</s>
 <s id="34">The devil’s grandmother lifted him into the folds of her sleeve, and welcomed her grandson.</s>
 <s id="35">The old woman set to work, lavishing the devil with food and drink.</s>
 <s id="36">When he fell asleep, she deftly plucked three gleaming hairs from his head.</s>
 <s id="37">With each plucked hair, the Devil briefly awoke and complained about his dreams, full of nearby villagers and their problems.</s>
 <s id="38">The next morning, the youth departed— armed with three golden hairs, and three pieces of information.</s>
 <s id="39">He shared the devil’s first dream with the ferryman.</s>
 <s id="40">If the boatman could hand his oars to a willing passenger, he would be free from his task.</s>
 <s id="41">Back at the village, the youth declared that there was a mouse gnawing at the root of the tree, and an enormous toad blocking the well.</s>
 <s id="42">The villagers rewarded him handsomely for his help.</s>
 <s id="43">Back from his journey, the youth thrust the devil’s hairs at the king— but his greedy father-in-law only had eyes for the gold.</s>
 <s id="44">The sly youth told the king that even greater wealth awaited him across the river.</s>
 <s id="45">Immediately, the king hastened to the riverbank.</s>
 <s id="46">Eager to claim his riches, he held out his hands impatiently to the grinning ferryman— who happily handed over his oars.</s>
</text>
