<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Applause) Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="2">I have a few pictures, and I'll talk a little bit about how I'm able to do what I do.</s>
 <s id="3">All these houses are built from between 70 and 80 percent recycled material, stuff that was headed to the mulcher, the landfill, the burn pile.</s>
 <s id="4">It was all just gone.</s>
 <s id="5">This is the first house I built.</s>
 <s id="6">This double front door here with the three-light transom, that was headed to the landfill.</s>
 <s id="7">Have a little turret there.</s>
 <s id="8">And then these buttons on the corbels here -- right there -- those are hickory nuts.</s>
 <s id="9">And these buttons there -- those are chicken eggs.</s>
 <s id="10">(Laughter) Of course, first you have breakfast, and then you fill the shell full of Bondo and paint it and nail it up, and you have an architectural button in just a fraction of the time.</s>
 <s id="11">This is a look at the inside.</s>
 <s id="12">You can see the three-light transom there with the eyebrow windows.</s>
 <s id="13">Certainly an architectural antique headed to the landfill -- even the lockset is probably worth 200 dollars.</s>
 <s id="14">Everything in the kitchen was salvaged.</s>
 <s id="15">There's a 1952 O'Keefe &amp;amp; Merritt stove, if you like to cook -- cool stove.</s>
 <s id="16">This is going up into the turret.</s>
 <s id="17">I got that staircase for 20 dollars, including delivery to my lot.</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) Then, looking up in the turret, you see there are bulges and pokes and sags and so forth.</s>
 <s id="19">Well, if that ruins your life, well, then, you shouldn't live there.</s>
 <s id="20">(Laughter) This is a laundry chute.</s>
 <s id="21">And this right here is a shoe last -- those are those cast-iron things you see at antique shops.</s>
 <s id="22">So I had one of those, so I made some low-tech gadgetry, where you just stomp on the shoe last, and then the door flies open and you throw your laundry down.</s>
 <s id="23">And then if you're smart enough, it goes on a basket on top of the washer.</s>
 <s id="24">If not, it goes into the toilet.</s>
 <s id="25">(Laughter) This is a bathtub I made, made out of scrap two-by-four.</s>
 <s id="26">Started with the rim, and then glued and nailed it up into a flat, corbeled it up and flipped it over, then did the two profiles on this side.</s>
 <s id="27">It's a two-person tub.</s>
 <s id="28">After all, it's not just a question of hygiene, but there's a possibility of recreation as well.</s>
 <s id="29">(Laughter) Then, this faucet here is just a piece of Osage orange.</s>
 <s id="30">It looks a little phallic, but after all, it's a bathroom.</s>
 <s id="31">(Laughter) This is a house based on a Budweiser can.</s>
 <s id="32">It doesn't look like a can of beer, but the design take-offs are absolutely unmistakable: the barley hops design worked up into the eaves, then the dentil work comes directly off the can's red, white, blue and silver.</s>
 <s id="33">Then, these corbels going down underneath the eaves are that little design that comes off the can.</s>
 <s id="34">I just put a can on a copier and kept enlarging it until I got the size I want.</s>
 <s id="35">Then, on the can it says, "This is the famous Budweiser beer, we know of no other beer, blah, blah, blah."</s>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">So we changed that and put, "This is the famous Budweiser house.</s>
  <s id="36.2">We don't know of any other house ..."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="37">and so forth and so on.</s>
 <s id="38">This is a deadbolt.</s>
 <s id="39">It's a fence from a 1930s shaper, which is a very angry woodworking machine.</s>
 <s id="40">And they gave me the fence, but they didn't give me the shaper, so we made a deadbolt out of it.</s>
 <s id="41">That'll keep bull elephants out, I promise.</s>
 <s id="42">(Laughter) And sure enough, we've had no problems with bull elephants.</s>
 <s id="43">(Laughter) The shower is intended to simulate a glass of beer.</s>
 <s id="44">We've got bubbles going up there, then suds at the top with lumpy tiles.</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">Where do you get lumpy tiles?</s>
  <s id="45.2">Well, of course, you don't.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="46">But I get a lot of toilets, and so you just dispatch a toilet with a hammer, and then you have lumpy tiles.</s>
 <s id="47">And then the faucet is a beer tap.</s>
 <s id="48">(Laughter) Then, this panel of glass is the same panel of glass that occurs in every middle-class front door in America.</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">We're getting tired of it.</s>
  <s id="49.2">It's kind of clichéd now.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">If you put it in the front door, your design fails.</s>
 <s id="51">So don't put it in the front door; put it somewhere else.</s>
 <s id="52">It's a pretty panel of glass.</s>
 <s id="53">But if you put it in the front door, people say, "Oh, you're trying to be like those guys, and you didn't make it."</s>
 <s id="54">So don't put it there.</s>
 <s id="55">Then, another bathroom upstairs.</s>
 <s id="56">This light up here is the same light that occurs in every middle-class foyer in America.</s>
 <s id="57">Don't put it in the foyer.</s>
 <s id="58">Put it in the shower, or in the closet, but not in the foyer.</s>
 <s id="59">Then, somebody gave me a bidet, so it got a bidet.</s>
 <s id="60">(Laughter) This little house here, those branches there are made out of Bois d'arc or Osage orange.</s>
 <s id="61">These pictures will keep scrolling as I talk a little bit.</s>
 <s id="62">In order to do what I do, you have to understand what causes waste in the building industry.</s>
 <s id="63">Our housing has become a commodity, and I'll talk a little bit about that.</s>
 <s id="64">But the first cause of waste is probably even buried in our DNA.</s>
 <s id="65">Human beings have a need for maintaining consistency of the apperceptive mass.</s>
 <s id="66">What does that mean?</s>
 <s id="67">What it means is, for every perception we have, it needs to tally with the one like it before, or we don't have continuity, and we become a little bit disoriented.</s>
 <s id="68">So I can show you an object you've never seen before.</s>
 <s id="69">Oh, that's a cell phone.</s>
 <s id="70">But you've never seen this one before.</s>
 <p id="p71">
  <s id="71.1">What you're doing is sizing up the pattern of structural features, and then you go through your databanks: Cell phone.</s>
  <s id="71.2">Oh!</s>
  <s id="71.3">That's a cell phone.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="72">If I took a bite out of it, you'd go, "Wait a second.</s>
 <s id="73">(Laughter) "That's not a cell phone.</s>
 <s id="74">That's one of those new chocolate cell phones."</s>
 <s id="75">(Laughter) You'd have to start a new category, right between cell phones and chocolate.</s>
 <s id="76">(Laughter) That's how we process information.</s>
 <s id="77">You translate that to the building industry.</s>
 <p id="p78">
  <s id="78.1">If we have a wall of windowpanes and one pane is cracked, we go, "Oh, dear.</s>
  <s id="78.2">That's cracked.</s>
  <s id="78.3">Let's repair it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="79">Let's take it out and throw it away so nobody can use it and put a new one in."</s>
 <s id="80">Because that's what you do with a cracked pane.</s>
 <s id="81">Never mind that it doesn't affect our lives at all.</s>
 <s id="82">It only rattles that expected pattern and unity of structural features.</s>
 <s id="83">However, if we took a small hammer, and we added cracks to all the other windows -- (Laughter) then we have a pattern.</s>
 <s id="84">Because Gestalt psychology emphasizes recognition of pattern over parts that comprise a pattern.</s>
 <s id="85">We'll go, "Ooh, that's nice."</s>
 <s id="86">So, that serves me every day.</s>
 <s id="87">Repetition creates pattern.</s>
 <s id="88">If I have 100 of these, 100 of those, it makes no difference what these and those are.</s>
 <s id="89">If I can repeat anything, I have the possibility of a pattern, from hickory nuts and chicken eggs, shards of glass, branches.</s>
 <s id="90">It doesn't make any difference.</s>
 <s id="91">That causes a lot of waste in the building industry.</s>
 <s id="92">The second cause is, Friedrich Nietzsche, along about 1885, wrote a book titled "The Birth of Tragedy."</s>
 <s id="93">And in there, he said cultures tend to swing between one of two perspectives: on the one hand, we have an Apollonian perspective, which is very crisp and premeditated and intellectualized and perfect.</s>
 <s id="94">On the other end of the spectrum, we have a Dionysian perspective, which is more given to the passions and intuition, tolerant of organic texture and human gesture.</s>
 <s id="95">So the way the Apollonian personality takes a picture or hangs a picture is, they'll get out a transit and a laser level and a micrometer.</s>
 <p id="p96">
  <s id="96.1">"OK, honey.</s>
  <s id="96.2">A thousandth of an inch to the left.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p97">
  <s id="97.1">That's where we want the picture.</s>
  <s id="97.2">Right.</s>
  <s id="97.3">Perfect!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="98">Predicated on plumb level, square and centered.</s>
 <s id="99">The Dionysian personality takes the picture and goes: (Laughter) That's the difference.</s>
 <s id="100">I feature blemish.</s>
 <s id="101">I feature organic process.</s>
 <s id="102">Dead center John Dewey.</s>
 <s id="103">Apollonian mindset creates mountains of waste.</s>
 <s id="104">If something isn't perfect, if it doesn't line up with that premeditated model?</s>
 <s id="105">Dumpster.</s>
 <p id="p106">
  <s id="106.1">"Oops.</s>
  <s id="106.2">Scratch.</s>
  <s id="106.3">Dumpster."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p107">
  <s id="107.1">"Oops" this, "oops" that.</s>
  <s id="107.2">Landfill, landfill, landfill.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="108">The third thing is arguably -- The Industrial Revolution started in the Renaissance with the rise of humanism, then got a little jump start along about the French Revolution.</s>
 <s id="109">By the middle of the 19th century, it's in full flower.</s>
 <s id="110">And we have dumaflaches and gizmos and contraptions that will do anything that we, up to that point, had to do by hand.</s>
 <s id="111">So now we have standardized materials.</s>
 <s id="112">Well, trees don't grow two inches by four inches, eight, ten and twelve feet tall.</s>
 <s id="113">(Laughter) We create mountains of waste.</s>
 <s id="114">And they're doing a pretty good job there in the forest, working all the byproduct of their industry -- with OSB and particle board and so forth and so on -- but it does no good to be responsible at the point of harvest in the forest if consumers are wasting the harvest at the point of consumption.</s>
 <s id="115">And that's what's happening.</s>
 <p id="p116">
  <s id="116.1">And so if something isn't standard, "Oops, dumpster."</s>
  <s id="116.2">"Oops" this.</s>
  <s id="116.3">"Oops, warped."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="117">If you buy a two-by-four and it's not straight, you can take it back.</s>
 <p id="p118">
  <s id="118.1">"Oh, I'm so sorry, sir.</s>
  <s id="118.2">We'll get you a straight one."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="119">Well, I feature all those warped things because repetition creates pattern, and it's from a Dionysian perspective.</s>
 <s id="120">The fourth thing is labor is disproportionately more expensive than materials.</s>
 <s id="121">Well, that's just a myth.</s>
 <s id="122">And there's a story: Jim Tulles, one of the guys I trained -- I said, "Jim, it's time now.</s>
 <p id="p123">
  <s id="123.1">I got a job for you as a foreman on a framing crew.</s>
  <s id="123.2">Time for you to go."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="124">"Dan, I just don't think I'm ready."</s>
 <p id="p125">
  <s id="125.1">"Jim, now it's time.</s>
  <s id="125.2">You're the down -- oh!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="126">So we hired on.</s>
 <s id="127">And he was out there with a tape measure, going through the trash heap, looking for header material, or the board that goes over a door, thinking he'd impress his boss -- that's how we taught him to do it.</s>
 <s id="128">The superintendent walked up and said, "What are you doing?"</s>
 <s id="129">"Oh, just looking for header material," waiting for that kudos.</s>
 <p id="p130">
  <s id="130.1">He said, "I'm not paying you to go through the trash.</s>
  <s id="130.2">Get back to work."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="131">And Jim had the wherewithal to say, "You know, if you were paying me 300 dollars an hour, I can see how you might say that.</s>
 <s id="132">But right now, I'm saving you five dollars a minute.</s>
 <s id="133">Do the math."</s>
 <p id="p134">
  <s id="134.1">(Laughter) "Good call, Tulles.</s>
  <s id="134.2">From now on, you guys hit this pile first."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="135">And the irony is that he wasn't very good at math.</s>
 <s id="136">(Laughter) But once in a while, you get access to the control room, and then you can kind of mess with the dials.</s>
 <s id="137">And that's what happened there.</s>
 <s id="138">The fifth thing is that maybe, after 2,500 years, Plato is still having his way with us in his notion of perfect forms.</s>
 <s id="139">He said that we have in our noggin the perfect idea of what we want, and we force environmental resources to accommodate that.</s>
 <s id="140">So we all have in our head the perfect house, the American dream, which is a house, the dream house.</s>
 <s id="141">The problem is we can't afford it.</s>
 <s id="142">So we have the American dream look-alike, which is a mobile home.</s>
 <s id="143">Now there's a blight on the planet.</s>
 <s id="144">(Laughter) It's a chattel mortgage, just like furniture, just like a car.</s>
 <s id="145">You write the check, and instantly, it depreciates 30 percent.</s>
 <s id="146">After a year, you can't get insurance on everything you have in it, only on 70 percent.</s>
 <s id="147">Wired with 14-Gauge wire, typically.</s>
 <s id="148">Nothing wrong with that, unless you ask it to do what 12-Gauge wire's supposed to do, and that's what happens.</s>
 <s id="149">It out-gasses formaldehyde -- so much so that there is a federal law in place to warn new mobile home buyers of the formaldehyde atmosphere danger.</s>
 <s id="150">Are we just being numbingly stupid?</s>
 <s id="151">The walls are this thick.</s>
 <s id="152">The whole thing has the structural value of corn.</s>
 <p id="p153">
  <s id="153.1">(Laughter) "So ...</s>
  <s id="153.2">I thought Palm Harbor Village was over there."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p154">
  <s id="154.1">"No, no.</s>
  <s id="154.2">We had a wind last night.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="155">It's gone now."</s>
 <s id="156">(Laughter) Then when they degrade, what do you do with them?</s>
 <s id="157">Now, all that -- that Apollonian, Platonic model -- is what the building industry is predicated on, and there are a number of things that exacerbate that.</s>
 <s id="158">One is that all the professionals, all the tradesmen, vendors, inspectors, engineers, architects all think like this.</s>
 <s id="159">And then it works its way back to the consumer, who demands the same model.</s>
 <p id="p160">
  <s id="160.1">It's a self-fulfilling prophecy.</s>
  <s id="160.2">We can't get out of it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="161">Then here come the marketeers and the advertisers.</s>
 <p id="p162">
  <s id="162.1">"Woo.</s>
  <s id="162.2">Woo-hoo."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="163">We buy stuff we didn't know we needed.</s>
 <s id="164">All we have to do is look at what one company did with carbonated prune juice.</s>
 <s id="165">How disgusting.</s>
 <s id="166">(Laughter) But you know what they did?</s>
 <s id="167">They hooked a metaphor into it and said, "I drink Dr. Pepper ..."</s>
 <s id="168">And pretty soon, we're swilling that stuff by the lake-ful, by the billions of gallons.</s>
 <p id="p169">
  <s id="169.1">It doesn't even have real prunes!</s>
  <s id="169.2">Doesn't even keep you regular.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="170">(Laughter) My oh my, that makes it worse.</s>
 <s id="171">And we get sucked into that faster than anything.</s>
 <s id="172">Then, a man named Jean-Paul Sartre wrote a book titled "Being and Nothingness."</s>
 <p id="p173">
  <s id="173.1">It's a pretty quick read.</s>
  <s id="173.2">You can snap through it in maybe -- (Laughter) maybe two years, if you read eight hours a day.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="174">In there, he talked about the divided self.</s>
 <s id="175">He said human beings act differently when they know they're alone than when they know somebody else is around.</s>
 <s id="176">So if I'm eating spaghetti, and I know I'm alone, I can eat like a backhoe.</s>
 <s id="177">I can wipe my mouth on my sleeve, napkin on the table, chew with my mouth open, make little noises, scratch wherever I want.</s>
 <p id="p178">
  <s id="178.1">(Laughter) But as soon as you walk in, I go, "Oops!</s>
  <s id="178.2">Lil' spaghetti sauce there."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="179">Napkin in my lap, half-bites, chew with my mouth closed, no scratching.</s>
 <s id="180">Now, what I'm doing is fulfilling your expectations of how I should live my life.</s>
 <s id="181">I feel that expectation, and so I accommodate it, and I'm living my life according to what you expect me to do.</s>
 <s id="182">That happens in the building industry as well.</s>
 <s id="183">That's why all subdivisions look the same.</s>
 <s id="184">Sometimes, we even have these formalized cultural expectations.</s>
 <s id="185">I'll bet all your shoes match.</s>
 <s id="186">Sure enough, we all buy into that ...</s>
 <s id="187">(Laughter) And with gated communities, we have a formalized expectation, with a homeowners' association.</s>
 <s id="188">Sometimes those guys are Nazis, my oh my.</s>
 <s id="189">That exacerbates and continues this model.</s>
 <s id="190">The last thing is gregariousness.</s>
 <s id="191">Human beings are a social species.</s>
 <s id="192">We like to hang together in groups, just like wildebeests, just like lions.</s>
 <s id="193">Wildebeests don't hang with lions, because lions eat wildebeests.</s>
 <s id="194">Human beings are like that.</s>
 <s id="195">We do what that group does that we're trying to identify with.</s>
 <s id="196">You see this in junior high a lot.</s>
 <s id="197">Those kids, they'll work all summer long -- kill themselves -- so that they can afford one pair of designer jeans.</s>
 <p id="p198">
  <s id="198.1">So along about September, they can stride in and go, "I'm important today.</s>
  <s id="198.2">See?</s>
  <s id="198.3">Don't touch my designer jeans!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="199">I see you don't have designer jeans.</s>
 <s id="200">You're not one of the beautiful -- See, I'm one of the beautiful people.</s>
 <s id="201">See my jeans?"</s>
 <s id="202">Right there is reason enough to have uniforms.</s>
 <s id="203">And so that happens in the building industry as well.</s>
 <s id="204">We have confused Maslow's hierarchy of needs, just a little bit.</s>
 <s id="205">On the bottom tier, we have basic needs: shelter, clothing, food, water, mating and so forth.</s>
 <p id="p206">
  <s id="206.1">Second: security.</s>
  <s id="206.2">Third: relationships.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="207">Fourth: status, self-esteem -- that is, vanity -- and we're taking vanity and shoving it down here.</s>
 <s id="208">And so we end up with vain decisions, and we can't even afford our mortgage.</s>
 <s id="209">We can't afford to eat anything except beans; that is, our housing has become a commodity.</s>
 <s id="210">And it takes a little bit of nerve to dive into those primal, terrifying parts of ourselves and make our own decisions and not make our housing a commodity, but make it something that bubbles up from seminal sources.</s>
 <s id="211">That takes a little bit of nerve, and, darn it, once in a while, you fail.</s>
 <s id="212">But that's okay.</s>
 <s id="213">If failure destroys you, then you can't do this.</s>
 <s id="214">I fail all the time, every day, and I've had some whopping failures, I promise -- big, public, humiliating, embarrassing failures.</s>
 <s id="215">Everybody points and laughs, and they say, "He tried it a fifth time, and it still didn't work!</s>
 <s id="216">What a moron!"</s>
 <s id="217">Early on, contractors come by and say, "Dan, you're a cute little bunny, but you know, this just isn't going to work.</s>
 <p id="p218">
  <s id="218.1">What don't you do this?</s>
  <s id="218.2">Why don't you do that?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="219">And your instinct is to say, "Well, why don't you suck an egg?"</s>
 <s id="220">(Laughter) But you don't say that, because they're the guys you're targeting.</s>
 <s id="221">And so what we've done -- and this isn't just in housing; it's in clothing and food and our transportation needs, our energy -- we sprawl just a little bit.</s>
 <s id="222">And when I get a little bit of press, I hear from people all over the world.</s>
 <s id="223">And we may have invented excess, but the problem of waste is worldwide.</s>
 <s id="224">We're in trouble.</s>
 <s id="225">And I don't wear ammo belts crisscrossing my chest and a red bandana.</s>
 <s id="226">But we're clearly in trouble.</s>
 <s id="227">And what we need to do is reconnect with those really primal parts of ourselves and make some decisions and say, "You know, I think I would like to put CDs across the wall there.</s>
 <s id="228">What do you think, honey?"</s>
 <s id="229">If it doesn't work, take it down.</s>
 <s id="230">What we need to do is reconnect with who we really are, and that's thrilling indeed.</s>
 <s id="231">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="232">(Applause)</s>
</text>
