<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I had about five minutes before I was set to deliver a talk to a bunch of business owners about visibility and being on camera.</s>
 <s id="2">After all, I was the so-called expert there, the former 20-year television news anchor and life and business coach.</s>
 <s id="3">I happened to take a look down at my cell phone just to catch the time, and I noticed that I had a missed call from my ex-husband.</s>
 <s id="4">I can still hear his voice.</s>
 <s id="5">"Darieth, what is going on?</s>
 <s id="6">I just got a call from some strange man who told me to go to this website, and now I'm looking at all of these photos of you naked.</s>
 <s id="7">Your private parts are all over this website.</s>
 <s id="8">Who's seen this?"</s>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">I couldn't think.</s>
  <s id="9.2">I couldn't breathe.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="10">I was so humiliated and so embarrassed and so ashamed.</s>
 <s id="11">I felt like my world was coming to an end.</s>
 <s id="12">And yet, this began for me months of pain and depression and anger and confusion and silence.</s>
 <s id="13">My manipulative, jealous, stalker ex-boyfriend did exactly what he said he would do: he put up a website with my name on it, and he posted this.</s>
 <s id="14">And this.</s>
 <s id="15">And several explicit photos that he had taken of me while I was asleep, living with him in Jamaica.</s>
 <s id="16">For months prior to that, he had been sending me threatening text messages like this.</s>
 <s id="17">He was trying to make me out to be some sleazy, low-life slut.</s>
 <s id="18">He had even threatened to kill me.</s>
 <s id="19">He told me that he would shoot me in my head and stab me in my heart, simply because I wanted to end the controlling relationship.</s>
 <s id="20">I couldn't believe this was happening to me.</s>
 <s id="21">I didn't even know what to call it.</s>
 <s id="22">You might know it as cyberharassment or cyberbullying.</s>
 <s id="23">The media calls it "revenge porn."</s>
 <s id="24">I now call it "digital domestic violence."</s>
 <s id="25">It typically stems from a relationship gone bad, where a controlling, jilted ex-lover can't handle rejection, so when they can't physically put their hands on you, they use different weapons: cell phones and laptops.</s>
 <s id="26">The ammunition?</s>
 <s id="27">Photos, videos, explicit information, content -- all posted online, without your consent.</s>
 <s id="28">I mean, let's face it -- we all live our lives online.</s>
 <s id="29">And the internet is a really small world.</s>
 <s id="30">We show off our baby photos, we start and grow our businesses, we make new relationships, we let the world in, one Facebook like at a time.</s>
 <s id="31">And you know what I found?</s>
 <s id="32">An even smaller world.</s>
 <s id="33">One in 25 women say they have been impacted by revenge porn.</s>
 <s id="34">For women under the age of 30, that number looks like one in 10.</s>
 <s id="35">And that leaves a few of you in this audience as potential victims.</s>
 <s id="36">You want to know what's even more alarming?</s>
 <s id="37">Lack of legislation and laws to adequately protect victims and punish perpetrators.</s>
 <s id="38">There's only one federal bill pending; it's called the ENOUGH Act, by Senator Kamala Harris.</s>
 <s id="39">It would criminalize revenge porn.</s>
 <s id="40">But that could take years to pass.</s>
 <s id="41">So what are we left with in the meantime?</s>
 <s id="42">Flimsy civil misdemeanors.</s>
 <s id="43">Currently, only 40 states and DC have some laws in place for revenge porn.</s>
 <s id="44">And those penalties vary -- we're talking $500 fines.</s>
 <s id="45">Five hundred dollars?</s>
 <s id="46">Are you kidding me?</s>
 <s id="47">Women are losing their jobs.</s>
 <s id="48">They're suffering from damaged relationships and damaged reputations.</s>
 <s id="49">They're falling into illness and depression.</s>
 <s id="50">And the suicide rates are climbing.</s>
 <s id="51">You're looking at a woman who spent 11 months in court, thirteen trips to the courthouse and thousands of dollars in legal fees, just to get two things: a protection from cyberstalking and cyberabuse, otherwise known as a PFA, and language from a judge that would force a third-party internet company to remove the content.</s>
 <s id="52">It's expensive, complicated and confusing.</s>
 <s id="53">And worse, legal loopholes and jurisdictional issues drag this out for months, while my private parts were on display for months.</s>
 <s id="54">How would you feel if your naked body was exposed for the world to see, and you waited helplessly for the content to be removed?</s>
 <s id="55">Eventually, I stumbled upon a private company to issue a DMCA notice to shut the website down.</s>
 <s id="56">DMCA -- Digital Millennium Copyright Act.</s>
 <s id="57">It's a law that regulates digital material and content.</s>
 <s id="58">Broadly, the aim of the DMCA is to protect both copyright owners and consumers.</s>
 <s id="59">So get this: people who take and share nude photos own the rights to those selfies, so they should be able to issue a DMCA to have the content removed.</s>
 <s id="60">But not so fast -- because the other fight we're dealing with is noncompliant and nonresponsive third-party internet companies.</s>
 <s id="61">And oh -- by the way, even in consenting relationships, just because you get a nude photo or a naked pic, does not give you the right to share it, even [without] the intent to do harm.</s>
 <s id="62">Back to my case, which happens to be further complicated because he was stalking and harassing me from another country, making it nearly impossible to get help here.</s>
 <s id="63">But wait a minute -- isn't the internet international?</s>
 <s id="64">Shouldn't we have some sort of policy in place that broadly protects us, regardless to borders or restrictions?</s>
 <s id="65">I just couldn’t give up; I had to keep fighting.</s>
 <s id="66">So I willingly, on three occasions, allowed for the invasion of both my cell phone and my laptop by the Department of Homeland Security and the Jamaican Embassy for thorough forensic investigation, because I had maintained all of the evidence.</s>
 <s id="67">I painstakingly shared my private parts with the all-male investigative team.</s>
 <s id="68">And it was an embarrassing, humiliating additional hoop to jump through.</s>
 <s id="69">But then something happened.</s>
 <s id="70">Jamaican authorities actually arrested him.</s>
 <s id="71">He's now facing charges under their malicious communications act, and if found guilty, could face thousands of dollars in fines and up to 10 years in prison.</s>
 <s id="72">And I've also learned that my case is making history -- it is the first international case under this new crime.</s>
 <s id="73">Wow, finally some justice.</s>
 <s id="74">But this got me to thinking.</s>
 <s id="75">Nobody deserves this.</s>
 <s id="76">Nobody deserves this level of humiliation and having to jump through all of these hoops.</s>
 <s id="77">Our cyber civil rights are at stake.</s>
 <s id="78">Here in the United States, we need to have clear, tough enforcement; we need to demand the accountability and responsiveness from online companies; we need to promote social responsibilities for posting, sharing and texting; and we need to restore dignity to victims.</s>
 <s id="79">And what about victims who neither have the time, money or resources to wage war, who are left disempowered, mislabeled and broken?</s>
 <s id="80">Two things: release the shame and end the silence.</s>
 <s id="81">Shame is at the core of all of this.</s>
 <s id="82">And for every silent prisoner of shame, it's the fear of judgment that's holding you hostage.</s>
 <s id="83">And the price to pay is the stripping away of your self-worth.</s>
 <s id="84">The day I ended my silence, I freed myself from shame.</s>
 <s id="85">And I freed myself from the fear of judgment from the one person who I thought would judge me the most -- my son, who actually told me, "Mom, you are the strongest person that I know.</s>
 <s id="86">You can get through this.</s>
 <s id="87">And besides, mom -- he chose the wrong woman to mess with."</s>
 <s id="88">(Laughter) (Applause) It was on that day that I decided to use my platform and my story and my voice.</s>
 <s id="89">And to get started, I asked myself this one simple question: Who do I need to become now?</s>
 <s id="90">That question, in the face of everything that I was challenged with, transformed my life and had me thinking about all kinds of possibilities.</s>
 <s id="91">I now own my story, I speak my truth, and I'm narrating a new chapter in my life.</s>
 <s id="92">It's called "50 Shades of Silence."</s>
 <s id="93">It's a global social justice project, and we're working to film an upcoming documentary to give voice and dignity to victims.</s>
 <s id="94">If you are a victim or you know someone who is, know this: in order to be empowered, you have to take care of yourself, and you have to love yourself.</s>
 <s id="95">You have to turn your anger into action, your pain into power and your setback into a setup for what's next for your life.</s>
 <s id="96">This is a process, and it's a journey of self-discovery that might include forgiveness.</s>
 <s id="97">But it definitely requires bravery, confidence and conviction.</s>
 <s id="98">I call it: finding your everyday courage.</s>
 <s id="99">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="100">(Applause)</s>
</text>
