<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">These days scientists know how you inherit characteristics from your parents.</s>
 <s id="2">They're able to calculate probabilities of having a specific trait or getting a genetic disease according to the information from the parents and the family history.</s>
 <s id="3">But how is this possible?</s>
 <s id="4">To understand how traits pass from one living being to its descendants, we need to go back in time to the 19th century and a man named Gregor Mendel.</s>
 <s id="5">Mendel was an Austrian monk and biologist who loved to work with plants.</s>
 <s id="6">By breeding the pea plants he was growing in the monastery's garden, he discovered the principles that rule heredity.</s>
 <s id="7">In one of most classic examples, Mendel combined a purebred yellow-seeded plant with a purebred green-seeded plant, and he got only yellow seeds.</s>
 <s id="8">He called the yellow-colored trait the dominant one, because it was expressed in all the new seeds.</s>
 <s id="9">Then he let the new yellow-seeded hybrid plants self-fertilize.</s>
 <s id="10">And in this second generation, he got both yellow and green seeds, which meant the green trait had been hidden by the dominant yellow.</s>
 <s id="11">He called this hidden trait the recessive trait.</s>
 <s id="12">From those results, Mendel inferred that each trait depends on a pair of factors, one of them coming from the mother and the other from the father.</s>
 <s id="13">Now we know that these factors are called alleles and represent the different variations of a gene.</s>
 <s id="14">Depending on which type of allele Mendel found in each seed, we can have what we call a homozygous pea, where both alleles are identical, and what we call a heterozygous pea, when the two alleles are different.</s>
 <s id="15">This combination of alleles is known as genotype and its result, being yellow or green, is called phenotype.</s>
 <s id="16">To clearly visualize how alleles are distributed amongst descendants, we can a diagram called the Punnett square.</s>
 <s id="17">You place the different alleles on both axes and then figure out the possible combinations.</s>
 <s id="18">Let's look at Mendel's peas, for example.</s>
 <s id="19">Let's write the dominant yellow allele as an uppercase "Y" and the recessive green allele as a lowercase "y."</s>
 <s id="20">The uppercase Y always overpowers his lowercase friend, so the only time you get green babies is if you have lowercase Y's.</s>
 <s id="21">In Mendel's first generation, the yellow homozygous pea mom will give each pea kid a yellow-dominant allele, and the green homozygous pea dad will give a green-recessive allele.</s>
 <s id="22">So all the pea kids will be yellow heterozygous.</s>
 <s id="23">Then, in the second generation, where the two heterozygous kids marry, their babies could have any of the three possible genotypes, showing the two possible phenotypes in a three-to-one proportion.</s>
 <s id="24">But even peas have a lot of characteristics.</s>
 <s id="25">For example, besides being yellow or green, peas may be round or wrinkled.</s>
 <s id="26">So we could have all these possible combinations: round yellow peas, round green peas, wrinkled yellow peas, wrinkled green peas.</s>
 <s id="27">To calculate the proportions for each genotype and phenotype, we can use a Punnett square too.</s>
 <s id="28">Of course, this will make it a little more complex.</s>
 <s id="29">And lots of things are more complicated than peas, like, say, people.</s>
 <s id="30">These days, scientists know a lot more about genetics and heredity.</s>
 <s id="31">And there are many other ways in which some characteristics are inherited.</s>
 <s id="32">But, it all started with Mendel and his peas.</s>
</text>
