<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">When I was nine years old, my mom asked me what I would want my house to look like, and I drew this fairy mushroom.</s>
 <s id="2">And then she actually built it.</s>
 <s id="3">(Laughter) I don't think I realized this was so unusual at the time, and maybe I still haven't, because I'm still designing houses.</s>
 <s id="4">This is a six-story bespoke home on the island of Bali.</s>
 <s id="5">It's built almost entirely from bamboo.</s>
 <s id="6">The living room overlooks the valley from the fourth floor.</s>
 <s id="7">You enter the house by a bridge.</s>
 <s id="8">It can get hot in the tropics, so we make big curving roofs to catch the breezes.</s>
 <s id="9">But some rooms have tall windows to keep the air conditioning in and the bugs out.</s>
 <s id="10">This room we left open.</s>
 <s id="11">We made an air-conditioned, tented bed.</s>
 <s id="12">And one client wanted a TV room in the corner of her living room.</s>
 <s id="13">Boxing off an area with tall walls just didn't feel right, so instead, we made this giant woven pod.</s>
 <s id="14">Now, we do have all the necessary luxuries, like bathrooms.</s>
 <s id="15">This one is a basket in the corner of the living room, and I've got tell you, some people actually hesitate to use it.</s>
 <s id="16">We have not quite figured out our acoustic insulation.</s>
 <s id="17">(Laughter) So there are lots of things that we're still working on, but one thing I have learned is that bamboo will treat you well if you use it right.</s>
 <s id="18">It's actually a wild grass.</s>
 <s id="19">It grows on otherwise unproductive land -- deep ravines, mountainsides.</s>
 <s id="20">It lives off of rainwater, spring water, sunlight, and of the 1,450 species of bamboo that grow across the world, we use just seven of them.</s>
 <s id="21">That's my dad.</s>
 <s id="22">He's the one who got me building with bamboo, and he is standing in a clump of Dendrocalamus asper niger that he planted just seven years ago.</s>
 <s id="23">Each year, it sends up a new generation of shoots.</s>
 <s id="24">That shoot, we watched it grow a meter in three days just last week, so we're talking about sustainable timber in three years.</s>
 <s id="25">Now, we harvest from hundreds of family-owned clumps.</s>
 <s id="26">Betung, as we call it, it's really long, up to 18 meters of usable length.</s>
 <s id="27">Try getting that truck down the mountain.</s>
 <s id="28">And it's strong: it has the tensile strength of steel, the compressive strength of concrete.</s>
 <s id="29">Slam four tons straight down on a pole, and it can take it.</s>
 <s id="30">Because it's hollow, it's lightweight, light enough to be lifted by just a few men, or, apparently, one woman.</s>
 <s id="31">(Laughter) (Applause) And when my father built Green School in Bali, he chose bamboo for all of the buildings on campus, because he saw it as a promise.</s>
 <s id="32">It's a promise to the kids.</s>
 <s id="33">It's one sustainable material that they will not run out of.</s>
 <s id="34">And when I first saw these structures under construction about six years ago, I just thought, this makes perfect sense.</s>
 <s id="35">It is growing all around us.</s>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">It's strong.</s>
  <s id="36.2">It's elegant.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="37">It's earthquake-resistant.</s>
 <s id="38">Why hasn't this happened sooner, and what can we do with it next?</s>
 <s id="39">So along with some of the original builders of Green School, I founded Ibuku.</s>
 <s id="40">Ibu means "mother," and ku means "mine," so it represents my Mother Earth, and at Ibuku, we are a team of artisans, architects and designers, and what we're doing together is creating a new way of building.</s>
 <s id="41">Over the past five years together, we have built over 50 unique structures, most of them in Bali.</s>
 <s id="42">Nine of them are at Green Village -- you've just seen inside some of these homes -- and we fill them with bespoke furniture, we surround them with veggie gardens, we would love to invite you all to come visit someday.</s>
 <s id="43">And while you're there, you can also see Green School -- we keep building classrooms there each year -- as well as an updated fairy mushroom house.</s>
 <s id="44">We're also working on a little house for export.</s>
 <s id="45">This is a traditional Sumbanese home that we replicated, right down to the details and textiles.</s>
 <s id="46">A restaurant with an open-air kitchen.</s>
 <s id="47">It looks a lot like a kitchen, right?</s>
 <s id="48">And a bridge that spans 22 meters across a river.</s>
 <s id="49">Now, what we're doing, it's not entirely new.</s>
 <s id="50">From little huts to elaborate bridges like this one in Java, bamboo has been in use across the tropical regions of the world for literally tens of thousands of years.</s>
 <s id="51">There are islands and even continents that were first reached by bamboo rafts.</s>
 <s id="52">But until recently, it was almost impossible to reliably protect bamboo from insects, and so, just about everything that was ever built out of bamboo is gone.</s>
 <s id="53">Unprotected bamboo weathers.</s>
 <s id="54">Untreated bamboo gets eaten to dust.</s>
 <s id="55">And so that's why most people, especially in Asia, think that you couldn't be poor enough or rural enough to actually want to live in a bamboo house.</s>
 <s id="56">And so we thought, what will it take to change their minds, to convince people that bamboo is worth building with, much less worth aspiring to?</s>
 <s id="57">First, we needed safe treatment solutions.</s>
 <s id="58">Borax is a natural salt.</s>
 <s id="59">It turns bamboo into a viable building material.</s>
 <s id="60">Treat it properly, design it carefully, and a bamboo structure can last a lifetime.</s>
 <s id="61">Second, build something extraordinary out of it.</s>
 <s id="62">Inspire people.</s>
 <s id="63">Fortunately, Balinese culture fosters craftsmanship.</s>
 <s id="64">It values the artisan.</s>
 <s id="65">So combine those with the adventurous outliers from new generations of locally trained architects and designers and engineers, and always remember that you are designing for curving, tapering, hollow poles.</s>
 <s id="66">No two poles alike, no straight lines, no two-by-fours here.</s>
 <s id="67">The tried-and-true, well-crafted formulas and vocabulary of architecture do not apply here.</s>
 <s id="68">We have had to invent our own rules.</s>
 <s id="69">We ask the bamboo what it's good at, what it wants to become, and what it says is: respect it, design for its strengths, protect it from water, and to make the most of its curves.</s>
 <s id="70">So we design in real 3D, making scale structural models out of the same material that we'll later use to build the house.</s>
 <s id="71">And bamboo model-making, it's an art, as well as some hardcore engineering.</s>
 <s id="72">So that's the blueprint of the house.</s>
 <s id="73">(Laughter) And we bring it to site, and with tiny rulers, we measure each pole, and consider each curve, and we choose a piece of bamboo from the pile to replicate that house on site.</s>
 <s id="74">When it comes down to the details, we consider everything.</s>
 <s id="75">Why are doors so often rectangular?</s>
 <s id="76">Why not round?</s>
 <s id="77">How could you make a door better?</s>
 <s id="78">Well, its hinges battle with gravity, and gravity will always win in the end, so why not have it pivot on the center where it can stay balanced?</s>
 <s id="79">And while you're at it, why not doors shaped like teardrops?</s>
 <s id="80">To reap the selective benefits and work within the constraints of this material, we have really had to push ourselves, and within that constraint, we have found space for something new.</s>
 <s id="81">It's a challenge: how do you make a ceiling if you don't have any flat boards to work with?</s>
 <s id="82">Let me tell you, sometimes I dream of sheet rock and plywood.</s>
 <s id="83">(Laughter) But if what you've got is skilled craftsmen and itsy bitsy little splits, weave that ceiling together, stretch a canvas over it, lacquer it.</s>
 <s id="84">How do you design durable kitchen countertops that do justice to this curving structure you've just built?</s>
 <s id="85">Slice up a boulder like a loaf of bread, hand-carve each to fit the other, leave the crusts on, and what we're doing, it is almost entirely handmade.</s>
 <s id="86">The structural connections of our buildings are reinforced by steel joints, but we use a lot of hand-whittled bamboo pins.</s>
 <s id="87">There are thousands of pins in each floor.</s>
 <s id="88">This floor is made of glossy and durable bamboo skin.</s>
 <s id="89">You can feel the texture under bare feet.</s>
 <s id="90">And the floor that you walk on, can it affect the way that you walk?</s>
 <s id="91">Can it change the footprint that you'll ultimately leave on the world?</s>
 <s id="92">I remember being nine years old and feeling wonder, and possibility, and a little bit of idealism.</s>
 <s id="93">And we've got a really long way to go, there's a lot left to learn, but one thing I know is that with creativity and commitment, you can create beauty and comfort and safety and even luxury out of a material that will grow back.</s>
 <s id="94">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="95">(Applause)</s>
</text>
