<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">When I was raising investment for my startup, a venture capitalist said to me, "Ashwini, I think you're going to raise a few million dollars.</s>
 <s id="2">And your company -- it's going to sell for 50 to 70 million.</s>
 <s id="3">You're going to be really excited.</s>
 <s id="4">Your early investors are going to be really excited.</s>
 <s id="5">And I'm going to be really upset.</s>
 <s id="6">So I'm not going to invest in this deal."</s>
 <s id="7">I remember just being dumbstruck.</s>
 <s id="8">Who would be unhappy with putting four or five million dollars into a company and having it sell for 50 to 70 million?</s>
 <s id="9">I was a first-time founder.</s>
 <s id="10">I didn't have a wealthy network of individuals to turn to for investment, so I went to venture capitalists the most common form of investor in a technology company.</s>
 <s id="11">But I'd never taken the time to understand what was motivating that VC to invest.</s>
 <s id="12">I believe we're living in a golden era of entrepreneurship.</s>
 <s id="13">There is more opportunity to build companies than ever before.</s>
 <s id="14">But the financial systems designed to fund that innovation, venture capital, they haven't evolved in the past 20 to 30 years.</s>
 <s id="15">Venture capital was designed to pour large sums of money into a small number of companies that can sell for over a billion dollars.</s>
 <s id="16">It was not designed to sprinkle capital across many companies that have the potential to succeed but for less, like my own.</s>
 <s id="17">That limits the number of ideas that get funded, the number of companies that are created and who can actually receive that funding to grow.</s>
 <s id="18">And I think it inspires a tough question: What's our goal with entrepreneurship?</s>
 <s id="19">If our goal is to create a tiny number of billion-dollar companies, let's stick with venture capital, it's working.</s>
 <s id="20">But if our goal is to inspire innovation and empower more people to build companies of all sizes, we need a new way to fund those ideas.</s>
 <s id="21">We need a more flexible system that doesn't squeeze entrepreneurs and investors into one rigid financial outcome.</s>
 <s id="22">We need to democratize access to capital.</s>
 <s id="23">In the summer of 2017, I went out to San Francisco, to join a tech accelerator with 30 other companies.</s>
 <s id="24">The accelerator was supposed to teach us how to raise venture capital.</s>
 <s id="25">But when I got out there, the startup community was buzzing about ICOs, or Initial Coin Offerings.</s>
 <s id="26">For the first time, ICOs had raised more money for young startups than venture capital had.</s>
 <s id="27">It was the first week of the program.</s>
 <s id="28">Tequila Friday.</s>
 <s id="29">And the founders couldn't stop talking.</s>
 <s id="30">"I'm going to raise an ICO."</s>
 <s id="31">"I'm going to raise an ICO."</s>
 <s id="32">Until one guy goes, "How cool if we did this all together?</s>
 <s id="33">We should do an ICO that combines the value of all of our companies and raise money as a group."</s>
 <s id="34">At that point, I had to ask the obvious question, "Guys, what's an ICO?"</s>
 <s id="35">ICOs were a way for young companies to raise money by issuing a digital currency tied to the value and services that the company provides.</s>
 <s id="36">The currency acts similar to shares in a company, like on the public stock market, increasing in value as it's traded online.</s>
 <s id="37">Most important, ICOs expanded the investor pool, from a few hundred venture capital firms to millions of everyday people, excited to invest.</s>
 <s id="38">This market represented more money.</s>
 <s id="39">It represented more investors.</s>
 <s id="40">Which meant a greater likelihood to get funded.</s>
 <s id="41">I was sold.</s>
 <s id="42">The idea, though, of doing it together still seemed a little crazy.</s>
 <s id="43">Startups compete with each other for investment, it takes hundreds of meetings to get a check.</s>
 <s id="44">That I would spend my precious 15 minutes in front of an investor talking not just about my own company, but all the companies in the batch, was unprecedented.</s>
 <s id="45">But the idea caught on.</s>
 <s id="46">And we decided to cooperate, rather than compete.</s>
 <s id="47">Every company put 10 percent of their equity into a communal pool that we then split into tradable cryptocurrency that investors could buy and sell.</s>
 <s id="48">Six months and four law firms later -- (Laughter) in January 2018, we launched the very first ICO that represented the value of nearly 30 companies and an entirely new way to raise capital.</s>
 <s id="49">We got a lot of press.</s>
 <s id="50">My favorite headline about us read, "VCs, read this and weep."</s>
 <s id="51">(Laughter) Our fund was naturally more diverse.</s>
 <s id="52">Twenty percent of the founders were women.</s>
 <s id="53">Fifty percent were international.</s>
 <s id="54">The investors were more excited, too.</s>
 <s id="55">They had a chance to get better returns, because we took out the middleman fees of venture capital.</s>
 <s id="56">And they could take their money and reinvest it, potentially funding more new ideas faster.</s>
 <s id="57">I believe this creates a virtuous cycle of capital that allows many more entrepreneurs to succeed.</s>
 <s id="58">Because access to capital is access to opportunity.</s>
 <s id="59">And we have only just begun to imagine what democratizing access to capital will do.</s>
 <s id="60">I would have never thought that my own search for funding would lead me to this stage, having helped nearly 30 companies get investment.</s>
 <s id="61">Imagine if other entrepreneurs tried to invent new ways to access capital rather than following the traditional route.</s>
 <s id="62">It would change what gets built, who builds it and the long-term impact on the economy.</s>
 <s id="63">And I believe that's way more exciting than just trying to invest in the next billion-dollar startup.</s>
 <s id="64">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="65">(Applause)</s>
</text>
