<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">It was an incredible surprise to me to find out that there was actually an organization that cared about both parts of my life.</s>
 <s id="2">Because, basically, I work as a theoretical physicist.</s>
 <s id="3">I develop and test models of the Big Bang, using observational data.</s>
 <s id="4">And I've been moonlighting for the last five years helping with a project in Africa.</s>
 <s id="5">And, I get a lot of flak for this at Cambridge.</s>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">People wonder, you know, "How do you have time to do this?"</s>
  <s id="6.2">And so on.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="7">And so it was simply astonishing to me to find an organization that actually appreciated both those sides.</s>
 <s id="8">So I thought I'd start off by just telling you a little bit about myself and why I lead this schizophrenic life.</s>
 <s id="9">Well, I was born in South Africa and my parents were imprisoned for resisting the racist regime.</s>
 <s id="10">When they were released, we left and we went as refugees to Kenya and Tanzania.</s>
 <s id="11">Both were very young countries then, and full of hope for the future.</s>
 <p id="p12">
  <s id="12.1">We had an amazing childhood.</s>
  <s id="12.2">We didn't have any money, but we were outdoors most of the time.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="13">We had fantastic friends and we saw the wonders of the world, like Kilimanjaro, Serengeti and the Olduvai Gorge.</s>
 <s id="14">Well, then we moved to London for high school.</s>
 <s id="15">And after that -- there's nothing much to say about that.</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">It was rather dull.</s>
  <s id="16.2">But I came back to Africa at the age of 17, as a volunteer teacher to Lesotho, which is a tiny country, surrounded at that time by apartheid South Africa.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="17">Well, 80 percent of the men in Lesotho worked in the mines over the border, in brutal conditions.</s>
 <s id="18">Nevertheless, I -- as I'm sure -- as a rather irritating young, white man coming into their village, I was welcomed with incredible hospitality and warmth.</s>
 <s id="19">But the kids were the best part.</s>
 <s id="20">The kids were amazing: extremely eager and often very bright.</s>
 <s id="21">And I'm just going to tell you one story, which got through to me.</s>
 <s id="22">I used to try to take the kids outside as often as possible, to try to connect the academic stuff with the real world.</s>
 <s id="23">And they weren't used to that.</s>
 <s id="24">But I took them outside one day and I said, "I want you to estimate the height of the building."</s>
 <s id="25">And I expected them to put a ruler next to the wall, size it up with a finger, and make an estimate of the height.</s>
 <s id="26">But there was one little boy, very small for his age.</s>
 <s id="27">He was the son of one of the poorest families in the village.</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">And he wasn't doing that.</s>
  <s id="28.2">He was scribbling with chalk on the pavement.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">And so, I said -- I was annoyed -- I said, "What are you doing?</s>
 <s id="30">I want you to estimate the height of the building."</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">He said, "OK.</s>
  <s id="31.2">I measured the height of a brick.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">I counted the number of bricks and now I'm multiplying."</s>
 <s id="33">Well -- (Laughter) -- I hadn't thought of that one.</s>
 <s id="34">And many experiences like this happened to me.</s>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">Another one is that I met a miner.</s>
  <s id="35.2">He was home on his three-month leave from the mines.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="36">Sitting next to him one day, he said, "There's only one thing that I really loved at school.</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">And you know what it was?</s>
  <s id="37.2">Shakespeare."</s>
  <s id="37.3">And he recited some to me.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="38">And these and many similar experiences convinced me that there are just tons of bright kids in Africa -- inventive kids, intellectual kids -- and starved of opportunity.</s>
 <s id="39">And if Africa is going to get fixed, it's by them, not by us.</s>
 <s id="40">Well, after -- (Applause) -- that's the truth.</s>
 <s id="41">Well, after Lesotho, I traveled across Africa before returning to England -- so gray and depressing, in comparison.</s>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">And I went to Cambridge.</s>
  <s id="42.2">And there, I fell for theoretical physics.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="43">Well, I'm not going to explain this equation, but theoretical physics is really an amazing subject.</s>
 <s id="44">We can write down all the laws of physics we know in one line.</s>
 <s id="45">And, admittedly, it's in a very shorthand notation.</s>
 <s id="46">And it contains 18 free parameters, OK, which we have to fit to the data.</s>
 <s id="47">So it's not the final story, but it's an incredibly powerful summary of everything we know about nature at the most basic level.</s>
 <s id="48">And apart from a few very important loose ends, which you've heard about here -- like dark energy and dark matter -- this equation describes, seems to describe everything about the universe and what's in it.</s>
 <s id="49">But there's one big puzzle remaining, and this was most succinctly put to me by my primary school math teacher in Tanzania, who's a wonderful Scottish lady who I still stay in touch with.</s>
 <s id="50">And she's now in her 80s.</s>
 <s id="51">And when I try to explain my work to her, she waved away all the details, and she said, "Neil, there's only one question that really matters.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">What banged?"</s>
  <s id="52.2">(Laughter) "Everyone talks about the Big Bang.</s>
  <s id="52.3">What banged?"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p53">
  <s id="53.1">And she's right.</s>
  <s id="53.2">It's a question we've all been avoiding.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="54">The standard explanation is that the universe somehow sprang into existence, full of a strange kind of energy -- inflationary energy -- which blew it up.</s>
 <s id="55">But the puzzle of why the universe emerged in that peculiar state is completely unsolved.</s>
 <s id="56">Now, I worked on that theory for a while, with Stephen Hawking and others.</s>
 <s id="57">But then I began to explore another alternative.</s>
 <s id="58">The alternative is that the Big Bang wasn't the beginning.</s>
 <s id="59">Perhaps the universe existed before the bang, and the bang was just a violent event in a pre-existing universe.</s>
 <s id="60">Well, this possibility is actually suggested by the latest theories, the unified theories, which try to explain all those 18 free parameters in a single framework, which will hopefully predict all of them.</s>
 <s id="61">And I'll just share a cartoon of this idea here.</s>
 <p id="p62">
  <s id="62.1">It's all I can convey.</s>
  <s id="62.2">According to these theories, there are extra dimensions of space, not just the three we're familiar with, but at every point in the room there are more dimensions.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="63">And in particular, there's one rather strange one, in the most elegant unified theories we have.</s>
 <s id="64">The strange one looks likes this: that we live in a three-dimensional world.</s>
 <s id="65">We live in one of these worlds, and I can only show it as a sheet, but it's really three-dimensional.</s>
 <s id="66">And a tiny distance away, there's another sheet, also three-dimensional, and they're separated by a gap.</s>
 <s id="67">The gap is very tiny, and I've blown it up so you can see it.</s>
 <s id="68">But it's really a tiny fraction of the size of an atomic nucleus.</s>
 <s id="69">I won't go into the details of why we think the universe is like this, but it comes out of the math and trying to explain the physics that we know.</s>
 <s id="70">Well, I got interested in this because it seemed to me that it was an obvious question.</s>
 <s id="71">Which is, what happens if these two, three-dimensional worlds should actually collide?</s>
 <s id="72">And if they collide, it would look a lot like the Big Bang.</s>
 <s id="73">But it's slightly different than in the conventional picture.</s>
 <s id="74">The conventional picture of the Big Bang is a point.</s>
 <p id="p75">
  <s id="75.1">Everything comes out of a point; you have infinite density.</s>
  <s id="75.2">And all the equations break down.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="76">No hope of describing that.</s>
 <p id="p77">
  <s id="77.1">In this picture, you'll notice, the bang is extended.</s>
  <s id="77.2">It's not a point.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="78">The density of matter is finite, and we have a chance of a consistent set of equations that can describe the whole process.</s>
 <s id="79">So, to cut a long story short, we've explored this alternative.</s>
 <s id="80">We've shown that it can fit all of the data that we have about the formation of galaxies, the fluctuations in the microwave background.</s>
 <s id="81">Furthermore, there's an experimental way to tell this theory, apart from the inflationary explanation that I told you before.</s>
 <s id="82">It involves gravitational waves.</s>
 <s id="83">And in this scenario, not only was the Big Bang not the beginning, as you can see from the picture, it can happen over and over again.</s>
 <s id="84">It may be that we live in an endless universe, both in space and in time.</s>
 <s id="85">And there've been bangs in the past, and there will be bangs in the future.</s>
 <s id="86">And maybe we live in an endless universe.</s>
 <s id="87">Well, making and testing models of the universe is, for me, the best way I have of enjoying and appreciating the universe.</s>
 <s id="88">We need to make the best mathematical models we can, the most consistent ones.</s>
 <s id="89">And then we scrutinize them, logically and with data.</s>
 <s id="90">And we try to convince ourselves -- we really try to convince ourselves they're wrong.</s>
 <s id="91">That's progress: when we prove things wrong.</s>
 <s id="92">And gradually, we hopefully move closer and closer to understanding the world.</s>
 <s id="93">As I pursued my career, something was always gnawing away inside me.</s>
 <s id="94">What about Africa?</s>
 <s id="95">What about those kids I'd left behind?</s>
 <s id="96">Instead of developing, as we'd all hoped in the '60s, things had gotten worse.</s>
 <s id="97">Africa was gripped by poverty, disease and war.</s>
 <s id="98">This is very graphically shown by the Worldmapper website and project.</s>
 <s id="99">And so the idea is to represent each country on a map, but scale the area according to some quantity.</s>
 <s id="100">So here's just the standard area map of the world.</s>
 <s id="101">By the way, Africa is very large.</s>
 <s id="102">And the next map now shows Africa's GDP in 1960, around the time of independence for many African states.</s>
 <p id="p103">
  <s id="103.1">Now, this is 1990, and then 2002.</s>
  <s id="103.2">And here's a projection for 2015.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="104">Big changes are happening in the world, but they're not helping Africa.</s>
 <p id="p105">
  <s id="105.1">What about Africa's population?</s>
  <s id="105.2">The population isn't out of proportion to its area, but Africa leads the world in deaths from often preventable causes: malnutrition, simple infections and birth complications.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p106">
  <s id="106.1">Then there's HIV/AIDS.</s>
  <s id="106.2">And then there are deaths from war.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="107">OK, currently there are 45,000 people a month dying in the Congo, as a consequence of the war there over coltan and diamonds and other things.</s>
 <s id="108">It's still going on.</s>
 <s id="109">What about Africa's capacity to do something about these problems?</s>
 <s id="110">Well, here's the number of physicians in Africa.</s>
 <s id="111">Here's the number of people in higher education.</s>
 <s id="112">And here -- most shocking to me -- the number of scientific research papers coming out of Africa.</s>
 <s id="113">It just doesn't exist scientifically.</s>
 <s id="114">And this was very eloquently argued at TED Africa: that all of the aid that's been given has completely failed to put Africa onto its own two feet.</s>
 <s id="115">Well, the transition to democracy in South Africa in 1994 was literally a dream come true for many of us.</s>
 <p id="p116">
  <s id="116.1">My parents were both elected to the first parliament, alongside Nelson and Winnie Mandela.</s>
  <s id="116.2">They were the only other couple.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="117">And in 2001, I took a research leave to visit them.</s>
 <s id="118">And while I was busy working -- I was working on these colliding worlds, in the day.</s>
 <s id="119">But I learned that there was a desperate shortage of skills, especially mathematical skills, in industry, in government, in education.</s>
 <s id="120">The ability to make and test models has become essential, not only to every single area of science today, but also to modern society itself.</s>
 <s id="121">And if you don't have math, you're not going to enter the modern age.</s>
 <p id="p122">
  <s id="122.1">So I had an idea.</s>
  <s id="122.2">And the idea was very simple.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="123">The idea was to set up an African Institute for Mathematical Sciences, or AIMS.</s>
 <s id="124">And let's recruit students from the whole of Africa, bring them together with lecturers from all over the world, and we'll try to give them a fantastic education.</s>
 <s id="125">Well, as a Cambridge professor, I had many contacts.</s>
 <s id="126">And to my astonishment, they backed me 100 percent.</s>
 <s id="127">They said, "Go and do it, and we'll come and lecture."</s>
 <s id="128">And I knew it would be amazing fun to bring brilliant students from these countries -- where they don't have any opportunities -- together with the best lecturers in the world -- who I knew would come, because of the interest in Africa -- and put them together and just let the sparks fly.</s>
 <s id="129">So we bought a derelict hotel near Cape Town.</s>
 <s id="130">It's an 80-room Art Deco hotel from the 1920s.</s>
 <s id="131">The area was kind of seedy, so we got an 80-room hotel for 100,000 dollars.</s>
 <p id="p132">
  <s id="132.1">It's a beautiful building.</s>
  <s id="132.2">We decided we would refurbish it and then put out the word: we're going to start the best math institute in Africa in this hotel.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="133">Well, the new South Africa is a very exciting country.</s>
 <s id="134">And those of you who haven't been there, you should go.</s>
 <s id="135">It's very, very interesting what's happening.</s>
 <s id="136">And we recruited wonderful staff, highly motivated staff.</s>
 <s id="137">The other thing that's happened, which was good for us, is the Internet.</s>
 <s id="138">Even though the Internet is very expensive all over Africa, there are Internet cafes everywhere.</s>
 <s id="139">And bright young Africans are desperate to join the global community, to be successful -- and they're very ambitious.</s>
 <s id="140">They want to be the next Einstein.</s>
 <s id="141">And so when word came out that AIMS was opening, it spread very quickly via e-mail and our website.</s>
 <s id="142">And we got lots of applicants.</s>
 <s id="143">Well, we designed AIMS as a 24-hour learning environment, and it was fantastic to start a university from the beginning.</s>
 <s id="144">You have to rethink, what is the university for?</s>
 <s id="145">And that's really exciting.</s>
 <s id="146">So we designed it to have interactive teaching.</s>
 <s id="147">No droning on at the chalkboard.</s>
 <s id="148">We emphasize problem-solving, working in groups, every student discovering and maximizing their own potential and not chasing grades.</s>
 <s id="149">Everyone lives together in this hotel -- lecturers and students -- and it's not surprising at all to find an impromptu tutorial at 1 a.m.</s>
 <s id="150">The students don't usually leave the computer lab till 2 or 3 a.m.</s>
 <s id="151">And then they're up again at eight in the morning.</s>
 <p id="p152">
  <s id="152.1">Lectures, problem-solving and so on.</s>
  <s id="152.2">It's an extraordinary place.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="153">We especially emphasize areas of great relevance to Africa's development, because, in those areas, scientists working in Africa will have a competitive advantage.</s>
 <s id="154">They'll publish, be invited to conferences.</s>
 <p id="p155">
  <s id="155.1">They'll do well.</s>
  <s id="155.2">They'll have successful careers.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="156">And AIMS has done extremely well.</s>
 <s id="157">Here is a list of last year's graduates, graduated in June, and what they're currently doing -- 48 of them.</s>
 <s id="158">And where they are is indicated over here.</s>
 <p id="p159">
  <s id="159.1">And where they've gone.</s>
  <s id="159.2">So these are all postgraduate students.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="160">And they've all gone on to master's and Ph.D. degrees in excellent places.</s>
 <s id="161">Five students can be educated at AIMS for the cost of educating one in the U.S. or Europe.</s>
 <s id="162">But more important, the pan-African student body is a continual source of strength, pride and commitment to Africa.</s>
 <s id="163">We illustrate AIMS' progress by coloring in the countries of Africa.</s>
 <s id="164">So here you can see behind this list.</s>
 <s id="165">When a county is colored yellow, we've received an application; orange, we've accepted an application; and green, a student has graduated.</s>
 <s id="166">So here is where we were after the first graduation in 2004.</s>
 <s id="167">And we set ourselves a goal of turning the continent green.</s>
 <s id="168">So there's 2005, -6, -7, -8.</s>
 <s id="169">(Applause) We're well on the way to achieving our initial goal.</s>
 <s id="170">We had some of the students filmed at home before they came to AIMS.</s>
 <s id="171">And I'll just show you one.</s>
 <s id="172">Tendai Mugwagwa: My name is Tendai Mugwagwa.</s>
 <s id="173">I have a Bachelor of Science with an education degree.</s>
 <s id="174">I will be attending AIMS.</s>
 <s id="175">My understanding of the course is that it covers quite a lot.</s>
 <s id="176">You know, from physics to medicine, in particular, epidemiology and also mathematical modeling.</s>
 <s id="177">Neil Turok: So Tendai came to AIMS and did very well.</s>
 <s id="178">And I'll let her take it from there.</s>
 <s id="179">TM: My name is Tendai Mugwagwa and I was a student at AIMS in 2003 and 2004.</s>
 <s id="180">After leaving AIMS, I went on to do a master's in applied mathematics at the University of Cape Town in South Africa.</s>
 <s id="181">After that, I came to the Netherlands where I'm now doing a Ph.D. in theoretical immunology.</s>
 <s id="182">Professor: Tendai is working very independently.</s>
 <s id="183">She communicates well with the immunologists at the hospital.</s>
 <s id="184">So all in all I have a very good Ph.D. student from South Africa.</s>
 <s id="185">So I'm happy she's here.</s>
 <s id="186">NT: Another student in the first year of AIMS was Shehu.</s>
 <s id="187">And he's shown here with his favorite high school teacher.</s>
 <s id="188">And then entering university in northern Nigeria.</s>
 <s id="189">And after AIMS, Shehu wanted to do high-energy physics, and he came to Cambridge.</s>
 <s id="190">He's about to finish his Ph.D., and he was filmed recently with someone you all know.</s>
 <s id="191">Shehu: And from there we will be able to, hopefully, make better predictions and then we compare it to the graph and also make some predictions.</s>
 <s id="192">Stephen Hawking: That is nice.</s>
 <p id="p193">
  <s id="193.1">NT: Here are the current students at AIMS.</s>
  <s id="193.2">There are 53 of them from 20 different countries, including 20 women.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="194">So now I'm going to get to my TED business.</s>
 <p id="p195">
  <s id="195.1">Well, we had a party.</s>
  <s id="195.2">This is Africa -- we have good parties in Africa.</s>
  <s id="195.3">And last month, they threw a surprise party for me.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="196">Here's somebody you've seen already.</s>
 <s id="197">(Applause) I want to point out a few other exceptional people in this picture.</s>
 <s id="198">So, we were having a party, as you can see they're completely eclipsing me at this point.</s>
 <p id="p199">
  <s id="199.1">This is Ezra.</s>
  <s id="199.2">She's from Darfur.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="200">She's a physicist, and somehow stays smiling, in spite of everything going on back home.</s>
 <s id="201">But she wants to continue in physics, and she's doing extremely well.</s>
 <p id="p202">
  <s id="202.1">This is Lydia.</s>
  <s id="202.2">Lydia is the first ever woman to graduate in mathematics in the Central African Republic.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p203">
  <s id="203.1">And she's now at AIMS.</s>
  <s id="203.2">(Applause) So now let me get to our TED wish.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="204">Well, it's not my TED wish; it's our wish, as you've already gathered.</s>
 <p id="p205">
  <s id="205.1">And our wish has two parts: one is a dream and the other's a plan.</s>
  <s id="205.2">OK.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p206">
  <s id="206.1">Our TED dream is that the next Einstein will be African.</s>
  <s id="206.2">(Applause) In striving for the heights of creative genius, we want to give thousands of people the motivation, the encouragement and the courage to obtain the high-level skills they need to help Africa.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="207">Among them will be not only brilliant scientists -- I'm sure of that from what we've seen at AIMS -- they'll also be the African Gates, Brins and Pages of the future.</s>
 <p id="p208">
  <s id="208.1">Well, I said we also have a plan.</s>
  <s id="208.2">And our plan is quite simple.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="209">AIMS is now a proven model.</s>
 <s id="210">And what we need to do is to replicate it.</s>
 <s id="211">We want to roll out 15 AIMS centers in the next five years, all over Africa.</s>
 <s id="212">Each will have a pan-African student body, but specialize in a different area of science.</s>
 <s id="213">We want to use science to overcome the national and cultural barriers, as it does at AIMS.</s>
 <s id="214">And we want to add elements to the curriculum.</s>
 <s id="215">We want to add entrepreneurship and policy skills.</s>
 <s id="216">The expanded AIMS will be a coherent pan-African institution, and its graduates will form a powerful network, working together for peace and progress across the continent.</s>
 <s id="217">Over the last year, we've been visiting sites in Africa, looking at potential sites for new AIMS centers.</s>
 <s id="218">And here are the ones we've selected.</s>
 <s id="219">And each of these centers has a strong local team, each is in a beautiful place, an interesting place, which international lecturers will be happy to visit.</s>
 <s id="220">And our partners across Africa are extremely enthusiastic about this.</s>
 <s id="221">Everyone wants an AIMS center in their country.</s>
 <s id="222">And last November, the conference of all the African ministers of science and technology, held in Mombasa, called for a comprehensive plan to roll out AIMS.</s>
 <s id="223">So we have political support right across the continent.</s>
 <s id="224">It won't be easy.</s>
 <s id="225">At every site there will be huge challenges.</s>
 <s id="226">Local scientists must play leading roles and governments must be persuaded to buy in.</s>
 <s id="227">Conditions are very difficult, but we cannot afford to compromise on those principles which made AIMS work.</s>
 <p id="p228">
  <s id="228.1">And we summarize them this way: the institutes have got to be relevant, innovative, cost-effective and high quality.</s>
  <s id="228.2">Why?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="229">Because we want Africa to be rich.</s>
 <s id="230">Easy to remember the basic rules we need.</s>
 <s id="231">So, just in ending, let me say the only people who can fix Africa are talented young Africans.</s>
 <s id="232">By unlocking and nurturing their creative potential, we can create a step change in Africa's future.</s>
 <s id="233">Over time, they will contribute to African development and to science in ways we can only imagine.</s>
 <s id="234">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="235">(Applause)</s>
</text>
