<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Music) This is the human test, a test to see if you are a human.</s>
 <s id="2">Please raise your hand if something applies to you.</s>
 <p id="p3">
  <s id="3.1">Are we agreed?</s>
  <s id="3.2">Yes?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="4">Then let's begin.</s>
 <s id="5">Have you ever eaten a booger long past your childhood?</s>
 <s id="6">(Laughter) It's okay, it's safe here.</s>
 <s id="7">Have you ever made a small, weird sound when you remembered something embarrassing?</s>
 <s id="8">Have you ever purposely lowercased the first letter of a text in order to come across as sad or disappointed?</s>
 <s id="9">(Laughter) Okay.</s>
 <p id="p10">
  <s id="10.1">Have you ever ended a text with a period as a sign of aggression?</s>
  <s id="10.2">Okay.</s>
  <s id="10.3">Period.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="11">Have you ever laughed or smiled when someone said something shitty to you and then spent the rest of the day wondering why you reacted that way?</s>
 <s id="12">Yes.</s>
 <s id="13">Have you ever seemed to lose your airplane ticket a thousand times as you walked from the check-in to the gate?</s>
 <s id="14">Yes.</s>
 <s id="15">Have you ever put on a pair of pants and then much later realized that there was a loose sock smushed up against your thigh?</s>
 <s id="16">(Laughter) Good.</s>
 <s id="17">Have you ever tried to guess someone else's password so many times that it locked their account?</s>
 <s id="18">Mmm.</s>
 <s id="19">Have you ever had a nagging feeling that one day you will be discovered as a fraud?</s>
 <s id="20">Yes, it's safe here.</s>
 <s id="21">Have you ever hoped that there was some ability you hadn't discovered yet that you were just naturally great at?</s>
 <s id="22">Mmm.</s>
 <s id="23">Have you ever broken something in real life, and then found yourself looking for an "undo" button in real life?</s>
 <s id="24">Have you ever misplaced your TED badge and then immediately started imagining what a three-day Vancouver vacation might look like?</s>
 <s id="25">Have you ever marveled at how someone you thought was so ordinary could suddenly become so beautiful?</s>
 <s id="26">Have you ever stared at your phone smiling like an idiot while texting with someone?</s>
 <s id="27">Have you ever subsequently texted that person the phrase "I'm staring at the phone smiling like an idiot"?</s>
 <s id="28">Have you ever been tempted to, and then gave in to the temptation, of looking through someone else's phone?</s>
 <s id="29">Have you ever had a conversation with yourself and then suddenly realized you're a real asshole to yourself?</s>
 <s id="30">(Laughter) Has your phone ever run out of battery in the middle of an argument, and it sort of felt like the phone was breaking up with both of you?</s>
 <s id="31">Have you ever thought that working on an issue between you was futile because it should just be easier than this, or this is supposed to happen just naturally?</s>
 <s id="32">Have you ever realized that very little, in the long run, just happens naturally?</s>
 <s id="33">Have you ever woken up blissfully and suddenly been flooded by the awful remembrance that someone had left you?</s>
 <s id="34">Have you ever lost the ability to imagine a future without a person that no longer was in your life?</s>
 <s id="35">Have you ever looked back on that event with the sad smile of autumn and the realization that futures will happen regardless?</s>
 <s id="36">Congratulations.</s>
 <s id="37">You have now completed the test.</s>
 <s id="38">You are all human.</s>
 <s id="39">(Applause)</s>
</text>
