<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I was one of the founding members of the Axis of Evil Comedy Tour.</s>
 <s id="2">The other founding members included Ahmed Ahmed, who is an Egyptian-American, who actually had the idea to go to the Middle East and try it out before we went out as a tour.</s>
 <s id="3">He went out solo and did it first.</s>
 <s id="4">Then there was Aron Kader, who was the Palestinian-American.</s>
 <s id="5">And then there was me, the Iranian-American of the group.</s>
 <s id="6">Now, being Iranian-American presents its own set of problems, as you know.</s>
 <s id="7">Those two countries aren't getting along these days.</s>
 <s id="8">So it causes a lot of inner conflict, you know, like part of me likes me, part of me hates me.</s>
 <s id="9">(Laughter) Part of me thinks I should have a nuclear program, the other part thinks I can't be trusted with one.</s>
 <s id="10">These are dilemmas I have every day.</s>
 <s id="11">But I was born in Iran; I'm now an American citizen, which means I have the American passport, which means I can travel.</s>
 <s id="12">Because if you only have the Iranian passport, you're kind of limited to the countries you can go to with open arms, you know -- Syria, Venezuela, North Korea.</s>
 <s id="13">(Laughter) So, anyone who's gotten their passport in America will tell you, when you get it, it still says what country you were born in.</s>
 <s id="14">So I remember getting my American passport.</s>
 <p id="p15">
  <s id="15.1">I was like, "Woo-hoo!</s>
  <s id="15.2">I'm going to travel."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">And I opened it up, it said, "Born in Iran."</s>
  <s id="16.2">I'm like, "Oh, come on, man!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="17">(Laughter) "I'm trying to go places."</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) But what's interesting is, I've never had trouble in any Western countries with my American passport, even though it says, "Born in Iran" -- no problems.</s>
 <s id="19">Where I've had problems is in some of the Arab countries.</s>
 <s id="20">I guess some of the Arab countries aren't getting along with Iran either.</s>
 <s id="21">So I was in Kuwait recently, doing a comedy show with some other American comedians.</s>
 <s id="22">They all went through.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">Then the border patrol saw my American passport: "Ah-ha!</s>
  <s id="23.2">American, great."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">Then he opened it up.</s>
  <s id="24.2">"Born in Iran?</s>
  <s id="24.3">Wait."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="25">(Laughter) And he started asking me questions.</s>
 <s id="26">He said, "What is your father's name?"</s>
 <s id="27">I said, "Well, he's passed away, but his name was Khosro."</s>
 <s id="28">He goes, "What is your grandfather's name?"</s>
 <s id="29">I said, "He passed away a long time ago.</s>
 <s id="30">His name was Jabbar."</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">He says, "You wait.</s>
  <s id="31.2">I'll be back," and he walked away.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">And I started freaking out, because I don't know what kind of crap my grandfather was into.</s>
 <s id="33">(Laughter) Thought the guy was going to come back and be like, "We've been looking for you for 200 years."</s>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">(Laughter) "Your grandfather has a parking violation.</s>
  <s id="34.2">It's way overdue.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="35">You owe us two billion dollars."</s>
 <s id="36">(Laughter) But as you can see, when I talk, I speak with an American accent, which you would think, as an Iranian-American actor, I should be able to play any part, good, bad, what have you.</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">But a lot of times in Hollywood, when casting directors find out you're of Middle Eastern descent, they go, "Oh, you're Iranian.</s>
  <s id="37.2">Great!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p38">
  <s id="38.1">Can you say 'I will kill you in the name of Allah?'"</s>
  <s id="38.2">I go, "I could say that, but what if I were to say, 'Hello.</s>
  <s id="38.3">I'm your doctor'?"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">They go, "Great!</s>
  <s id="39.2">And then you hijack the hospital."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">(Laughter) Like, I think you're missing the point here.</s>
 <s id="41">Don't get me wrong, I don't mind playing bad guys.</s>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">I want to play a bad guy.</s>
  <s id="42.2">I want to rob a bank.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="43">I want to rob a bank in a film, but do it with a gun, not with a bomb strapped around me, right?</s>
 <s id="44">(Laughter) Because I imagine the director: "Maz, I think your character would rob the bank with a bomb around him."</s>
 <s id="45">"Why would I do that?</s>
 <s id="46">If I want the money, why would I kill myself?"</s>
 <s id="47">(Laughter) Right?</s>
 <s id="48">(Applause) "Gimme all your money, or I'll blow myself up!"</s>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) "Well, then blow yourself up.</s>
 <s id="50">(Laughter) Just do it outside, please."</s>
 <s id="51">(Laughter) But the fact is, there's good people everywhere.</s>
 <s id="52">That's what I try and show in my stand-up, good people everywhere.</s>
 <s id="53">All it takes in one person to mess it up.</s>
 <s id="54">Like a couple months ago in Times Square in New York, there was a Pakistani Muslim guy who tried to blow up a car bomb.</s>
 <s id="55">Now, I happened to be in Times Square that night doing a comedy show.</s>
 <s id="56">And a few months before that, there was a white American guy in Austin, Texas who flew his airplane into the IRS building, and I happened to be in Austin that day doing a stand-up comedy show.</s>
 <s id="57">Now I'll tell you, as a Middle-Eastern male, when you show up around a lot of these activities, you start feeling guilty at one point.</s>
 <p id="p58">
  <s id="58.1">(Laughter) I was watching the news.</s>
  <s id="58.2">I'm like, "Am I involved in this crap?"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">(Laughter) "I didn't get the memo.</s>
  <s id="59.2">What's going on?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="60">(Laughter) But what was interesting was, the Pakistani Muslim guy -- see, he gives a bad name to Muslims and Middle Easterners and Pakistanis from all over the world.</s>
 <s id="61">And one thing that happened there was also the Pakistani Taliban took credit for that failed car bombing.</s>
 <s id="62">My question is: Why would you take credit for a failed car bombing?</s>
 <s id="63">"We just want to say: we tried."</s>
 <s id="64">(Laughter) "And furthermore ...</s>
 <s id="65">(Laughter) it is the thought that counts."</s>
 <s id="66">(Laughter) (Applause) "And in conclusion, win some, lose some."</s>
 <p id="p67">
  <s id="67.1">(Laughter) But what happened was, when the white guy flew his plane into the building, I know all my Middle Eastern and Muslim friends in the States were watching TV, going, "Please, don't be Middle Eastern.</s>
  <s id="67.2">Don't be Hassan or Hussein."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">And the name came out: Jack.</s>
  <s id="68.2">I'm like, "Woooo!</s>
  <s id="68.3">That's not one of us!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="69">But I kept watching the news in case they came back, and were like, "Before he did it, he converted to Islam."</s>
 <p id="p70">
  <s id="70.1">"Damn it!</s>
  <s id="70.2">Why Jack?</s>
  <s id="70.3">Why?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="71">But the fact is, I've been lucky to get a chance to perform all over the world, and I did a lot of shows in the Middle East.</s>
 <s id="72">I just did a seven-country solo tour.</s>
 <s id="73">I was in Oman, and I was in Saudi Arabia.</s>
 <s id="74">I was in Dubai.</s>
 <s id="75">And it's great, there's good people everywhere.</s>
 <s id="76">And you learn great things about these places.</s>
 <s id="77">I encourage people always to go visit these places.</s>
 <s id="78">For example, Dubai -- cool place.</s>
 <s id="79">They're obsessed with having the biggest, tallest, longest, as we all know.</s>
 <s id="80">They have a mall there, the Dubai Mall.</s>
 <s id="81">It is so big, they have taxis in the mall.</s>
 <p id="p82">
  <s id="82.1">I was walking.</s>
  <s id="82.2">I heard, "Beep!</s>
  <s id="82.3">Beep!"</s>
  <s id="82.4">I'm like, "What are you doing here?"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p83">
  <s id="83.1">He goes, "I'm going to the Zara store.</s>
  <s id="83.2">It's three miles away.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p84">
  <s id="84.1">Out of my way.</s>
  <s id="84.2">Out of my way.</s>
  <s id="84.3">Out of my way."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="85">(Laughter) And what's crazy -- there's a recession going on, even in Dubai, but you wouldn't know by the prices.</s>
 <s id="86">Like in the Dubai Mall, they sell frozen yogurt by the gram.</s>
 <s id="87">It's like a drug deal.</s>
 <p id="p88">
  <s id="88.1">I was walking by.</s>
  <s id="88.2">The guy goes, "Psst!</s>
  <s id="88.3">Habibi, my friend."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="89">(Laughter) "You want some frozen yogurt?</s>
 <p id="p90">
  <s id="90.1">(Laughter) Come here.</s>
  <s id="90.2">Come here.</s>
  <s id="90.3">Come here.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p91">
  <s id="91.1">I have one gram, five gram, 10 gram.</s>
  <s id="91.2">How many gram do you want?"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p92">
  <s id="92.1">(Laughter) I bought five grams.</s>
  <s id="92.2">10 dollars.</s>
  <s id="92.3">10 dollars!</s>
  <s id="92.4">I said, "What's in this?"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p93">
  <s id="93.1">He's like, "Good stuff, man.</s>
  <s id="93.2">Colombian.</s>
  <s id="93.3">Top of the line."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="94">(Laughter) The other thing you learn when you travel in these countries, in the Middle East, Latin American, South American countries, a lot of times when they build stuff, there's no rules and regulations.</s>
 <s id="95">For example, I took my two-year-old son to the playground at the Dubai Mall.</s>
 <s id="96">And I've taken him to playgrounds all over the United States.</s>
 <s id="97">And when you put your two-year-old on a slide in the United States, they put something on the slide to slow the kid down as he comes down the slide.</s>
 <s id="98">Not in the Middle East.</s>
 <p id="p99">
  <s id="99.1">(Laughter) I put my two-year-old on the slide, he went whoosh!</s>
  <s id="99.2">He took off!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p100">
  <s id="100.1">(Laughter) I went down and, "Where's my son?"</s>
  <s id="100.2">"On the third floor, sir.</s>
  <s id="100.3">Third floor."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p101">
  <s id="101.1">(Laughter) "You take a taxi.</s>
  <s id="101.2">You go to Zara.</s>
  <s id="101.3">Make a left."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p102">
  <s id="102.1">(Laughter) "Try the yogurt.</s>
  <s id="102.2">It's very good.</s>
  <s id="102.3">Little expensive."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="103">(Laughter) But one thing I try to do with my stand-up is break stereotypes.</s>
 <s id="104">And I've been guilty of stereotyping as well.</s>
 <p id="p105">
  <s id="105.1">I was in Dubai.</s>
  <s id="105.2">And there's a lot of Indians who work in Dubai.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="106">And they don't get paid that well.</s>
 <s id="107">And I got it in my head that all the Indians must be workers.</s>
 <s id="108">I forgot there's obviously successful Indians in Dubai too.</s>
 <s id="109">I was doing a show, and they said, "We'll send a driver to pick you up."</s>
 <s id="110">I went down to the lobby, and saw this Indian guy.</s>
 <s id="111">I go, "He must be my driver," since he's standing there in a cheap suit, thin mustache, staring at me.</s>
 <s id="112">I say, "Excuse me, are you my driver?"</s>
 <p id="p113">
  <s id="113.1">He goes, "No, sir.</s>
  <s id="113.2">I own the hotel."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p114">
  <s id="114.1">(Laughter) I go, "I'm sorry!</s>
  <s id="114.2">Why were you staring at me?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="115">He goes, "I thought you were my driver."</s>
 <s id="116">(Laughter) (Applause) (Laughter) I'll leave you with this: I try, with my stand-up, to break stereotypes, present Middle Easterners and Muslims in a positive light.</s>
 <s id="117">I hope that in the coming years, more film and television programs come out of Hollywood, presenting us in a positive light.</s>
 <p id="p118">
  <s id="118.1">Who knows?</s>
  <s id="118.2">Maybe one day, we'll even have our own James Bond.</s>
  <s id="118.3">Right?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="119">"My name is Bond.</s>
 <s id="120">Jamal Bond."</s>
 <p id="p121">
  <s id="121.1">(Laughter) Til then, I'll keep telling jokes.</s>
  <s id="121.2">Hope you keep laughing.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p122">
  <s id="122.1">Have a good day.</s>
  <s id="122.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="123">(Applause)</s>
</text>
