<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The Devil has come to town.</s>
 <s id="2">But don’t worry – all he wants to do is stage a magic show.</s>
 <s id="3">This absurd premise forms the central plot of Mikhail Bulgakov’s masterpiece, "The Master and Margarita."</s>
 <s id="4">Written in Moscow during the 1930s, this surreal blend of political satire, historical fiction, and occult mysticism has earned a legacy as one of the 20th century’s greatest novels– and one of its strangest.</s>
 <s id="5">The story begins when a meeting between two members of Moscow’s literary elite is interrupted by a strange gentleman named Woland, who presents himself as a foreign scholar invited to give a presentation on black magic.</s>
 <s id="6">As the stranger engages the two companions in a philosophical debate and makes ominous predictions about their fates, the reader is suddenly transported to 1st century Jerusalem.</s>
 <s id="7">There a tormented Pontius Pilate reluctantly sentences Jesus of Nazareth to death.</s>
 <s id="8">With the narrative shifting between the two settings, Woland and his entourage– Azazello, Koroviev, Hella, and a giant cat named Behemoth– are seen to have uncanny magical powers, which they use to stage their performance while leaving a trail of havoc and confusion in their wake.</s>
 <s id="9">Much of the novel’s dark humor comes not only from this demonic mischief, but also the backdrop against which it occurs.</s>
 <s id="10">Bulgakov’s story takes place in the same setting where it was written– the USSR at the height of the Stalinist period.</s>
 <s id="11">There, artists and authors worked under strict censorship, subject to imprisonment, exile, or execution if they were seen as undermining state ideology.</s>
 <s id="12">Even when approved, their work– along with housing, travel, and everything else– was governed by a convoluted bureaucracy.</s>
 <s id="13">In the novel, Woland manipulates this system along with the fabric of reality, to hilarious results.</s>
 <s id="14">As heads are separated from bodies and money rains from the sky, the citizens of Moscow react with petty-self interest, illustrating how Soviet society bred greed and cynicism despite its ideals.</s>
 <s id="15">And the matter-of-fact narration deliberately blends the strangeness of the supernatural events with the everyday absurdity of Soviet life.</s>
 <s id="16">So how did Bulgakov manage to publish such a subversive novel under an oppressive regime?</s>
 <s id="17">Well… he didn’t.</s>
 <s id="18">He worked on "The Master and Margarita" for over ten years.</s>
 <s id="19">But while Stalin’s personal favor may have kept Bulgakov safe from severe persecution, many of his plays and writings were kept from production, leaving him safe but effectively silenced.</s>
 <s id="20">Upon the author’s death in 1940, the manuscript remained unpublished.</s>
 <s id="21">A censored version was eventually printed in the 1960s, while copies of the unabridged manuscript continued to circulate among underground literary circles.</s>
 <s id="22">The full text was only published in 1973, over 30 years after its completion.</s>
 <s id="23">Bulgakov’s experiences with censorship and artistic frustration lend an autobiographical air to the second part of the novel, when we are finally introduced to its namesake.</s>
 <s id="24">"The Master" is a nameless author who’s worked for years on a novel but burned the manuscript after it was rejected by publishers– just as Bulgakov had done with his own work.</s>
 <s id="25">Yet the true protagonist is the Master’s mistress Margarita.</s>
 <s id="26">Her devotion to her lover’s abandoned dream bears a strange connection to the diabolical company’s escapades– and carries the story to its surreal climax.</s>
 <s id="27">Despite its dark humor and complex structure, "The Master and Margarita" is, at its heart, a meditation on art, love, and redemption, that never loses itself in cynicism.</s>
 <s id="28">And the book’s long overdue publication and survival against the odds is a testament to what Woland tells the Master: “Manuscripts don’t burn.”</s>
</text>
