<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I've spent the last decade subjecting myself to pain and humiliation, hopefully for a good cause, which is self-improvement.</s>
 <s id="2">And I've done this in three parts.</s>
 <s id="3">So first I started with the mind.</s>
 <s id="4">And I decided to try to get smarter by reading the entire Encyclopedia Britannica from A to Z -- or, more precisely, from "a-ak" to "Zywiec."</s>
 <s id="5">And here's a little image of that.</s>
 <s id="6">And this was an amazing year.</s>
 <s id="7">It was really a fascinating journey.</s>
 <s id="8">It was painful at times, especially for those around me.</s>
 <s id="9">My wife started to fine me one dollar for every irrelevant fact I inserted into conversation.</s>
 <s id="10">So it had its downsides.</s>
 <s id="11">But after that, I decided to work on the spirit.</s>
 <s id="12">As I mentioned last year, I grew up with no religion at all.</s>
 <s id="13">I'm Jewish, but I'm Jewish in the same way the Olive Garden is Italian.</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) Not really.</s>
 <s id="15">But I decided to learn about the Bible and my heritage by actually diving in and trying to live it and immerse myself in it.</s>
 <s id="16">So I decided to follow all the rules of the Bible.</s>
 <s id="17">And from the Ten Commandments to growing my beard -- because Leviticus says you cannot shave.</s>
 <s id="18">So this is what I looked like by the end.</s>
 <s id="19">Thank you for that reaction.</s>
 <s id="20">(Laughter) I look a little like Moses, or Ted Kaczynski.</s>
 <s id="21">I got both of them.</s>
 <s id="22">So there was the topiary there.</s>
 <s id="23">And there's the sheep.</s>
 <s id="24">Now the final part of the trilogy was I wanted to focus on the body and try to be the healthiest person I could be, the healthiest person alive.</s>
 <s id="25">So that's what I've been doing the last couple of years.</s>
 <s id="26">And I just finished a couple of months ago.</s>
 <s id="27">And I have to say, thank God.</s>
 <s id="28">Because living so healthily was killing me.</s>
 <s id="29">(Laughter) It was so overwhelming, because the amount of things you have to do, it's just mind-boggling.</s>
 <s id="30">I was listening to all the experts and talking to sort of a board of medical advisers.</s>
 <s id="31">And they were telling me all the things I had to do.</s>
 <s id="32">I had to eat right, exercise, meditate, pet dogs, because that lowers the blood pressure.</s>
 <s id="33">I wrote the book on a treadmill, and it took me about a thousand miles to write the book.</s>
 <s id="34">I had to put on sunscreen.</s>
 <s id="35">This was no small feat, because if you listen to dermatologists, they say that you should have a shot glass full of sunscreen.</s>
 <s id="36">And you have to reapply it every two to four hours.</s>
 <s id="37">So I think half of my book advance went into sunscreen.</s>
 <s id="38">I was like a glazed doughnut for most of the year.</s>
 <s id="39">There was the washing of hands.</s>
 <s id="40">I had to do that properly.</s>
 <s id="41">And my immunologist told me that I should also wipe down all of the remote controls and iPhones in my house, because those are just orgies of germs.</s>
 <s id="42">So that took a lot of time.</s>
 <s id="43">I also tried to be the safest person I could be, because that's a part of health.</s>
 <s id="44">I was inspired by the Danish Safety Council.</s>
 <s id="45">They started a public campaign that says, "A walking helmet is a good helmet."</s>
 <s id="46">So they believe you should not just wear helmets for biking, but also for walking around.</s>
 <s id="47">And you can see there they're shopping with their helmets.</s>
 <s id="48">(Laughter) Well yeah, I tried that.</s>
 <s id="49">Now it's a little extreme, I admit.</s>
 <s id="50">But if you think about this, this is actually -- the "Freakonomics" authors wrote about this -- that more people die on a per mile basis from drunk walking than from drunk driving.</s>
 <s id="51">So something to think about tonight if you've had a couple.</s>
 <s id="52">So I finished, and it was a success in a sense.</s>
 <s id="53">All of the markers went in the right direction.</s>
 <s id="54">My cholesterol went down, I lost weight, my wife stopped telling me that I looked pregnant.</s>
 <s id="55">So that was nice.</s>
 <s id="56">And it was successful overall.</s>
 <s id="57">But I also learned that I was too healthy, and that was unhealthy.</s>
 <s id="58">I was so focused on doing all these things that I was neglecting my friends and family.</s>
 <s id="59">And as Dan Buettner can tell you, having a strong social network is so crucial to our health.</s>
 <s id="60">So I finished.</s>
 <s id="61">And I kind of went overboard on the week after the project was over.</s>
 <s id="62">I went to the dark side, and I just indulged myself.</s>
 <s id="63">It was like something out of Caligula.</s>
 <s id="64">(Laughter) Without the sex part.</s>
 <s id="65">Because I have three young kids, so that wasn't happening.</s>
 <s id="66">But the over-eating and over-drinking, definitely.</s>
 <s id="67">And I finally have stabilized.</s>
 <s id="68">So now I'm back to adopting many -- not all; I don't wear a helmet anymore -- but dozens of healthy behaviors that I adopted during my year.</s>
 <s id="69">It was really a life-changing project.</s>
 <s id="70">And I, of course, don't have time to go into all of them.</s>
 <s id="71">Let me just tell you two really quickly.</s>
 <s id="72">The first is -- and this was surprising to me; I didn't expect this to come out -- but I live a much quieter life now.</s>
 <s id="73">Because we live in such a noisy world.</s>
 <s id="74">There's trains and planes and cars and Bill O'Reilly, he's very noisy.</s>
 <s id="75">(Laughter) And this is a real underestimated, under-appreciated health hazard -- not just because it harms our hearing, which it obviously does, but it actually initiates the fight-or-flight response.</s>
 <s id="76">A loud noise will get your fight-or-flight response going.</s>
 <s id="77">And this, over the years, can cause real damage, cardiovascular damage.</s>
 <s id="78">The World Health Organization just did a big study that they published this year.</s>
 <s id="79">And it was done in Europe.</s>
 <s id="80">And they estimated that 1.6 million years of healthy living are lost every year in Europe because of noise pollution.</s>
 <s id="81">So they think it's actually very deadly.</s>
 <s id="82">And by the way, it's also terrible for your brain.</s>
 <s id="83">It really impairs cognition.</s>
 <s id="84">And our Founding Fathers knew about this.</s>
 <s id="85">When they wrote the Constitution, they put dirt all over the cobblestones outside the hall so that they could concentrate.</s>
 <s id="86">So without noise reduction technology, our country would not exist.</s>
 <s id="87">So as a patriot, I felt it was important to -- I wear all the earplugs and the earphones, and it's really improved my life in a surprising and unexpected way.</s>
 <s id="88">And the second point I want to make, the final point, is that -- and it's actually been a theme of TEDMED -- that joy is so important to your health, that very few of these behaviors will stick with me unless there's some sense of pleasure and joy in them.</s>
 <s id="89">And just to give you one instance of this: food.</s>
 <s id="90">The junk food industry is really great at pressing our pleasure buttons and figuring out what's the most pleasurable.</s>
 <s id="91">But I think we can use their techniques and apply them to healthy food.</s>
 <s id="92">To give just one example, we love crunchiness, mouthfeel.</s>
 <s id="93">So I basically have tried to incorporate crunchiness into a lot of my recipes -- throw in some sunflower seeds.</s>
 <s id="94">And you can almost trick yourself into thinking you're eating Doritos.</s>
 <s id="95">(Laughter) And it has made me a healthier person.</s>
 <s id="96">So that is it.</s>
 <s id="97">The book about it comes out in April.</s>
 <s id="98">It's called "Drop Dead Healthy."</s>
 <s id="99">And I hope that I don't get sick during the book tour.</s>
 <s id="100">That's my greatest hope.</s>
 <s id="101">So thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="102">(Applause)</s>
</text>
