<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Last year here at TED I asked you to give me your data, to put your data on the web, on the basis that if people put data onto the web -- government data, scientific data, community data, whatever it is -- it will be used by other people to do wonderful things, in ways that they never could have imagined.</s>
 <s id="2">So, today I'm back just to show you a few things, to show you, in fact, there is an open data movement afoot, now, around the world.</s>
 <s id="3">The cry of "Raw data now!"</s>
 <s id="4">which I made people make in the auditorium, was heard around the world.</s>
 <s id="5">So, let's roll the video.</s>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">A classic story, the first one which lots of people picked up, was when in March -- on March 10th in fact, soon after TED -- Paul Clarke, in the U.K. government, blogged, "Oh, I've just got some raw data.</s>
  <s id="6.2">Here it is, it's about bicycle accidents."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="7">Two days it took the Times Online to make a map, a mashable map -- we call these things mash-ups -- a mashed-up user interface that allows you to go in there and have a look and find out whether your bicycle route to work was affected.</s>
 <s id="8">Here's more data, traffic survey data, again, put out by the U.K. government, and because they put it up using the Linked Data standards, then a user could just make a map, just by clicking.</s>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">Does this data affect things?</s>
  <s id="9.2">Well, let's get back to 2008.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="10">Look at Zanesville, Ohio.</s>
 <p id="p11">
  <s id="11.1">Here's a map a lawyer made.</s>
  <s id="11.2">He put on it the water plant, and which houses are there, which houses have been connected to the water.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="12">And he got, from other data sources, information to show which houses are occupied by white people.</s>
 <s id="13">Well, there was too much of a correlation, he felt, between which houses were occupied by white people and which houses had water, and the judge was not impressed either.</s>
 <s id="14">The judge was not impressed to the tune of 10.9 million dollars.</s>
 <s id="15">That's the power of taking one piece of data, another piece of data, putting it together, and showing the result.</s>
 <s id="16">Let's look at some data from the U.K. now.</s>
 <s id="17">This is U.K. government data, a completely independent site, Where Does My Money Go.</s>
 <s id="18">It allows anybody to go there and burrow down.</s>
 <s id="19">You can burrow down by a particular type of spending, or you can go through all the different regions and compare them.</s>
 <s id="20">So, that's happening in the U.K. with U.K. government data.</s>
 <s id="21">Yes, certainly you can do it over here.</s>
 <s id="22">Here's a site which allows you to look at recovery spending in California.</s>
 <s id="23">Take an arbitrary example, Long Beach, California, you can go and have a look at what recovery money they've been spending on different things such as energy.</s>
 <s id="24">In fact, this is the graph of the number of data sets in the repositories of data.gov, and data.gov.uk.</s>
 <s id="25">And I'm delighted to see a great competition between the U.K. in blue, and the U.S. in red.</s>
 <s id="26">How can you use this stuff?</s>
 <s id="27">Well, for example, if you have lots of data about places you can take, from a postcode -- which is like a zip plus four -- for a specific group of houses, you can make paper, print off a paper which has got very, very specific things about the bus stops, the things specifically near you.</s>
 <s id="28">On a larger scale, this is a mash-up of the data which was released about the Afghan elections.</s>
 <s id="29">It allows you to set your own criteria for what sort of things you want to look at.</s>
 <s id="30">The red circles are polling stations, selected by your criteria.</s>
 <s id="31">And then you can select also other things on the map to see what other factors, like the threat level.</s>
 <s id="32">So, that was government data.</s>
 <s id="33">I also talked about community-generated data -- in fact I edited some.</s>
 <s id="34">This is the wiki map, this is the Open Street Map.</s>
 <s id="35">"Terrace Theater" I actually put on the map because it wasn't on the map before TED last year.</s>
 <s id="36">I was not the only person editing the open street map.</s>
 <s id="37">Each flash on this visualization -- put together by ITO World -- shows an edit in 2009 made to the Open Street Map.</s>
 <s id="38">Let's now spin the world during the same year.</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">Every flash is an edit.</s>
  <s id="39.2">Somebody somewhere looking at the Open Street Map, and realizing it could be better.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">You can see Europe is ablaze with updates.</s>
 <s id="41">Some places, perhaps not as much as they should be.</s>
 <s id="42">Here focusing in on Haiti.</s>
 <s id="43">The map of Port au-Prince at the end of 2009 was not all it could be, not as good as the map of California.</s>
 <s id="44">Fortunately, just after the earthquake, GeoEye, a commercial company, released satellite imagery with a license, which allowed the open-source community to use it.</s>
 <s id="45">This is January, in time lapse, of people editing ... that's the earthquake.</s>
 <s id="46">After the earthquake, immediately, people all over the world, mappers who wanted to help, and could, looked at that imagery, built the map, quickly building it up.</s>
 <s id="47">We're focusing now on Port-au-Prince.</s>
 <s id="48">The light blue is refugee camps these volunteers had spotted from the [satellite images].</s>
 <s id="49">So, now we have, immediately, a real-time map showing where there are refugee camps -- rapidly became the best map to use if you're doing relief work in Port-au-Prince.</s>
 <s id="50">Witness the fact that it's here on this Garmin device being used by rescue team in Haiti.</s>
 <s id="51">There's the map showing, on the left-hand side, that hospital -- actually that's a hospital ship.</s>
 <s id="52">This is a real-time map that shows blocked roads, damaged buildings, refugee camps -- it shows things that are needed [for rescue and relief work].</s>
 <s id="53">So, if you've been involved in that at all, I just wanted to say: Whatever you've been doing, whether you've just been chanting, "Raw data now!"</s>
 <s id="54">or you've been putting government or scientific data online, I just wanted to take this opportunity to say: Thank you very much, and we have only just started!</s>
 <s id="55">(Applause)</s>
</text>
