<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Music) [Sanskrit] This is an ode to the mother goddess, that most of us in India learn when we are children.</s>
 <s id="2">I learned it when I was four at my mother's knee.</s>
 <s id="3">That year she introduced me to dance, and thus began my tryst with classical dance.</s>
 <s id="4">Since then -- it's been four decades now -- I've trained with the best in the field, performed across the globe, taught young and old alike, created, collaborated, choreographed, and wove a rich tapestry of artistry, achievement and awards.</s>
 <s id="5">The crowning glory was in 2007, when I received this country's fourth highest civilian award, the Padma Shri, for my contribution to art.</s>
 <s id="6">(Applause) But nothing, nothing prepared me for what I was to hear on the first of July 2008.</s>
 <s id="7">I heard the word "carcinoma."</s>
 <s id="8">Yes, breast cancer.</s>
 <s id="9">As I sat dumbstruck in my doctor's office, I heard other words: "cancer," "stage," "grade."</s>
 <s id="10">Until then, Cancer was the zodiac sign of my friend, stage was what I performed on, and grades were what I got in school.</s>
 <s id="11">That day, I realized I had an unwelcome, uninvited, new life partner.</s>
 <s id="12">As a dancer, I know the nine rasas or the navarasas: anger, valor, disgust, humor and fear.</s>
 <s id="13">I thought I knew what fear was.</s>
 <s id="14">That day, I learned what fear was.</s>
 <s id="15">Overcome with the enormity of it all and the complete feeling of loss of control, I shed copious tears and asked my dear husband, Jayant.</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">I said, "Is this it?</s>
  <s id="16.2">Is this the end of the road?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="17">Is this the end of my dance?"</s>
 <s id="18">And he, the positive soul that he is, said, "No, this is just a hiatus, a hiatus during the treatment, and you'll get back to doing what you do best."</s>
 <s id="19">I realized then that I, who thought I had complete control of my life, had control of only three things: My thought, my mind -- the images that these thoughts created -- and the action that derived from it.</s>
 <s id="20">So here I was wallowing in a vortex of emotions and depression and what have you, with the enormity of the situation, wanting to go to a place of healing, health and happiness.</s>
 <s id="21">I wanted to go from where I was to where I wanted to be, for which I needed something.</s>
 <s id="22">I needed something that would pull me out of all this.</s>
 <s id="23">So I dried my tears, and I declared to the world at large ...</s>
 <s id="24">I said, "Cancer's only one page in my life, and I will not allow this page to impact the rest of my life."</s>
 <s id="25">I also declared to the world at large that I would ride it out, and I would not allow cancer to ride me.</s>
 <s id="26">But to go from where I was to where I wanted to be, I needed something.</s>
 <s id="27">I needed an anchor, an image, a peg to peg this process on, so that I could go from there.</s>
 <s id="28">And I found that in my dance, my dance, my strength, my energy, my passion, my very life breath.</s>
 <s id="29">But it wasn't easy.</s>
 <s id="30">Believe me, it definitely wasn't easy.</s>
 <s id="31">How do you keep cheer when you go from beautiful to bald in three days?</s>
 <s id="32">How do you not despair when, with the body ravaged by chemotherapy, climbing a mere flight of stairs was sheer torture, that to someone like me who could dance for three hours?</s>
 <s id="33">How do you not get overwhelmed by the despair and the misery of it all?</s>
 <s id="34">All I wanted to do was curl up and weep.</s>
 <s id="35">But I kept telling myself fear and tears are options I did not have.</s>
 <s id="36">So I would drag myself into my dance studio -- body, mind and spirit -- every day into my dance studio, and learn everything I learned when I was four, all over again, reworked, relearned, regrouped.</s>
 <s id="37">It was excruciatingly painful, but I did it.</s>
 <s id="38">Difficult.</s>
 <s id="39">I focused on my mudras, on the imagery of my dance, on the poetry and the metaphor and the philosophy of the dance itself.</s>
 <s id="40">And slowly, I moved out of that miserable state of mind.</s>
 <s id="41">But I needed something else.</s>
 <s id="42">I needed something to go that extra mile, and I found it in that metaphor which I had learned from my mother when I was four.</s>
 <s id="43">The metaphor of Mahishasura Mardhini, of Durga.</s>
 <s id="44">Durga, the mother goddess, the fearless one, created by the pantheon of Hindu gods.</s>
 <s id="45">Durga, resplendent, bedecked, beautiful, her 18 arms ready for warfare, as she rode astride her lion into the battlefield to destroy Mahishasur.</s>
 <s id="46">Durga, the epitome of creative feminine energy, or shakti.</s>
 <s id="47">Durga, the fearless one.</s>
 <s id="48">I made that image of Durga and her every attribute, her every nuance, my very own.</s>
 <s id="49">Powered by the symbology of a myth and the passion of my training, I brought laser-sharp focus into my dance, laser-sharp focus to such an extent that I danced a few weeks after surgery.</s>
 <s id="50">I danced through chemo and radiation cycles, much to the dismay of my oncologist.</s>
 <s id="51">I danced between chemo and radiation cycles and badgered him to fit it to my performing dance schedule.</s>
 <s id="52">What I had done is I had tuned out of cancer and tuned into my dance.</s>
 <s id="53">Yes, cancer has just been one page in my life.</s>
 <s id="54">My story is a story of overcoming setbacks, obstacles and challenges that life throws at you.</s>
 <s id="55">My story is the power of thought.</s>
 <s id="56">My story is the power of choice.</s>
 <s id="57">It's the power of focus.</s>
 <s id="58">It's the power of bringing ourselves to the attention of something that so animates you, so moves you, that something even like cancer becomes insignificant.</s>
 <s id="59">My story is the power of a metaphor.</s>
 <s id="60">It's the power of an image.</s>
 <s id="61">Mine was that of Durga, Durga the fearless one.</s>
 <s id="62">She was also called Simhanandini, the one who rode the lion.</s>
 <s id="63">As I ride out, as I ride my own inner strength, my own inner resilience, armed as I am with what medication can provide and continue treatment, as I ride out into the battlefield of cancer, asking my rogue cells to behave, I want to be known not as a cancer survivor, but as a cancer conqueror.</s>
 <s id="64">I present to you an excerpt of that work "Simhanandini."</s>
 <s id="65">(Applause) (Music) (Applause)</s>
</text>
