<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">For the past decade, I've been studying non-state armed groups: armed organizations like terrorists, insurgents or militias.</s>
 <s id="2">I document what these groups do when they're not shooting.</s>
 <s id="3">My goal is to better understand these violent actors and to study ways to encourage transition from violent engagement to nonviolent confrontation.</s>
 <s id="4">I work in the field, in the policy world and in the library.</s>
 <s id="5">Understanding non-state armed groups is key to solving most ongoing conflict, because war has changed.</s>
 <s id="6">It used to be a contest between states.</s>
 <s id="7">No longer.</s>
 <s id="8">It is now a conflict between states and non-state actors.</s>
 <s id="9">For example, of the 216 peace agreements signed between 1975 and 2011, 196 of them were between a state and a non-state actor.</s>
 <s id="10">So we need to understand these groups; we need to either engage them or defeat them in any conflict resolution process that has to be successful.</s>
 <s id="11">So how do we do that?</s>
 <s id="12">We need to know what makes these organizations tick.</s>
 <s id="13">We know a lot about how they fight, why they fight, but no one looks at what they're doing when they're not fighting.</s>
 <s id="14">Yet, armed struggle and unarmed politics are related.</s>
 <s id="15">It is all part of the same organization.</s>
 <s id="16">We cannot understand these groups, let alone defeat them, if we don't have the full picture.</s>
 <s id="17">And armed groups today are complex organizations.</s>
 <s id="18">Take the Lebanese Hezbollah, known for its violent confrontation against Israel.</s>
 <s id="19">But since its creation in the early 1980s, Hezbollah has also set up a political party, a social-service network, and a military apparatus.</s>
 <s id="20">Similarly, the Palestinian Hamas, known for its suicide attacks against Israel, also runs the Gaza Strip since 2007.</s>
 <s id="21">So these groups do way more than just shoot.</s>
 <s id="22">They multi-task.</s>
 <s id="23">They set up complex communication machines -- radio stations, TV channels, Internet websites and social media strategies.</s>
 <s id="24">And up here, you have the ISIS magazine, printed in English and published to recruit.</s>
 <s id="25">Armed groups also invest in complex fund-raising -- not looting, but setting up profitable businesses; for example, construction companies.</s>
 <s id="26">Now, these activities are keys.</s>
 <s id="27">They allow these groups to increase their strength, increase their funds, to better recruit and to build their brand.</s>
 <s id="28">Armed groups also do something else: they build stronger bonds with the population by investing in social services.</s>
 <s id="29">They build schools, they run hospitals, they set up vocational-training programs or micro-loan programs.</s>
 <s id="30">Hezbollah offers all of these services and more.</s>
 <s id="31">Armed groups also seek to win the population over by offering something that the state is not providing: safety and security.</s>
 <s id="32">The initial rise of the Taliban in war-torn Afghanistan, or even the beginning of the ascent of ISIS, can be understood also by looking at these groups' efforts to provide security.</s>
 <s id="33">Now, unfortunately, in these cases, the provision of security came at an unbearably high price for the population.</s>
 <s id="34">But in general, providing social services fills a gap, a governance gap left by the government, and allows these groups to increase their strength and their power.</s>
 <s id="35">For example, the 2006 electoral victory of the Palestinian Hamas cannot be understood without acknowledging the group's social work.</s>
 <s id="36">Now, this is a really complex picture, yet in the West, when we look at armed groups, we only think of the violent side.</s>
 <s id="37">But that's not enough to understand these groups' strength, strategy or long-term vision.</s>
 <s id="38">These groups are hybrid.</s>
 <s id="39">They rise because they fill a gap left by the government, and they emerge to be both armed and political, engage in violent struggle and provide governance.</s>
 <s id="40">And the more these organizations are complex and sophisticated, the less we can think of them as the opposite of a state.</s>
 <s id="41">Now, what do you call a group like Hezbollah?</s>
 <s id="42">They run part of a territory, they administer all their functions, they pick up the garbage, they run the sewage system.</s>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">Is this a state?</s>
  <s id="43.2">Is it a rebel group?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">Or maybe something else, something different and new?</s>
 <s id="45">And what about ISIS?</s>
 <s id="46">The lines are blurred.</s>
 <s id="47">We live in a world of states, non-states, and in-between, and the more states are weak, like in the Middle East today, the more non-state actors step in and fill that gap.</s>
 <s id="48">This matters for governments, because to counter these groups, they will have to invest more in non-military tools.</s>
 <s id="49">Filling that governance gap has to be at the center of any sustainable approach.</s>
 <s id="50">This also matters very much for peacemaking and peacebuilding.</s>
 <s id="51">If we better understand armed groups, we will better know what incentives to offer to encourage the transition from violence to nonviolence.</s>
 <s id="52">So in this new contest between states and non-states, military power can win some battles, but it will not give us peace nor stability.</s>
 <s id="53">To achieve these objectives, what we need is a long-term investment in filling that security gap, in filling that governance gap that allowed these groups to thrive in the first place.</s>
 <s id="54">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="55">(Applause)</s>
</text>
