<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">From asteroids capable of destroying entire species, to gamma-ray bursts and supernovae that could exterminate life on Earth, outer space has no shortage of forces that could wreak havoc on our tiny planet.</s>
 <s id="2">But there’s something in space that seems more terrifying than any of these – something that wipes out everything it comes near.</s>
 <s id="3">Could the Earth be swallowed by a black hole?</s>
 <s id="4">A black hole is an object so dense that space and time around it are inescapably modified, warped into an infinite sink.</s>
 <s id="5">Nothing, not even light, can move fast enough to escape a black hole’s gravitational pull once it passes a certain boundary, known as the event horizon.</s>
 <s id="6">Thus, a black hole is like a cosmic vacuum cleaner with infinite capacity, gobbling up everything in its path, and letting nothing out.</s>
 <s id="7">To determine whether a black hole could swallow the Earth, we first have to figure out where they are.</s>
 <s id="8">But since they don’t emit light, how’s that possible?</s>
 <s id="9">Fortunately, we’re able to observe their effect on the space around them.</s>
 <s id="10">When matter approaches a black hole, the immense gravitational field accelerates it to high speed.</s>
 <s id="11">This emits an enormous amount of light.</s>
 <s id="12">And for objects too far away to be sucked in, the massive gravitational force still affects their orbits.</s>
 <s id="13">If we observe several stars orbiting around an apparently empty point, a black hole could be leading the dance.</s>
 <s id="14">Similarly, light that passes close enough to an event horizon will be deflected in a phenomenon known as gravitational lensing.</s>
 <s id="15">Most of the black holes that we’ve found can be thought of as two main types.</s>
 <s id="16">The smaller ones, called stellar mass black holes, have a mass up to 100 times larger than that of our sun.</s>
 <s id="17">They’re formed when a massive star consumes all its nuclear fuel and its core collapses.</s>
 <s id="18">We’ve observed several of these objects as close as 3000 light-years away, and there could be up to 100 million small black holes just in the Milky Way galaxy.</s>
 <s id="19">So should we be worried?</s>
 <s id="20">Probably not.</s>
 <s id="21">Despite their large mass, stellar black holes only have a radius of around 300 kilometers or less, making the chances of a direct hit with us miniscule.</s>
 <s id="22">Although because their gravitational fields can affect a planet from a large distance, they could be dangerous even without a direct collision.</s>
 <s id="23">If a typical stellar-mass black hole were to pass in the region of Neptune, the orbit of the Earth would be considerably modified, with dire results.</s>
 <s id="24">Still, the combination of how small they are and how vast the galaxy is means that stellar black holes don’t give us much to worry about.</s>
 <s id="25">But we still have to meet the second type: supermassive black holes.</s>
 <s id="26">These have masses millions or billions times greater than that of our sun and have event horizons that could span billions of kilometers.</s>
 <s id="27">These giants have grown to immense proportions by swallowing matter and merging with other black holes.</s>
 <s id="28">Unlike their stellar cousins, supermassive black holes aren’t wandering through space.</s>
 <s id="29">Instead, they lie at the center of galaxies, including our own.</s>
 <s id="30">Our solar system is in a stable orbit around a supermassive black hole that resides at the center of the Milky Way, at a safe distance of 25,000 light-years.</s>
 <s id="31">But that could change.</s>
 <s id="32">If our galaxy collides with another, the Earth could be thrown towards the galactic center, close enough to the supermassive black hole to be eventually swallowed up.</s>
 <s id="33">In fact, a collision with the Andromeda Galaxy is predicted to happen 4 billion years from now, which may not be great news for our home planet.</s>
 <s id="34">But before we judge them too harshly, black holes aren’t simply agents of destruction.</s>
 <s id="35">They played a crucial role in the formation of galaxies, the building blocks of our universe.</s>
 <s id="36">Far from being shadowy characters in the cosmic play, black holes have fundamentally contributed in making the universe a bright and astonishing place.</s>
</text>
