<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <p id="p1">
  <s id="1.1">[Yoruba: Freeborn Ijebu-Ode son,] [of true Ogbogbo Clan,] [whose wealth and resources surpass all that Europe ever had,] [whose altar is filled with gold.]</s>
  <s id="1.2">This chant is called the oríkì.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="2">My grandmother used to sing it to me when I was a child in Nigeria.</s>
 <s id="3">See, an oríkì is the song of praise of the Yoruba people, and this particularly speaks of treasures that the West does not have.</s>
 <s id="4">Mama -- that's what I call my grandmother -- told me many stories about Yoruba mythology.</s>
 <s id="5">You see, the Yorubas are an ethnic group from the southwestern part of Nigeria, and I was always fascinated by these stories.</s>
 <s id="6">I was always intrigued.</s>
 <s id="7">And Yoruba culture has inspired my art since I was a child.</s>
 <s id="8">You see, African art is not just what you buy at Harlem markets in New York.</s>
 <s id="9">Every artist has a name, and every artist has a story.</s>
 <s id="10">This is my story.</s>
 <s id="11">See, mama had tattoos on her arms and her legs.</s>
 <s id="12">As a child, I thought she was born with them, with beautiful black lines and detailed symbols.</s>
 <s id="13">And then she told me that they were actually symbols from the Yoruba mythology.</s>
 <s id="14">I never knew how this was going to influence the artist that I am today.</s>
 <s id="15">You see, as a young child, I saw art everywhere.</s>
 <s id="16">I remember the house we lived in in Ilorin, in Stadium Road.</s>
 <s id="17">We had marble floors, and you know, I would look at the marble floors, and I would see all sorts of patterns and designs in it, and I thought everybody could see them.</s>
 <s id="18">So I would call my brother, and I would be like, "Ikeolu, come and see this marble design, see this pattern, see this mask."</s>
 <s id="19">And he would tell me, "Laolu, I don't see anything."</s>
 <s id="20">So I would use ink, and I would trace out what I saw on the floor.</s>
 <s id="21">And then when my mom noticed, she got really upset.</s>
 <s id="22">(Laughter) But that didn't stop me.</s>
 <s id="23">I switched from ink to chalk, because I got in trouble a lot with my teachers and my parents.</s>
 <s id="24">So I remember my mom said, "Laolu, we are Christians.</s>
 <s id="25">Why don't you draw like other people?</s>
 <s id="26">Why don't you draw landscapes or maybe you draw chairs or furniture, or maybe even draw Jesus?"</s>
 <s id="27">You know, I could paint the whole house if I had a chance, but when I grew up, I knew being an artist was not an option, so I wanted to be the person my parents wanted me to be, so I went to law school.</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">Of course, that's my dad there.</s>
  <s id="28.2">He was so proud that day.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">And this was what my notebooks looked like in law school.</s>
 <s id="30">(Laughter) Of course I would miss classes, and I would make up excuses why I wasn't going to class.</s>
 <s id="31">But when I started working at the Human Rights Commission as a human rights attorney, my mind was elsewhere.</s>
 <s id="32">I saw a very tough reality.</s>
 <s id="33">I worked with children who had to choose between getting an education and actually being forced into marriage.</s>
 <s id="34">I was so frustrated seeing all the injustice around me, and my only outlet was art, so I started painting.</s>
 <s id="35">This piece is called "Dreamscape."</s>
 <s id="36">So when you zoom into this piece, you're going to see a girl child and the accidental birth, the fact that our future is controlled by where we are born.</s>
 <s id="37">Now, the next one you see a man and a man holding hands, a woman and a woman holding hands.</s>
 <s id="38">You see, in Nigeria, same-sex relationship is criminalized.</s>
 <s id="39">You can actually get 14 years for that.</s>
 <s id="40">With my art, I like to tell stories.</s>
 <s id="41">Through my art, I like to start a conversation.</s>
 <s id="42">So in this one, you see the map of Africa, you see the questions, you see crying, and there you see syringes plugged into Africa and the natural resources being drained out.</s>
 <s id="43">So I asked myself, where does it go?</s>
 <s id="44">Who benefits from all of this?</s>
 <s id="45">You see, with my art, the way I weave my art around the patterns, the masks, the stories, and the way I use my lines, it's all from the Yoruba culture.</s>
 <s id="46">So in 2013, I made a big gamble.</s>
 <s id="47">I quit my job and I moved to New York City to practice art full time.</s>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">Of course, my parents were like, "Oh, [it's just a phase.]</s>
  <s id="48.2">He'll come back."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="49">But life as an artist in New York was not easy, because I was broke, no money, no gallery agents, no representation, so no gallery would show my work.</s>
 <s id="50">So I thought to myself, I need to survive.</s>
 <s id="51">So I started painting on clothes to make a living.</s>
 <s id="52">I started painting on shoes.</s>
 <s id="53">I started customizing things for people.</s>
 <s id="54">And then soon I realized the power, because people were so proud to wear their stories.</s>
 <s id="55">So I started painting on everything.</s>
 <s id="56">I painted on guitars, I started doing murals, anything I could find my hand on I painted, and everything became my canvas.</s>
 <s id="57">So one day, I was just going on my Instagram feed, and I saw this picture.</s>
 <p id="p58">
  <s id="58.1">It was Reign.</s>
  <s id="58.2">She took a picture standing in front my art, and the moment I saw that photo, something happened in that moment.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="59">I could actually see my artwork go into her and come out of her literally, and that's how I started painting on human bodies.</s>
 <s id="60">As a child I saw art on the marble floors, I saw art on walls, but now I see art on people's faces and people's bodies.</s>
 <s id="61">I remember my grandmother, and I realized that most of my creative instincts were actually based on my childhood memories and the art on my grandmother's skin.</s>
 <s id="62">Now I look at all the people I painted, and I think to myself, like, what would it look like if we all walked around like gods and goddesses from Yoruba mythology?</s>
 <s id="63">And boom, that's how The Sacred Art of the Ori was born.</s>
 <s id="64">You see, Ori in Yoruba mythology means your soul, it means your essence, it means your instincts.</s>
 <s id="65">And I realized that only when you tap into your Ori, then you can actually move mountains.</s>
 <s id="66">So there's something so immediate about painting on human bodies.</s>
 <s id="67">It's like art in motion.</s>
 <s id="68">It's like a 3D experience.</s>
 <s id="69">So one day, I was just doing my regular work in Brooklyn, and I got an email that said, "Hi, I'm a big fan of your work.</s>
 <s id="70">Would you like to paint for my music video?</s>
 <s id="71">Signed, Beyoncé."</s>
 <s id="72">Like, Beyoncé emailed me.</s>
 <s id="73">I was like, what?</s>
 <s id="74">(Laughter) I was like, what, how did she even know me?</s>
 <p id="p75">
  <s id="75.1">I thought this can't be true.</s>
  <s id="75.2">Of course I thought it was a scam.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="76">The Nigerian in me was like, nah.</s>
 <s id="77">(Laughter) (Applause) But incredibly enough, it was real, it was true, and things happened really fast.</s>
 <s id="78">You see, Beyoncé wanted to pay homage to New Orleans, and my art reminded her of her creole origins.</s>
 <s id="79">So when "Lemonade" dropped, of course, boom, everything just went from zero to 100 real fast.</s>
 <s id="80">People featured me in magazines, interviews.</s>
 <s id="81">People stopped me in the street.</s>
 <s id="82">People knew my name, like -- And sometimes I had to step back and just chill, and, like, take everything in.</s>
 <s id="83">You know, as artists, we work so hard all our lives for our art to be recognized, and for this I feel blessed.</s>
 <s id="84">However, the attorney in me is still there, so I use my art to fight for what I believe in.</s>
 <s id="85">My Yoruba heritage is always there.</s>
 <s id="86">I'd like to share with you tonight some of my art in motion.</s>
 <s id="87">Please, welcome with me on stage.</s>
 <s id="88">(Music) (Applause) Now, this is Geli, and this is Reign.</s>
 <s id="89">These are the first two people I ever painted in my life, and I spent the past day painting on them.</s>
 <s id="90">Tonight, they represent my hopes and my fears.</s>
 <s id="91">Now, I put my fears on the back.</s>
 <s id="92">I put my hopes in front.</s>
 <s id="93">What are my hopes?</s>
 <s id="94">I hope that people know that Africa is not just one huge, nameless continent that is all the same.</s>
 <s id="95">I also hope that people know that in Nigeria, we have over 350 ethnic groups and languages, and I am just one artist from one of them.</s>
 <s id="96">(Applause) I also hope that you know that I hope I will be able to change the way people talk about African art on the continent and here, and I hope you know that African art is not just what you buy at Harlem markets in New York and that every piece of art you see has a story, and every artist has a name.</s>
 <s id="97">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="98">(Applause)</s>
</text>
