<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Picture it: a big, sweaty, tattooed man in a cowboy hat and chaps, is in the ring as the arena full of fans cheer him on.</s>
 <s id="2">Their hero: "Cowboy" Gator Magraw.</s>
 <s id="3">Gator bounces off the ropes and is quickly body-slammed to the mat.</s>
 <s id="4">His wild opponent leaps into the air, crashing down onto Gator's rib cage.</s>
 <s id="5">Gator struggles to breathe, wondering: "Is this really what my father wanted for me?"</s>
 <s id="6">(Laughter) That wild man in the chaps ...</s>
 <s id="7">was me.</s>
 <s id="8">(Laughter) (Applause) (Cheers) And the answer to the question, surprisingly, is yes.</s>
 <s id="9">(Laughter) I grew up watching professional wrestling with my dad.</s>
 <s id="10">And like him, I loved everything about it: the showmanship, the athletic skill, the drama.</s>
 <s id="11">I'd be this little boy, bouncing all over our living room, pretending to be my favorite wrestlers from TV.</s>
 <s id="12">My dad actually reminded me a little bit of Hulk Hogan, but I was Hulk Hogan and he was Andre the Giant.</s>
 <s id="13">I'd get all serious on him and say things like, "Dad ...</s>
 <s id="14">someday I am going to be world heavyweight champion."</s>
 <s id="15">And he would usually smile and very calmly say, "OK, then I guess I can count on you to be my retirement fund."</s>
 <s id="16">(Laughter) When I was 16, a small wrestling show came to my little town in Minnesota.</s>
 <s id="17">I couldn't believe it.</s>
 <s id="18">Nothing like that had ever come to my town before.</s>
 <s id="19">So I got to the arena early in the morning the day of the show, waiting out in the parking lot to see if I could spot some wrestlers pulling up in their cars.</s>
 <s id="20">It wasn't as creepy as it sounds.</s>
 <s id="21">But I could definitely tell who the wrestlers were, just the way they walked.</s>
 <s id="22">They were tall and confident and intimidating, with their tank tops and Zubaz and fanny packs.</s>
 <s id="23">Why wouldn't I want to be them?</s>
 <s id="24">(Laughter) All I could think about was who are these people, and what are they like?</s>
 <s id="25">How did they become wrestlers?</s>
 <s id="26">So before the show started, I walked into this tiny arena -- more like a gymnasium -- and I asked them if I could help set up the wrestling ring.</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">"Sure, kid.</s>
  <s id="27.2">No problem."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="28">And then I pleaded with them to show me some wrestling moves.</s>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">"Sure, kid.</s>
  <s id="29.2">No problem."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">Man, they would just punch and kick me -- hard!</s>
 <s id="31">But I never complained.</s>
 <s id="32">They would come to my town for one night every couple of months that year, and then -- poof! -- next day, they were gone.</s>
 <s id="33">By the next year, they finally told me about an actual wrestling training camp that one of the wrestlers was running, and I begged my parents to sign me up.</s>
 <s id="34">Next thing I knew, I was a high school senior by day and wrestling in front of live audiences by night.</s>
 <s id="35">I had this giant poster of an alligator hanging on my bedroom wall.</s>
 <s id="36">So when I needed to come up with a wrestling name at the last minute and Jesse "The Body" Ventura was already taken -- (Laughter) I went with "Gator."</s>
 <s id="37">I also wrestled in a t-shirt and camouflage pants because that's what I had in my closet.</s>
 <s id="38">I hadn't quite figured out how to develop my own persona yet, but I was learning.</s>
 <s id="39">It was sort of like an apprenticeship.</s>
 <s id="40">But I was a wrestler.</s>
 <s id="41">And my dad would come to all my matches wearing a t-shirt that said, "Papa Gator" across the front.</s>
 <s id="42">(Laughter) And he'd brag to his friends about how his son was going to pay for his retirement someday.</s>
 <s id="43">(Laughter) And I would've.</s>
 <s id="44">Not long after I started wrestling, my dad unexpectedly passed away.</s>
 <s id="45">And as you can imagine, especially as a teenage boy, it destroyed me.</s>
 <s id="46">If you've ever lost someone, you know what a difficult time that can be.</s>
 <s id="47">Your mind -- it's not working right.</s>
 <s id="48">The whole thing is just so surreal.</s>
 <s id="49">I wanted to feel normal again, even if it was for just a second, so I went back to wrestling almost immediately.</s>
 <s id="50">Wrestling belonged to me and my dad, you know?</s>
 <s id="51">So there I was, sitting in the locker room, getting ready for a match within days of my dad passing away.</s>
 <s id="52">He was gone.</s>
 <s id="53">And sitting there alone -- it felt like I was hiding.</s>
 <s id="54">But it also felt like I needed to be there.</s>
 <s id="55">One of the wrestlers who'd been on the scene a long time knew what I was going through, and he came over to see how I was holding up.</s>
 <s id="56">I couldn't get the words out.</s>
 <s id="57">I just said, "I don't know what I'm doing."</s>
 <s id="58">And then we just sat there in silence -- just ... silence.</s>
 <s id="59">Before he got up to get ready for his own match, he gave me this piece of advice that would change the entire direction of my life.</s>
 <s id="60">He told me the best wrestlers are just themselves, but "turned up."</s>
 <s id="61">He said successful wrestlers find the traits within themselves they're the strongest at and make those the focus of who they become in the ring.</s>
 <s id="62">So there I sat -- a scared teenager who didn't know who he was or why he was even wrestling anymore.</s>
 <p id="p63">
  <s id="63.1">I looked around the locker room at some of the other wrestlers, and I thought, "I look so different.</s>
  <s id="63.2">How can I ever be like them?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="64">And then it hit me.</s>
 <s id="65">That's the moment I realized I didn't have to be like them.</s>
 <s id="66">What I did have to do was find out: What did it mean to be me?</s>
 <s id="67">What made me unique, and how could I use it to my advantage?</s>
 <s id="68">I knew I wasn't a chiseled athlete like some of these guys, but I really didn't care.</s>
 <s id="69">So the first thing I thought was, "How can I amplify something as simple as: comfortable with my own body?"</s>
 <s id="70">I didn't know.</s>
 <s id="71">And then I thought: Speedo.</s>
 <s id="72">(Laughter) (Applause) Or "trunks," as we call them in wrestling.</s>
 <s id="73">Yeah, trunks.</s>
 <s id="74">I could be this big guy who was comfortable wearing these little trunks in front of a bunch of strangers.</s>
 <s id="75">So I ditched the t-shirt and camouflage pants, and Gator's new wardrobe was born.</s>
 <s id="76">(Laughter) I was also pretty good at drawing cartoons, so I wondered if I could turn that up.</s>
 <s id="77">I could design my own wrestling costumes, so each pair of trunks would have its own unique design and color, all of them completely different -- and extremely comfortable, by the way.</s>
 <s id="78">(Laughter) And I was also the funny kid in school, believe it or not.</s>
 <s id="79">So I thought maybe I could turn that up.</s>
 <s id="80">Maybe I could go from the boy who made his buddies laugh to the man who could rally hundreds or thousands.</s>
 <s id="81">So I committed to the idea that my character wasn't going to be as scary as some of the others.</s>
 <s id="82">I'd be hilarious from the moment I walked into the arena.</s>
 <s id="83">With every wrestling match, I dug deeper.</s>
 <s id="84">I found out that I could laugh at myself.</s>
 <s id="85">So this guy would dance and sing his entrance music all the way to the ring.</s>
 <s id="86">That was dancing, by the way.</s>
 <s id="87">(Laughter) I found out that I was an OK wrestler, but I was an even better entertainer.</s>
 <s id="88">And turning myself up made me unforgettable to the fans.</s>
 <s id="89">I was trying to find those things about me -- the simple things that were special, and then ask, "How can I turn them up?"</s>
 <s id="90">Now, I knew I wanted my character to be a man's man like my dad was.</s>
 <s id="91">I thought, "What's more of a man's man than a cowboy?"</s>
 <p id="p92">
  <s id="92.1">And that's when Gator became "Cowboy" ...</s>
  <s id="92.2">Gator ...</s>
 </p>
 <s id="93">Yeah, I needed a last name.</s>
 <p id="p94">
  <s id="94.1">I thought about it until my head hurt.</s>
  <s id="94.2">I couldn't come up with anything.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="95">I'm sitting there watching TV one night, flipping through the channels, and this commercial comes on about a country singer who had just won an Entertainer of the Year award.</s>
 <s id="96">Tim McGraw.</s>
 <s id="97">He's a cool cowboy with a great last name.</s>
 <s id="98">And I liked his music.</s>
 <s id="99">It was just all part of my process.</s>
 <s id="100">But I just kept turning myself up until I became Cowboy Gator Magraw!</s>
 <s id="101">(Laughter) (Applause) And I knew that if I kept turning myself up and pushing myself harder, the opportunities would come.</s>
 <s id="102">And then it finally happened.</s>
 <s id="103">In the middle of the night, I got a phone call.</s>
 <s id="104">It was the call I wish my dad was around to hear.</s>
 <s id="105">The WWE, the biggest wrestling organization in the world, wanted me to come and be a part of Monday Night Raw.</s>
 <s id="106">Yes -- all of my hard work and miles on the road were finally paying off.</s>
 <s id="107">I got to walk down the WWE Raw entrance ramp on live television -- (Laughter) dressed up as a fake security guard -- (Laughter) to escort another wrestler to the ring.</s>
 <s id="108">(Laughter) Sure, I was disappointed I didn't get to wrestle, but very few wrestlers get any kind of call from the WWE.</s>
 <s id="109">Maybe one in a few hundred.</s>
 <s id="110">And becoming Cowboy Gator Magraw is what got me there.</s>
 <s id="111">So instead of walking away that day, I decided to turn myself up again and become the best security guard I could.</s>
 <s id="112">In fact, I did it so well, I was the only guard to get a close-up on TV that night.</s>
 <s id="113">That's a big deal, you know?</s>
 <s id="114">(Laughter) And I got to sit backstage that entire day with some of the most famous pro wrestlers in the world, some of which were heroes of mine as a kid.</s>
 <s id="115">And I got to listen to them and learn from them, and for that day, I was accepted as one of them.</s>
 <s id="116">Maybe my experience with the WWE wasn't ideal.</s>
 <s id="117">I mean, I didn't get to wrestle.</s>
 <s id="118">But it made me work harder, turning myself up louder year after year.</s>
 <s id="119">I was becoming the biggest version of myself in the ring, and other people took notice.</s>
 <s id="120">Before I knew it, I'd gone from wrestling maybe once a month in Minnesota to as often as four times a week all over the United States on the independent wrestling circuit.</s>
 <s id="121">I was literally living my dream.</s>
 <s id="122">While wrestling over the next few years, I suffered a pretty bad shoulder injury right around the same time my wife and I found out that we were expecting our first child.</s>
 <s id="123">I know what you're thinking, but believe me when I say those two events are completely unrelated.</s>
 <s id="124">(Laughter) But I needed shoulder surgery, and I wanted to be home with my family.</s>
 <s id="125">It was my turn to be a dad.</s>
 <s id="126">So on July 27, 2007, I wrestled my final match, and walked away from professional wrestling to pursue the next chapter of my life.</s>
 <s id="127">And as time passed, the strangest thing started to happen.</s>
 <s id="128">I found out that once someone has been turned up, it's pretty hard to turn them down.</s>
 <s id="129">I left the ring but Gator stayed with me, and I use the turned-up version of myself every day.</s>
 <s id="130">My beautiful wife has been with me through this entire journey.</s>
 <s id="131">And by the way -- she does not like pro wrestling.</s>
 <s id="132">(Laughter) Like, at all.</s>
 <s id="133">But she was always my biggest fan.</s>
 <s id="134">She still is.</s>
 <s id="135">She knows there's always going to be some part of Gator Magraw in here, and she wants our daughter and twin sons to discover themselves the way that I did, but probably with fewer body slams and steel chair shots to the head.</s>
 <s id="136">I mean, do you know how many times she's had to remind me not to clothesline the referees at my kid's soccer games?</s>
 <s id="137">(Laughter) I mean, it was just the one time, and my daughter was clearly fouled!</s>
 <s id="138">(Laughter) As a parent now, I've begun to realize that my dad wanted something much more valuable than a retirement fund.</s>
 <s id="139">Like most parents, he just wanted his kids to reach their fullest potential.</s>
 <s id="140">I'm trying to teach my children that turning yourself up is just not some perfect idea of how to be great, it's a way of living -- constantly looking for what makes you different and how you can amplify it for the world to see.</s>
 <s id="141">And by the way, my kids don't like wrestling, either.</s>
 <s id="142">(Laughter) But that's OK with me, because they each have their own unique talents that can be turned up just like the rest of us.</s>
 <s id="143">My one son -- he's a whiz at electronics.</s>
 <s id="144">So maybe helping him turn up makes him become the next Steve Jobs.</s>
 <s id="145">My other son and my daughter -- they're great at art, so maybe helping them turn up their gifts helps them become the next Pablo Picasso.</s>
 <s id="146">You never know what you have the ability to do until you dig.</s>
 <s id="147">And don't be afraid to put yourself out there.</s>
 <s id="148">I mean, look around.</s>
 <s id="149">They say that if you get nervous in front of an audience, just imagine them in their underwear.</s>
 <s id="150">But then I think, "Hey, I've wrestled in less."</s>
 <s id="151">(Laughter) (Applause) Look, the wrestling circus doesn't need to come to your town before you get an invitation to be the real you -- the bigger, more stunning version of yourself.</s>
 <s id="152">It doesn't even necessarily come from our parents.</s>
 <s id="153">Turning yourself up means looking inward toward our true selves and harnessing the voice that says, "Maybe, just maybe, I am more than I thought I was."</s>
 <s id="154">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="155">(Applause)</s>
</text>
