<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I come from Egypt, which is also called Umm al-Dunya, the Mother of the World.</s>
 <s id="2">It's a rich country filled with stories of rebellion, stories of civilizational triumph and downfall and the rich, religious, ethnic, cultural and linguistic diversity.</s>
 <s id="3">Growing up in such an environment, I became a strong believer in the power of storytelling.</s>
 <s id="4">As I searched for the medium with which to tell my story, I stumbled upon graphic design.</s>
 <s id="5">I would like to share with you a project of how graphic design can bring the Arabic language to life.</s>
 <s id="6">But first, let me tell you why I want to do this.</s>
 <s id="7">I believe that graphic design can change the world.</s>
 <s id="8">At least in my very own city of Cairo, it helped overthrow two separate dictators.</s>
 <s id="9">As you can see from those photos, the power and potential of graphic design as a tool for positive change is undeniably strong.</s>
 <s id="10">Egypt's 2011 revolution was also a grassroots design revolution.</s>
 <s id="11">Everyone became a creator.</s>
 <s id="12">People were the real designers and, just overnight, Cairo was flooded with posters, signage, graffiti.</s>
 <s id="13">Visual communication was the medium that spoke far louder than words when the population of over 90 million voices were suppressed for almost 30 years.</s>
 <s id="14">It was precisely this political and social suppression, coupled with decades of colonialism and miseducation that slowly eroded the significance of the Arabic script in the region.</s>
 <s id="15">All of these countries once used Arabic.</s>
 <s id="16">Now it's just the green and the blue.</s>
 <s id="17">To put it simply, the Arabic script is dying.</s>
 <s id="18">In postcolonial Arab countries functioning in an increasingly globalized world, it is a growing alarm that less and less people are using the Arabic script to communicate.</s>
 <s id="19">As I was studying my master's in Italy, I noticed myself missing Arabic.</s>
 <s id="20">I missed looking at the letters, digesting their meaning.</s>
 <s id="21">So one day, I walked into one of the biggest libraries in Italy in search of an Arabic book.</s>
 <s id="22">I was surprised to find that this is what they had under the category of "Arabic/Middle Eastern books."</s>
 <s id="23">(Laughter) Fear, terrorism and destruction.</s>
 <s id="24">One word: ISIS.</s>
 <s id="25">My heart ached that this is how we are portrayed to the world, even from a literary perspective.</s>
 <s id="26">I asked myself: Whatever happened to the world-renowned writers like Naguib Mahfouz, Khalil Gibran, iconic poets like Mutanabbi, Nizar Qabbani?</s>
 <s id="27">Think about this.</s>
 <s id="28">The cultural products of an entire region of the world, as rich, as diverse, have been deemed redundant, if not ignored altogether.</s>
 <s id="29">The cultural products of an entire region of the world have been barred from imparting any kind of real impact on global media productions and contemporary social discourse.</s>
 <s id="30">And then I reminded myself of my number one belief: design can change the world.</s>
 <s id="31">All you need is for someone to catch a glimpse of your work, feel, connect.</s>
 <s id="32">And so I started.</s>
 <s id="33">I thought about how can I stop the world from seeing us as evil, as terrorists of this planet, and start perceiving us as equals, fellow humans?</s>
 <s id="34">How can I save and honor the Arabic script and share it with other people, other cultures?</s>
 <s id="35">And then it hit me: What if I combined the two most significant symbols of innocence and Arab identity?</s>
 <s id="36">Maybe then people could resonate.</s>
 <s id="37">What's more pure, innocent and fun as LEGO?</s>
 <s id="38">It's a universal child's toy.</s>
 <s id="39">You play with them, you build with them, and with them, you imagine endless possibilities.</s>
 <s id="40">My eureka moment was to find a bilingual solution for Arabic education, because effective communication and education is the road to more tolerant communities.</s>
 <s id="41">However, the Arabic and Latin scripts do not only represent different worlds but also create technical difficulties for both Eastern and Western communities on a daily basis.</s>
 <s id="42">There are so many reasons why Arabic and Latin are different, but here are some of the main ones.</s>
 <s id="43">Yes, both use upward and downward strokes, but have completely different baselines.</s>
 <s id="44">Arabic tends to be more calligraphic and connectivity is important to the Arabic language, whose letters have to be mostly joined in order to articulate a given word.</s>
 <s id="45">It also uses an entirely different system of punctuation and diacritics.</s>
 <s id="46">But most importantly, Arabic has no capital letters.</s>
 <s id="47">Instead it has four different letter forms: initial, medial, isolated and final.</s>
 <s id="48">I want to introduce the Arabic language to young learners, foreign speakers, but most importantly help refugees integrate to their host societies through creating a bilingual learning system, a two-way flow of communication.</s>
 <s id="49">And I called it "Let's Play."</s>
 <s id="50">The idea is to simply create a fun and engaging way of learning Modern Standard Arabic through LEGO.</s>
 <p id="p51">
  <s id="51.1">These are the two words.</s>
  <s id="51.2">"Let's Play."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="52">Every colored bar marks an Arabic letter.</s>
 <s id="53">As you can see, the letter is explained in form, sound and examples of words in function, in addition to the equivalent in Latin.</s>
 <s id="54">Together, they form a fun pocket book with the 29 Arabic letters and the four different forms, plus a 400-word dictionary.</s>
 <s id="55">So this is how the page looks like.</s>
 <s id="56">You have the letter, the transliteration in Latin and the description underneath.</s>
 <s id="57">I'll take you through the process.</s>
 <s id="58">So first in my tiny studio in Florence, I built the letters.</s>
 <s id="59">I photographed each letter separately, and then I retouched every letter and chose the correct color background and typefaces to use.</s>
 <s id="60">Ultimately, I created the full letter set, which is 29 letters times four different forms.</s>
 <s id="61">That's 116 letters build just in one week.</s>
 <s id="62">I believe that information should and can be fun, portable.</s>
 <s id="63">This book is the final product, which I would eventually like to publish and translate into as many languages in the world, so that Arabic teaching and learning becomes fun, easy and accessible globally.</s>
 <s id="64">With this book, I hope to save my nation's beautiful script.</s>
 <s id="65">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="66">Working on this project was a form of visual meditation, like a Sufi dance, a prayer to a better planet.</s>
 <s id="67">One set of building blocks made two languages.</s>
 <s id="68">LEGO is just a metaphor.</s>
 <s id="69">It's because we are all made of the same building unit, is that I can see a future where the barriers between people all come tumbling down.</s>
 <s id="70">So no matter how ugly the world around us gets, or how many discouraging books on ISIS, the terrorist group, and not Isis, the ancient Egyptian goddess, continue to be published, I will keep building one colorful world.</s>
 <s id="71">Shukran, which means "thank you."</s>
 <p id="p72">
  <s id="72.1">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="72.2">Thank you so much.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="73">Thank you.</s>
</text>
