<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The idea behind the Stuxnet computer worm is actually quite simple.</s>
 <s id="2">We don't want Iran to get the bomb.</s>
 <s id="3">Their major asset for developing nuclear weapons is the Natanz uranium enrichment facility.</s>
 <s id="4">The gray boxes that you see, these are real-time control systems.</s>
 <s id="5">Now if we manage to compromise these systems that control drive speeds and valves, we can actually cause a lot of problems with the centrifuge.</s>
 <s id="6">The gray boxes don't run Windows software; they are a completely different technology.</s>
 <s id="7">But if we manage to place a good Windows virus on a notebook that is used by a maintenance engineer to configure this gray box, then we are in business.</s>
 <s id="8">And this is the plot behind Stuxnet.</s>
 <s id="9">So we start with a Windows dropper.</s>
 <s id="10">The payload goes onto the gray box, damages the centrifuge, and the Iranian nuclear program is delayed -- mission accomplished.</s>
 <s id="11">That's easy, huh?</s>
 <s id="12">I want to tell you how we found that out.</s>
 <s id="13">When we started our research on Stuxnet six months ago, it was completely unknown what the purpose of this thing was.</s>
 <s id="14">The only thing that was known is it's very, very complex on the Windows part, the dropper part, used multiple zero-day vulnerabilities.</s>
 <s id="15">And it seemed to want to do something with these gray boxes, these real-time control systems.</s>
 <s id="16">So that got our attention, and we started a lab project where we infected our environment with Stuxnet and checked this thing out.</s>
 <s id="17">And then some very funny things happened.</s>
 <s id="18">Stuxnet behaved like a lab rat that didn't like our cheese -- sniffed, but didn't want to eat.</s>
 <s id="19">Didn't make sense to me.</s>
 <s id="20">And after we experimented with different flavors of cheese, I realized, well, this is a directed attack.</s>
 <s id="21">It's completely directed.</s>
 <s id="22">The dropper is prowling actively on the gray box if a specific configuration is found, and even if the actual program code that it's trying to infect is actually running on that target.</s>
 <s id="23">And if not, Stuxnet does nothing.</s>
 <s id="24">So that really got my attention, and we started to work on this nearly around the clock, because I thought, "Well, we don't know what the target is.</s>
 <s id="25">It could be, let's say for example, a U.S. power plant, or a chemical plant in Germany.</s>
 <s id="26">So we better find out what the target is soon."</s>
 <s id="27">So we extracted and decompiled the attack code, and we discovered that it's structured in two digital bombs -- a smaller one and a bigger one.</s>
 <s id="28">And we also saw that they are very professionally engineered by people who obviously had all insider information.</s>
 <s id="29">They knew all the bits and bites that they had to attack.</s>
 <s id="30">They probably even know the shoe size of the operator.</s>
 <s id="31">So they know everything.</s>
 <s id="32">And if you have heard that the dropper of Stuxnet is complex and high-tech, let me tell you this: the payload is rocket science.</s>
 <s id="33">It's way above everything that we have ever seen before.</s>
 <s id="34">Here you see a sample of this actual attack code.</s>
 <s id="35">We are talking about -- around about 15,000 lines of code.</s>
 <s id="36">Looks pretty much like old-style assembly language.</s>
 <s id="37">And I want to tell you how we were able to make sense out of this code.</s>
 <s id="38">So what we were looking for is, first of all, system function calls, because we know what they do.</s>
 <s id="39">And then we were looking for timers and data structures and trying to relate them to the real world -- to potential real world targets.</s>
 <s id="40">So we do need target theories that we can prove or disprove.</s>
 <s id="41">In order to get target theories, we remember that it's definitely hardcore sabotage, it must be a high-value target and it is most likely located in Iran, because that's where most of the infections had been reported.</s>
 <s id="42">Now you don't find several thousand targets in that area.</s>
 <s id="43">It basically boils down to the Bushehr nuclear power plant and to the Natanz fuel enrichment plant.</s>
 <s id="44">So I told my assistant, "Get me a list of all centrifuge and power plant experts from our client base."</s>
 <s id="45">And I phoned them up and picked their brain in an effort to match their expertise with what we found in code and data.</s>
 <s id="46">And that worked pretty well.</s>
 <s id="47">So we were able to associate the small digital warhead with the rotor control.</s>
 <s id="48">The rotor is that moving part within the centrifuge, that black object that you see.</s>
 <s id="49">And if you manipulate the speed of this rotor, you are actually able to crack the rotor and eventually even have the centrifuge explode.</s>
 <s id="50">What we also saw is that the goal of the attack was really to do it slowly and creepy -- obviously in an effort to drive maintenance engineers crazy, that they would not be able to figure this out quickly.</s>
 <s id="51">The big digital warhead -- we had a shot at this by looking very closely at data and data structures.</s>
 <s id="52">So for example, the number 164 really stands out in that code; you can't overlook it.</s>
 <s id="53">I started to research scientific literature on how these centrifuges are actually built in Natanz and found they are structured in what is called a cascade, and each cascade holds 164 centrifuges.</s>
 <s id="54">So that made sense, that was a match.</s>
 <s id="55">And it even got better.</s>
 <s id="56">These centrifuges in Iran are subdivided into 15, what is called, stages.</s>
 <s id="57">And guess what we found in the attack code?</s>
 <s id="58">An almost identical structure.</s>
 <s id="59">So again, that was a real good match.</s>
 <s id="60">And this gave us very high confidence for what we were looking at.</s>
 <s id="61">Now don't get me wrong here, it didn't go like this.</s>
 <s id="62">These results have been obtained over several weeks of really hard labor.</s>
 <s id="63">And we often went into just a dead end and had to recover.</s>
 <s id="64">Anyway, so we figured out that both digital warheads were actually aiming at one and the same target, but from different angles.</s>
 <s id="65">The small warhead is taking one cascade, and spinning up the rotors and slowing them down, and the big warhead is talking to six cascades and manipulating valves.</s>
 <s id="66">So in all, we are very confident that we have actually determined what the target is.</s>
 <s id="67">It is Natanz, and it is only Natanz.</s>
 <s id="68">So we don't have to worry that other targets might be hit by Stuxnet.</s>
 <s id="69">Here's some very cool stuff that we saw -- really knocked my socks off.</s>
 <s id="70">Down there is the gray box, and on the top you see the centrifuges.</s>
 <s id="71">Now what this thing does is it intercepts the input values from sensors -- so for example, from pressure sensors and vibration sensors -- and it provides legitimate program code, which is still running during the attack, with fake input data.</s>
 <s id="72">And as a matter of fact, this fake input data is actually prerecorded by Stuxnet.</s>
 <s id="73">So it's just like from the Hollywood movies where during the heist, the observation camera is fed with prerecorded video.</s>
 <s id="74">That's cool, huh?</s>
 <s id="75">The idea here is obviously not only to fool the operators in the control room.</s>
 <s id="76">It actually is much more dangerous and aggressive.</s>
 <s id="77">The idea is to circumvent a digital safety system.</s>
 <s id="78">We need digital safety systems where a human operator could not act quick enough.</s>
 <s id="79">So for example, in a power plant, when your big steam turbine gets too over speed, you must open relief valves within a millisecond.</s>
 <s id="80">Obviously, this cannot be done by a human operator.</s>
 <s id="81">So this is where we need digital safety systems.</s>
 <s id="82">And when they are compromised, then real bad things can happen.</s>
 <s id="83">Your plant can blow up.</s>
 <s id="84">And neither your operators nor your safety system will notice it.</s>
 <s id="85">That's scary.</s>
 <s id="86">But it gets worse.</s>
 <s id="87">And this is very important, what I'm going to say.</s>
 <s id="88">Think about this: this attack is generic.</s>
 <s id="89">It doesn't have anything to do, in specifics, with centrifuges, with uranium enrichment.</s>
 <s id="90">So it would work as well, for example, in a power plant or in an automobile factory.</s>
 <s id="91">It is generic.</s>
 <s id="92">And you don't have -- as an attacker -- you don't have to deliver this payload by a USB stick, as we saw it in the case of Stuxnet.</s>
 <s id="93">You could also use conventional worm technology for spreading.</s>
 <s id="94">Just spread it as wide as possible.</s>
 <s id="95">And if you do that, what you end up with is a cyber weapon of mass destruction.</s>
 <s id="96">That's the consequence that we have to face.</s>
 <s id="97">So unfortunately, the biggest number of targets for such attacks are not in the Middle East.</s>
 <s id="98">They're in the United States and Europe and in Japan.</s>
 <s id="99">So all of the green areas, these are your target-rich environments.</s>
 <s id="100">We have to face the consequences, and we better start to prepare right now.</s>
 <s id="101">Thanks.</s>
 <s id="102">(Applause) Chris Anderson: I've got a question.</s>
 <s id="103">Ralph, it's been quite widely reported that people assume that Mossad is the main entity behind this.</s>
 <s id="104">Is that your opinion?</s>
 <s id="105">Ralph Langner: Okay, you really want to hear that?</s>
 <p id="p106">
  <s id="106.1">Yeah.</s>
  <s id="106.2">Okay.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="107">My opinion is that the Mossad is involved, but that the leading force is not Israel.</s>
 <s id="108">So the leading force behind that is the cyber superpower.</s>
 <s id="109">There is only one, and that's the United States -- fortunately, fortunately.</s>
 <s id="110">Because otherwise, our problems would even be bigger.</s>
 <p id="p111">
  <s id="111.1">CA: Thank you for scaring the living daylights out of us.</s>
  <s id="111.2">Thank you, Ralph.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="112">(Applause)</s>
</text>
