<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">You may have noticed that I'm wearing two different shoes.</s>
 <s id="2">It probably looks funny -- it definitely feels funny -- but I wanted to make a point.</s>
 <s id="3">Let's say my left shoe corresponds to a sustainable footprint, meaning we humans consume less natural resources than our planet can regenerate, and emit less carbon dioxide than our forests and oceans can reabsorb.</s>
 <s id="4">That's a stable and healthy condition.</s>
 <s id="5">Today's situation is more like my other shoe.</s>
 <s id="6">It's way oversized.</s>
 <s id="7">At the second of August in 2017, we had already consumed all resources our planet can regenerate this year.</s>
 <s id="8">This is like spending all your money until the 18th of a month and then needing a credit from the bank for the rest of the time.</s>
 <s id="9">For sure, you can do this for some months in a row, but if you don't change your behavior, sooner or later, you will run into big problems.</s>
 <s id="10">We all know the devastating effects of this excessive exploitation: global warming, rising of the sea levels, melting of the glaciers and polar ice, increasingly extreme climate patterns and more.</s>
 <s id="11">The enormity of this problem really frustrates me.</s>
 <s id="12">What frustrates me even more is that there are solutions to this, but we keep doing things like we always did.</s>
 <s id="13">Today I want to share with you how a new solar technology can contribute to a sustainable future of buildings.</s>
 <s id="14">Buildings consume about 40 percent of our total energy demand, so tackling this consumption would significantly reduce our climate emissions.</s>
 <s id="15">A building designed along sustainable principles can produce all the power it needs by itself.</s>
 <s id="16">To achieve this, you first have to reduce the consumption as much as possible, by using well-insulated walls or windows, for instance.</s>
 <s id="17">These technologies are commercially available.</s>
 <s id="18">Then you need energy for warm water and heating.</s>
 <s id="19">You can get this in a renewable way from the sun through solar-thermal installations or from the ground and air, with heat pumps.</s>
 <s id="20">All of these technologies are available.</s>
 <s id="21">Then you are left with the need for electricity.</s>
 <s id="22">In principle, there are several ways to get renewable electricity, but how many buildings do you know which have a windmill on the roof or a water power plant in the garden?</s>
 <s id="23">Probably not so many, because usually, it doesn't make sense.</s>
 <s id="24">But the sun provides abundant energy to our roofs and facades.</s>
 <s id="25">The potential to harvest this energy at our buildings' surfaces is enormous.</s>
 <s id="26">Let's take Europe as an example.</s>
 <s id="27">If you would utilize all areas which have a nice orientation to the sun and they're not overly shaded, the power generated by photovoltaics would correspond to about 30 percent of our total energy demand.</s>
 <s id="28">But today's photovoltaics have some issues.</s>
 <s id="29">They do offer a good cost-performance ratio, but they aren't really flexible in terms of their design, and this makes aesthetics a challenge.</s>
 <s id="30">People often imagine pictures like this when thinking about solar cells on buildings.</s>
 <s id="31">This may work for solar farms, but when you think of buildings, of streets, of architecture, aesthetics does matter.</s>
 <s id="32">This is the reason why we don't see many solar cells on buildings today.</s>
 <s id="33">They just don't match.</s>
 <s id="34">Our team is working on a totally different solar-cell technology, which is called organic photovoltaics or OPV.</s>
 <s id="35">The term organic describes that the material used for light absorption and charge transport are mainly based on the element carbon, and not on metals.</s>
 <s id="36">We utilize the mixture of a polymer which is set up by different repeating units, like the pearls in a pearl chain, and a small molecule which has the shape of a football and is called fullerene.</s>
 <s id="37">These two compounds are mixed and dissolved to become an ink.</s>
 <s id="38">And like ink, they can be printed with simple printing techniques like slot-die coating in a continuous roll-to-roll process on flexible substrates.</s>
 <s id="39">The resulting thin layer is the active layer, absorbing the energy of the sun.</s>
 <s id="40">This active layer is extremely effective.</s>
 <s id="41">You only need a layer thickness of 0.2 micrometers to absorb the energy of the sun.</s>
 <s id="42">This is 100 times thinner than a human hair.</s>
 <s id="43">To give you another example, take one kilogram of the basic polymer and use it to formulate the active ink.</s>
 <s id="44">With this amount of ink, you can print a solar cell the size of a complete football field.</s>
 <s id="45">So OPV is extremely material efficient, which I think is a crucial thing when talking about sustainability.</s>
 <s id="46">After the printing process, you can have a solar module which could look like this ...</s>
 <s id="47">It looks a bit like a plastic foil and actually has many of its features.</s>
 <s id="48">It's lightweight ...</s>
 <s id="49">it's bendable ...</s>
 <s id="50">and it's semi-transparent.</s>
 <s id="51">But it can harvest the energy of the sun outdoors and also of this indoor light, as you can see with this small, illuminated LED.</s>
 <s id="52">You can use it in its plastic form and take advantage of its low weight and its bendability.</s>
 <s id="53">The first is important when thinking about buildings in warmer regions.</s>
 <s id="54">Here, the roofs are not designed to bear additionally heavy loads.</s>
 <s id="55">They aren't designed for snow in winter, for instance, so heavy silicon solar cells cannot be used for light harvesting, but these lightweight solar foils are very well suited.</s>
 <s id="56">The bendability is important if you want to combine the solar cell with membrane architecture.</s>
 <s id="57">Imagine the sails of the Sydney Opera as power plants.</s>
 <s id="58">Alternatively, you can combine the solar foils with conventional construction materials like glass.</s>
 <s id="59">Many glass facade elements contain a foil anyway, to create laminated safety glass.</s>
 <s id="60">It's not a big deal to add a second foil in the production process, but then the facade element contains the solar cell and can produce electricity.</s>
 <s id="61">Besides looking nice, these integrated solar cells come along with two more important benefits.</s>
 <s id="62">Do you remember the solar cell attached to a roof I showed before?</s>
 <s id="63">In this case, we install the roof first, and as a second layer, the solar cell.</s>
 <s id="64">This is adding on the installation costs.</s>
 <s id="65">In the case of integrated solar cells, at the site of construction, only one element is installed, being at the same time the envelope of the building and the solar cell.</s>
 <s id="66">Besides saving on the installation costs, this also saves resources, because the two functions are combined into one element.</s>
 <s id="67">Earlier, I've talked about optics.</s>
 <s id="68">I really like this solar panel -- maybe you have different taste or different design needs ...</s>
 <s id="69">No problem.</s>
 <s id="70">With the printing process, the solar cell can change its shape and design very easily.</s>
 <s id="71">This will give the flexibility to architects, to planners and building owners, to integrate this electricity-producing technology as they wish.</s>
 <s id="72">I want to stress that this is not just happening in the labs.</s>
 <s id="73">It will take several more years to get to mass adoption, but we are at the edge of commercialization, meaning there are several companies out there with production lines.</s>
 <s id="74">They are scaling up their capacities, and so are we, with the inks.</s>
 <s id="75">(Shoe drops) This smaller footprint is much more comfortable.</s>
 <s id="76">(Laughter) It is the right size, the right scale.</s>
 <s id="77">We have to come back to the right scale when it comes to energy consumption.</s>
 <s id="78">And making buildings carbon-neutral is an important part here.</s>
 <s id="79">In Europe, we have the goal to decarbonize our building stock [by] 2050.</s>
 <s id="80">I hope organic photovoltaics will be a big part of this.</s>
 <s id="81">Here are a couple of examples.</s>
 <s id="82">This is the first commercial installation of fully printed organic solar cells.</s>
 <s id="83">"Commercial" means that the solar cells were printed on industrial equipment.</s>
 <s id="84">The so-called "solar trees" were part of the German pavilion at the World Expo in Milan in 2015.</s>
 <s id="85">They provided shading during the day and electricity for the lighting in the evening.</s>
 <s id="86">You may wonder why this hexagonal shape was chosen for the solar cells.</s>
 <s id="87">Easy answer: the architects wanted to have a specific shading pattern on the floor and asked for it, and then it was printed as requested.</s>
 <s id="88">Being far from a real product, this free-form installation hooked the imagination of the visiting architects much more than we expected.</s>
 <s id="89">This other application is closer to the projects and applications we are targeting.</s>
 <s id="90">In an office building in São Paulo, Brazil, semitransparent OPV panels are integrated into the glass facade, serving different needs.</s>
 <s id="91">First, they provided shading for the meeting rooms behind.</s>
 <s id="92">Second, the logo of the company is displayed in an innovative way.</s>
 <s id="93">And of course, electricity is produced, reducing the energy footprint of the building.</s>
 <s id="94">This is pointing towards a future where buildings are no longer energy consumers, but energy providers.</s>
 <s id="95">I want to see solar cells seamlessly integrated into our building shells to be both resource-efficient and a pleasure to look at.</s>
 <s id="96">For roofs, silicon solar cells will often continue to be a good solution.</s>
 <s id="97">But to exploit the potential of all facades and other areas, such as semitransparent areas, curved surfaces and shadings, I believe organic photovoltaics can offer a significant contribution, and they can be made in any form architects and planners will want them to.</s>
 <s id="98">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="99">(Applause)</s>
</text>
