<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Cigarettes aren’t good for us.</s>
 <s id="2">That’s hardly news--we’ve known about the dangers of smoking for decades.</s>
 <s id="3">But how exactly do cigarettes harm us?</s>
 <s id="4">Let’s look at what happens as their ingredients make their way through our bodies, and how we benefit physically when we finally give up smoking.</s>
 <s id="5">With each inhalation, smoke brings its more than 5,000 chemical substances into contact with the body’s tissues.</s>
 <s id="6">From the start, tar, a black, resinous material, begins to coat the teeth and gums, damaging tooth enamel, and eventually causing decay.</s>
 <s id="7">Over time, smoke also damages nerve-endings in the nose, causing loss of smell.</s>
 <s id="8">Inside the airways and lungs, smoke increases the likelihood of infections, as well as chronic diseases like bronchitis and emphysema.</s>
 <s id="9">It does this by damaging the cilia, tiny hairlike structures whose job it is to keep the airways clean.</s>
 <s id="10">It then fills the alveoli, tiny air sacs that enable the exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide between the lungs and blood.</s>
 <s id="11">A toxic gas called carbon monoxide crosses that membrane into the blood, binding to hemoglobin and displacing the oxygen it would usually have transported around the body.</s>
 <s id="12">That’s one of the reasons smoking can lead to oxygen deprivation and shortness of breath.</s>
 <s id="13">Within about 10 seconds, the bloodstream carries a stimulant called nicotine to the brain, triggering the release of dopamine and other neurotransmitters including endorphins that create the pleasurable sensations which make smoking highly addictive.</s>
 <s id="14">Nicotine and other chemicals from the cigarette simultaneously cause constriction of blood vessels and damage their delicate endothelial lining, restricting blood flow.</s>
 <s id="15">These vascular effects lead to thickening of blood vessel walls and enhance blood platelet stickiness, increasing the likelihood that clots will form and trigger heart attacks and strokes.</s>
 <s id="16">Many of the chemicals inside cigarettes can trigger dangerous mutations in the body’s DNA that make cancers form.</s>
 <s id="17">Additionally, ingredients like arsenic and nickel may disrupt the process of DNA repair, thus compromising the body’s ability to fight many cancers.</s>
 <s id="18">In fact, about one of every three cancer deaths in the United States is caused by smoking.</s>
 <s id="19">And it’s not just lung cancer.</s>
 <s id="20">Smoking can cause cancer in multiple tissues and organs, as well as damaged eyesight and weakened bones.</s>
 <s id="21">It makes it harder for women to get pregnant.</s>
 <s id="22">And in men, it can cause erectile dysfunction.</s>
 <s id="23">But for those who quit smoking, there’s a huge positive upside with almost immediate and long-lasting physical benefits.</s>
 <s id="24">Just 20 minutes after a smoker’s final cigarette, their heart rate and blood pressure begin to return to normal.</s>
 <s id="25">After 12 hours, carbon monoxide levels stabilize, increasing the blood’s oxygen-carrying capacity.</s>
 <s id="26">A day after ceasing, heart attack risk begins to decrease as blood pressure and heart rates normalize.</s>
 <s id="27">After two days, the nerve endings responsible for smell and taste start to recover.</s>
 <s id="28">Lungs become healthier after about one month, with less coughing and shortness of breath.</s>
 <s id="29">The delicate hair-like cilia in the airways and lungs start recovering within weeks, and are restored after 9 months, improving resistance to infection.</s>
 <s id="30">By the one-year anniversary of quitting, heart disease risk plummets to half as blood vessel function improves.</s>
 <s id="31">Five years in, the chance of a clot forming dramatically declines, and the risk of stroke continues to reduce.</s>
 <s id="32">After ten years, the chances of developing fatal lung cancer go down by 50%, probably because the body’s ability to repair DNA is once again restored.</s>
 <s id="33">Fifteen years in, the likelihood of developing coronary heart disease is essentially the same as that of a non-smoker.</s>
 <s id="34">There’s no point pretending this is all easy to achieve.</s>
 <s id="35">Quitting can lead to anxiety and depression, resulting from nicotine withdrawal.</s>
 <s id="36">But fortunately, such effects are usually temporary.</s>
 <s id="37">And quitting is getting easier, thanks to a growing arsenal of tools.</s>
 <s id="38">Nicotine replacement therapy through gum, skin patches, lozenges, and sprays may help wean smokers off cigarettes.</s>
 <s id="39">They work by stimulating nicotine receptors in the brain and thus preventing withdrawal symptoms, without the addition of other harmful chemicals.</s>
 <s id="40">Counselling and support groups, cognitive behavioral therapy, and moderate intensity exercise also help smokers stay cigarette-free.</s>
 <s id="41">That’s good news, since quitting puts you and your body on the path back to health.</s>
</text>
