<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I'm turning 44 next month, and I have the sense that 44 is going to be a very good year, a year of fulfillment, realization.</s>
 <s id="2">I have that sense, not because of anything particular in store for me, but because I read it would be a good year in a 1968 book by Norman Mailer.</s>
 <s id="3">"He felt his own age, forty-four ..."</s>
 <s id="4">wrote Mailer in "The Armies of the Night," "... felt as if he were a solid embodiment of bone, muscle, heart, mind, and sentiment to be a man, as if he had arrived."</s>
 <s id="5">Yes, I know Mailer wasn't writing about me.</s>
 <s id="6">But I also know that he was; for all of us -- you, me, the subject of his book, age more or less in step, proceed from birth along the same great sequence: through the wonders and confinements of childhood; the emancipations and frustrations of adolescence; the empowerments and millstones of adulthood; the recognitions and resignations of old age.</s>
 <s id="7">There are patterns to life, and they are shared.</s>
 <s id="8">As Thomas Mann wrote: "It will happen to me as to them."</s>
 <s id="9">We don't simply live these patterns.</s>
 <s id="10">We record them, too.</s>
 <s id="11">We write them down in books, where they become narratives that we can then read and recognize.</s>
 <s id="12">Books tell us who we've been, who we are, who we will be, too.</s>
 <s id="13">So they have for millennia.</s>
 <s id="14">As James Salter wrote, "Life passes into pages if it passes into anything."</s>
 <s id="15">And so six years ago, a thought leapt to mind: if life passed into pages, there were, somewhere, passages written about every age.</s>
 <s id="16">If I could find them, I could assemble them into a narrative.</s>
 <s id="17">I could assemble them into a life, a long life, a hundred-year life, the entirety of that same great sequence through which the luckiest among us pass.</s>
 <s id="18">I was then 37 years old, "an age of discretion," wrote William Trevor.</s>
 <s id="19">I was prone to meditating on time and age.</s>
 <s id="20">An illness in the family and later an injury to me had long made clear that growing old could not be assumed.</s>
 <s id="21">And besides, growing old only postponed the inevitable, time seeing through what circumstance did not.</s>
 <s id="22">It was all a bit disheartening.</s>
 <s id="23">A list, though, would last.</s>
 <s id="24">To chronicle a life year by vulnerable year would be to clasp and to ground what was fleeting, would be to provide myself and others a glimpse into the future, whether we made it there or not.</s>
 <s id="25">And when I then began to compile my list, I was quickly obsessed, searching pages and pages for ages and ages.</s>
 <s id="26">Here we were at every annual step through our first hundred years.</s>
 <s id="27">"Twenty-seven ... a time of sudden revelations," "sixty-two, ... of subtle diminishments."</s>
 <s id="28">I was mindful, of course, that such insights were relative.</s>
 <s id="29">For starters, we now live longer, and so age more slowly.</s>
 <s id="30">Christopher Isherwood used the phrase "the yellow leaf" to describe a man at 53, only one century after Lord Byron used it to describe himself at 36.</s>
 <s id="31">(Laughter) I was mindful, too, that life can swing wildly and unpredictably from one year to the next, and that people may experience the same age differently.</s>
 <s id="32">But even so, as the list coalesced, so, too, on the page, clear as the reflection in the mirror, did the life that I had been living: finding at 20 that "... one is less and less sure of who one is;" emerging at 30 from the "... wasteland of preparation into active life;" learning at 40 "... to close softly the doors to rooms [I would] not be coming back to."</s>
 <s id="33">There I was.</s>
 <s id="34">Of course, there we all are.</s>
 <s id="35">Milton Glaser, the great graphic designer whose beautiful visualizations you see here, and who today is 85 -- all those years "... a ripening and an apotheosis," wrote Nabokov -- noted to me that, like art and like color, literature helps us to remember what we've experienced.</s>
 <s id="36">And indeed, when I shared the list with my grandfather, he nodded in recognition.</s>
 <s id="37">He was then 95 and soon to die, which, wrote Roberto Bolaño, "... is the same as never dying."</s>
 <s id="38">And looking back, he said to me that, yes, Proust was right that at 22, we are sure we will not die, just as a thanatologist named Edwin Shneidman was right that at 90, we are sure we will.</s>
 <s id="39">It had happened to him, as to them.</s>
 <s id="40">Now the list is done: a hundred years.</s>
 <s id="41">And looking back over it, I know that I am not done.</s>
 <s id="42">I still have my life to live, still have many more pages to pass into.</s>
 <s id="43">And mindful of Mailer, I await 44.</s>
 <s id="44">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="45">(Applause)</s>
</text>
