<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">How much do you need to know about a person before you'd feel comfortable making a loan?</s>
 <s id="2">Suppose you wanted to lend 1,000 dollars to the person sitting two rows behind you.</s>
 <s id="3">What would you need to know about that person before you'd feel comfortable?</s>
 <s id="4">My mom came to the US from India in her late thirties.</s>
 <s id="5">She's a doctor in Brooklyn, and she often lets friends and neighbors come to see her for health services, whether they can pay right away or not.</s>
 <s id="6">I remember running into her patients with her at the grocery store or on the sidewalk, and sometimes they would come and pay her right on the spot for previous appointments.</s>
 <s id="7">She would thank them, and ask them about their families and their health.</s>
 <s id="8">She gave them credit because she trusted them.</s>
 <s id="9">Most of us are like my mom.</s>
 <s id="10">We would give credit to someone we know or that we live next to.</s>
 <s id="11">But most of us are probably not going to lend to a stranger unless we know a little something about them.</s>
 <s id="12">Banks, credit card companies and other financial institutions don't know us on a personal level, but they do have a way of trusting us, and that's through our credit scores.</s>
 <s id="13">Our credit scores have been created through an aggregation and analysis of our public consumer credit data.</s>
 <s id="14">And because of them, we have pretty much easy access to all of the goods and services that we need, from getting electricity to buying a home, or taking a risk and starting a business.</s>
 <s id="15">But ...</s>
 <s id="16">there are 2.5 billion people around the world that don't have a credit score.</s>
 <s id="17">That's a third of the world's population.</s>
 <s id="18">They don't have a score because there are no formal public records on them -- no bank accounts, no credit histories and no social security numbers.</s>
 <s id="19">And because they don't have a score, they don't have access to the credit or financial products that can improve their lives.</s>
 <s id="20">They are not trusted.</s>
 <s id="21">So we wanted to find a way to build trust and to open up financial access for these 2.5 billion.</s>
 <s id="22">So we created a mobile application that builds credit scores for them using mobile data.</s>
 <s id="23">There are currently over one billion smartphones in emerging markets.</s>
 <s id="24">And people are using them the same way that we do.</s>
 <s id="25">They're texting their friends, they're looking up directions, they're browsing the Internet and they're even making financial transactions.</s>
 <s id="26">Over time, this data is getting captured on our phones, and it provides a really rich picture of a person's life.</s>
 <s id="27">Our customers give us access to this data and we capture it through our mobile application.</s>
 <s id="28">It helps us understand the creditworthiness of people like Jenipher, a small-business owner in Nairobi, Kenya.</s>
 <s id="29">Jenipher is 65 years old, and for decades has been running a food stall in the central business district.</s>
 <s id="30">She has three sons who she put through vocational school, and she's also the leader of her local chama, or savings group.</s>
 <s id="31">Jenipher's food stall does well.</s>
 <s id="32">She makes just enough every day to cover her expenses.</s>
 <s id="33">But she's not financially secure.</s>
 <s id="34">Any emergency could force her into debt.</s>
 <s id="35">And she has no discretionary income to improve her family's way of living, for emergencies, or for investing into growing her business.</s>
 <s id="36">If Jenipher wants credit, her options are limited.</s>
 <s id="37">She could get a microloan, but she'd have to form a group that could help vouch for her credibility.</s>
 <s id="38">And even then, the loan sizes would be way too small to really have an impact on her business, averaging around 150 dollars.</s>
 <s id="39">Loan sharks are always an option, but with interest rates that are well above 300 percent, they're financially risky.</s>
 <s id="40">And because Jenipher doesn't have collateral or a credit history, she can't walk into a bank and ask for a business loan.</s>
 <s id="41">But one day, Jenipher's son convinced her to download our application and apply for a loan.</s>
 <s id="42">Jenipher answered a few questions on her phone and she gave us access to a few key data points on her device.</s>
 <s id="43">And here's what we saw.</s>
 <s id="44">So, bad news first.</s>
 <s id="45">Jenipher had a low savings balance and no previous loan history.</s>
 <s id="46">These are factors that would have thrown up a red flag to a traditional bank.</s>
 <s id="47">But there were other points in her history that showed us a much richer picture of her potential.</s>
 <s id="48">So for one, we saw that she made regular phone calls to her family in Uganda.</s>
 <s id="49">Well, it turns out that the data shows a four percent increase in repayment among people who consistently communicate with a few close contacts.</s>
 <s id="50">We could also see that though she traveled around a lot throughout the day, she actually had pretty regular travel patterns, and she was either at home or at her food stall.</s>
 <s id="51">And the data shows a six percent increase in repayment among customers who are consistent with where they spend most of their time.</s>
 <s id="52">We could also see that she communicated a lot with many different people throughout the day and that she had a strong support network.</s>
 <s id="53">Our data shows that people who communicate with more than 58 different contacts tend to be more likely to be good borrowers.</s>
 <s id="54">In Jenipher's case, she communicated with 89 different individuals, which showed a nine percent increase in her repayment.</s>
 <s id="55">These are just some of the thousands of different data points that we look at to understand a person's creditworthiness.</s>
 <s id="56">And after analyzing all of these different data points, we took the first risk and gave Jenipher a loan.</s>
 <s id="57">This is data that would not be found on a paper trail or in any formal financial record.</s>
 <s id="58">But it proves trust.</s>
 <s id="59">By looking beyond income, we can see that people in emerging markets that may seem risky and unpredictable on the surface are actually willing and have the capacity to repay.</s>
 <s id="60">Our credit scores have helped us deliver over 200,000 loans in Kenya in just the past year.</s>
 <s id="61">And our repayment rates are above 90 percent -- which, by the way, is in line with traditional bank repayment rates.</s>
 <s id="62">With something as simple as a credit score, we're giving people the power to build their own futures.</s>
 <s id="63">Our customers have used their loans for family expenses, emergencies, travel and for investing back into growing their businesses.</s>
 <s id="64">They're now building better economies and communities where more people can succeed.</s>
 <s id="65">Over the past two years of using our product, Jenipher has increased her savings by 60 percent.</s>
 <s id="66">She's also started two additional food stalls and is now making plans for her own restaurant.</s>
 <s id="67">She's applying for a small-business loan from a commercial bank, because she now has the credit history to prove she deserves it.</s>
 <s id="68">I saw Jenipher in Nairobi just last week, and she told me how excited she was to get started.</s>
 <p id="p69">
  <s id="69.1">She said, "Only my son believed I could do this.</s>
  <s id="69.2">I didn't think this was for me."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="70">She's lived her whole life believing that there was a part of the world that was closed off to her.</s>
 <s id="71">Our job now is to open the world to Jenipher and the billions like her that deserve to be trusted.</s>
 <s id="72">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="73">(Applause)</s>
</text>
