<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <p id="p1">
  <s id="1.1">Great creativity.</s>
  <s id="1.2">In times of need, we need great creativity.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p2">
  <s id="2.1">Discuss.</s>
  <s id="2.2">Great creativity is astonishingly, absurdly, rationally, irrationally powerful.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="3">Great creativity can spread tolerance, champion freedom, make education seem like a bright idea.</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) Great creativity can turn a spotlight on deprivation, or show that deprivation ain't necessarily so.</s>
 <s id="5">Great creativity can make politicians electable, or parties unelectable.</s>
 <s id="6">It can make war seem like tragedy or farce.</s>
 <s id="7">Creativity is the meme-maker that puts slogans on our t-shirts and phrases on our lips.</s>
 <s id="8">It's the pathfinder that shows us a simple road through an impenetrable moral maze.</s>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">Science is clever, but great creativity is something less knowable, more magical.</s>
  <s id="9.2">And now we need that magic.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="10">This is a time of need.</s>
 <s id="11">Our climate is changing quickly, too quickly.</s>
 <s id="12">And great creativity is needed to do what it does so well: to provoke us to think differently with dramatic creative statements.</s>
 <s id="13">To tempt us to act differently with delightful creative scraps.</s>
 <s id="14">Here is one such scrap from an initiative I'm involved in using creativity to inspire people to be greener.</s>
 <s id="15">(Video) Man: You know, rather than drive today, I'm going to walk.</s>
 <s id="16">Narrator: And so he walked, and as he walked he saw things.</s>
 <s id="17">Strange and wonderful things he would not otherwise have seen.</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">A deer with an itchy leg.</s>
  <s id="18.2">A flying motorcycle.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="19">A father and daughter separated from a bicycle by a mysterious wall.</s>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">And then he stopped.</s>
  <s id="20.2">Walking in front of him was her.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="21">The woman who as a child had skipped with him through fields and broken his heart.</s>
 <s id="22">Sure, she had aged a little.</s>
 <s id="23">In fact, she had aged a lot.</s>
 <s id="24">But he felt all his old passion for her return.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">"Ford," he called softly.</s>
  <s id="25.2">For that was her name.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">"Don't say another word, Gusty," she said, for that was his name.</s>
 <s id="27">"I know a tent next to a caravan, exactly 300 yards from here.</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">Let's go there and make love.</s>
  <s id="28.2">In the tent."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">Ford undressed.</s>
  <s id="29.2">She spread one leg, and then the other.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">Gusty entered her boldly and made love to her rhythmically while she filmed him, because she was a keen amateur pornographer.</s>
 <s id="31">The earth moved for both of them.</s>
 <s id="32">And they lived together happily ever after.</s>
 <s id="33">And all because he decided to walk that day.</s>
 <s id="34">(Applause) Andy Hobsbawm: We've got the science, we've had the debate.</s>
 <s id="35">The moral imperative is on the table.</s>
 <s id="36">Great creativity is needed to take it all, make it simple and sharp.</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">To make it connect.</s>
  <s id="37.2">To make it make people want to act.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="38">So this is a call, a plea, to the incredibly talented TED community.</s>
 <s id="39">Let's get creative against climate change.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">And let's do it soon.</s>
  <s id="40.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="41">(Applause)</s>
</text>
