<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I can't think of anyone who just has one interest in life, and that's all they want to do for the rest of their life.</s>
 <s id="2">[The Way We Work] Around 15 percent of American workers don't have traditional full-time jobs.</s>
 <s id="3">They're half-time, part-time, contract workers or temps.</s>
 <s id="4">The term "side hustle" just seems to fit with this ethos where people are putting together a few different things to make a living.</s>
 <s id="5">The word "side hustle" has its roots in popular African American newspapers.</s>
 <s id="6">In the 1920s, these papers used the word "hustle" to refer to some kind of scam.</s>
 <s id="7">By the 1950s, they were using "side hustle" to refer to legitimate work, too.</s>
 <s id="8">A side hustle is a little different than a second job.</s>
 <s id="9">A second job is about necessity.</s>
 <s id="10">While a side hustle can certainly bring in extra income, it's a little more aspirational.</s>
 <s id="11">Side hustle captures a certain kind of scrappy, entrepreneurial spirit.</s>
 <s id="12">I've interviewed more than 100 women of color on Side Hustle Pro who started successful side hustles.</s>
 <s id="13">Nailah Ellis-Brown started Ellis Island Tea out of her trunk.</s>
 <s id="14">Arsha Jones started her famous Capital City Co Mambo Sauce with one product and a PayPal link.</s>
 <s id="15">All these women are running side hustles.</s>
 <s id="16">What exactly does this tell us?</s>
 <s id="17">First, that people are seeing opportunity within their communities.</s>
 <s id="18">The goal here isn't necessarily to be the next Coca-Cola or Google.</s>
 <s id="19">Scale is great, but there's also beauty in a successful business that's built for a specific audience.</s>
 <s id="20">Second, people are increasingly interested in being their own boss.</s>
 <s id="21">Being your own boss takes discipline.</s>
 <s id="22">Self-made millionaires tend to have one big trait in common: they make decisions, hold themselves accountable and push through in the face of challenges.</s>
 <s id="23">A side hustle is a great way to try out being your own boss and see if you have those skills before fully stepping out on your own.</s>
 <s id="24">Third, people are multipassionate.</s>
 <s id="25">I want to stress that not every side hustle is started because someone hates their job.</s>
 <s id="26">Many are started simply because people are interested in lots of different things.</s>
 <s id="27">Lisa Price, who started a hair and beauty company, Carol's Daughter, was working in television production when she started side-hustling.</s>
 <s id="28">She says she actually loved her job.</s>
 <s id="29">It was the fact that she came home every day feeling good that led her to start experimenting with making fragrances and hair oils in her kitchen.</s>
 <s id="30">We're always being taught that we're supposed to know what we want to do when we grow up.</s>
 <s id="31">But when you're multipassionate, you want to dip and dabble in those different things.</s>
 <s id="32">It doesn't mean that you're not committed to your job, it just means that you have other outlets that bring you joy.</s>
 <s id="33">And that brings me to the final thing the side hustle revolution shows us: people want to make a bet on themselves.</s>
 <s id="34">Side hustles are appealing because it's easier to take that chance when you have some kind of income coming in.</s>
 <s id="35">Even if a side hustle doesn't take off, it's still an investment in yourself.</s>
 <s id="36">Forty-one percent of millennials who have a side hustle say they've shared this information with their employers.</s>
 <s id="37">They're not worried about their managers reacting negatively.</s>
 <s id="38">They recognize all the learning and growth that comes with running a side hustle.</s>
 <s id="39">Everyone is looking to feel fulfilled.</s>
 <s id="40">Thirty-eight percent of baby boomers feel some kind of regret about their career.</s>
 <s id="41">No one wants that.</s>
 <s id="42">The truth is that there are many different ways to find happiness through what we do.</s>
 <s id="43">Side hustles are about embracing that hope that we can be the ones making the decisions in how we spend our work lives.</s>
</text>
