<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Phyllis Rodriguez: We are here today because of the fact that we have what most people consider an unusual friendship.</s>
 <s id="2">And it is.</s>
 <s id="3">And yet, it feels natural to us now.</s>
 <s id="4">I first learned that my son had been in the World Trade Center on the morning of September 11th, 2001.</s>
 <s id="5">We didn't know if he had perished yet until 36 hours later.</s>
 <s id="6">At the time, we knew that it was political.</s>
 <s id="7">We were afraid of what our country was going to do in the name of our son -- my husband, Orlando, and I and our family.</s>
 <s id="8">And when I saw it -- and yet, through the shock, the terrible shock, and the terrible explosion in our lives, literally, we were not vengeful.</s>
 <s id="9">And a couple of weeks later when Zacarias Moussaoui was indicted on six counts of conspiracy to commit terrorism, and the U.S. government called for a death penalty for him, if convicted, my husband and I spoke out in opposition to that, publicly.</s>
 <s id="10">Through that and through human rights groups, we were brought together with several other victims' families.</s>
 <s id="11">When I saw Aicha in the media, coming over when her son was indicted, and I thought, "What a brave woman.</s>
 <s id="12">Someday I want to meet that woman when I'm stronger."</s>
 <s id="13">I was still in deep grief; I knew I didn't have the strength.</s>
 <s id="14">I knew I would find her someday, or we would find each other.</s>
 <s id="15">Because, when people heard that my son was a victim, I got immediate sympathy.</s>
 <s id="16">But when people learned what her son was accused of, she didn't get that sympathy.</s>
 <s id="17">But her suffering is equal to mine.</s>
 <s id="18">So we met in November 2002, and Aicha will now tell you how that came about.</s>
 <s id="19">(Translator) Aicha el-Wafi: Good afternoon, ladies and gentlemen.</s>
 <s id="20">I am the mother of Zacarias Moussaoui.</s>
 <s id="21">And I asked the Organization of Human Rights to put me in touch with the parents of the victims.</s>
 <s id="22">So they introduced me to five families.</s>
 <s id="23">And I saw Phyllis, and I watched her.</s>
 <s id="24">She was the only mother in the group.</s>
 <s id="25">The others were brothers, sisters.</s>
 <s id="26">And I saw in her eyes that she was a mother, just like me.</s>
 <s id="27">I suffered a lot as a mother.</s>
 <s id="28">I was married when I was 14.</s>
 <s id="29">I lost a child when I was 15, a second child when I was 16.</s>
 <s id="30">So the story with Zacarias was too much really.</s>
 <s id="31">And I still suffer, because my son is like he's buried alive.</s>
 <s id="32">I know she really cried for her son.</s>
 <s id="33">But she knows where he is.</s>
 <s id="34">My son, I don't know where he is.</s>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">I don't know if he's alive.</s>
  <s id="35.2">I don't know if he's tortured.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="36">I don't know what happened to him.</s>
 <s id="37">So that's why I decided to tell my story, so that my suffering is something positive for other women.</s>
 <s id="38">For all the women, all the mothers that give life, you can give back, you can change.</s>
 <s id="39">It's up to us women, because we are women, because we love our children.</s>
 <s id="40">We must be hand-in-hand and do something together.</s>
 <s id="41">It's not against women, it's for us, for us women, for our children.</s>
 <s id="42">I talk against violence, against terrorism.</s>
 <s id="43">I go to schools to talk to young, Muslim girls so they don't accept to be married against their will very young.</s>
 <s id="44">So if I can save one of the young girls, and avoid that they get married and suffer as much as I did, well this is something good.</s>
 <s id="45">This is why I'm here in front of you.</s>
 <s id="46">PR: I would like to say that I have learned so much from Aicha, starting with that day we had our very first meeting with other family members -- which was a very private meeting with security, because it was November 2002, and, frankly, we were afraid of the super-patriotism of that time in the country -- those of us family members.</s>
 <s id="47">But we were all so nervous.</s>
 <s id="48">"Why does she want to meet us?"</s>
 <s id="49">And then she was nervous.</s>
 <s id="50">"Why did we want to meet her?"</s>
 <s id="51">What did we want from each other?</s>
 <s id="52">Before we knew each others' names, or anything, we had embraced and wept.</s>
 <s id="53">Then we sat in a circle with support, with help, from people experienced in this kind of reconciliation.</s>
 <s id="54">And Aicha started, and she said, "I don't know if my son is guilty or innocent, but I want to tell you how sorry I am for what happened to your families.</s>
 <s id="55">I know what it is to suffer, and I feel that if there is a crime, a person should be tried fairly and punished."</s>
 <s id="56">But she reached out to us in that way, and it was, I'd like to say, it was an ice-breaker.</s>
 <s id="57">And what happened then is we all told our stories, and we all connected as human beings.</s>
 <s id="58">By the end of the afternoon -- it was about three hours after lunch -- we'd felt as if we'd known each other forever.</s>
 <s id="59">Now what I learned from her, is a woman, not only who could be so generous under these present circumstances and what it was then, and what was being done to her son, but the life she's had.</s>
 <s id="60">I never had met someone with such a hard life, from such a totally different culture and environment from my own.</s>
 <s id="61">And I feel that we have a special connection, which I value very much.</s>
 <s id="62">And I think it's all about being afraid of the other, but making that step and then realizing, "Hey, this wasn't so hard.</s>
 <s id="63">Who else can I meet that I don't know, or that I'm so different from?"</s>
 <s id="64">So, Aicha, do you have a couple of words for conclusion?</s>
 <s id="65">Because our time is up.</s>
 <s id="66">(Laughter) (Translator) AW: I wanted to say that we have to try to know other people, the other.</s>
 <s id="67">You have to be generous, and your hearts must be generous, your mind must be generous.</s>
 <s id="68">You must be tolerant.</s>
 <s id="69">You have to fight against violence.</s>
 <s id="70">And I hope that someday we'll all live together in peace and respecting each other.</s>
 <s id="71">This is what I wanted to say.</s>
 <s id="72">(Applause)</s>
</text>
