<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">As a result of my studies, I found a thread, that the essence of religion was compassion.</s>
 <s id="2">That every single one of the major world religions -- Judaism, Islam, Christianity, Hinduism, Buddhism and Confucianism ...</s>
 <s id="3">they all insisted on what's often known as the Golden Rule: never treat others as you would not like to be treated yourself.</s>
 <s id="4">My wish was that you would get a panel of activists and together, we would craft a charter, a brief statement reminding the world that this is what religion is about.</s>
 <s id="5">[Great big story in partnership with TED] Narrator: They had a big idea to change the world.</s>
 <s id="6">But they couldn't do it alone.</s>
 <p id="p7">
  <s id="7.1">(Voices overlapping) So, my wish ...</s>
  <s id="7.2">My wish ...</s>
  <s id="7.3">I wish ...</s>
 </p>
 <s id="8">And now, here's my wish.</s>
 <s id="9">[Torchbearers] [Ideas in action] (Shouting, fire crackling) KA: Our nations seem to be crumbling by the day.</s>
 <s id="10">And this should make us uncomfortable.</s>
 <s id="11">We've all got huge problems in our cities.</s>
 <s id="12">Problems of inequity and cruelty and violence.</s>
 <s id="13">So, what can we do?</s>
 <s id="14">What can we do to change things?</s>
 <s id="15">Every city has to be compassionate.</s>
 <s id="16">And people often ask me, what should a compassionate city be like?</s>
 <s id="17">And I said, "Well, a compassionate city should be an uncomfortable city."</s>
 <s id="18">One is Louisville, Kentucky, where the mayor, Greg Fischer, actually campaigned on the idea of compassion.</s>
 <s id="19">[Greg Fischer, mayor of Louisville, KY] Greg Fischer: When I announced compassion as a city value, it got a lot of attention.</s>
 <s id="20">A city is a platform for human potential to come alive.</s>
 <s id="21">Compassion makes individuals stronger and makes our city stronger.</s>
 <s id="22">KA: People just can't call themselves a compassionate city, unless they've got a practical course of action.</s>
 <s id="23">GF: So the questions then is, how do you bring compassion to life?</s>
 <s id="24">How do you change the culture of your city?</s>
 <s id="25">What if you could start at the beginning of a young child's life?</s>
 <s id="26">(Clock ticking) My name is Megan Clem Mattingly.</s>
 <s id="27">I am the Compassionate Schools Project teacher.</s>
 <s id="28">Compassion is a very teachable thing.</s>
 <s id="29">OK, I see a lot of friends who are looking ready.</s>
 <s id="30">Every CSP class begins with calming and focusing.</s>
 <s id="31">And then we have some sort of core practice that we're doing whether we're talking about self-awareness or empathy-building skills.</s>
 <s id="32">We are starting at the ground level, we're building that foundation for our students at age five and up, to be more compassionate citizens.</s>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">Kid: Leave me alone!</s>
  <s id="33.2">MCM: Jeremy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="34">Look at Miss Madeleine, Jeremy.</s>
 <s id="35">Jeremiah: Just go, count me out.</s>
 <s id="36">MCM: Jeremiah, we're going to try harder to get our self-regulation back, sir.</s>
 <s id="37">Jeremiah: This is the second reason I hate my life.</s>
 <s id="38">MCM: Jeremiah, come here, I need you to tell me more about that.</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">MCM: Anger or frustration, which feeling was bringing -- Anger, I can tell.</s>
  <s id="39.2">Look at your hands.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">So, before we talk about it, can you calm yourself down?</s>
 <s id="41">No? it's hard to, isn't it?</s>
 <s id="42">Can you try to make your hands look like mine?</s>
 <s id="43">Look.</s>
 <s id="44">Can you try to let go of that?</s>
 <s id="45">Look at your face, I see a smile there.</s>
 <s id="46">You're trying real hard to hang on to that anger.</s>
 <s id="47">I see every day these changes happening in these students.</s>
 <s id="48">And I have all the hope in the world that this project will change our education.</s>
 <s id="49">GF: We define compassion as respect for each and every one of our citizens so that their human potential is flourishing, thriving.</s>
 <s id="50">(Many voices) Grant me the serenity to accept the things that I cannot change, the courage to change the things that I can and the wisdom to know the difference, just for today.</s>
 <s id="51">Keep coming back, it works.</s>
 <s id="52">GF: Hotel Louisville is a great example of how to think about a whole system of getting a person back on track.</s>
 <s id="53">So it's a shelter for women and their families, but it's also an operating hotel.</s>
 <s id="54">Cynthia Brown: Hotel Louisville was not just a women's rehab facility, it is a workforce program.</s>
 <s id="55">We run the hotel, we do all the jobs here.</s>
 <s id="56">Every job that one of us has has their own individual skills.</s>
 <s id="57">It gets us a sense of responsibility, because we can put this on our resumes when we leave.</s>
 <s id="58">I think the compassion really comes from the girls that are in the rehab because we depend on each other a lot.</s>
 <s id="59">We need each other.</s>
 <s id="60">(Overlapping voices) If I was not here at Hotel Louisville, I would be sitting in jail, doing my time.</s>
 <s id="61">I was given that chance.</s>
 <s id="62">And I just -- I want to live, I want to live life.</s>
 <s id="63">[Remind yourself: You can do this You are a good person] GF: It lifts us all up to say, this is the kind of city we are, and this is the kind of city we aspire to be.</s>
 <s id="64">And that any way we can help other cities and take us to even greater heights is what we want to do.</s>
 <s id="65">It's this ripple effect; we're not perfect as a city, but boy, we're working to be better every day.</s>
 <s id="66">KA: Here you have a city which is doing great things with compassion.</s>
 <s id="67">Cities and mayors are going to play an important role as leaders of the future.</s>
 <s id="68">I'd like to see a thousand compassionate cities in the next decade that remind the rest of the world what our duty is.</s>
 <s id="69">Always treat all others as you'd like to be treated yourself.</s>
 <s id="70">[Share and sign the Charter for Compassion] [CharterForCompassion.org]</s>
</text>
