<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The theme of my talk today is, "Be an artist, right now."</s>
 <s id="2">Most people, when this subject is brought up, get tense and resist it: "Art doesn't feed me, and right now I'm busy.</s>
 <p id="p3">
  <s id="3.1">I have to go to school, get a job, send my kids to lessons ... "</s>
  <s id="3.2">You think, "I'm too busy.</s>
  <s id="3.3">I don't have time for art."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="4">There are hundreds of reasons why we can't be artists right now.</s>
 <s id="5">Don't they just pop into your head?</s>
 <s id="6">There are so many reasons why we can't be, indeed, we're not sure why we should be.</s>
 <s id="7">We don't know why we should be artists, but we have many reasons why we can't be.</s>
 <s id="8">Why do people instantly resist the idea of associating themselves with art?</s>
 <s id="9">Perhaps you think art is for the greatly gifted or for the thoroughly and professionally trained.</s>
 <s id="10">And some of you may think you've strayed too far from art.</s>
 <s id="11">Well you might have, but I don't think so.</s>
 <s id="12">This is the theme of my talk today.</s>
 <s id="13">We are all born artists.</s>
 <s id="14">If you have kids, you know what I mean.</s>
 <s id="15">Almost everything kids do is art.</s>
 <s id="16">They draw with crayons on the wall.</s>
 <s id="17">They dance to Son Dam Bi's dance on TV, but you can't even call it Son Dam Bi's dance -- it becomes the kids' own dance.</s>
 <s id="18">So they dance a strange dance and inflict their singing on everyone.</s>
 <s id="19">Perhaps their art is something only their parents can bear, and because they practice such art all day long, people honestly get a little tired around kids.</s>
 <s id="20">Kids will sometimes perform monodramas -- playing house is indeed a monodrama or a play.</s>
 <s id="21">And some kids, when they get a bit older, start to lie.</s>
 <s id="22">Usually parents remember the very first time their kid lies.</s>
 <s id="23">They're shocked.</s>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">"Now you're showing your true colors," Mom says.</s>
  <s id="24.2">She thinks, "Why does he take after his dad?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="25">She questions him, "What kind of a person are you going to be?"</s>
 <s id="26">But you shouldn't worry.</s>
 <s id="27">The moment kids start to lie is the moment storytelling begins.</s>
 <s id="28">They are talking about things they didn't see.</s>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">It's amazing.</s>
  <s id="29.2">It's a wonderful moment.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">Parents should celebrate.</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">"Hurray!</s>
  <s id="31.2">My boy finally started to lie!"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">All right!</s>
  <s id="32.2">It calls for celebration.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">For example, a kid says, "Mom, guess what?</s>
  <s id="33.2">I met an alien on my way home."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="34">Then a typical mom responds, "Stop that nonsense."</s>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">Now, an ideal parent is someone who responds like this: "Really?</s>
  <s id="35.2">An alien, huh?</s>
  <s id="35.3">What did it look like?</s>
  <s id="35.4">Did it say anything?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">Where did you meet it?"</s>
  <s id="36.2">"Um, in front of the supermarket."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="37">When you have a conversation like this, the kid has to come up with the next thing to say to be responsible for what he started.</s>
 <s id="38">Soon, a story develops.</s>
 <s id="39">Of course this is an infantile story, but thinking up one sentence after the next is the same thing a professional writer like me does.</s>
 <s id="40">In essence, they are not different.</s>
 <s id="41">Roland Barthes once said of Flaubert's novels, "Flaubert did not write a novel.</s>
 <s id="42">He merely connected one sentence after another.</s>
 <s id="43">The eros between sentences, that is the essence of Flaubert's novel."</s>
 <s id="44">That's right -- a novel, basically, is writing one sentence, then, without violating the scope of the first one, writing the next sentence.</s>
 <s id="45">And you continue to make connections.</s>
 <s id="46">Take a look at this sentence: "One morning, as Gregor Samsa was waking up from anxious dreams, he discovered that in his bed he had been changed into a monstrous verminous bug."</s>
 <s id="47">Yes, it's the first sentence of Franz Kafka's "The Metamorphosis."</s>
 <s id="48">Writing such an unjustifiable sentence and continuing in order to justify it, Kafka's work became the masterpiece of contemporary literature.</s>
 <s id="49">Kafka did not show his work to his father.</s>
 <s id="50">He was not on good terms with his father.</s>
 <s id="51">On his own, he wrote these sentences.</s>
 <s id="52">Had he shown his father, "My boy has finally lost it," he would've thought.</s>
 <p id="p53">
  <s id="53.1">And that's right.</s>
  <s id="53.2">Art is about going a little nuts and justifying the next sentence, which is not much different from what a kid does.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="54">A kid who has just started to lie is taking the first step as a storyteller.</s>
 <s id="55">Kids do art.</s>
 <s id="56">They don't get tired and they have fun doing it.</s>
 <s id="57">I was in Jeju Island a few days ago.</s>
 <s id="58">When kids are on the beach, most of them love playing in the water.</s>
 <s id="59">But some of them spend a lot of time in the sand, making mountains and seas -- well, not seas, but different things -- people and dogs, etc.</s>
 <s id="60">But parents tell them, "It will all be washed away by the waves."</s>
 <s id="61">In other words, it's useless.</s>
 <s id="62">There's no need.</s>
 <s id="63">But kids don't mind.</s>
 <s id="64">They have fun in the moment and they keep playing in the sand.</s>
 <s id="65">Kids don't do it because someone told them to.</s>
 <s id="66">They aren't told by their boss or anyone, they just do it.</s>
 <s id="67">When you were little, I bet you spent time enjoying the pleasure of primitive art.</s>
 <s id="68">When I ask my students to write about their happiest moment, many write about an early artistic experience they had as a kid.</s>
 <s id="69">Learning to play piano for the first time and playing four hands with a friend, or performing a ridiculous skit with friends looking like idiots -- things like that.</s>
 <s id="70">Or the moment you developed the first film you shot with an old camera.</s>
 <s id="71">They talk about these kinds of experiences.</s>
 <s id="72">You must have had such a moment.</s>
 <s id="73">In that moment, art makes you happy because it's not work.</s>
 <p id="p74">
  <s id="74.1">Work doesn't make you happy, does it?</s>
  <s id="74.2">Mostly it's tough.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="75">The French writer Michel Tournier has a famous saying.</s>
 <s id="76">It's a bit mischievous, actually.</s>
 <p id="p77">
  <s id="77.1">"Work is against human nature.</s>
  <s id="77.2">The proof is that it makes us tired."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p78">
  <s id="78.1">Right?</s>
  <s id="78.2">Why would work tire us if it's in our nature?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="79">Playing doesn't tire us.</s>
 <s id="80">We can play all night long.</s>
 <s id="81">If we work overnight, we should be paid for overtime.</s>
 <p id="p82">
  <s id="82.1">Why?</s>
  <s id="82.2">Because it's tiring and we feel fatigue.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p83">
  <s id="83.1">But kids, usually they do art for fun.</s>
  <s id="83.2">It's playing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="84">They don't draw to sell the work to a client or play the piano to earn money for the family.</s>
 <s id="85">Of course, there were kids who had to.</s>
 <s id="86">You know this gentleman, right?</s>
 <s id="87">He had to tour around Europe to support his family -- Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart -- but that was centuries ago, so we can make him an exception.</s>
 <s id="88">Unfortunately, at some point our art -- such a joyful pastime -- ends.</s>
 <s id="89">Kids have to go to lessons, to school, do homework and of course they take piano or ballet lessons, but they aren't fun anymore.</s>
 <p id="p90">
  <s id="90.1">You're told to do it and there's competition.</s>
  <s id="90.2">How can it be fun?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="91">If you're in elementary school and you still draw on the wall, you'll surely get in trouble with your mom.</s>
 <s id="92">Besides, if you continue to act like an artist as you get older, you'll increasingly feel pressure -- people will question your actions and ask you to act properly.</s>
 <s id="93">Here's my story: I was an eighth grader and I entered a drawing contest at school in Gyeongbokgung.</s>
 <s id="94">I was trying my best, and my teacher came around and asked me, "What are you doing?"</s>
 <s id="95">"I'm drawing diligently," I said.</s>
 <s id="96">"Why are you using only black?"</s>
 <s id="97">Indeed, I was eagerly coloring the sketchbook in black.</s>
 <s id="98">And I explained, "It's a dark night and a crow is perching on a branch."</s>
 <p id="p99">
  <s id="99.1">Then my teacher said, "Really?</s>
  <s id="99.2">Well, Young-ha, you may not be good at drawing but you have a talent for storytelling."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="100">Or so I wished.</s>
 <p id="p101">
  <s id="101.1">"Now you'll get it, you rascal!" was the response.</s>
  <s id="101.2">(Laughter) "You'll get it!" he said.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="102">You were supposed to draw the palace, the Gyeonghoeru, etc., but I was coloring everything in black, so he dragged me out of the group.</s>
 <s id="103">There were a lot of girls there as well, so I was utterly mortified.</s>
 <s id="104">None of my explanations or excuses were heard, and I really got it big time.</s>
 <s id="105">If he was an ideal teacher, he would have responded like I said before, "Young-ha may not have a talent for drawing, but he has a gift for making up stories," and he would have encouraged me.</s>
 <s id="106">But such a teacher is seldom found.</s>
 <s id="107">Later, I grew up and went to Europe's galleries -- I was a university student -- and I thought this was really unfair.</s>
 <p id="p108">
  <s id="108.1">Look what I found.</s>
  <s id="108.2">(Laughter) Works like this were hung in Basel while I was punished and stood in front of the palace with my drawing in my mouth.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p109">
  <s id="109.1">Look at this.</s>
  <s id="109.2">Doesn't it look just like wallpaper?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="110">Contemporary art, I later discovered, isn't explained by a lame story like mine.</s>
 <s id="111">No crows are brought up.</s>
 <s id="112">Most of the works have no title, Untitled.</s>
 <s id="113">Anyways, contemporary art in the 20th century is about doing something weird and filling the void with explanation and interpretation -- essentially the same as I did.</s>
 <s id="114">Of course, my work was very amateur, but let's turn to more famous examples.</s>
 <s id="115">This is Picasso's.</s>
 <p id="p116">
  <s id="116.1">He stuck handlebars into a bike seat and called it "Bull's Head."</s>
  <s id="116.2">Sounds convincing, right?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="117">Next, a urinal was placed on its side and called "Fountain".</s>
 <s id="118">That was Duchamp.</s>
 <s id="119">So filling the gap between explanation and a weird act with stories -- that's indeed what contemporary art is all about.</s>
 <s id="120">Picasso even made the statement, "I draw not what I see but what I think."</s>
 <s id="121">Yes, it means I didn't have to draw Gyeonghoeru.</s>
 <p id="p122">
  <s id="122.1">I wish I knew what Picasso said back then.</s>
  <s id="122.2">I could have argued better with my teacher.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="123">Unfortunately, the little artists within us are choked to death before we get to fight against the oppressors of art.</s>
 <s id="124">They get locked in.</s>
 <s id="125">That's our tragedy.</s>
 <s id="126">So what happens when little artists get locked in, banished or even killed?</s>
 <s id="127">Our artistic desire doesn't go away.</s>
 <s id="128">We want to express, to reveal ourselves, but with the artist dead, the artistic desire reveals itself in dark form.</s>
 <s id="129">In karaoke bars, there are always people who sing "She's Gone" or "Hotel California," miming the guitar riffs.</s>
 <p id="p130">
  <s id="130.1">Usually they sound awful.</s>
  <s id="130.2">Awful indeed.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="131">Some people turn into rockers like this.</s>
 <s id="132">Or some people dance in clubs.</s>
 <s id="133">People who would have enjoyed telling stories end up trolling on the Internet all night long.</s>
 <s id="134">That's how a writing talent reveals itself on the dark side.</s>
 <s id="135">Sometimes we see dads get more excited than their kids playing with Legos or putting together plastic robots.</s>
 <p id="p136">
  <s id="136.1">They go, "Don't touch it.</s>
  <s id="136.2">Daddy will do it for you."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="137">The kid has already lost interest and is doing something else, but the dad alone builds castles.</s>
 <s id="138">This shows the artistic impulses inside us are suppressed, not gone.</s>
 <s id="139">But they can often reveal themselves negatively, in the form of jealousy.</s>
 <p id="p140">
  <s id="140.1">You know the song "I would love to be on TV"?</s>
  <s id="140.2">Why would we love it?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="141">TV is full of people who do what we wished to do, but never got to.</s>
 <s id="142">They dance, they act -- and the more they do, they are praised.</s>
 <s id="143">So we start to envy them.</s>
 <s id="144">We become dictators with a remote and start to criticize the people on TV.</s>
 <p id="p145">
  <s id="145.1">"He just can't act."</s>
  <s id="145.2">"You call that singing?</s>
  <s id="145.3">She can't hit the notes."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="146">We easily say these sorts of things.</s>
 <s id="147">We get jealous, not because we're evil, but because we have little artists pent up inside us.</s>
 <s id="148">That's what I think.</s>
 <s id="149">What should we do then?</s>
 <s id="150">Yes, that's right.</s>
 <s id="151">Right now, we need to start our own art.</s>
 <s id="152">Right this minute, we can turn off TV, log off the Internet, get up and start to do something.</s>
 <s id="153">Where I teach students in drama school, there's a course called Dramatics.</s>
 <s id="154">In this course, all students must put on a play.</s>
 <s id="155">However, acting majors are not supposed to act.</s>
 <s id="156">They can write the play, for example, and the writers may work on stage art.</s>
 <s id="157">Likewise, stage art majors may become actors, and in this way you put on a show.</s>
 <p id="p158">
  <s id="158.1">Students at first wonder whether they can actually do it, but later they have so much fun.</s>
  <s id="158.2">I rarely see anyone who is miserable doing a play.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="159">In school, the military or even in a mental institution, once you make people do it, they enjoy it.</s>
 <s id="160">I saw this happen in the army -- many people had fun doing plays.</s>
 <s id="161">I have another experience: In my writing class, I give students a special assignment.</s>
 <s id="162">I have students like you in the class -- many who don't major in writing.</s>
 <s id="163">Some major in art or music and think they can't write.</s>
 <s id="164">So I give them blank sheets of paper and a theme.</s>
 <s id="165">It can be a simple theme: Write about the most unfortunate experience in your childhood.</s>
 <p id="p166">
  <s id="166.1">There's one condition: You must write like crazy.</s>
  <s id="166.2">Like crazy!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p167">
  <s id="167.1">I walk around and encourage them, "Come on, come on!"</s>
  <s id="167.2">They have to write like crazy for an hour or two.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="168">They only get to think for the first five minutes.</s>
 <s id="169">The reason I make them write like crazy is because when you write slowly and lots of thoughts cross your mind, the artistic devil creeps in.</s>
 <p id="p170">
  <s id="170.1">This devil will tell you hundreds of reasons why you can't write: "People will laugh at you.</s>
  <s id="170.2">This is not good writing!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p171">
  <s id="171.1">What kind of sentence is this?</s>
  <s id="171.2">Look at your handwriting!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="172">It will say a lot of things.</s>
 <s id="173">You have to run fast so the devil can't catch up.</s>
 <s id="174">The really good writing I've seen in my class was not from the assignments with a long deadline, but from the 40- to 60-minute crazy writing students did in front of me with a pencil.</s>
 <s id="175">The students go into a kind of trance.</s>
 <s id="176">After 30 or 40 minutes, they write without knowing what they're writing.</s>
 <s id="177">And in this moment, the nagging devil disappears.</s>
 <s id="178">So I can say this: It's not the hundreds of reasons why one can't be an artist, but rather, the one reason one must be that makes us artists.</s>
 <s id="179">Why we cannot be something is not important.</s>
 <s id="180">Most artists became artists because of the one reason.</s>
 <s id="181">When we put the devil in our heart to sleep and start our own art, enemies appear on the outside.</s>
 <p id="p182">
  <s id="182.1">Mostly, they have the faces of our parents.</s>
  <s id="182.2">(Laughter) Sometimes they look like our spouses, but they are not your parents or spouses.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p183">
  <s id="183.1">They are devils.</s>
  <s id="183.2">Devils.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="184">They came to Earth briefly transformed to stop you from being artistic, from becoming artists.</s>
 <s id="185">And they have a magic question.</s>
 <p id="p186">
  <s id="186.1">When we say, "I think I'll try acting.</s>
  <s id="186.2">There's a drama school in the community center," or "I'd like to learn Italian songs," they ask, "Oh, yeah?</s>
  <s id="186.3">A play?</s>
  <s id="186.4">What for?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="187">The magic question is, "What for?"</s>
 <s id="188">But art is not for anything.</s>
 <s id="189">Art is the ultimate goal.</s>
 <s id="190">It saves our souls and makes us live happily.</s>
 <s id="191">It helps us express ourselves and be happy without the help of alcohol or drugs.</s>
 <s id="192">So in response to such a pragmatic question, we need to be bold.</s>
 <p id="p193">
  <s id="193.1">"Well, just for the fun of it.</s>
  <s id="193.2">Sorry for having fun without you," is what you should say.</s>
  <s id="193.3">"I'll just go ahead and do it anyway."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="194">The ideal future I imagine is where we all have multiple identities, at least one of which is an artist.</s>
 <p id="p195">
  <s id="195.1">Once I was in New York and got in a cab.</s>
  <s id="195.2">I took the backseat, and in front of me I saw something related to a play.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="196">So I asked the driver, "What is this?"</s>
 <p id="p197">
  <s id="197.1">He said it was his profile.</s>
  <s id="197.2">"Then what are you?"</s>
  <s id="197.3">I asked.</s>
  <s id="197.4">"An actor," he said.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p198">
  <s id="198.1">He was a cabby and an actor.</s>
  <s id="198.2">I asked, "What roles do you usually play?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="199">He proudly said he played King Lear.</s>
 <s id="200">King Lear.</s>
 <s id="201">"Who is it that can tell me who I am?" -- a great line from King Lear.</s>
 <s id="202">That's the world I dream of.</s>
 <s id="203">Someone is a golfer by day and writer by night.</s>
 <s id="204">Or a cabby and an actor, a banker and a painter, secretly or publicly performing their own arts.</s>
 <s id="205">In 1990, Martha Graham, the legend of modern dance, came to Korea.</s>
 <s id="206">The great artist, then in her 90s, arrived at Gimpo Airport and a reporter asked her a typical question: "What do you have to do to become a great dancer?</s>
 <s id="207">Any advice for aspiring Korean dancers?"</s>
 <p id="p208">
  <s id="208.1">Now, she was the master.</s>
  <s id="208.2">This photo was taken in 1948 and she was already a celebrated artist.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="209">In 1990, she was asked this question.</s>
 <s id="210">And here's what she answered: "Just do it."</s>
 <p id="p211">
  <s id="211.1">Wow.</s>
  <s id="211.2">I was touched.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p212">
  <s id="212.1">Only those three words and she left the airport.</s>
  <s id="212.2">That's it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="213">So what should we do now?</s>
 <p id="p214">
  <s id="214.1">Let's be artists, right now.</s>
  <s id="214.2">Right away.</s>
  <s id="214.3">How?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="215">Just do it!</s>
 <s id="216">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="217">(Applause)</s>
</text>
