<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I've been in Afghanistan for 21 years.</s>
 <s id="2">I work for the Red Cross and I'm a physical therapist.</s>
 <s id="3">My job is to make arms and legs -- well it's not completely true.</s>
 <s id="4">We do more than that.</s>
 <s id="5">We provide the patients, the Afghan disabled, first with the physical rehabilitation then with the social reintegration.</s>
 <s id="6">It's a very logical plan, but it was not always like this.</s>
 <s id="7">For many years, we were just providing them with artificial limbs.</s>
 <s id="8">It took quite many years for the program to become what it is now.</s>
 <s id="9">Today, I would like to tell you a story, the story of a big change, and the story of the people who made this change possible.</s>
 <s id="10">I arrived in Afghanistan in 1990 to work in a hospital for war victims.</s>
 <s id="11">And then, not only for war victims, but it was for any kind of patient.</s>
 <s id="12">I was also working in the orthopedic center, we call it.</s>
 <s id="13">This is the place where we make the legs.</s>
 <s id="14">At that time I found myself in a strange situation.</s>
 <s id="15">I felt not quite ready for that job.</s>
 <s id="16">There was so much to learn.</s>
 <s id="17">There were so many things new to me.</s>
 <s id="18">But it was a terrific job.</s>
 <s id="19">But as soon as the fighting intensified, the physical rehabilitation was suspended.</s>
 <s id="20">There were many other things to do.</s>
 <s id="21">So the orthopedic center was closed because physical rehabilitation was not considered a priority.</s>
 <s id="22">It was a strange sensation.</s>
 <s id="23">Anyway, you know every time I make this speech -- it's not the first time -- but it's an emotion.</s>
 <s id="24">It's something that comes out from the past.</s>
 <s id="25">It's 21 years, but they are still all there.</s>
 <s id="26">Anyway, in 1992, the Mujahideen took all Afghanistan.</s>
 <s id="27">And the orthopedic center was closed.</s>
 <s id="28">I was assigned to work for the homeless, for the internally displaced people.</s>
 <s id="29">But one day, something happened.</s>
 <s id="30">I was coming back from a big food distribution in a mosque where tens and tens of people were squatting in terrible conditions.</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">I wanted to go home.</s>
  <s id="31.2">I was driving.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">You know, when you want to forget, you don't want to see things, so you just want to go to your room, to lock yourself inside and say, "That's enough."</s>
 <s id="33">A bomb fell not far from my car -- well, far enough, but big noise.</s>
 <s id="34">And everybody disappeared from the street.</s>
 <s id="35">The cars disappeared as well.</s>
 <s id="36">I ducked.</s>
 <s id="37">And only one figure remained in the middle of the road.</s>
 <s id="38">It was a man in a wheelchair desperately trying to move away.</s>
 <s id="39">Well I'm not a particularly brave person, I have to confess it, but I could not just ignore him.</s>
 <s id="40">So I stopped the car and I went to help.</s>
 <s id="41">The man was without legs and only with one arm.</s>
 <s id="42">Behind him there was a child, his son, red in the face in an effort to push the father.</s>
 <s id="43">So I took him into a safe place.</s>
 <s id="44">And I ask, "What are you doing out in the street in this situation?"</s>
 <s id="45">"I work," he said.</s>
 <s id="46">I wondered, what work?</s>
 <s id="47">And then I ask an even more stupid question: "Why don't you have the prostheses?</s>
 <s id="48">Why don't you have the artificial legs?"</s>
 <s id="49">And he said, "The Red Cross has closed."</s>
 <s id="50">Well without thinking, I told him "Come tomorrow.</s>
 <s id="51">We will provide you with a pair of legs."</s>
 <s id="52">The man, his name was Mahmoud, and the child, whose name was Rafi, left.</s>
 <p id="p53">
  <s id="53.1">And then I said, "Oh, my God.</s>
  <s id="53.2">What did I say?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="54">The center is closed, no staff around.</s>
 <s id="55">Maybe the machinery is broken.</s>
 <s id="56">Who is going to make the legs for him?"</s>
 <s id="57">So I hoped that he would not come.</s>
 <s id="58">This is the streets of Kabul in those days.</s>
 <s id="59">So I said, "Well I will give him some money."</s>
 <s id="60">And so the following day, I went to the orthopedic center.</s>
 <s id="61">And I spoke with a gatekeeper.</s>
 <s id="62">I was ready to tell him, "Listen, if someone such-and-such comes tomorrow, please tell him that it was a mistake.</s>
 <s id="63">Nothing can be done.</s>
 <s id="64">Give him some money."</s>
 <s id="65">But Mahmoud and his son were already there.</s>
 <s id="66">And they were not alone.</s>
 <s id="67">There were 15, maybe 20, people like him waiting.</s>
 <s id="68">And there was some staff too.</s>
 <s id="69">Among them there was my right-hand man, Najmuddin.</s>
 <s id="70">And the gatekeeper told me, "They come everyday to see if the center will open."</s>
 <s id="71">I said, "No.</s>
 <p id="p72">
  <s id="72.1">We have to go away.</s>
  <s id="72.2">We cannot stay here."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="73">They were bombing -- not very close -- but you could hear the noise of the bombs.</s>
 <s id="74">So, "We cannot stay here, it's dangerous.</s>
 <s id="75">It's not a priority."</s>
 <s id="76">But Najmuddin told me, "Listen now, we're here."</s>
 <s id="77">At least we can start repairing the prostheses, the broken prostheses of the people and maybe try to do something for people like Mahmoud."</s>
 <p id="p78">
  <s id="78.1">I said, "No, please.</s>
  <s id="78.2">We cannot do that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="79">It's really dangerous.</s>
 <s id="80">We have other things to do."</s>
 <s id="81">But they insisted.</s>
 <s id="82">When you have 20 people in front of you, looking at you and you are the one who has to decide ...</s>
 <s id="83">So we started doing some repairs.</s>
 <s id="84">Also one of the physical therapists reported that Mahmoud could be provided with a leg, but not immediately.</s>
 <s id="85">The legs were swollen and the knees were stiff, so he needed a long preparation.</s>
 <s id="86">Believe me, I was worried because I was breaking the rules.</s>
 <s id="87">I was doing something that I was not supposed to do.</s>
 <s id="88">In the evening, I went to speak with the bosses at the headquarters, and I told them -- I lied -- I told them, "Listen, we are going to start a couple of hours per day, just a few repairs."</s>
 <s id="89">Maybe some of them are here now.</s>
 <s id="90">(Laughter) So we started.</s>
 <s id="91">I was working, I was going everyday to work for the homeless.</s>
 <s id="92">And Najmuddin was staying there, doing everything and reporting on the patients.</s>
 <s id="93">He was telling me, "Patients are coming."</s>
 <s id="94">We knew that many more patients could not come, prevented by the fighting.</s>
 <s id="95">But people were coming.</s>
 <s id="96">And Mahmoud was coming every day.</s>
 <s id="97">And slowly, slowly week after week his legs were improving.</s>
 <s id="98">The stump or cast prosthesis was made, and he was starting the real physical rehabilitation.</s>
 <s id="99">He was coming every day, crossing the front line.</s>
 <s id="100">A couple of times I crossed the front line in the very place where Mahmoud and his son were crossing.</s>
 <s id="101">I tell you, it was something so sinister that I was astonished he could do it every day.</s>
 <s id="102">But finally, the great day arrived.</s>
 <s id="103">Mahmoud was going to be discharged with his new legs.</s>
 <s id="104">It was April, I remember, a very beautiful day.</s>
 <s id="105">April in Kabul is beautiful, full of roses, full of flowers.</s>
 <s id="106">We could not possibly stay indoors, with all these sandbags at the windows.</s>
 <s id="107">Very sad, dark.</s>
 <s id="108">So we chose a small spot in the garden.</s>
 <s id="109">And Mahmoud put on his prostheses, the other patients did the same, and they started practicing for the last time before being discharged.</s>
 <s id="110">Suddenly, they started fighting.</s>
 <s id="111">Two groups of Mujahideen started fighting.</s>
 <s id="112">We could hear in the air the bullets passing.</s>
 <s id="113">So we dashed, all of us, towards the shelter.</s>
 <s id="114">Mahmoud grabbed his son, I grabbed someone else.</s>
 <s id="115">Everybody was grabbing something.</s>
 <s id="116">And we ran.</s>
 <s id="117">You know, 50 meters can be a long distance if you are totally exposed, but we managed to reach the shelter.</s>
 <s id="118">Inside, all of us panting, I sat a moment and I heard Rafi telling his father, "Father, you can run faster than me."</s>
 <s id="119">(Laughter) And Mahmoud, "Of course I can.</s>
 <s id="120">I can run, and now you can go to school.</s>
 <s id="121">No need of staying with me all the day pushing my wheelchair."</s>
 <s id="122">Later on, we took them home.</s>
 <s id="123">And I will never forget Mahmoud and his son walking together pushing the empty wheelchair.</s>
 <s id="124">And then I understood, physical rehabilitation is a priority.</s>
 <s id="125">Dignity cannot wait for better times.</s>
 <s id="126">From that day on, we never closed a single day.</s>
 <s id="127">Well sometimes we were suspended for a few hours, but we never, we never closed it again.</s>
 <s id="128">I met Mahmoud one year later.</s>
 <s id="129">He was in good shape -- a bit thinner.</s>
 <s id="130">He needed to change his prostheses -- a new pair of prostheses.</s>
 <s id="131">I asked about his son.</s>
 <p id="p132">
  <s id="132.1">He told me, "He's at school.</s>
  <s id="132.2">He'd doing quite well."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="133">But I understood he wanted to tell me something.</s>
 <s id="134">So I asked him, "What is that?"</s>
 <s id="135">He was sweating.</s>
 <s id="136">He was clearly embarrassed.</s>
 <s id="137">And he was standing in front of me, his head down.</s>
 <s id="138">He said, "You have taught me to walk.</s>
 <s id="139">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="140">Now help me not to be a beggar anymore."</s>
 <s id="141">That was the job.</s>
 <s id="142">"My children are growing.</s>
 <s id="143">I feel ashamed.</s>
 <s id="144">I don't want them to be teased at school by the other students."</s>
 <s id="145">I said, "Okay."</s>
 <s id="146">I thought, how much money do I have in my pocket?</s>
 <s id="147">Just to give him some money.</s>
 <s id="148">It was the easiest way.</s>
 <s id="149">He read my mind, and he said, "I ask for a job."</s>
 <s id="150">And then he added something I will never forget for the rest of my life.</s>
 <s id="151">He said, "I am a scrap of a man, but if you help me, I'm ready to do anything, even if I have to crawl on the ground."</s>
 <s id="152">And then he sat down.</s>
 <s id="153">I sat down too with goosebumps everywhere.</s>
 <s id="154">Legless, with only one arm, illiterate, unskilled -- what job for him?</s>
 <s id="155">Najmuddin told me, "Well we have a vacancy in the carpentry shop."</s>
 <p id="p156">
  <s id="156.1">"What?"</s>
  <s id="156.2">I said, "Stop."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="157">"Well yes, we need to increase the production of feet.</s>
 <s id="158">We need to employ someone to glue and to screw the sole of the feet.</s>
 <s id="159">We need to increase the production."</s>
 <s id="160">"Excuse me?"</s>
 <s id="161">I could not believe.</s>
 <s id="162">And then he said, "No, we can modify the workbench maybe to put a special stool, a special anvil, special vice, and maybe an electric screwdriver."</s>
 <s id="163">I said, "Listen, it's insane.</s>
 <s id="164">And it's even cruel to think of anything like this.</s>
 <s id="165">That's a production line and a very fast one.</s>
 <s id="166">It's cruel to offer him a job knowing that he's going to fail."</s>
 <s id="167">But with Najmuddin, we cannot discuss.</s>
 <s id="168">So the only things I could manage to obtain was a kind of a compromise.</s>
 <s id="169">Only one week -- one week try and not a single day more.</s>
 <s id="170">One week later, Mahmoud was the fastest in the production line.</s>
 <s id="171">I told Najmuddin, "That's a trick.</s>
 <s id="172">I can't believe it."</s>
 <s id="173">The production was up 20 percent.</s>
 <s id="174">"It's a trick, it's a trick," I said.</s>
 <s id="175">And then I asked for verification.</s>
 <s id="176">It was true.</s>
 <s id="177">The comment of Najmuddin was Mahmoud has something to prove.</s>
 <s id="178">I understood that I was wrong again.</s>
 <s id="179">Mahmoud had looked taller.</s>
 <s id="180">I remember him sitting behind the workbench smiling.</s>
 <s id="181">He was a new man, taller again.</s>
 <s id="182">Of course, I understood that what made him stand tall -- yeah they were the legs, thank you very much -- but as a first step, it was the dignity.</s>
 <s id="183">He has regained his full dignity thanks to that job.</s>
 <s id="184">So of course, I understood.</s>
 <s id="185">And then we started a new policy -- a new policy completely different.</s>
 <s id="186">We decided to employ as many disabled as possible to train them in any possible job.</s>
 <s id="187">It became a policy of "positive discrimination," we call it now.</s>
 <s id="188">And you know what?</s>
 <s id="189">It's good for everybody.</s>
 <s id="190">Everybody benefits from that -- those employed, of course, because they get a job and dignity.</s>
 <s id="191">But also for the newcomers.</s>
 <s id="192">They are 7,000 every year -- people coming for the first time.</s>
 <s id="193">And you should see the faces of these people when they realize that those assisting them are like them.</s>
 <s id="194">Sometimes you see them, they look, "Oh."</s>
 <s id="195">And you see the faces.</s>
 <s id="196">And then the surprise turns into hope.</s>
 <s id="197">And it's easy for me as well to train someone who has already passed through the experience of disability.</s>
 <s id="198">Poof, they learn much faster -- the motivation, the empathy they can establish with the patient is completely different, completely.</s>
 <s id="199">Scraps of men do not exist.</s>
 <s id="200">People like Mahmoud are agents of change.</s>
 <s id="201">And when you start changing, you cannot stop.</s>
 <s id="202">So employing people, yes, but also we started programming projects of microfinance, education.</s>
 <s id="203">And when you start, you cannot stop.</s>
 <s id="204">So you do vocational training, home education for those who cannot go to school.</s>
 <s id="205">Physical therapies can be done, not only in the orthopedic center, but also in the houses of the people.</s>
 <s id="206">There is always a better way to do things.</s>
 <s id="207">That's Najmuddin, the one with the white coat.</s>
 <s id="208">Terrible Najmuddin, is that one.</s>
 <s id="209">I have learned a lot from people like Najmuddin, Mahmoud, Rafi.</s>
 <s id="210">They are my teachers.</s>
 <s id="211">I have a wish, a big wish, that this way of working, this way of thinking, is going to be implemented in other countries.</s>
 <s id="212">There are plenty of countries at war like Afghanistan.</s>
 <s id="213">It is possible and it is not difficult.</s>
 <s id="214">All we have to do is to listen to the people that we are supposed assist, to make them part of the decision-making process and then, of course, to adapt.</s>
 <s id="215">This is my big wish.</s>
 <p id="p216">
  <s id="216.1">Well don't think that the changes in Afghanistan are over; not at all.</s>
  <s id="216.2">We are going on.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="217">Recently we have just started a program, a sport program -- basketball for wheelchair users.</s>
 <s id="218">We transport the wheelchairs everywhere.</s>
 <s id="219">We have several teams in the main part of Afghanistan.</s>
 <s id="220">At the beginning, when Anajulina told me, "We would like to start it," I hesitated.</s>
 <s id="221">I said, "No," you can imagine.</s>
 <s id="222">I said, "No, no, no, no, we can't."</s>
 <s id="223">And then I asked the usual question: "Is it a priority?</s>
 <s id="224">Is it really necessary?"</s>
 <s id="225">Well now you should see me.</s>
 <s id="226">I never miss a single training session.</s>
 <s id="227">The night before a match I'm very nervous.</s>
 <s id="228">And you should see me during the match.</s>
 <s id="229">I shout like a true Italian.</s>
 <p id="p230">
  <s id="230.1">(Laughter) What's next?</s>
  <s id="230.2">What is going to be the next change?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="231">Well I don't know yet, but I'm sure Najmuddin and his friends, they have it already in mind.</s>
 <p id="p232">
  <s id="232.1">That was my story.</s>
  <s id="232.2">Thank you very much.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="233">(Applause)</s>
</text>
