<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">If you do it right, it should sound like: TICK-tat, TICK-tat, TICK-tat, TICK-tat, TICK-tat, TICK-tat.</s>
 <s id="2">If you do it wrong, it sounds like: Tick-TAT, tick-TAT, tick-TAT.</s>
 <p id="p3">
  <s id="3.1">[Small thing.</s>
  <s id="3.2">Big idea.]</s>
  <s id="3.3">[Kyra Gaunt on the Jump Rope] The jump rope is such a simple object.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="4">It can be made out of rope, a clothesline, twine.</s>
 <p id="p5">
  <s id="5.1">It has, like, a twirl on it.</s>
  <s id="5.2">(Laughs) I'm not sure how to describe that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="6">What's important is that it has a certain weight, and that they have that kind of whip sound.</s>
 <s id="7">It's not clear what the origin of the jump rope is.</s>
 <s id="8">There's some evidence that it began in ancient Egypt, Phoenicia, and then it most likely traveled to North America with Dutch settlers.</s>
 <s id="9">The rope became a big thing when women's clothes became more fitted and the pantaloon came into being.</s>
 <s id="10">And so, girls were able to jump rope because their skirts wouldn't catch the ropes.</s>
 <s id="11">Governesses used it to train their wards to jump rope.</s>
 <s id="12">Even formerly enslaved African children in the antebellum South jumped rope, too.</s>
 <s id="13">In the 1950s, in Harlem, Bronx, Brooklyn, Queens, you could see on the sidewalk, lots of girls playing with ropes.</s>
 <s id="14">Sometimes they would take two ropes and turn them as a single rope together, but you could separate them and turn them in like an eggbeater on each other.</s>
 <s id="15">The skipping rope was like a steady timeline -- tick, tick, tick, tick -- upon which you can add rhymes and rhythms and chants.</s>
 <s id="16">Those ropes created a space where we were able to contribute to something that was far greater than the neighborhood.</s>
 <s id="17">Double Dutch jump rope remains a powerful symbol of culture and identity for black women.</s>
 <s id="18">Back from the 1950s to the 1970s, girls weren't supposed to play sports.</s>
 <s id="19">Boys played baseball, basketball and football, and girls weren't allowed.</s>
 <s id="20">A lot has changed, but in that era, girls would rule the playground.</s>
 <s id="21">They'd make sure that boys weren't a part of that.</s>
 <s id="22">It's their space, it's a girl-power space.</s>
 <s id="23">It's where they get to shine.</s>
 <s id="24">But I also think it's for boys, because boys overheard those, which is why, I think, so many hip-hop artists sampled from things that they heard in black girls' game songs.</s>
 <s id="25">(Chanting) ... cold, thick shake, act like you know how to flip, Filet-O-Fish, Quarter Pounder, french fries, ice cold, thick shake, act like you know how to jump.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">Why "Country Grammar" by Nelly became a Grammy Award-winning single was because people already knew "We're going down down baby your street in a Range Rover ... "</s>
  <s id="26.2">That's the beginning of "Down down, baby, down down the roller coaster, sweet, sweet baby, I'll never let you go."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">All people who grew up in any black urban community would know that music.</s>
 <s id="28">And so, it was a ready-made hit.</s>
 <s id="29">The Double Dutch rope playing helped maintain these songs and helped maintain the chants and the gestures that go along with it, which is very natural to what I call "kinetic orality" -- word of mouth and word of body.</s>
 <s id="30">It's the thing that gets passed down over generations.</s>
 <s id="31">In some ways, the rope is the thing that helps carry it.</s>
 <s id="32">You need some object to carry memory through.</s>
 <s id="33">So, a jump rope, you can use it for all different kinds of things.</s>
 <s id="34">It crosses cultures.</s>
 <s id="35">And I think it lasted because people need to move.</s>
 <s id="36">And I think sometimes the simplest objects can make the most creative uses.</s>
</text>
