<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So my name is Taylor Wilson.</s>
 <s id="2">I am 17 years old and I am a nuclear physicist, which may be a little hard to believe, but I am.</s>
 <s id="3">And I would like to make the case that nuclear fusion will be that point, that the bridge that T. Boone Pickens talked about will get us to.</s>
 <s id="4">So nuclear fusion is our energy future.</s>
 <s id="5">And the second point, making the case that kids can really change the world.</s>
 <s id="6">So you may ask -- (Applause) You may ask me, well how do you know what our energy future is?</s>
 <s id="7">Well I built a fusion reactor when I was 14 years old.</s>
 <s id="8">That is the inside of my nuclear fusion reactor.</s>
 <s id="9">I started building this project when I was about 12 or 13 years old.</s>
 <s id="10">I decided I wanted to make a star.</s>
 <s id="11">Now most of you are probably saying, well there's no such thing as nuclear fusion.</s>
 <s id="12">I don't see any nuclear power plants with fusion energy.</s>
 <s id="13">Well it doesn't break even.</s>
 <s id="14">It doesn't produce more energy out than I put in, but it still does some pretty cool stuff.</s>
 <s id="15">And I assembled this in my garage, and it now lives in the physics department of the University of Nevada, Reno.</s>
 <s id="16">And it slams together deuterium, which is just hydrogen with an extra neutron in it.</s>
 <s id="17">So this is similar to the reaction of the proton chain that's going on inside the Sun.</s>
 <s id="18">And I'm slamming it together so hard that that hydrogen fuses together, and in the process it has some byproducts, and I utilize those byproducts.</s>
 <s id="19">So this previous year, I won the Intel International Science and Engineering Fair.</s>
 <s id="20">I developed a detector that replaces the current detectors that Homeland Security has.</s>
 <s id="21">For hundreds of dollars, I've developed a system that exceeds the sensitivity of detectors that are hundreds of thousands of dollars.</s>
 <s id="22">I built this in my garage.</s>
 <s id="23">(Applause) And I've developed a system to produce medical isotopes.</s>
 <s id="24">Instead of requiring multi-million-dollar facilities I've developed a device that, on a very small scale, can produce these isotopes.</s>
 <s id="25">So that's my fusion reactor in the background there.</s>
 <s id="26">That is me at the control panel of my fusion reactor.</s>
 <s id="27">Oh, by the way, I make yellowcake in my garage, so my nuclear program is as advanced as the Iranians.</s>
 <s id="28">So maybe I don't want to admit to that.</s>
 <s id="29">This is me at CERN in Geneva, Switzerland, which is the preeminent particle physics laboratory in the world.</s>
 <s id="30">And this is me with President Obama, showing him my Homeland Security research.</s>
 <s id="31">(Applause) So in about seven years of doing nuclear research, I started out with a dream to make a "star in a jar," a star in my garage, and I ended up meeting the president and developing things that I think can change the world, and I think other kids can too.</s>
 <s id="32">So thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="33">(Applause)</s>
</text>
