<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The evil wizard MoldeVort has been trying to kill you for years, and today it looks like he’s going to succeed.</s>
 <s id="2">But your friends are on their way, and if you can survive until they arrive, they should be able to help stop him.</s>
 <s id="3">The evil wizard’s protective charms ward off every spell you know, so in an act of desperation you throw the only object in reach at him: Pythagoras’s cursed chessboard.</s>
 <s id="4">It works, but with a catch.</s>
 <s id="5">MoldeVort starts in one corner of the 5x5 board.</s>
 <s id="6">You have a few minutes to choose four distinct positive whole numbers.</s>
 <s id="7">MoldeVort gets to say one of them, and if you can pick a square on the board whose center is exactly that distance away, the curse will force him to move to that spot.</s>
 <s id="8">Then he’ll have to choose any of the four numbers, and the process repeats until you can’t keep him inside the board with legal moves.</s>
 <s id="9">Then he’ll break free of the spell and almost certainly kill you.</s>
 <p id="p10">
  <s id="10.1">What four numbers can you choose to keep MoldeVort trapped by your spell long enough for help to arrive?</s>
  <s id="10.2">And what’s your strategy?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="11">Pause the video to figure it out yourself.</s>
 <s id="12">Answer in 3 Answer in 2 Answer in 1 The trick here is to keep MoldeVort where you want him.</s>
 <s id="13">And one way to figure out how to do that is to play out the game as MoldeVort would: always trying to escape.</s>
 <s id="14">You’re dealing with a relatively small board, so the numbers can’t be too big.</s>
 <s id="15">Let’s start by trying 1, 2, 3, 4 to see what happens.</s>
 <s id="16">Moldevort could escape those numbers in just three moves.</s>
 <s id="17">By saying 2, then 3, he would force you to let him into one of the middle points of the grid, and then a 4 would break him free.</s>
 <s id="18">But that means you’ll need to allow a number larger than 4, which is the distance from one end of a row to another.</s>
 <s id="19">How is that even possible?</s>
 <s id="20">Through diagonal moves.</s>
 <s id="21">There are, in fact, points that are distance 5 from each other, which we know thanks to the Pythagorean Theorem.</s>
 <s id="22">That states that the squares of the sides of a right triangle add up to the square of its hypotenuse.</s>
 <s id="23">One of the most famous Pythagorean triples is 3, 4, 5, and that triangle is hiding all over your chessboard.</s>
 <s id="24">So if MoldeVort was here, and he said 5, you could move him to these spaces.</s>
 <s id="25">There’s another insight that will help.</s>
 <s id="26">The board is very symmetrical: If MoldeVort is in a corner, it doesn’t really matter to you which corner it is.</s>
 <s id="27">So we can think of the corners as being functionally the same, and color them all blue.</s>
 <s id="28">Similarly, the spaces neighboring the corners behave the same as each other, and we’ll make them red.</s>
 <s id="29">Finally, the midpoints of the sides are a third type.</s>
 <s id="30">So instead of having to develop a strategy for each of the 16 spaces on the outside of the board, we can reduce the problem to just three.</s>
 <s id="31">Meanwhile, all the inside spaces are bad for us, because if MoldeVort ever reaches one, he’ll be able to say any number larger than 3 and go free.</s>
 <s id="32">Orange spaces are trouble too, since any number except 1, 2, or 4 would take him to an inside space or off the board.</s>
 <s id="33">So orange is out and you’ll need to keep him on blue and red.</s>
 <s id="34">That means 2 is bad, since it could take MoldeVort to orange on the first turn.</s>
 <s id="35">But the four other smallest numbers, 1, 3, 4, and 5, might work.</s>
 <s id="36">Let’s try them and see what happens.</s>
 <s id="37">If MoldeVort says 1, you can make him go from blue to red or red to blue.</s>
 <s id="38">And the same works if he says 3.</s>
 <s id="39">Thanks to our diagonals, this is even true if he says 5.</s>
 <s id="40">If he says 4, you can keep him on the color he’s already on by moving the length of a row or column.</s>
 <s id="41">So these four numbers work!</s>
 <s id="42">Even if your friends don’t get here right away, you’ll be able to keep the world’s most evil wizard contained for as long as you need.</s>
</text>
