<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Imagine a place so dark you can't see the nose on your face.</s>
 <s id="2">Eyes opened or closed, it's all the same because the sun never shines there.</s>
 <s id="3">Up ahead, you see a light.</s>
 <s id="4">When you creep in to investigate, a blue light flits around you.</s>
 <s id="5">"I could watch this forever," you think.</s>
 <s id="6">But you can't because the mouth of an anglerfish has just sprung open and eaten you alive.</s>
 <s id="7">You are just one of many creatures at the bottom of the ocean who learn too late to appreciate the power of bioluminescence.</s>
 <s id="8">Bioluminescence refers to the ability of certain living things to create light.</s>
 <s id="9">The human body can make stuff like ear wax and toe nails, but these organisms can turn parts of their body into glow sticks.</s>
 <s id="10">It's like nature made them ready to rave.</s>
 <s id="11">Why?</s>
 <s id="12">In one way or another, bioluminescence improves a living thing's chances of survival.</s>
 <s id="13">Take the firefly.</s>
 <s id="14">It's ability to glow green helps it attract a mate on a warm, summer night, but it's just one of many living things that can glow.</s>
 <s id="15">The railroad worm, Phrixothrix hirtus, can light up its body in two colors: red and green.</s>
 <s id="16">Would you eat something that looks like an airport runway?</s>
 <s id="17">Neither would any sensible predator.</s>
 <s id="18">The flashing lights keep the worm safe.</s>
 <s id="19">Then there's the deep sea shrimp, Acantherphyra purpurea.</s>
 <s id="20">When it feels threatened, it spews a cloud of glowing goo from its mouth.</s>
 <s id="21">Who doesn't run the other way when they've just been puked on?</s>
 <s id="22">Plus, that puke attracts bigger predators who want to eat the shrimp's enemy.</s>
 <s id="23">So what if you can't bioluminesce?</s>
 <s id="24">No problem!</s>
 <s id="25">There are other ways for living things to make bioluminescence work for them, even if they weren't born with the equipment to glow.</s>
 <s id="26">Let's revisit the anglerfish moments before it tried to eat you.</s>
 <s id="27">That glowing bait on top of its head?</s>
 <s id="28">It comes from a pocket of skin called the esca.</s>
 <s id="29">The esca holds bioluminescent bacteria.</s>
 <s id="30">The anglerfish can't glow there by itself, so it holds a sack of glowing bacteria instead.</s>
 <s id="31">Remember the firefly?</s>
 <s id="32">It can actually make itself glow.</s>
 <s id="33">Inside its lantern are two chemicals, a luciferin and a luciferase.</s>
 <s id="34">When firefly luciferase and luciferin mix together in the presence of oxygen and fuel for the cell, called ATP, the chemical reaction gives off energy in the form of light.</s>
 <s id="35">Once scientists figured out how the firefly creates its luciferase and luciferin, they used genetic engineering to make this light-producing reaction occur inside other living things that can't glow.</s>
 <s id="36">For example, they inserted the genes, or instructions, for a cell to create firefly luciferase and luciferin into a tobacco plant.</s>
 <s id="37">Once there, the tobacco plant followed the instructions slipped into its DNA and lit up like a Christmas tree.</s>
 <s id="38">The beauty of bioluminescence, unlike the light from the sun or an incandescent bulb, is that it's not hot.</s>
 <s id="39">It takes place in a range of temperatures that don't burn a living thing.</s>
 <s id="40">And unlike a glow stick, which fades out as the chemicals inside get used up, bioluminescent reactions use replenishable resources.</s>
 <s id="41">That's one reason engineers are trying to develop bioluminescent trees.</s>
 <s id="42">Just think, if planted on the side of highways, they could light the way, using only oxygen and other freely available, clean resources to run.</s>
 <s id="43">Talk about survival advantage!</s>
 <s id="44">That could help our planet live longer.</s>
 <s id="45">Do you find yourself thinking of other ways to put bioluminescence to good use?</s>
 <s id="46">That glow stick you swing at a rave may help you find a mate, but how else can bioluminescence improve your survival?</s>
 <s id="47">If you start thinking in this way, you have seen the light.</s>
</text>
