<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The discovery of an alien monolith on planet RH-1729 has scientists across the world racing to unlock its mysteries.</s>
 <s id="2">Your engineering team has developed an elegant probe to study it.</s>
 <s id="3">The probe is a collection of 27 cube modules capable of running all the scientific tests necessary to analyze the monolith.</s>
 <s id="4">The modules can self-assemble into a large 3x3x3 cube, with each individual module placed anywhere in the cube, and at any orientation.</s>
 <s id="5">It can also break itself apart and reassemble into any other orientation.</s>
 <s id="6">Now comes your job.</s>
 <s id="7">The probe will need a special protective coating for each of the extreme environments it passes through.</s>
 <s id="8">The red coating will seal it against the cold of deep space, the purple coating will protect it from the intense heat as it enters the atmosphere of RH-1729, and the green coating will shield it from the alien planet’s electric storms.</s>
 <s id="9">You can apply the coatings to each of the faces of all 27 of the cubic modules in any way you like, but each face can only take a single color coating.</s>
 <s id="10">You need to figure out how you can apply the colors so the cubes can re-assemble themselves to show only red, then purple, then green.</s>
 <s id="11">How can you apply the colored coatings to the 27 cubes so the probe will be able to make the trip?</s>
 <s id="12">Pause here if you want to figure it out yourself.</s>
 <s id="13">You can start by painting the outside of the complete cube red, since you’ll need that regardless.</s>
 <s id="14">Then you can break it into 27 pieces, and look at what you have.</s>
 <s id="15">There are 8 corner cubes, which each have three red faces, 12 edge cubes, which have two red faces, 6 face cubes, which have 1 red face, and a single center cube, which has no red faces.</s>
 <s id="16">You’ve painted a total of 54 faces red at this point, so you’ll need the same number of faces for the green and purple cubes, too.</s>
 <s id="17">When you’re done, you’ll have painted 54 faces red, 54 faces green, and 54 faces purple.</s>
 <s id="18">That’s 162 faces, which is precisely how many the cubes have in total.</s>
 <s id="19">So there’s no margin for waste.</s>
 <s id="20">If there’s any way to do this, it’ll probably be highly symmetrical.</s>
 <s id="21">Maybe you can use that to help you.</s>
 <s id="22">You look at the center cube.</s>
 <s id="23">You’d better paint it half green and half purple, so you can use it as a corner for each of those cubes, and not waste a single face.</s>
 <s id="24">There’ll need to be center cubes with no green and no purple too.</s>
 <s id="25">So you take 2 corner cubes from the red cube and paint the 3 blank faces of 1 purple, and the 3 blank faces of the other green.</s>
 <s id="26">Now you’ve got the 6 face cubes that each have 1 face painted red.</s>
 <s id="27">That leaves 5 empty faces on each.</s>
 <s id="28">You can split them in half.</s>
 <s id="29">In the first group, you paint 3 faces green and 2 faces purple; In the second group, paint 3 faces purple and 2 green.</s>
 <s id="30">Counting on symmetry, you replicate these piles again with the colors rearranged.</s>
 <s id="31">That gives you 6 with 1 green face, 6 with 1 red face, and 6 with 1 purple face.</s>
 <s id="32">Counting up what you’ve completely painted, you see 8 corner cubes in each color, 6 edge cubes in each color, 6 face cubes in each color, and 1 center cube.</s>
 <s id="33">That means you just need 6 more edge cubes in green and purple.</s>
 <s id="34">And there are exactly 6 cubes left, each with 4 empty faces.</s>
 <s id="35">You paint 2 faces of each green and 2 faces of each purple.</s>
 <s id="36">And now you have a cube that’s perfectly painted to make an incredible trip.</s>
 <s id="37">It rearranges itself to be red in deep space, purple as it enters RH-1729’s atmosphere, and green when it flies through the electric storms.</s>
 <s id="38">As it reaches the monolith, you realize you’ve achieved something humans have dreamt of for eons: alien contact.</s>
</text>
