<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">A canvas drenched in sunset hues, colors radiating like flame.</s>
 <s id="2">At first glance, this painting may appear to be an impossible, abstract image.</s>
 <s id="3">But a closer look reveals the tender stems, lush petals and velvety texture of a Canna Lily.</s>
 <s id="4">This metamorphosis of natural subjects into abstract geometry is commonplace in the work of Georgia O’Keeffe— the revolutionary American painter and sculptor.</s>
 <s id="5">But the magic behind this transformation remains just as elusive as the artist herself.</s>
 <s id="6">Born in Wisconsin in 1887, O’Keeffe spent her childhood plucking wildflowers and arranging fruits to paint.</s>
 <s id="7">At seventeen, she moved to Chicago to study at the prestigious Art Institute.</s>
 <s id="8">Her teachers trained her to faithfully reproduce reality in the conventions of European masters.</s>
 <s id="9">Although she enjoyed the solitude and precision of this work, O’Keeffe felt little personal connection to it.</s>
 <s id="10">After moving to New York, she was increasingly drawn to the clean lines, striking composition and vivid colors of Japanese art.</s>
 <s id="11">O’Keeffe soon found a teacher whose lessons inspired her to put those interests into practice.</s>
 <s id="12">Unlike her previous teachers, Arthur Wesley Dow urged his students to focus on more abstract representations of light, shape, and color.</s>
 <s id="13">These lessons manifested in O’Keeffe’s first series of abstract drawings.</s>
 <s id="14">Rendered in charcoal, they present a series of undulating lines, bold shading and billowing clouds.</s>
 <s id="15">These drawings defy easy classification— suggesting, but never quite matching, any specific natural reference.</s>
 <s id="16">Earlier European painters in the Cubist tradition had employed rigid geometry to abstract external subjects.</s>
 <s id="17">But here, O’Keeffe employed the shapes and rhythms of nature to capture her internal feelings.</s>
 <s id="18">Experiments like these would soon become a cornerstone of an artistic movement called American Modernism.</s>
 <s id="19">Although no single style defines Modernist painting, its proponents shared a desire to challenge the realist traditions that dominated art education.</s>
 <s id="20">Beginning in the late 1910’s, Modernist painting often used geometric shapes and bold colors to probe the American psyche.</s>
 <s id="21">O’Keeffe threw herself into these experiments — but she was reluctant to share her new work.</s>
 <s id="22">However, when a friend sent her charcoals to the art dealer Alfred Stieglitz, he became entranced.</s>
 <s id="23">In 1916, he arranged for a grand exhibition in New York.</s>
 <s id="24">This marked the beginning of O’Keeffe’s career as a popular artist— and a relationship that would lead to marriage in 1924.</s>
 <s id="25">Marriage didn’t diminish O’Keeffe’s taste for solitude.</s>
 <s id="26">She travelled widely to teach, and often retreated to paint for months at a time.</s>
 <s id="27">Whether she was exploring the craggy canyons of Texas, the quiet forests of South Carolina, or the sun-bleached desert of New Mexico, her creative process was based on ritual and close observation.</s>
 <s id="28">She paid meticulous attention to small details, and spent hours mixing paints to create exactly the right colors.</s>
 <s id="29">When she found the perfect hue, she’d record it in her ever-growing collection of handmade color cards.</s>
 <s id="30">O’Keeffe also experimented with perspective to celebrate objects that were often overlooked.</s>
 <s id="31">In "Rams Head with Hollyhock," she places a weathered skull and a delicate flower high above the hills below.</s>
 <s id="32">This massive skull overshadows the landscape, casting both the skeleton and the mountains in a new, eerie light.</s>
 <s id="33">The public was captivated by her unique perspective and secretive behavior.</s>
 <s id="34">She was particularly praised for her massive flower paintings, ranging from fiery poppies to ghostly calla lillies.</s>
 <s id="35">Stieglitz and other critics of the time were infatuated by Freudian psychology, and were quick to link these paintings to female genitalia.</s>
 <s id="36">But O’Keeffe dismissed such interpretations.</s>
 <s id="37">She resented the male gaze that dominated the art world, and demanded her work be respected for its emotional evocation of the natural world.</s>
 <s id="38">Eventually, O’Keeffe settled down in New Mexico, near one of her favorite artist retreats.</s>
 <s id="39">In her 70’s, her eyesight began to fail, but she continued to mine the landscape’s mysteries in new, tactile mediums.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">O’Keeffe kept creating until her death at 98, and is remembered as the “Mother of American Modernism.”</s>
  <s id="40.2">Decades on, her work retains its wild energy— and O’Keeffe her personal mystique.</s>
 </p>
</text>
