<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">At roughly 4pm on July 20, 1969, mankind was just minutes away from landing on the surface of the moon.</s>
 <s id="2">But before the astronauts began their final descent, an emergency alarm lit up.</s>
 <s id="3">Something was overloading the computer, and threatened to abort the landing.</s>
 <s id="4">Back on Earth, Margaret Hamilton held her breath.</s>
 <s id="5">She'd led the team developing the pioneering in-flight software, so she knew this mission had no room for error.</s>
 <s id="6">But the nature of this last-second emergency would soon prove her software was working exactly as planned.</s>
 <s id="7">Born 33 years earlier in Paoli, Indiana, Hamilton had always been inquisitive.</s>
 <s id="8">In college, she studied mathematics and philosophy, before taking a research position at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology to pay for grad school.</s>
 <s id="9">Here, she encountered her first computer while developing software to support research into the new field of chaos theory.</s>
 <s id="10">Next at MIT's Lincoln Laboratory, Hamilton developed software for America’s first air defense system to search for enemy aircraft.</s>
 <s id="11">But when she heard that renowned engineer Charles Draper was looking for help sending mankind to the moon, she immediately joined his team.</s>
 <s id="12">NASA looked to Draper and his group of over 400 engineers to invent the first compact digital flight computer, the Apollo Guidance Computer.</s>
 <s id="13">Using input from astronauts, this device would be responsible for guiding, navigating and controlling the spacecraft.</s>
 <s id="14">At a time when unreliable computers filled entire rooms, the AGC needed to operate without any errors, and fit in one cubic foot of space.</s>
 <s id="15">Draper divided the lab into two teams, one for designing hardware and one for developing software.</s>
 <s id="16">Hamilton led the team that built the on-board flight software for both the Command and Lunar Modules.</s>
 <s id="17">This work, for which she coined the term “software engineering," was incredibly high stakes.</s>
 <s id="18">Human lives were on the line, so every program had to be perfect.</s>
 <s id="19">Margaret’s software needed to quickly detect unexpected errors and recover from them in real time.</s>
 <s id="20">But this kind of adaptable program was difficult to build, since early software could only process jobs in a predetermined order.</s>
 <s id="21">To solve this problem, Margaret designed her program to be “asynchronous,” meaning the software's more important jobs would interrupt less important ones.</s>
 <s id="22">Her team assigned every task a unique priority to ensure that each job occurred in the correct order and at the right time— regardless of any surprises.</s>
 <s id="23">After this breakthrough, Margaret realized her software could help the astronauts work in an asynchronous environment as well.</s>
 <s id="24">She designed Priority Displays that would interrupt astronaut’s regularly scheduled tasks to warn them of emergencies.</s>
 <s id="25">The astronaut could then communicate with Mission Control to determine the best path forward.</s>
 <s id="26">This marked the first time flight software communicated directly— and asynchronously— with a pilot.</s>
 <s id="27">It was these fail safes that triggered the alarms just before the lunar landing.</s>
 <s id="28">Buzz Aldrin quickly realized his mistake— he’d inadvertently flipped the rendezvous radar switch.</s>
 <s id="29">This radar would be essential on their journey home, but here it was using up vital computational resources.</s>
 <s id="30">Fortunately, the Apollo Guidance Computer was well equipped to manage this.</s>
 <s id="31">During the overload, the software restart programs allowed only the highest priority jobs to be processed— including the programs necessary for landing.</s>
 <s id="32">The Priority Displays gave the astronauts a choice— to land or not to land.</s>
 <s id="33">With minutes to spare, Mission Control gave the order.</s>
 <s id="34">The Apollo 11 landing was about the astronauts, Mission Control, software and hardware all working together as an integrated system of systems.</s>
 <s id="35">Hamilton’s contributions were essential to the work of engineers and scientists inspired by President John F. Kennedy’s goal to reach the Moon.</s>
 <s id="36">And her life-saving work went far beyond Apollo 11— no bugs were ever found in the in-flight software for any crewed Apollo missions.</s>
 <s id="37">After her work on Apollo, Hamilton founded a company that uses its unique universal systems language to create breakthroughs for systems and software.</s>
 <s id="38">In 2003, NASA honored her achievements with the largest financial award they’d ever given to an individual.</s>
 <s id="39">And 47 years after her software first guided astronauts to the moon, Hamilton was awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom for changing the way we think about technology.</s>
</text>
