<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Sitting around a campfire, you can feel its heat, smell the woody smoke, and hear it crackle.</s>
 <s id="2">If you get too close, it burns your eyes and stings your nostrils.</s>
 <s id="3">You could stare at the bright flames forever as they twist and flicker in endless incarnations.</s>
 <s id="4">But what exactly are you looking at?</s>
 <s id="5">The flames are obviously not solid, nor are they liquid.</s>
 <s id="6">Mingling with the air, they’re more like a gas, but more visible--and more fleeting.</s>
 <s id="7">And on a scientific level, fire differs from gas because gases can exist in the same state indefinitely while fires always burn out eventually.</s>
 <s id="8">One misconception is that fire is a plasma, the fourth state of matter in which atoms are stripped of their electrons.</s>
 <s id="9">Like fire and unlike the other kinds of matter, plasmas don’t exist in a stable state on earth.</s>
 <s id="10">They only form when gas is exposed to an electric field or superheated to temperatures of thousands or tens of thousands of degrees.</s>
 <s id="11">By contrast, fuels like wood and paper burn at a few hundred degrees —far below the threshold of what's usually considered a plasma.</s>
 <s id="12">So if fire isn’t a solid, liquid, gas, or a plasma, what does that leave?</s>
 <s id="13">It turns out fire isn’t actually matter at all.</s>
 <s id="14">Instead, it’s our sensory experience of a chemical reaction called combustion.</s>
 <s id="15">In a way, fire is like the leaves changing color in fall, the smell of fruit as it ripens, or a firefly’s blinking light.</s>
 <s id="16">All of these are sensory clues that a chemical reaction is taking place.</s>
 <s id="17">What differs about fire is that it engages a lot of our senses at the same time, creating the kind of vivid experience we expect to come from a physical thing.</s>
 <s id="18">Combustion creates that sensory experience using fuel, heat, and oxygen.</s>
 <s id="19">In a campfire, when the logs are heated to their ignition temperature, the walls of their cells decompose, releasing sugars and other molecules into the air.</s>
 <s id="20">These molecules then react with airborne oxygen to create carbon dioxide and water.</s>
 <s id="21">At the same time, any trapped water in the logs vaporizes, expands, ruptures the wood around it, and escapes with a satisfying crackle.</s>
 <s id="22">As the fire heats up, the carbon dioxide and water vapor created by combustion expand.</s>
 <s id="23">Now that they’re less dense, they rise in a thinning column.</s>
 <s id="24">Gravity causes this expansion and rising, which gives flames their characteristic taper.</s>
 <s id="25">Without gravity, molecules don’t separate by density and the flames have a totally different shape.</s>
 <s id="26">We can see all of this because combustion also generates light.</s>
 <s id="27">Molecules emit light when heated, and the color of the light depends on the temperature of the molecules.</s>
 <s id="28">The hottest flames are white or blue.</s>
 <s id="29">The type of molecules in a fire can also influence flame color.</s>
 <s id="30">For instance, any unreacted carbon atoms from the logs form little clumps of soot that rise into the flames and emit the yellow-orange light we associate with a campfire.</s>
 <s id="31">Substances like copper, calcium chloride, and potassium chloride can add their own characteristic hues to the mix.</s>
 <s id="32">Besides colorful flames, fire also continues to generate heat as it burns.</s>
 <s id="33">This heat sustains the flames by keeping the fuel at or above ignition temperature.</s>
 <s id="34">Eventually, though, even the hottest fires run out of fuel or oxygen.</s>
 <s id="35">Then, those twisting flames give a final hiss and disappear with a wisp of smoke as if they were never there at all.</s>
</text>
