<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">There is nothing bigger or older than the universe.</s>
 <s id="2">The questions I would like to talk about are: one, where did we come from?</s>
 <s id="3">How did the universe come into being?</s>
 <s id="4">Are we alone in the universe?</s>
 <s id="5">Is there alien life out there?</s>
 <s id="6">What is the future of the human race?</s>
 <s id="7">Up until the 1920s, everyone thought the universe was essentially static and unchanging in time.</s>
 <s id="8">Then it was discovered that the universe was expanding.</s>
 <s id="9">Distant galaxies were moving away from us.</s>
 <s id="10">This meant they must have been closer together in the past.</s>
 <s id="11">If we extrapolate back, we find we must have all been on top of each other about 15 billion years ago.</s>
 <s id="12">This was the Big Bang, the beginning of the universe.</s>
 <s id="13">But was there anything before the Big Bang?</s>
 <s id="14">If not, what created the universe?</s>
 <s id="15">Why did the universe emerge from the Big Bang the way it did?</s>
 <s id="16">We used to think that the theory of the universe could be divided into two parts.</s>
 <s id="17">First, there were the laws like Maxwell's equations and general relativity that determined the evolution of the universe, given its state over all of space at one time.</s>
 <s id="18">And second, there was no question of the initial state of the universe.</s>
 <s id="19">We have made good progress on the first part, and now have the knowledge of the laws of evolution in all but the most extreme conditions.</s>
 <s id="20">But until recently, we have had little idea about the initial conditions for the universe.</s>
 <s id="21">However, this division into laws of evolution and initial conditions depends on time and space being separate and distinct.</s>
 <s id="22">Under extreme conditions, general relativity and quantum theory allow time to behave like another dimension of space.</s>
 <s id="23">This removes the distinction between time and space, and means the laws of evolution can also determine the initial state.</s>
 <s id="24">The universe can spontaneously create itself out of nothing.</s>
 <s id="25">Moreover, we can calculate a probability that the universe was created in different states.</s>
 <s id="26">These predictions are in excellent agreement with observations by the WMAP satellite of the cosmic microwave background, which is an imprint of the very early universe.</s>
 <s id="27">We think we have solved the mystery of creation.</s>
 <s id="28">Maybe we should patent the universe and charge everyone royalties for their existence.</s>
 <s id="29">I now turn to the second big question: are we alone, or is there other life in the universe?</s>
 <s id="30">We believe that life arose spontaneously on the Earth, so it must be possible for life to appear on other suitable planets, of which there seem to be a large number in the galaxy.</s>
 <s id="31">But we don't know how life first appeared.</s>
 <s id="32">We have two pieces of observational evidence on the probability of life appearing.</s>
 <s id="33">The first is that we have fossils of algae from 3.5 billion years ago.</s>
 <s id="34">The Earth was formed 4.6 billion years ago and was probably too hot for about the first half billion years.</s>
 <s id="35">So life appeared on Earth within half a billion years of it being possible, which is short compared to the 10-billion-year lifetime of a planet of Earth type.</s>
 <s id="36">This suggests that the probability of life appearing is reasonably high.</s>
 <s id="37">If it was very low, one would have expected it to take most of the ten billion years available.</s>
 <s id="38">On the other hand, we don't seem to have been visited by aliens.</s>
 <s id="39">I am discounting the reports of UFOs.</s>
 <s id="40">Why would they appear only to cranks and weirdos?</s>
 <s id="41">If there is a government conspiracy to suppress the reports and keep for itself the scientific knowledge the aliens bring, it seems to have been a singularly ineffective policy so far.</s>
 <s id="42">Furthermore, despite an extensive search by the SETI project, we haven't heard any alien television quiz shows.</s>
 <s id="43">This probably indicates that there are no alien civilizations at our stage of development within a radius of a few hundred light years.</s>
 <s id="44">Issuing an insurance policy against abduction by aliens seems a pretty safe bet.</s>
 <s id="45">This brings me to the last of the big questions: the future of the human race.</s>
 <s id="46">If we are the only intelligent beings in the galaxy, we should make sure we survive and continue.</s>
 <s id="47">But we are entering an increasingly dangerous period of our history.</s>
 <s id="48">Our population and our use of the finite resources of planet Earth are growing exponentially, along with our technical ability to change the environment for good or ill.</s>
 <s id="49">But our genetic code still carries the selfish and aggressive instincts that were of survival advantage in the past.</s>
 <s id="50">It will be difficult enough to avoid disaster in the next hundred years, let alone the next thousand or million.</s>
 <s id="51">Our only chance of long-term survival is not to remain inward-looking on planet Earth, but to spread out into space.</s>
 <s id="52">The answers to these big questions show that we have made remarkable progress in the last hundred years.</s>
 <s id="53">But if we want to continue beyond the next hundred years, our future is in space.</s>
 <s id="54">That is why I am in favor of manned -- or should I say, personned -- space flight.</s>
 <s id="55">All of my life I have sought to understand the universe and find answers to these questions.</s>
 <s id="56">I have been very lucky that my disability has not been a serious handicap.</s>
 <s id="57">Indeed, it has probably given me more time than most people to pursue the quest for knowledge.</s>
 <s id="58">The ultimate goal is a complete theory of the universe, and we are making good progress.</s>
 <s id="59">Thank you for listening.</s>
 <s id="60">Chris Anderson: Professor, if you had to guess either way, do you now believe that it is more likely than not that we are alone in the Milky Way, as a civilization of our level of intelligence or higher?</s>
 <s id="61">This answer took seven minutes, and really gave me an insight into the incredible act of generosity this whole talk was for TED.</s>
 <s id="62">Stephen Hawking: I think it quite likely that we are the only civilization within several hundred light years; otherwise we would have heard radio waves.</s>
 <s id="63">The alternative is that civilizations don't last very long, but destroy themselves.</s>
 <s id="64">CA: Professor Hawking, thank you for that answer.</s>
 <s id="65">We will take it as a salutary warning, I think, for the rest of our conference this week.</s>
 <s id="66">Professor, we really thank you for the extraordinary effort you made to share your questions with us today.</s>
 <s id="67">Thank you very much indeed.</s>
 <s id="68">(Applause)</s>
</text>
