<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Good morning everybody.</s>
 <s id="2">I'd like to talk about a couple of things today.</s>
 <s id="3">The first thing is water.</s>
 <s id="4">Now I see you've all been enjoying the water that's been provided for you here at the conference, over the past couple of days.</s>
 <s id="5">And I'm sure you'll feel that it's from a safe source.</s>
 <s id="6">But what if it wasn't?</s>
 <s id="7">What if it was from a source like this?</s>
 <s id="8">Then statistics would actually say that half of you would now be suffering with diarrhea.</s>
 <s id="9">I talked a lot in the past about statistics, and the provision of safe drinking water for all.</s>
 <s id="10">But they just don't seem to get through.</s>
 <s id="11">And I think I've worked out why.</s>
 <s id="12">It's because, using current thinking, the scale of the problem just seems too huge to contemplate solving.</s>
 <s id="13">So we just switch off: us, governments and aid agencies.</s>
 <s id="14">Well, today, I'd like to show you that through thinking differently, the problem has been solved.</s>
 <s id="15">By the way, since I've been speaking, another 13,000 people around the world are suffering now with diarrhea.</s>
 <s id="16">And four children have just died.</s>
 <s id="17">I invented Lifesaver bottle because I got angry.</s>
 <s id="18">I, like most of you, was sitting down, the day after Christmas in 2004, when I was watching the devastating news of the Asian tsunami as it rolled in, playing out on TV.</s>
 <s id="19">The days and weeks that followed, people fleeing to the hills, being forced to drink contaminated water or face death.</s>
 <s id="20">That really stuck with me.</s>
 <s id="21">Then, a few months later, Hurricane Katrina slammed into the side of America.</s>
 <s id="22">"Okay," I thought, "here's a First World country, let's see what they can do."</s>
 <s id="23">Day one: nothing.</s>
 <s id="24">Day two: nothing.</s>
 <s id="25">Do you know it took five days to get water to the Superdome?</s>
 <s id="26">People were shooting each other on the streets for TV sets and water.</s>
 <s id="27">That's when I decided I had to do something.</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">Now I spent a lot of time in my garage, over the next weeks and months, and also in my kitchen -- much to the dismay of my wife.</s>
  <s id="28.2">(Laughter) However, after a few failed prototypes, I finally came up with this, the Lifesaver bottle.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">Okay, now for the science bit.</s>
 <s id="30">Before Lifesaver, the best hand filters were only capable of filtering down to about 200 nanometers.</s>
 <s id="31">The smallest bacteria is about 200 nanometers.</s>
 <s id="32">So a 200-nanometer bacteria is going to get through a 200-nanometer hole.</s>
 <s id="33">The smallest virus, on the other hand, is about 25 nanometers.</s>
 <s id="34">So that's definitely going to get through those 200 nanometer holes.</s>
 <s id="35">Lifesaver pores are 15 nanometers.</s>
 <s id="36">So nothing is getting through.</s>
 <s id="37">Okay, I'm going to give you a bit of a demonstration.</s>
 <s id="38">Would you like to see that?</s>
 <s id="39">I spent all the time setting this up, so I guess I should.</s>
 <s id="40">We're in the fine city of Oxford.</s>
 <s id="41">So -- someone's done that up.</s>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">Fine city of Oxford, so what I've done is I've gone and got some water from the River Cherwell, and the River Thames, that flow through here.</s>
  <s id="42.2">And this is the water.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="43">But I got to thinking, you know, if we were in the middle of a flood zone in Bangladesh, the water wouldn't look like this.</s>
 <s id="44">So I've gone and got some stuff to add into it.</s>
 <s id="45">And this is from my pond.</s>
 <s id="46">(Sniffs) (Coughs) Have a smell of that, mister cameraman.</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">Okay.</s>
  <s id="47.2">(Laughs) Right.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="48">We're just going to pour that in there.</s>
 <s id="49">Audience: Ugh!</s>
 <p id="p50">
  <s id="50.1">Michael Pritchard: Okay.</s>
  <s id="50.2">We've got some runoff from a sewage plant farm.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="51">So I'm just going to put that in there.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">(Laughter) Put that in there.</s>
  <s id="52.2">There we go.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="53">(Laughter) And some other bits and pieces, chuck that in there.</s>
 <s id="54">And I've got a gift here from a friend of mine's rabbit.</s>
 <s id="55">So we're just going to put that in there as well.</s>
 <p id="p56">
  <s id="56.1">(Laughter) Okay.</s>
  <s id="56.2">(Laughter) Now.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="57">The Lifesaver bottle works really simply.</s>
 <s id="58">You just scoop the water up.</s>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">Today I'm going to use a jug just to show you all.</s>
  <s id="59.2">Let's get a bit of that poo in there.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p60">
  <s id="60.1">That's not dirty enough.</s>
  <s id="60.2">Let's just stir that up a little bit.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p61">
  <s id="61.1">Okay, so I'm going to take this really filthy water, and put it in here.</s>
  <s id="61.2">Do you want a drink yet?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p62">
  <s id="62.1">(Laughter) Okay.</s>
  <s id="62.2">There we go.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="63">Replace the top.</s>
 <p id="p64">
  <s id="64.1">Give it a few pumps.</s>
  <s id="64.2">Okay?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="65">That's all that's necessary.</s>
 <s id="66">Now as soon as I pop the teat, sterile drinking water is going to come out.</s>
 <p id="p67">
  <s id="67.1">I've got to be quick.</s>
  <s id="67.2">Okay, ready?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">There we go.</s>
  <s id="68.2">Mind the electrics.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="69">That is safe, sterile drinking water.</s>
 <s id="70">(Applause) Cheers.</s>
 <s id="71">(Applause) There you go Chris.</s>
 <s id="72">(Applause) What's it taste of?</s>
 <s id="73">Chris Anderson: Delicious.</s>
 <s id="74">Michael Pritchard: Okay.</s>
 <p id="p75">
  <s id="75.1">Let's see Chris's program throughout the rest of the show.</s>
  <s id="75.2">Okay?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p76">
  <s id="76.1">(Laughter) Okay.</s>
  <s id="76.2">Lifesaver bottle is used by thousands of people around the world.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="77">It'll last for 6,000 liters.</s>
 <s id="78">And when it's expired, using failsafe technology, the system will shut off, protecting the user.</s>
 <p id="p79">
  <s id="79.1">Pop the cartridge out.</s>
  <s id="79.2">Pop a new one in.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="80">It's good for another 6,000 liters.</s>
 <s id="81">So let's look at the applications.</s>
 <s id="82">Traditionally, in a crisis, what do we do?</s>
 <s id="83">We ship water.</s>
 <s id="84">Then, after a few weeks, we set up camps.</s>
 <s id="85">And people are forced to come into the camps to get their safe drinking water.</s>
 <s id="86">What happens when 20,000 people congregate in a camp?</s>
 <p id="p87">
  <s id="87.1">Diseases spread.</s>
  <s id="87.2">More resources are required.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="88">The problem just becomes self-perpetuating.</s>
 <s id="89">But by thinking differently, and shipping these, people can stay put.</s>
 <s id="90">They can make their own sterile drinking water, and start to get on with rebuilding their homes and their lives.</s>
 <s id="91">Now, it doesn't require a natural disaster for this to work.</s>
 <s id="92">Using the old thinking, of national infrastructure and pipe work, is too expensive.</s>
 <s id="93">When you run the numbers on a calculator, you run out of noughts.</s>
 <s id="94">So here is the "thinking different" bit.</s>
 <p id="p95">
  <s id="95.1">Instead of shipping water, and using man-made processes to do it, let's use Mother Nature.</s>
  <s id="95.2">She's got a fantastic system.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="96">She picks the water up from there, desalinates it, for free, transports it over there, and dumps it onto the mountains, rivers, and streams.</s>
 <p id="p97">
  <s id="97.1">And where do people live?</s>
  <s id="97.2">Near water.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p98">
  <s id="98.1">All we've go to do is make it sterile.</s>
  <s id="98.2">How do we do that?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="99">Well, we could use the Lifesaver bottle.</s>
 <s id="100">Or we could use one of these.</s>
 <s id="101">The same technology, in a jerry can.</s>
 <s id="102">This will process 25,000 liters of water; that's good enough for a family of four, for three years.</s>
 <s id="103">And how much does it cost?</s>
 <s id="104">About half a cent a day to run.</s>
 <s id="105">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="106">(Applause) So, by thinking differently, and processing water at the point of use, mothers and children no longer have to walk four hours a day to collect their water.</s>
 <s id="107">They can get it from a source nearby.</s>
 <s id="108">So with just eight billion dollars, we can hit the millennium goal's target of halving the number of people without access to safe drinking water.</s>
 <s id="109">To put that into context, The U.K. government spends about 12 billion pounds a year on foreign aid.</s>
 <s id="110">But why stop there?</s>
 <s id="111">With 20 billion dollars, everyone can have access to safe drinking water.</s>
 <s id="112">So the three-and-a-half billion people that suffer every year as a result, and the two million kids that die every year, will live.</s>
 <s id="113">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="114">(Applause)</s>
</text>
