<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Just to put everything in context, and to kind of give you a background to where I'm coming from, so that a lot of the things I'm going to say, and the things I'm going to do -- or things I'm going to tell you I've done -- you will understand exactly why and how I got motivated to be where I am.</s>
 <s id="2">I graduated high school in Cleveland, Ohio, 1975.</s>
 <s id="3">And just like my parents did when they finished studying abroad, we went back home.</s>
 <s id="4">Finished university education, got a medical degree, 1986.</s>
 <s id="5">And by the time I was an intern house officer, I could barely afford to maintain my mother's 13-year-old car -- and I was a paid doctor.</s>
 <s id="6">This brings us to why a lot of us, who are professionals, are now, as they say, in diaspora.</s>
 <s id="7">Now, are we going to make that a permanent thing, where we all get trained, and we leave, and we don't go back?</s>
 <s id="8">Perhaps not, I should certainly hope not -- because that is not my vision.</s>
 <s id="9">All right, for good measure, that's where Nigeria is on the African map, and just there is the Delta region that I'm sure everybody's heard of.</s>
 <s id="10">People getting kidnapped, where the oil comes from, the oil that sometimes I think has driven us all crazy in Nigeria.</s>
 <p id="p11">
  <s id="11.1">But, critical poverty: this slide is from a presentation I gave not that long ago.</s>
  <s id="11.2">Gapminder.org tells the story of the gap between Africa and the rest of the world in terms of health care.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="12">Very interesting.</s>
 <s id="13">How many people do you think are on that taxi?</s>
 <s id="14">And believe it or not, that is a taxi in Nigeria.</s>
 <s id="15">And the capital -- well, what used to be the capital of Nigeria -- Lagos, that's a taxi, and you have police on them.</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">So, tell me, how many policemen do you think are on this taxi?</s>
  <s id="16.2">And now?</s>
  <s id="16.3">Three.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">So, when these kind of people -- and, believe me, it's not just the police that use these taxis in Lagos.</s>
  <s id="17.2">We all do.</s>
  <s id="17.3">I've been on one of these, and I didn't have a helmet, either.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="18">And it just reminds me of the thought of what happens when one of us on a taxi like this falls off, has an accident and needs a hospital.</s>
 <s id="19">Believe it or not, some of us do survive.</s>
 <s id="20">Some of us do survive malaria; we do survive AIDS.</s>
 <s id="21">And like I tell my family, and my wife reminds me every time, "You're risking your life, you know, every time you go to that country."</s>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">And she's right.</s>
  <s id="22.2">Every time you go there, you know that if you actually need critical care -- critical care of any sort -- if you have an accident -- of which there are many, there are accidents everywhere -- where do they go?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">Where do they go when they need help for this kind of stuff?</s>
 <s id="24">I'm not saying instead of, I'm saying as well as, AIDS, TB, malaria, typhoid -- the list goes on.</s>
 <s id="25">I'm saying, where do they go when they're like me?</s>
 <s id="26">When I go back home -- and I do all kinds of things, I teach, I train -- but I catch one of these things, or I'm chronically ill with one of those, where do they go?</s>
 <s id="27">What's the economic impact when one of them dies or becomes disabled?</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">I think it's quite significant.</s>
  <s id="28.2">This is where they go.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">These are not old pictures and these are not from some downtrodden -- this is a major hospital.</s>
  <s id="29.2">In fact, it's from a major teaching hospital in Nigeria.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">Now that is less than a year old, in an operating room.</s>
 <s id="31">That's sterilizing equipment in Nigeria.</s>
 <s id="32">You remember all that oil?</s>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">Yes, I'm sorry if it upsets some of you, but I think you need to see this.</s>
  <s id="33.2">That's the floor, OK?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="34">You can say some of this is education.</s>
 <p id="p35">
  <s id="35.1">You can say it's hygiene.</s>
  <s id="35.2">I'm not pleading poverty.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="36">I'm saying we need more than just, you know, vaccination, malaria, AIDS, because I want to be treated in a proper hospital if something happens to me out there.</s>
 <s id="37">In fact, when I start running around saying, "Hey, boys and girls, you're cardiologists in the U.S., can you come home with me and do a mission?"</s>
 <s id="38">I want them to think, "Well there's some hope."</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">Now, have a look at that.</s>
  <s id="39.2">That's the anesthesiology machine.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">And that's my specialty, right?</s>
 <s id="41">Anesthesiology and critical care -- look at that bag.</s>
 <s id="42">It's been taped with tape that we even stopped using in the U.K.</s>
 <s id="43">And believe me, these are current pictures.</s>
 <p id="p44">
  <s id="44.1">Now, if something like this, which has happened in the U.K., that's where they go.</s>
  <s id="44.2">This is the intensive care unit in which I work.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="45">All right, this is a slide from a talk I gave about intensive care units in Nigeria, and jokingly we refer to it as "Expensive Scare."</s>
 <s id="46">Because it's scary and it's expensive, but we need to have it, OK?</s>
 <s id="47">So, these are the problems.</s>
 <s id="48">There are no prizes for telling us what the problems are, are there?</s>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">I think we all know.</s>
  <s id="49.2">And several speakers before and speakers after me are going to tell us even more problems.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p50">
  <s id="50.1">These are a few of them.</s>
  <s id="50.2">So, what did I do?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="51">There we go -- we're going on a mission.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">We're going to do some open-heart surgery.</s>
  <s id="52.2">I was the only Brit, on a team of about nine American cardiac surgeons, cardiac nurse, intensive care nurse.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="53">We all went out and did a mission and we've done three of them so far.</s>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">Just so you know, I do believe in missions, I do believe in aid and I do believe in charity.</s>
  <s id="54.2">They have their place, but where do they go for those things we talked about earlier?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">Because it's not everyone that's going to benefit from a mission.</s>
 <s id="56">Health is wealth, in the words of Hans Rosling.</s>
 <s id="57">You get wealthier faster if you are healthy first.</s>
 <p id="p58">
  <s id="58.1">So, here we are, mission.</s>
  <s id="58.2">Big trouble.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="59">Open-heart surgery in Nigeria -- big trouble.</s>
 <s id="60">That's Mike, Mike comes out from Mississippi.</s>
 <s id="61">Does he look like he's happy?</s>
 <p id="p62">
  <s id="62.1">It took us two days just to organize the place, but hey, you know, we worked on it.</s>
  <s id="62.2">Does he look happy?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="63">Yes, that's the medical advice the committee chairman says, "Yes, I told you, you weren't going to be able to, you can't do this, I just know it."</s>
 <p id="p64">
  <s id="64.1">Look, that's the technician we had.</s>
  <s id="64.2">So yes, you go on, all right?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="65">(Laughter) I got him to come with me -- anesthesia tech -- come with me from the U.K.</s>
 <s id="66">Yes, let's just go work this thing out.</s>
 <s id="67">See, that's one of the problems we have in Nigeria and in Africa generally.</s>
 <s id="68">We get a lot of donated equipment.</s>
 <p id="p69">
  <s id="69.1">Equipment that's obsolete, equipment that doesn't quite work, or it works and you can't fix it.</s>
  <s id="69.2">And there's nothing wrong with that, so long as we use it and we move on.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p70">
  <s id="70.1">But we had problems with it.</s>
  <s id="70.2">We had severe problems there.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p71">
  <s id="71.1">He had to get on the phone.</s>
  <s id="71.2">This guy was always on the phone.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="72">So what we going to do now?</s>
 <s id="73">It looks like all these Americans are here and yes, one Brit, and he's not going to do anything -- he thinks he's British actually, and he's actually Nigerian, I just thought about that.</s>
 <p id="p74">
  <s id="74.1">We eventually got it working, is the truth, but it was one of these.</s>
  <s id="74.2">Even older than the one you saw.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="75">The reason I have this picture here, this X-ray, it's just to tell you where and how we were viewing X-rays.</s>
 <p id="p76">
  <s id="76.1">Do you figure where that is?</s>
  <s id="76.2">It was on a window.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p77">
  <s id="77.1">I mean, what's an X-ray viewing box?</s>
  <s id="77.2">Please.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="78">Well, nowadays everything's on PAX anyway.</s>
 <p id="p79">
  <s id="79.1">You look at your X-rays on a screen and you do stuff with them, you email them.</s>
  <s id="79.2">But we were still using X-rays, but we didn't even have a viewing box!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="80">And we were doing open-heart surgery.</s>
 <p id="p81">
  <s id="81.1">OK, I know it's not AIDS, I know it's not malaria, but we still need this stuff.</s>
  <s id="81.2">Oh yeah, echo -- this was just to get the children ready and the adults ready.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p82">
  <s id="82.1">People still believe in Voodoo.</s>
  <s id="82.2">Heart disease, VSD, hole in the heart, tetralogies.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="83">You still get people who believe in it and they came.</s>
 <s id="84">At 67 percent oxygen saturation, the normal is about 97.</s>
 <s id="85">Her condition, open-heart surgery that as she required, would have been treated when she was a child.</s>
 <p id="p86">
  <s id="86.1">We had to do these for adults.</s>
  <s id="86.2">So, we did succeed and we still do.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p87">
  <s id="87.1">We've done three.</s>
  <s id="87.2">We're planning another one in July in the north of the country.</s>
  <s id="87.3">So, we certainly still do open-heart, but you can see the contrast between everything that was shipped in -- we ship everything, instruments.</s>
  <s id="87.4">We had explosions because the kit was designed and installed by people who weren't used to it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="88">The oxygen tanks didn't quite work right.</s>
 <s id="89">But how many did we do the first one? 12.</s>
 <s id="90">We did 12 open-heart surgical patients successfully.</s>
 <s id="91">Here is our very first patient, out of intensive care, and just watch that chair, all right?</s>
 <s id="92">This is what I mean about appropriate technology.</s>
 <s id="93">That's what he was doing, propping up the bed because the bed simply didn't work.</s>
 <s id="94">Have you seen one of those before?</s>
 <p id="p95">
  <s id="95.1">No?</s>
  <s id="95.2">Yes?</s>
  <s id="95.3">Doesn't matter, it worked.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="96">I'm sure you've all seen or heard this before: "We, the willing, have been doing so much with so little for so long -- (Applause) -- we are now qualified to do anything with nothing."</s>
 <p id="p97">
  <s id="97.1">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="97.2">Sustainable Solutions -- this was my first company.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="98">This one's sole aim is to provide the very things that I think are missing.</s>
 <s id="99">So, we put my hand in my pocket and say, "Guys, let's just buy stuff.</s>
 <s id="100">Let's go set up a company that teaches people, educates them, gives them the tools they need to keep going."</s>
 <s id="101">And that's a perfect example of one.</s>
 <p id="p102">
  <s id="102.1">Usually when you buy a ventilator in a hospital, you buy a different one for children, you buy a different one for transport.</s>
  <s id="102.2">This one will do everything, and it will do it at half the price and doesn't need compressed air.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p103">
  <s id="103.1">If you're in America and you don't know about this one, we do, because we make it our duty to find out what's appropriate technology for Africa -- what's appropriately priced, does the job, and we move on.</s>
  <s id="103.2">Anesthesia machine: multi-parameter monitor, operating lights, suction.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="104">This little unit here -- remember your little 12-volt plug in the car, that charges your, whatever, Game Boy, telephone?</s>
 <s id="105">That's exactly how the outlets are designed.</s>
 <p id="p106">
  <s id="106.1">Yes, it will take a solar panel.</s>
  <s id="106.2">Yes a solar panel will charge it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="107">But if you've got mains as well, it will charge the batteries in there.</s>
 <p id="p108">
  <s id="108.1">And guess what?</s>
  <s id="108.2">We have a little pedal charger too, just in case.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p109">
  <s id="109.1">And guess what, if it all fails, if you can find a car that's still got a live battery and you stick it in, it will still work.</s>
  <s id="109.2">Then you can customize it.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p110">
  <s id="110.1">Is it dental surgery you want?</s>
  <s id="110.2">General surgery you want?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="111">Decide which instruments, stock it up with consumables.</s>
 <s id="112">And currently we're working on oxygen -- oxygen delivery on-site.</s>
 <s id="113">The technology for oxygen delivery is not new.</s>
 <p id="p114">
  <s id="114.1">Oxygen concentrators are very old technology.</s>
  <s id="114.2">What is new, and what we will have in a few months, I hope, is that ability to use this same renewable energy system to provide and produce oxygen on site.</s>
  <s id="114.3">Zeolite -- it's not new -- zeolite removes nitrogen from air and nitrogen is 78 percent of air.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p115">
  <s id="115.1">If you take nitrogen out, what's left?</s>
  <s id="115.2">Oxygen, pretty much.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p116">
  <s id="116.1">So that's not new.</s>
  <s id="116.2">What we're doing is applying this technology to it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="117">These are the basic features of my device, or our device.</s>
 <s id="118">This is what makes it so special.</s>
 <p id="p119">
  <s id="119.1">Apart from the awards it's won, it's portable and it's certified.</s>
  <s id="119.2">It's registered, the MHRA -- and the CE mark, for those who don't know, for Europe, is the equivalent of the FDA in the U.S.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="120">If you compare it with what's on the market, price-wise, size-wise, ease of use, complexity ...</s>
 <s id="121">This picture was taken last year.</s>
 <s id="122">These are members of my graduating class, 1986.</s>
 <s id="123">It was in this gentleman's house in the Potomac, for those of you who are familiar with Maryland.</s>
 <p id="p124">
  <s id="124.1">There are too many of us outside and everybody, just to borrow a bit from Hans -- Hans Rosling, he's my guy -- if the size of the text represents what gets the most attention, it's the problems.</s>
  <s id="124.2">But what we really need are African solutions that are appropriate for Africa -- looking at the culture, looking at the people, looking at how much money they've got.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="125">African people, because they will do it with a passion, I hope.</s>
 <s id="126">And lots and lots of that little bit down there, sacrifice.</s>
 <p id="p127">
  <s id="127.1">You have to do it.</s>
  <s id="127.2">Africans have to do it, in conjunction with everyone else.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="128">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="129">(Applause)</s>
</text>
