<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The world makes you something that you're not, but you know inside what you are, and that question burns in your heart: How will you become that?</s>
 <s id="2">I may be somewhat unique in this, but I am not alone, not alone at all.</s>
 <s id="3">So when I became a fashion model, I felt that I'd finally achieved the dream that I'd always wanted since I was a young child.</s>
 <s id="4">My outside self finally matched my inner truth, my inner self.</s>
 <s id="5">For complicated reasons which I'll get to later, when I look at this picture, at that time I felt like, Geena, you've done it, you've made it, you have arrived.</s>
 <s id="6">But this past October, I realized that I'm only just beginning.</s>
 <s id="7">All of us are put in boxes by our family, by our religion, by our society, our moment in history, even our own bodies.</s>
 <s id="8">Some people have the courage to break free, not to accept the limitations imposed by the color of their skin or by the beliefs of those that surround them.</s>
 <s id="9">Those people are always the threat to the status quo, to what is considered acceptable.</s>
 <s id="10">In my case, for the last nine years, some of my neighbors, some of my friends, colleagues, even my agent, did not know about my history.</s>
 <s id="11">I think, in mystery, this is called the reveal.</s>
 <s id="12">Here is mine.</s>
 <s id="13">I was assigned boy at birth based on the appearance of my genitalia.</s>
 <s id="14">I remember when I was five years old in the Philippines walking around our house, I would always wear this t-shirt on my head.</s>
 <s id="15">And my mom asked me, "How come you always wear that t-shirt on your head?"</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">I said, "Mom, this is my hair.</s>
  <s id="16.2">I'm a girl."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="17">I knew then how to self-identify.</s>
 <s id="18">Gender has always been considered a fact, immutable, but we now know it's actually more fluid, complex and mysterious.</s>
 <s id="19">Because of my success, I never had the courage to share my story, not because I thought what I am is wrong, but because of how the world treats those of us who wish to break free.</s>
 <s id="20">Every day, I am so grateful because I am a woman.</s>
 <s id="21">I have a mom and dad and family who accepted me for who I am.</s>
 <s id="22">Many are not so fortunate.</s>
 <s id="23">There's a long tradition in Asian culture that celebrates the fluid mystery of gender.</s>
 <s id="24">There is a Buddhist goddess of compassion.</s>
 <s id="25">There is a Hindu goddess, hijra goddess.</s>
 <s id="26">So when I was eight years old, I was at a fiesta in the Philippines celebrating these mysteries.</s>
 <s id="27">I was in front of the stage, and I remember, out comes this beautiful woman right in front of me, and I remember that moment something hit me: That is the kind of woman I would like to be.</s>
 <s id="28">So when I was 15 years old, still dressing as a boy, I met this woman named T.L.</s>
 <s id="29">She is a transgender beauty pageant manager.</s>
 <s id="30">That night she asked me, "How come you are not joining the beauty pageant?"</s>
 <s id="31">She convinced me that if I joined that she would take care of the registration fee and the garments, and that night, I won best in swimsuit and best in long gown and placed second runner up among 40-plus candidates.</s>
 <s id="32">That moment changed my life.</s>
 <s id="33">All of a sudden, I was introduced to the world of beauty pageants.</s>
 <s id="34">Not a lot of people could say that your first job is a pageant queen for transgender women, but I'll take it.</s>
 <s id="35">So from 15 to 17 years old, I joined the most prestigious pageant to the pageant where it's at the back of the truck, literally, or sometimes it would be a pavement next to a rice field, and when it rains -- it rains a lot in the Philippines -- the organizers would have to move it inside someone's house.</s>
 <s id="36">I also experienced the goodness of strangers, especially when we would travel in remote provinces in the Philippines.</s>
 <s id="37">But most importantly, I met some of my best friends in that community.</s>
 <s id="38">In 2001, my mom, who had moved to San Francisco, called me and told me that my green card petition came through, that I could now move to the United States.</s>
 <s id="39">I resisted it.</s>
 <s id="40">I told my mom, "Mom, I'm having fun.</s>
 <s id="41">I'm here with my friends, I love traveling, being a beauty pageant queen."</s>
 <s id="42">But then two weeks later she called me, she said, "Did you know that if you move to the United States you could change your name and gender marker?"</s>
 <s id="43">That was all I needed to hear.</s>
 <s id="44">My mom also told me to put two E's in the spelling of my name.</s>
 <s id="45">She also came with me when I had my surgery in Thailand at 19 years old.</s>
 <s id="46">It's interesting, in some of the most rural cities in Thailand, they perform some of the most prestigious, safe and sophisticated surgery.</s>
 <s id="47">At that time in the United States, you needed to have surgery before you could change your name and gender marker.</s>
 <s id="48">So in 2001, I moved to San Francisco, and I remember looking at my California driver's license with the name Geena and gender marker F.</s>
 <s id="49">That was a powerful moment.</s>
 <s id="50">For some people, their I.D. is their license to drive or even to get a drink, but for me, that was my license to live, to feel dignified.</s>
 <s id="51">All of a sudden, my fears were minimized.</s>
 <s id="52">I felt that I could conquer my dream and move to New York and be a model.</s>
 <s id="53">Many are not so fortunate.</s>
 <s id="54">I think of this woman named Islan Nettles.</s>
 <s id="55">She's from New York, she's a young woman who was courageously living her truth, but hatred ended her life.</s>
 <s id="56">For most of my community, this is the reality in which we live.</s>
 <s id="57">Our suicide rate is nine times higher than that of the general population.</s>
 <s id="58">Every November 20, we have a global vigil for Transgender Day of Remembrance.</s>
 <s id="59">I'm here at this stage because it's a long history of people who fought and stood up for injustice.</s>
 <s id="60">This is Marsha P. Johnson and Sylvia Rivera.</s>
 <s id="61">Today, this very moment, is my real coming out.</s>
 <s id="62">I could no longer live my truth for and by myself.</s>
 <s id="63">I want to do my best to help others live their truth without shame and terror.</s>
 <s id="64">I am here, exposed, so that one day there will never be a need for a November 20 vigil.</s>
 <s id="65">My deepest truth allowed me to accept who I am.</s>
 <s id="66">Will you?</s>
 <s id="67">Thank you very much.</s>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
  <s id="68.2">Thank you.</s>
  <s id="68.3">Thank you.</s>
  <s id="68.4">(Applause) Kathryn Schulz: Geena, one quick question for you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="69">I'm wondering what you would say, especially to parents, but in a more broad way, to friends, to family, to anyone who finds themselves encountering a child or a person who is struggling with and uncomfortable with a gender that's being assigned them, what might you say to the family members of that person to help them become good and caring and kind family members to them?</s>
 <p id="p70">
  <s id="70.1">Geena Rocero: Sure.</s>
  <s id="70.2">Well, first, really, I'm so blessed.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="71">The support system, with my mom especially, and my family, that in itself is just so powerful.</s>
 <s id="72">I remember every time I would coach young trans women, I would mentor them, and sometimes when they would call me and tell me that their parents can't accept it, I would pick up that phone call and tell my mom, "Mom, can you call this woman?"</s>
 <s id="73">And sometimes it works, sometimes it doesn't, so — But it's just, gender identity is in the core of our being, right?</s>
 <s id="74">I mean, we're all assigned gender at birth, so what I'm trying to do is to have this conversation that sometimes that gender assignment doesn't match, and there should be a space that would allow people to self-identify, and that's a conversation that we should have with parents, with colleagues.</s>
 <s id="75">The transgender movement, it's at the very beginning, to compare to how the gay movement started.</s>
 <s id="76">There's still a lot of work that needs to be done.</s>
 <s id="77">There should be an understanding.</s>
 <s id="78">There should be a space of curiosity and asking questions, and I hope all of you guys will be my allies.</s>
 <p id="p79">
  <s id="79.1">KS: Thank you.</s>
  <s id="79.2">That was so lovely.</s>
  <s id="79.3">GR: Thank you.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="80">(Applause)</s>
</text>
