<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <p id="p1">
  <s id="1.1">Australians call them “runners."</s>
  <s id="1.2">The British know them as “trainers."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="2">Americans refer to them as “tennis shoes” or “sneakers."</s>
 <s id="3">Whatever you call them, these rubber-soled, casual shoes are worn by billions of people around the world.</s>
 <s id="4">Originally invented in the late 19th century, these simple canvas and rubber creations have changed a lot since they first hit the pavement.</s>
 <s id="5">Today, sneaker consumption is at an all-time high.</s>
 <s id="6">No country buys more sneakers than the United States, where people purchase 3 pairs a year on average.</s>
 <s id="7">To meet this demand, roughly 23 billion shoes are produced each year, mostly in factories across China and Southeast Asia.</s>
 <s id="8">But making shoes has become more complicated, more labor-intensive, and in some ways, more dangerous, for the workers involved and for our planet.</s>
 <s id="9">Shoe manufacturing accounts for roughly one-fifth of the fashion industry’s carbon emissions.</s>
 <s id="10">Sneakers alone generate 313 million metric tons of carbon dioxide every year, which is equivalent to the annual emissions of 66 million cars.</s>
 <s id="11">To better understand your shoe’s carbon footprint, let’s dive into the anatomy of a sneaker.</s>
 <s id="12">For starters, the heel, insole, midsole, and upper layer are usually made from synthetic textiles like polyester, nylon, latex, and polyurethane.</s>
 <s id="13">Mining the fossil fuels that make up these materials emits tons of greenhouse gases.</s>
 <s id="14">And processing those raw ingredients into synthetic textiles also uses a lot of energy, further compounding that pollution.</s>
 <s id="15">Some sneaker tops are made from natural sources like leather, but tanning this material relies on chromium; a carcinogenic chemical that can damage freshwater ecosystems.</s>
 <s id="16">The outer soles of most shoes are made of rubber that’s gone through a process called vulcanization.</s>
 <s id="17">This technique adds sulfur to superheated raw rubber to create a material that’s both elastic and sturdy.</s>
 <s id="18">Until recently, sneakers used natural rubber for this process.</s>
 <s id="19">But today, most outer soles are made with a synthetic blend of natural rubber and byproducts from coal and oil.</s>
 <s id="20">Producing these materials accounts for 20% of a sneaker’s carbon footprint.</s>
 <s id="21">But more than two-thirds of the shoe’s carbon impact comes from the next step: manufacturing.</s>
 <s id="22">A typical sneaker is comprised of 65 discrete parts, each of which is produced by specialized machinery.</s>
 <s id="23">This means it’s cheaper for factories to mass-produce each piece separately rather than manufacturing every part under one roof.</s>
 <s id="24">But the transportation required to ship these pieces to one assembly plant emits even more CO2.</s>
 <s id="25">Once the components arrive at the assembly line, they undergo cutting, pouring, melting, baking, cooling, and gluing, before the final products can be stitched together.</s>
 <s id="26">The assembly of a typical sneaker requires more than 360 steps, and accounts for the remaining 20% of a sneaker’s environmental impact.</s>
 <s id="27">The dispersion of factories fuels another problem as well: labor abuse.</s>
 <s id="28">Most brands don’t own or operate their factories, so the plants they work with are in countries with little to no worker protection laws.</s>
 <s id="29">As a result, many laborers earn below the living wage, and are exposed to harmful chemicals, like toxic glue fumes.</s>
 <s id="30">When manufacturing is complete, the shoes are packaged and transported to stores around the globe.</s>
 <s id="31">For many, these shoes could last years.</s>
 <s id="32">But for someone running 20 miles a week, a pair of running shoes will start wearing out after roughly 6 months.</s>
 <s id="33">Since the shoes are made of so many different materials, they’re almost impossible to break down into recyclable components.</s>
 <s id="34">20% of these shoes are incinerated, while the rest are tossed into landfills where they can take up to 1,000 years to degrade.</s>
 <s id="35">So, how can we balance our love of sneakers with the need for sustainability?</s>
 <s id="36">First, designers should streamline design elements and focus on eco-friendly materials.</s>
 <s id="37">Factories need to develop energy efficient manufacturing processes that consolidate steps and sneaker parts.</s>
 <s id="38">And consumers should support companies using clean energy and ethical manufacturing processes.</s>
 <s id="39">We can also buy fewer shoes, wear them for longer, and donate those we no longer need.</s>
 <s id="40">So no matter what your style, we can all take steps towards a sustainable future.</s>
</text>
