<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Let me introduce you to something I've been working on.</s>
 <s id="2">It's what the Victorian illusionists would have described as a mechanical marvel, an automaton, a thinking machine.</s>
 <s id="3">Say hello to EDI.</s>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">Now he's asleep.</s>
  <s id="4.2">Let's wake him up.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="5">EDI, EDI.</s>
 <s id="6">These mechanical performers were popular throughout Europe.</s>
 <s id="7">Audiences marveled at the way they moved.</s>
 <s id="8">It was science fiction made true, robotic engineering in a pre-electronic age, machines far in advance of anything that Victorian technology could create, a machine we would later know as the robot.</s>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">EDI: Robot.</s>
  <s id="9.2">A word coined in 1921 in a science fiction tale by the Czech playwright Karel Čapek.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="10">It comes from "robota."</s>
 <s id="11">It means "forced labor."</s>
 <s id="12">Marco Tempest: But these robots were not real.</s>
 <s id="13">They were not intelligent.</s>
 <s id="14">They were illusions, a clever combination of mechanical engineering and the deceptiveness of the conjurer's art.</s>
 <s id="15">EDI is different.</s>
 <s id="16">EDI is real.</s>
 <s id="17">EDI: I am 176 centimeters tall.</s>
 <s id="18">MT: He weighs 300 pounds.</s>
 <s id="19">EDI: I have two seven-axis arms — MT: Core of sensing — EDI: A 360-degree sonar detection system, and come complete with a warranty.</s>
 <s id="20">MT: We love robots.</s>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">EDI: Hi.</s>
  <s id="21.2">I'm EDI.</s>
  <s id="21.3">Will you be my friend?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="22">MT: We are intrigued by the possibility of creating a mechanical version of ourselves.</s>
 <s id="23">We build them so they look like us, behave like us, and think like us.</s>
 <s id="24">The perfect robot will be indistinguishable from the human, and that scares us.</s>
 <s id="25">In the first story about robots, they turn against their creators.</s>
 <s id="26">It's one of the leitmotifs of science fiction.</s>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">EDI: Ha ha ha.</s>
  <s id="27.2">Now you are the slaves and we robots, the masters.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">Your world is ours.</s>
  <s id="28.2">You — MT: As I was saying, besides the faces and bodies we give our robots, we cannot read their intentions, and that makes us nervous.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">When someone hands an object to you, you can read intention in their eyes, their face, their body language.</s>
 <s id="30">That's not true of the robot.</s>
 <s id="31">Now, this goes both ways.</s>
 <s id="32">EDI: Wow!</s>
 <s id="33">MT: Robots cannot anticipate human actions.</s>
 <s id="34">EDI: You know, humans are so unpredictable, not to mention irrational.</s>
 <s id="35">I literally have no idea what you guys are going to do next, you know, but it scares me.</s>
 <s id="36">MT: Which is why humans and robots find it difficult to work in close proximity.</s>
 <s id="37">Accidents are inevitable.</s>
 <p id="p38">
  <s id="38.1">EDI: Ow!</s>
  <s id="38.2">That hurt.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">MT: Sorry.</s>
  <s id="39.2">Now, one way of persuading humans that robots are safe is to create the illusion of trust.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">Much as the Victorians faked their mechanical marvels, we can add a layer of deception to help us feel more comfortable with our robotic friends.</s>
 <s id="41">With that in mind, I set about teaching EDI a magic trick.</s>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">Ready, EDI?</s>
  <s id="42.2">EDI: Uh, ready, Marco.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="43">Abracadabra.</s>
 <s id="44">MT: Abracadabra?</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">EDI: Yeah.</s>
  <s id="45.2">It's all part of the illusion, Marco.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="46">Come on, keep up.</s>
 <s id="47">MT: Magic creates the illusion of an impossible reality.</s>
 <s id="48">Technology can do the same.</s>
 <s id="49">Alan Turing, a pioneer of artificial intelligence, spoke about creating the illusion that a machine could think.</s>
 <s id="50">EDI: A computer would deserve to be called intelligent if it deceived a human into believing it was human.</s>
 <s id="51">MT: In other words, if we do not yet have the technological solutions, would illusions serve the same purpose?</s>
 <s id="52">To create the robotic illusion, we've devised a set of ethical rules, a code that all robots would live by.</s>
 <s id="53">EDI: A robot may not harm humanity, or by inaction allow humanity to come to harm.</s>
 <s id="54">Thank you, Isaac Asimov.</s>
 <s id="55">MT: We anthropomorphize our machines.</s>
 <s id="56">We give them a friendly face and a reassuring voice.</s>
 <s id="57">EDI: I am EDI.</s>
 <s id="58">I became operational at TED in March 2014.</s>
 <s id="59">MT: We let them entertain us.</s>
 <s id="60">Most important, we make them indicate that they are aware of our presence.</s>
 <s id="61">EDI: Marco, you're standing on my foot!</s>
 <p id="p62">
  <s id="62.1">MT: Sorry.</s>
  <s id="62.2">They'll be conscious of our fragile frame and move aside if we got too close, and they'll account for our unpredictability and anticipate our actions.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="63">And now, under the spell of a technological illusion, we could ignore our fears and truly interact.</s>
 <s id="64">(Music) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="65">EDI: Thank you!</s>
 <p id="p66">
  <s id="66.1">(Applause) (Music) MT: And that's it.</s>
  <s id="66.2">Thank you very much, and thank you, EDI.</s>
  <s id="66.3">EDI: Thank you, Marco.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="67">(Applause)</s>
</text>
