<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The attacking infantry advances steadily, their elephants already having broken the defensive line.</s>
 <s id="2">The king tries to retreat, but enemy cavalry flanks him from the rear.</s>
 <s id="3">Escape is impossible.</s>
 <s id="4">But this isn’t a real war– nor is it just a game.</s>
 <s id="5">Over the roughly one-and-a-half millennia of its existence, chess has been known as a tool of military strategy, a metaphor for human affairs, and a benchmark of genius.</s>
 <s id="6">While our earliest records of chess are in the 7th century, legend tells that the game’s origins lie a century earlier.</s>
 <s id="7">Supposedly, when the youngest prince of the Gupta Empire was killed in battle, his brother devised a way of representing the scene to their grieving mother.</s>
 <s id="8">Set on the 8x8 ashtapada board used for other popular pastimes, a new game emerged with two key features: different rules for moving different types of pieces, and a single king piece whose fate determined the outcome.</s>
 <s id="9">The game was originally known as chaturanga– a Sanskrit word for "four divisions."</s>
 <p id="p10">
  <s id="10.1">But with its spread to Sassanid Persia, it acquired its current name and terminology– "chess," derived from "shah," meaning king, and “checkmate” from "shah mat," or “the king is helpless.”</s>
  <s id="10.2">After the 7th century Islamic conquest of Persia, chess was introduced to the Arab world.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="11">Transcending its role as a tactical simulation, it eventually became a rich source of poetic imagery.</s>
 <s id="12">Diplomats and courtiers used chess terms to describe political power.</s>
 <s id="13">Ruling caliphs became avid players themselves.</s>
 <s id="14">And historian al-Mas’udi considered the game a testament to human free will compared to games of chance.</s>
 <s id="15">Medieval trade along the Silk Road carried the game to East and Southeast Asia, where many local variants developed.</s>
 <s id="16">In China, chess pieces were placed at intersections of board squares rather than inside them, as in the native strategy game Go.</s>
 <s id="17">The reign of Mongol leader Tamerlane saw an 11x10 board with safe squares called citadels.</s>
 <s id="18">And in Japanese shogi, captured pieces could be used by the opposing player.</s>
 <s id="19">But it was in Europe that chess began to take on its modern form.</s>
 <s id="20">By 1000 AD, the game had become part of courtly education.</s>
 <s id="21">Chess was used as an allegory for different social classes performing their proper roles, and the pieces were re-interpreted in their new context.</s>
 <s id="22">At the same time, the Church remained suspicious of games.</s>
 <s id="23">Moralists cautioned against devoting too much time to them, with chess even being briefly banned in France.</s>
 <s id="24">Yet the game proliferated, and the 15th century saw it cohering into the form we know today.</s>
 <s id="25">The relatively weak piece of advisor was recast as the more powerful queen– perhaps inspired by the recent surge of strong female leaders.</s>
 <s id="26">This change accelerated the game’s pace, and as other rules were popularized, treatises analyzing common openings and endgames appeared.</s>
 <s id="27">Chess theory was born.</s>
 <s id="28">With the Enlightenment era, the game moved from royal courts to coffeehouses.</s>
 <s id="29">Chess was now seen as an expression of creativity, encouraging bold moves and dramatic plays.</s>
 <s id="30">This "Romantic" style reached its peak in the Immortal Game of 1851, where Adolf Anderssen managed a checkmate after sacrificing his queen and both rooks.</s>
 <s id="31">But the emergence of formal competitive play in the late 19th century meant that strategic calculation would eventually trump dramatic flair.</s>
 <s id="32">And with the rise of international competition, chess took on a new geopolitical importance.</s>
 <s id="33">During the Cold War, the Soviet Union devoted great resources to cultivating chess talent, dominating the championships for the rest of the century.</s>
 <s id="34">But the player who would truly upset Russian dominance was not a citizen of another country but an IBM computer called Deep Blue.</s>
 <s id="35">Chess-playing computers had been developed for decades, but Deep Blue’s triumph over Garry Kasparov in 1997 was the first time a machine had defeated a sitting champion.</s>
 <s id="36">Today, chess software is capable of consistently defeating the best human players.</s>
 <s id="37">But just like the game they’ve mastered, these machines are products of human ingenuity.</s>
 <s id="38">And perhaps that same ingenuity will guide us out of this apparent checkmate.</s>
</text>
