<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In early 1828, Sojourner Truth approached the Grand Jury of Kingston, New York.</s>
 <s id="2">She had no experience with the legal system, no money, and no power in the eyes of the court.</s>
 <s id="3">Ignoring the jury’s scorn, Truth said she was there to fight for custody of her five-year-old son Peter, who’d been illegally sold to an enslaver in Alabama.</s>
 <s id="4">As the trial played out over the next several months, Truth raised funds, strategized with lawyers, and held her faith.</s>
 <s id="5">Finally in the spring of 1828, Peter was returned to her care— but Truth’s work was far from over.</s>
 <s id="6">She would dedicate the rest of her life to pursuing justice and spiritual understanding.</s>
 <s id="7">Truth was born into slavery as Isabella Baumfree in the late 18th century in Ulster County, New York.</s>
 <s id="8">Although New York state had announced the abolition of slavery in 1799, the emancipation act was gradual.</s>
 <s id="9">Those who were currently enslaved were forced to serve a period of indentured servitude until their mid-20s.</s>
 <s id="10">Throughout this period, enslavers repeatedly sold Baumfree, tearing her from her loved ones.</s>
 <s id="11">Often, she was explicitly prevented from pursuing new relationships.</s>
 <s id="12">Eventually, she married an enslaved man named Thomas, with whom she had three children.</s>
 <s id="13">She was desperate to keep her new family together— but the slow progress of abolition threatened this hope.</s>
 <s id="14">Baumfree’s enslaver, John Dumont, had promised to free her by 1826.</s>
 <s id="15">When he failed to keep his word, Baumfree fled for her safety.</s>
 <s id="16">During the escape, she was only able to rescue her youngest daughter Sophia, while her other children remained in bondage.</s>
 <s id="17">It would be two years before she regained custody of Peter.</s>
 <s id="18">After that, she would wait another two years before she saw any of her other children.</s>
 <s id="19">During this time, Baumfree found solace in her faith and became increasingly dedicated to religious reflection.</s>
 <s id="20">After settling in Kingston, New York, she joined a Methodist community that shared her political views.</s>
 <s id="21">She continued her practice of speaking aloud to God in private, and one night, her evening prayers took on even more sacred significance.</s>
 <s id="22">Baumfree claimed to hear the voice of God, telling her to leave Kingston, and share her holy message with others.</s>
 <s id="23">Though she never learned to read or write, Baumfree became known as an electrifying orator, whose speeches drew on Biblical references, spiritual ideals, and her experience of slavery.</s>
 <s id="24">Her sermons denounced the oppression of African Americans and women in general, and became prominent in campaigns for both abolition and women’s rights.</s>
 <s id="25">In 1843, she renamed herself Sojourner Truth and embarked on a legendary speaking tour.</s>
 <s id="26">Truth saw her journey as a mission from God.</s>
 <s id="27">Her faith often led her to the nation’s most hostile regions, where she spoke to bigoted audiences as the only Black woman in the crowd.</s>
 <s id="28">Truth was confident God would protect her, but some crowds responded to her bravery with violence.</s>
 <s id="29">During one of her sermons, a mob of white men threatened to set fire to the tent where she was speaking.</s>
 <s id="30">In her memoir, Truth recalled steeling herself to confront them: “Have I not faith enough to go out and quell that mob… I felt as if I had three hearts!</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">And that they were so large, my body could hardly hold them!”</s>
  <s id="31.2">She placated the men with song and prayer, until they had no desire to harm her.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">Truth’s speeches impacted thousands of people in communities across the nation, but her activism went far beyond public speaking.</s>
 <s id="33">During the Civil War, she became involved with the Union Army, recruiting soldiers and organizing supplies for Black troops.</s>
 <s id="34">Her work was so well regarded that she was invited to meet President Lincoln.</s>
 <s id="35">She took the occasion to argue that all formerly enslaved people should be granted land by the government.</s>
 <s id="36">Truth continued to travel and speak well into her 80s.</s>
 <s id="37">Until her death in 1883, she remained an outspoken critic who fought for her right to be heard in a hostile world.</s>
 <s id="38">As Truth once said, “I feel safe even in the midst of my enemies; for the truth is powerful and will prevail."</s>
</text>
