<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So, a funny thing happened on my way to becoming a brilliant, world-class neuropsychologist: I had a baby.</s>
 <s id="2">And that's not to say I ever went on to become a brilliant, world-class neuropsychologist.</s>
 <s id="3">Sorry, TED.</s>
 <s id="4">But I did go on to be a reasonably astute, arguably world-class worrier.</s>
 <s id="5">One of my girlfriends in graduate school, Marie, said, "Kim, I figured it out.</s>
 <s id="6">It's not that you're more neurotic than everyone else; it's just that you're more honest about how neurotic you are."</s>
 <s id="7">So in the spirit of full disclosure, I brought some pictures to share.</s>
 <s id="8">Awwww.</s>
 <s id="9">(Laughter) I'll just say: July.</s>
 <s id="10">(Laughter) Zip!</s>
 <s id="11">(Laughter) For safety.</s>
 <s id="12">(Laughter) Water wings -- an inch of water.</s>
 <s id="13">And then, finally, all suited up for the 90-minute drive to Copper Mountain.</s>
 <s id="14">So you can get kind of a feel for this.</s>
 <s id="15">So my baby, Vander, is eight years old now.</s>
 <s id="16">And, despite being cursed with my athletic inability, he plays soccer.</s>
 <s id="17">He's interested in playing football.</s>
 <s id="18">He wants to learn how to ride a unicycle.</s>
 <s id="19">So why would I worry?</s>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">Because this is what I do.</s>
  <s id="20.2">This is what I teach.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">It's what I study.</s>
  <s id="21.2">It's what I treat.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="22">And I know that kids get concussed every year.</s>
 <s id="23">In fact, more than four million people sustain a concussion every year, and these data are just among kids under 14 who were seen in emergency rooms.</s>
 <s id="24">And so when kids sustain a concussion, we talk about them getting dinged or getting their bell rung, but what is it that we're really talking about?</s>
 <s id="25">Let's take a look.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">[Concussive Force] "Starsky and Hutch"?</s>
  <s id="26.2">Arguably, yes.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">So, a car accident.</s>
 <s id="28">Forty miles an hour into a fixed barrier: 35 Gs.</s>
 <s id="29">A heavyweight boxer punches you straight in the face: 58 Gs.</s>
 <s id="30">(Music) In case you missed it, we'll look again.</s>
 <s id="31">So look to the right-hand side of the screen.</s>
 <s id="32">(Music) What would you say?</s>
 <s id="33">How many Gs?</s>
 <s id="34">Close.</s>
 <s id="35">Seventy-two?</s>
 <s id="36">Would it be crazy to know: 103 Gs?</s>
 <s id="37">The average concussive impact is 95 Gs.</s>
 <s id="38">Now, when the kid on the right doesn't get up, we know they've had a concussion.</s>
 <s id="39">But how about the kid on the left, or the athlete that leaves the field of play?</s>
 <s id="40">How do we know if he or she has sustained a concussion?</s>
 <s id="41">How do we know that legislation that would require they be pulled from play, cleared for return to play, applies to them?</s>
 <s id="42">The definition of concussion doesn't actually require a loss of consciousness.</s>
 <s id="43">It requires only a change in consciousness, and that can be any one or a number of symptoms, including feeling foggy, feeling dizzy, hearing a ringing in your ear, being more impulsive or hostile than usual.</s>
 <s id="44">So given all of that and given how darn neurotic I am, how do I get any sleep at all?</s>
 <s id="45">Because I know our brains are resilient.</s>
 <s id="46">They're designed to recover from an injury.</s>
 <s id="47">If -- God forbid -- any of us left here tonight and sustained a concussion, most of us would go on to fully recover inside of a couple hours to a couple of weeks.</s>
 <s id="48">But kids are more vulnerable to brain injury.</s>
 <s id="49">In fact, high-school athletes are three times more likely to sustain catastrophic injuries relative even to their college-age peers, and it takes them longer to return to a symptom-free baseline.</s>
 <s id="50">After that first injury, their risk for second injury is exponentially greater.</s>
 <s id="51">From there, their risk for a third injury, greater still, and so on.</s>
 <s id="52">And here's the really alarming part: We don't fully understand the long-term impact of multiple injuries.</s>
 <s id="53">You guys may be familiar with this research that's coming out of the NFL.</s>
 <s id="54">In a nutshell, this research suggests that, among retired NFL players with three or more career concussions, the incidence of early-onset dementing disease is much greater than it is for the general population.</s>
 <s id="55">So you've all seen that -- New York Times, you've seen it.</s>
 <s id="56">What you may not be familiar with is that this research was spearheaded by NFL wives who said, "Isn't it weird that my 46-year-old husband is forever losing his keys?"</s>
 <s id="57">"Isn't it weird that my 47-year-old husband is forever losing the car?"</s>
 <s id="58">"Isn't it weird that my 48-year-old husband is forever losing his way home in the car, from the driveway?"</s>
 <s id="59">I may have forgotten to mention that my son is an only child.</s>
 <s id="60">So it's going to be really important that he be able to drive me around someday.</s>
 <s id="61">(Laughter) So, how do we guarantee the safety of our kids?</s>
 <s id="62">How can we 100 percent guarantee the safety of our kids?</s>
 <s id="63">Let me tell you what I've come up with.</s>
 <s id="64">(Laughter) If only.</s>
 <s id="65">My little boy's right there, and he's like, "She's not kidding.</s>
 <s id="66">She's totally not kidding."</s>
 <s id="67">So in all seriousness: Should my kid play football?</s>
 <s id="68">Should your kid play football?</s>
 <s id="69">I don't know.</s>
 <s id="70">But I do know there are three things you can do.</s>
 <s id="71">The first: study up.</s>
 <s id="72">You have to be familiar with the issues we're talking about today.</s>
 <s id="73">There are some great resources out there.</s>
 <s id="74">The CDC has a program, HEADS UP.</s>
 <s id="75">It's at CDC.gov.</s>
 <s id="76">HEADS UP is specific to concussion in kids.</s>
 <s id="77">The second is a resource I'm personally really proud of.</s>
 <s id="78">We've just rolled this out in the last couple months -- CO Kids With Brain Injury.</s>
 <s id="79">This is a great resource for student athletes, teachers, parents, professionals, athletic and coaching staff.</s>
 <s id="80">It's a great place to start if you have questions.</s>
 <s id="81">The second thing is: speak up.</s>
 <s id="82">Just two weeks ago, a bill introduced by Senator Kefalas that would have required athletes, kids under 18, to wear a helmet when they're riding their bike, died in committee.</s>
 <s id="83">It died, in large part, because it lacked constituent buy-in; it lacked stakeholder traction.</s>
 <s id="84">Now, I'm not here to tell you what kind of legislation you should or shouldn't support, but I am going to tell you that, if it matters to you, your legislators need to know that.</s>
 <s id="85">Speak up also with coaching staff.</s>
 <s id="86">Ask about what kind of protective equipment is available.</s>
 <s id="87">What's the budget for protective equipment?</s>
 <s id="88">How old it is?</s>
 <s id="89">Maybe offer to spearhead a fundraiser to buy new gear.</s>
 <s id="90">Which brings us to: suit up.</s>
 <s id="91">Wear a helmet.</s>
 <s id="92">The only way to prevent a bad outcome is to prevent that first injury from happening.</s>
 <s id="93">Recently, one of my graduate students, Tom, said, "Kim, I've decided to wear a bike helmet on the way to class."</s>
 <s id="94">And Tom knows that that little bit of foam in a bike helmet can reduce the g-force of impact by half.</s>
 <s id="95">Now, I thought it was because I have this totally compelling helmet crusade, this epiphany of Tom's.</s>
 <s id="96">As it turns out, it occurred to Tom that a $20 helmet is a good way to protect a $100,000 graduate education.</s>
 <s id="97">(Laughter) So ...</s>
 <s id="98">Should Vander play football?</s>
 <s id="99">I can't say no, but I can guarantee that every time he leaves the house, that kid's wearing a helmet -- like, to the car, or at school.</s>
 <s id="100">So whether athlete, scholar, overprotected kid, neurotic mom, or otherwise, here's my baby, Vander, reminding you to mind your matter.</s>
 <s id="101">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="102">(Applause)</s>
</text>
