<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">It starts with a tickle in your throat that becomes a cough.</s>
 <s id="2">Your muscles begin to ache, you grow irritable, and you lose your appetite.</s>
 <s id="3">It's official: you've got the flu.</s>
 <s id="4">It's logical to assume that this miserable medley of symptoms is the result of the infection coursing through your body, but is that really the case?</s>
 <s id="5">What's actually making you feel sick?</s>
 <s id="6">What if your body itself was driving this vicious onslaught?</s>
 <s id="7">You first get ill when a pathogen like the flu virus gets into your system, infecting and killing your cells.</s>
 <s id="8">But this unwelcome intrusion has another effect: it alerts your body's immune system to your plight.</s>
 <s id="9">As soon as it becomes aware of infection, your body leaps to your defense.</s>
 <s id="10">Cells called macrophages charge in as the first line of attack, searching for and destroying the viruses and infected cells.</s>
 <s id="11">Afterwards, the macrophages release protein molecules called cytokines whose job is to recruit and organize more virus-busting cells from your immune system.</s>
 <s id="12">If this coordinated effort is strong enough, it'll wipe out the infection before you even notice it.</s>
 <s id="13">But that's just your body setting the scene for some real action.</s>
 <s id="14">In some cases, viruses spread further, even into the blood and vital organs.</s>
 <s id="15">To avoid this sometimes dangerous fate, your immune system must launch a stronger attack, coordinating its activity with the brain.</s>
 <s id="16">That's where those unpleasant symptoms come in, starting with the surging temperature, aches and pains, and sleepiness.</s>
 <s id="17">So why do we experience this?</s>
 <s id="18">When the immune system is under serious attack, it secretes more cytokines, which trigger two responses.</s>
 <s id="19">First, the vagus nerve, which runs through the body into the brain, quickly transmits the information to the brain stem, passing near an important area of pain processing.</s>
 <s id="20">Second, cytokines travel through the body to the hypothalamus, the part of the brain responsible for controlling temperature, thirst, hunger, and sleep, among other things.</s>
 <s id="21">When it receives this message, the hypothalamus produces another molecule called prostaglandin E2, which gears it up for war.</s>
 <s id="22">The hypothalamus sends signals that instruct your muscles to contract and causes a rise in body temperature.</s>
 <s id="23">It also makes you sleepy, and you lose your appetite and thirst.</s>
 <s id="24">But what's the point of all of these unpleasant symptoms?</s>
 <s id="25">Well, we're not yet sure, but some theorize that they aid in recovery.</s>
 <s id="26">The rise in temperature can slow bacteria and help your immune system destroy pathogens.</s>
 <s id="27">Sleep lets your body channel more energy towards fighting infection.</s>
 <s id="28">When you stop eating, your liver can take up much of the iron in your blood, and since iron is essential for bacterial survival, that effectively starves them.</s>
 <s id="29">Your reduced thirst makes you mildly dehydrated, diminishing transmission through sneezes, coughs, vomit, or diarrhea.</s>
 <s id="30">Though it's worth noting that if you don't drink enough water, that dehydration can become dangerous.</s>
 <s id="31">Even the body's aches make you more sensitive, drawing attention to infected cuts that might be worsening, or even causing your condition.</s>
 <s id="32">In addition to physical symptoms, sickness can also make you irritable, sad, and confused.</s>
 <s id="33">That's because cytokines and prostaglandin can reach even higher structures in your brain, disrupting the activity of neurotransmitters, like glutamate, endorphins, serotonin, and dopamine.</s>
 <s id="34">This affects areas like the limbic system, which oversees emotions, and your cerebral cortex, which is involved in reasoning.</s>
 <s id="35">So it's actually the body's own immune response that causes much of the discomfort you feel every time you get ill.</s>
 <s id="36">Unfortunately, it doesn't always work perfectly.</s>
 <s id="37">Most notably, millions of people worldwide suffer from autoimmune diseases, in which the immune system treats normal bodily cues as threats, so the body attacks itself.</s>
 <s id="38">But for the majority of the human race, millions of years of evolution have fine-tuned the immune system so that it works for, rather than against us.</s>
 <s id="39">The symptoms of our illnesses are annoying, but collectively, they signify an ancient process that will continue barricading our bodies against the outside world for centuries to come.</s>
</text>
