<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Hello.</s>
 <s id="2">I'm a toy developer.</s>
 <s id="3">With a dream of creating new toys that have never been seen before, I began working at a toy company nine years ago.</s>
 <s id="4">When I first started working there, I proposed many new ideas to my boss every day.</s>
 <s id="5">However, my boss always asked if I had the data to prove it would sell, and asked me to think of product development after analyzing market data.</s>
 <s id="6">Data, data, data.</s>
 <s id="7">So I analyzed the market data before thinking of a product.</s>
 <s id="8">However, I was unable to think of anything new at that moment.</s>
 <s id="9">(Laughter) My ideas were unoriginal.</s>
 <s id="10">I wasn't getting any new ideas and I grew tired of thinking.</s>
 <s id="11">It was so hard that I became this skinny.</s>
 <p id="p12">
  <s id="12.1">(Laughter) It's true.</s>
  <s id="12.2">(Applause) You've all probably had similar experiences and felt this way too.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">Your boss was being difficult.</s>
  <s id="13.2">The data was difficult.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">You become sick of thinking.</s>
 <s id="15">Now, I throw out the data.</s>
 <s id="16">It's my dream to create new toys.</s>
 <s id="17">And now, instead of data, I'm using a game called Shiritori to come up with new ideas.</s>
 <s id="18">I would like to introduce this method today.</s>
 <s id="19">What is Shiritori?</s>
 <s id="20">Take apple, elephant and trumpet, for example.</s>
 <s id="21">It's a game where you take turns saying words that start with the last letter of the previous word.</s>
 <s id="22">It's the same in Japanese and English.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">You can play Shiritori as you like: "neko, kora, raibu, burashi," etc, etc.</s>
  <s id="23.2">[Cat, cola, concert, brush] Many random words will come out.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="24">You force those words to connect to what you want to think of and form ideas.</s>
 <s id="25">In my case, for example, since I want to think of toys, what could a toy cat be?</s>
 <s id="26">A cat that lands after doing a somersault from a high place?</s>
 <s id="27">How about a toy with cola?</s>
 <s id="28">A toy gun where you shoot cola and get someone soaking wet?</s>
 <p id="p29">
  <s id="29.1">(Laughter) Ridiculous ideas are okay.</s>
  <s id="29.2">The key is to keep them flowing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="30">The more ideas you produce, you're sure to come up with some good ones, too.</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">A brush, for example.</s>
  <s id="31.2">Can we make a toothbrush into a toy?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">We could combine a toothbrush with a guitar and -- (Music noises) -- you've got a toy you can play with while brushing your teeth.</s>
 <s id="33">(Laughter) (Applause) Kids who don't like to brush their teeth might begin to like it.</s>
 <s id="34">Can we make a hat into a toy?</s>
 <s id="35">How about something like a roulette game, where you try the hat on one by one, and then, when someone puts it on, a scary alien breaks through the top screaming, "Ahh!"</s>
 <s id="36">I wonder if there would be a demand for this at parties?</s>
 <s id="37">Ideas that didn't come out while you stare at the data will start to come out.</s>
 <s id="38">Actually, this bubble wrap, which is used to pack fragile objects, combined with a toy, made Mugen Pop Pop, a toy where you can pop the bubbles as much as you like.</s>
 <s id="39">It was a big hit when it reached stores.</s>
 <s id="40">Data had nothing to do with its success.</s>
 <s id="41">Although it's only popping bubbles, it's a great way to kill time, so please pass this around amongst yourselves today and play with it.</s>
 <s id="42">(Applause) Anyway, you continue to come up with useless ideas.</s>
 <s id="43">Think up many trivial ideas, everyone.</s>
 <s id="44">If you base your ideas on data analysis and know what you're aiming for, you'll end up trying too hard, and you can't produce new ideas.</s>
 <s id="45">Even if you know what your aim is, think of ideas as freely as if you were throwing darts with your eyes closed.</s>
 <s id="46">If you do this, you surely will hit somewhere near the center.</s>
 <s id="47">At least one will.</s>
 <s id="48">That's the one you should choose.</s>
 <s id="49">If you do so, that idea will be in demand and, moreover, it will be brand new.</s>
 <s id="50">That is how I think of new ideas.</s>
 <s id="51">It doesn't have to be Shiritori; there are many different methods.</s>
 <s id="52">You just have to choose words at random.</s>
 <s id="53">You can flip through a dictionary and choose words at random.</s>
 <s id="54">For example, you could look up two random letters and gather the results or go to the store and connect product names with what you want to think of.</s>
 <s id="55">The point is to gather random words, not information from the category you're thinking for.</s>
 <s id="56">If you do this, the ingredients for the association of ideas are collected and form connections that will produce many ideas.</s>
 <s id="57">The greatest advantage to this method is the continuous flow of images.</s>
 <s id="58">Because you're thinking of one word after another, the image of the previous word is still with you.</s>
 <s id="59">That image will automatically be related with future words.</s>
 <s id="60">Unconsciously, a concert will be connected to a brush and a roulette game will be connected to a hat.</s>
 <s id="61">You wouldn't even realize it.</s>
 <s id="62">You can come up with ideas that you wouldn't have thought of otherwise.</s>
 <s id="63">This method is, of course, not just for toys.</s>
 <s id="64">You can collect ideas for books, apps, events, and many other projects.</s>
 <s id="65">I hope you all try this method.</s>
 <s id="66">There are futures that are born from data.</s>
 <s id="67">However, using this silly game called Shiritori, I look forward to the exciting future you will create, a future you couldn't even imagine.</s>
 <s id="68">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="69">(Applause)</s>
</text>
