<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Last year ...</s>
 <s id="2">was hell.</s>
 <s id="3">(Laughter) It was my first time eating Nigerian "jollof."</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) Actually, in all seriousness, I was going through a lot of personal turmoil.</s>
 <s id="5">Faced with enormous stress, I suffered an anxiety attack.</s>
 <s id="6">On some days, I could do no work.</s>
 <s id="7">On other days, I just wanted to lay in my bed and cry.</s>
 <s id="8">My doctor asked if I'd like to speak with a mental health professional about my stress and anxiety.</s>
 <s id="9">Mental health?</s>
 <s id="10">I clammed up and violently shook my head in protest.</s>
 <s id="11">I felt a profound sense of a shame.</s>
 <s id="12">I felt the weight of stigma.</s>
 <s id="13">I have a loving, supportive family and incredibly loyal friends, yet I could not entertain the idea of speaking to anyone about my feeling of pain.</s>
 <s id="14">I felt suffocated by the rigid architecture of our African masculinity.</s>
 <s id="15">"People have real problems, Sangu.</s>
 <s id="16">Get over yourself!"</s>
 <s id="17">The first time I heard "mental health," I was a boarding school student fresh off the boat from Ghana, at the Peddie School in New Jersey.</s>
 <s id="18">I had just gone through the brutal experience of losing seven loved ones in the same month.</s>
 <s id="19">The school nurse, concerned about what I'd gone through -- God bless her soul -- she inquired about my mental health.</s>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">"Is she mental?"</s>
  <s id="20.2">I thought.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="21">Does she not know I'm an African man?</s>
 <s id="22">(Laughter) Like Okonkwo in "Things Fall Apart," we African men neither process nor express our emotions.</s>
 <s id="23">We deal with our problems.</s>
 <s id="24">(Applause) We deal with our problems.</s>
 <s id="25">I called my brother and laughed about "Oyibo" people -- white people -- and their strange diseases -- depression, ADD and those "weird things."</s>
 <s id="26">Growing up in West Africa, when people used the term "mental," what came to mind was a madman with dirty, dread-locked hair, bumbling around half-naked on the streets.</s>
 <s id="27">We all know this man.</s>
 <s id="28">Our parents warned us about him.</s>
 <s id="29">"Mommy, mommy, why is he mad?"</s>
 <s id="30">"Drugs!</s>
 <s id="31">If you even look at drugs, you end up like him."</s>
 <s id="32">(Laughter) Come down with pneumonia, and your mother will rush you to the nearest hospital for medical treatment.</s>
 <s id="33">But dare to declare depression, and your local pastor will be driving out demons and blaming witches in your village.</s>
 <s id="34">According to the World Health Organization, mental health is about being able to cope with the normal stressors of life; to work productively and fruitfully; and to be able to make a contribution to your community.</s>
 <s id="35">Mental health includes our emotional, psychological and social well-being.</s>
 <s id="36">Globally, 75 percent of all mental illness cases can be found in low-income countries.</s>
 <s id="37">Yet most African governments invest less than one percent of their health care budget in mental health.</s>
 <s id="38">Even worse, we have a severe shortage of psychiatrists in Africa.</s>
 <s id="39">Nigeria, for example, is estimated to have 200 -- in a country of almost 200 million.</s>
 <s id="40">In all of Africa, 90 percent of our people lack access to treatment.</s>
 <s id="41">As a result, we suffer in solitude, silenced by stigma.</s>
 <s id="42">We as Africans often respond to mental health with distance, ignorance, guilt, fear and anger.</s>
 <s id="43">In a study conducted by Arboleda-Flórez, directly asking, "What is the cause of mental illness?"</s>
 <s id="44">34 percent of Nigerian respondents cited drug misuse; 19 percent said divine wrath and the will of God -- (Laughter) 12 percent, witchcraft and spiritual possession.</s>
 <s id="45">But few cited other known causes of mental illness, like genetics, socioeconomic status, war, conflict or the loss of a loved one.</s>
 <s id="46">The stigmatization against mental illness often results in the ostracizing and demonizing of sufferers.</s>
 <s id="47">Photojournalist Robin Hammond has documented some of these abuses ...</s>
 <s id="48">in Uganda, in Somalia, and here in Nigeria.</s>
 <s id="49">For me, the stigma is personal.</s>
 <s id="50">In 2009, I received a frantic call in the middle of the night.</s>
 <s id="51">My best friend in the world -- a brilliant, philosophical, charming, hip young man -- was diagnosed with schizophrenia.</s>
 <s id="52">I witnessed some of the friends we'd grown up with recoil.</s>
 <s id="53">I heard the snickers.</s>
 <s id="54">I heard the whispers.</s>
 <s id="55">"Did you hear he has gone mad?"</s>
 <s id="56">(Kru English) "He has gone crazy!"</s>
 <s id="57">Derogatory, demeaning commentary about his condition -- words we would never say about someone with cancer or someone with malaria.</s>
 <s id="58">Somehow, when it comes to mental illness, our ignorance eviscerates all empathy.</s>
 <s id="59">I stood by his side as his community isolated him, but our love never wavered.</s>
 <s id="60">Tacitly, I became passionate about mental health.</s>
 <s id="61">Inspired by his plight, I helped found the mental health special interest alumni group at my college.</s>
 <s id="62">And during my tenure as a resident tutor in graduate school, I supported many undergraduates with their mental health challenges.</s>
 <s id="63">I saw African students struggle and unable to speak to anyone.</s>
 <s id="64">Even with this knowledge and with their stories in tow, I, in turn, struggled, and could not speak to anyone when I faced my own anxiety, so deep is our fear of being the madman.</s>
 <s id="65">All of us -- but we Africans especially -- need to realize that our mental struggles do not detract from our virility, nor does our trauma taint our strength.</s>
 <s id="66">We need to see mental health as important as physical health.</s>
 <s id="67">We need to stop suffering in silence.</s>
 <s id="68">We must stop stigmatizing disease and traumatizing the afflicted.</s>
 <s id="69">Talk to your friends.</s>
 <s id="70">Talk to your loved ones.</s>
 <s id="71">Talk to health professionals.</s>
 <s id="72">Be vulnerable.</s>
 <s id="73">Do so with the confidence that you are not alone.</s>
 <s id="74">Speak up if you're struggling.</s>
 <s id="75">Being honest about how we feel does not make us weak; it makes us human.</s>
 <s id="76">It is time to end the stigma associated with mental illness.</s>
 <s id="77">So the next time your hear "mental," do not just think of the madman.</s>
 <s id="78">Think of me.</s>
 <s id="79">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="80">(Applause)</s>
</text>
