<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Music) I want everyone to put their hands on top of their head.</s>
 <p id="p2">
  <s id="2.1">Yeah, yeah, yeah.</s>
  <s id="2.2">Put your hands on top of your head.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p3">
  <s id="3.1">Just relax.</s>
  <s id="3.2">Just stay calm.</s>
  <s id="3.3">Everything will be nice and smooth if you just participate and just relax, okay?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">Yeah.</s>
  <s id="4.2">All right, now put your hands down.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p5">
  <s id="5.1">Don't be no hero.</s>
  <s id="5.2">Put your hands down.</s>
  <s id="5.3">Okay?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">All right.</s>
  <s id="6.2">Now.</s>
  <s id="6.3">Cool.</s>
  <s id="6.4">Good.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="7">I want you to run all that financial aid.</s>
 <s id="8">Yeah, sucka, put the scholarships in the bag, yeah, yeah.</s>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">Put the scholarships in the bag.</s>
  <s id="9.2">Yeah, you too, yeah, yeah, yeah.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p10">
  <s id="10.1">Yeah, you.</s>
  <s id="10.2">Yeah, yeah.</s>
  <s id="10.3">You over there, go put the Pell Grants in the bag.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p11">
  <s id="11.1">Put the Pell Grants in there too.</s>
  <s id="11.2">Yeah, you.</s>
  <s id="11.3">Go.</s>
  <s id="11.4">Yeah, yeah, yeah.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="12">You, go over to that booth and get me some of them subsidized, some of them subsidized loans.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">It ain't a game no more.</s>
  <s id="13.2">I know you're hiding the money somewhere here.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">With all this tuition you got me and my homies payin' -- Woo! -- I'm about to get gangster-scholar up in here.</s>
 <p id="p15">
  <s id="15.1">Up in here.</s>
  <s id="15.2">I'm about to go N.W.A. meets Beastie Boys if I don't see the cash, man.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="16">Cause we're not gonna take it. ♪ Oh ...</s>
 <s id="17">Oh, you thought I was playing.</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">Oh, you thought this was a game.</s>
  <s id="18.2">Back up, back up.</s>
  <s id="18.3">Mind your business, that's all.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">What do you, think this is a game?</s>
  <s id="19.2">What?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">Huh?</s>
  <s id="20.2">You don't even know me.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">I'll say something else.</s>
  <s id="21.2">Don't call me crazy.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="22">Do not call me -- Rives, tell 'em don't call me crazy before I go crazy.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">I'm telling you, now I'm about to go crazy.</s>
  <s id="23.2">I'm about to go Tupac Thug Life in here.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">Like, "I ain't a killer but don't push me.</s>
  <s id="24.2">Revenge is like the sweetest joy --" Woo!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">I'm about to go Biggie Smalls Brooklyn type, like, "Super Nintendo, Sega Genesis.</s>
  <s id="25.2">When I was dead broke --" Woo!</s>
  <s id="25.3">I'm about to go KRS-One cuckoo for Cocoa Puffs-type wild.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">Like, "Wa da da dang, wa da da da dang, listen to my nine millimeter go bang."</s>
  <s id="26.2">You know what?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p27">
  <s id="27.1">You are dumb.</s>
  <s id="27.2">You are really dumb.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">Hide your kids, hide your wife, 'cause we gettin' financial aid all up and in and around here.</s>
  <s id="28.2">You think this is a game?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">You think I want to be out here doing this?</s>
 <s id="30">Do you know how hard it was to find these guns?</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">All right, I'm sorry.</s>
  <s id="31.2">You understand?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">I'm just trying to get my education.</s>
  <s id="32.2">You know what I mean?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="33">I'm just trying to fight for the opportunity that my great-great-great-grandfather died for, you know what I'm saying?</s>
 <s id="34">You know how my ancestors did sit-ins, just so I can sit in a classroom.</s>
 <s id="35">And all these years, all y'all been doing is strangling the life out of my bank statement, leaving my pockets as vacant as parking lots.</s>
 <s id="36">Professor Willie Lynch taught you well, huh?</s>
 <s id="37">Keep the body, take the money.</s>
 <s id="38">Force feed my people deception and failure.</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">Condition our brains to malfunction at the sight of success.</s>
  <s id="39.2">Just keep the cycle going.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">Make us pay for an education that will end up failing us.</s>
 <s id="41">Put us in debt so we're giving back the money we earned from our back-breaking work.</s>
 <s id="42">This seems all too familiar.</s>
 <s id="43">Sounds like the rust of shackles locking their way onto my degree.</s>
 <s id="44">Sounds like the Thirteenth Amendment in reverse.</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">Lecture halls shouldn't feel like cotton fields, shouldn't sound like muffled freedom songs trapped in the jaws of a generation's dreams.</s>
  <s id="45.2">Oho!</s>
  <s id="45.3">Oh, it all makes sense.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="46">Give us enough to get by but not enough to provide for ourselves.</s>
 <s id="47">Keep us psychologically feeble so we lose our purpose in the process.</s>
 <s id="48">Stop thieving our aspirations out of our sleep.</s>
 <s id="49">Don't call it financial aid if you're not helping anyone with it.</s>
 <s id="50">We have fought.</s>
 <s id="51">We have fought way too hard to let green paper build a barricade in front of our futures.</s>
 <s id="52">I will not let you potentially rob food out of my children's stomach.</s>
 <s id="53">Best believe I'm going out blasting.</s>
 <s id="54">I ain't no killer, but don't push me.</s>
 <s id="55">I wish it didn't come to this, but I have to for my cousins in Haiti who don't even know what a college looks like, for my best friend Raymond sitting in cell block nine instead of a university, for the nooses hanging my GPA by its neck.</s>
 <s id="56">There is no other option.</s>
 <s id="57">There is no other way.</s>
 <s id="58">Just, please, put the money in the bag.</s>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">Put the money in the bag.</s>
  <s id="59.2">I just want to go to school, man.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p60">
  <s id="60.1">I just want to get my education.</s>
  <s id="60.2">I just want to learn.</s>
  <s id="60.3">I just want to grow.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="61">Put the money in the bag, please.</s>
 <s id="62">Just put the money in the bag.</s>
</text>
