<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <p id="p1">
  <s id="1.1">The annals of Ancient Egyptian king Thutmose III described a marvelous foreign bird that “gives birth daily.”</s>
  <s id="1.2">Zoroastrians viewed them as spirits whose cries told of the cosmic struggle between darkness and light.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="2">Romans brought them on their military campaigns to foretell the success of future battles.</s>
 <s id="3">And today, this bird still occupies an important, though much less honorable position – on our dinner plates.</s>
 <s id="4">The modern chicken is descended primarily from the Red Junglefowl, and partially from three other closely related species, all native to India and Southeast Asia.</s>
 <s id="5">The region’s bamboo plants produce massive amounts of fruit just once every few decades.</s>
 <s id="6">Junglefowls’ ability to lay eggs daily may have evolved to take advantage of these rare feasts, increasing their population when food was abundant.</s>
 <s id="7">This was something humans could exploit on a consistent basis, and the birds’ weak flight capabilities and limited need for space made them easy to capture and contain.</s>
 <s id="8">The earliest domesticated chickens, dating at least back to 7,000 years ago, weren’t bred for food, but for something considered less savory today.</s>
 <s id="9">The aggressiveness of breeding males, armed with natural leg spurs, made cockfighting a popular entertainment.</s>
 <s id="10">By the second millennium BCE, chickens had spread from the Indus Valley to China and the Middle East to occupy royal menageries and to be used in religious rituals.</s>
 <s id="11">But it was in Egypt where the next chapter in the bird’s history began.</s>
 <s id="12">When a hen naturally incubates eggs, she will stop laying new ones and sit on a “clutch” of 6 or more eggs for 21 days.</s>
 <s id="13">By the middle of the 1st millennium BCE, the Egyptians had learned to artificially incubate chicken eggs by placing them in baskets over hot ashes.</s>
 <s id="14">That freed up hens to continue laying daily, and what had been a royal delicacy or religious offering became a common meal.</s>
 <s id="15">Around the same time as Egyptians were incubating eggs, Phoenician merchants introduced chickens to Europe, where they quickly became an essential part of European livestock.</s>
 <s id="16">However, for a long time, the chicken’s revered status continued to exist alongside its culinary one.</s>
 <s id="17">The Ancient Greeks used fighting roosters as inspirational examples for young soldiers.</s>
 <s id="18">The Romans consulted chickens as oracles.</s>
 <s id="19">And as late as the 7th Century, the chicken was considered a symbol for Christianity.</s>
 <s id="20">Over the next few centuries, chickens accompanied humans wherever they went, spreading throughout the world through trade, conquest, and colonization.</s>
 <s id="21">After the Opium Wars, Chinese breeds were brought to England and crossed with local chickens.</s>
 <s id="22">This gave rise to a phenomenon called “Hen Fever” or “The Fancy”, with farmers all over Europe striving to breed new varieties with particular combinations of traits.</s>
 <s id="23">This trend also caught the attention of a certain Charles Darwin, who wondered if a similar selective breeding process occurred in nature.</s>
 <s id="24">Darwin would observe hundreds of chickens while finalizing his historic work introducing the theory of Evolution.</s>
 <s id="25">But the chicken’s greatest contribution to science was yet to come.</s>
 <s id="26">In the early 20th century, a trio of British scientists conducted extensive crossbreeding of chickens, building on Gregor Mendel’s studies of genetic inheritance.</s>
 <s id="27">With their high genetic diversity, many distinct traits, and only 7 months between generations, chickens were the perfect subject.</s>
 <s id="28">This work resulted in the famous Punnett Square, used to show the genotypes that would result from breeding a given pairing.</s>
 <s id="29">Since then, numerous breeding initiatives have made chickens bigger and meatier, and allowed them to lay more eggs than ever.</s>
 <s id="30">Meanwhile, chicken production has shifted to an industrial, factory-like model, with birds raised in spaces with a footprint no larger than a sheet of paper.</s>
 <s id="31">And while there’s been a shift towards free-range farming due to animal rights and environmental concerns, most of the world’s more than 22 billion chickens today are factory farmed.</s>
 <s id="32">From gladiators and gifts to the gods, to traveling companions and research subjects, chickens have played many roles over the centuries.</s>
 <s id="33">And though they may not have come before the proverbial egg, chickens’ fascinating history tells us a great deal about our own.</s>
</text>
