<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Water is virtually everywhere, from soil moisture and ice caps, to the cells inside our own bodies.</s>
 <s id="2">Depending on factors like location, fat index, age, and sex, the average human is between 55-60% water.</s>
 <s id="3">At birth, human babies are even wetter.</s>
 <s id="4">Being 75% water, they are swimmingly similar to fish.</s>
 <s id="5">But their water composition drops to 65% by their first birthday.</s>
 <s id="6">So what role does water play in our bodies, and how much do we actually need to drink to stay healthy?</s>
 <s id="7">The H20 in our bodies works to cushion and lubricate joints, regulate temperature, and to nourish the brain and spinal cord.</s>
 <s id="8">Water isn't only in our blood.</s>
 <s id="9">An adult's brain and heart are almost three quarters water.</s>
 <s id="10">That's roughly equivalent to the amount of moisture in a banana.</s>
 <s id="11">Lungs are more similar to an apple at 83%.</s>
 <s id="12">And even seemingly dry human bones are 31% water.</s>
 <s id="13">If we are essentially made of water, and surrounded by water, why do we still need to drink so much?</s>
 <s id="14">Well, each day we lose two to three liters through our sweat, urine, and bowel movements, and even just from breathing.</s>
 <s id="15">While these functions are essential to our survival, we need to compensate for the fluid loss.</s>
 <s id="16">Maintaining a balanced water level is essential to avoid dehydration or over-hydration, both of which can have devastating effects on overall health.</s>
 <s id="17">At first detection of low water levels, sensory receptors in the brain's hypothalamus signal the release of antidiuretic hormone.</s>
 <s id="18">When it reached the kidneys, it creates aquaporins, special channels that enable blood to absorb and retain more water, leading to concentrated, dark urine.</s>
 <s id="19">Increased dehydration can cause notable drops in energy, mood, skin moisture, and blood pressure, as well as signs of cognitive impairment.</s>
 <s id="20">A dehydrated brain works harder to accomplish the same amount as a normal brain, and it even temporarily shrinks because of its lack of water.</s>
 <s id="21">Over-hydration, or hyponatremia, is usually caused by overconsumption of water in a short amount of time.</s>
 <s id="22">Athletes are often the victims of over-hydration because of complications in regulating water levels in extreme physical conditions.</s>
 <s id="23">Whereas the dehydrated brain amps up the production of antidiuretic hormone, the over-hydrated brain slows, or even stops, releasing it into the blood.</s>
 <s id="24">Sodium electrolytes in the body become diluted, causing cells to swell.</s>
 <s id="25">In severe cases, the kidneys can't keep up with the resulting volumes of dilute urine.</s>
 <s id="26">Water intoxication then occurs, possibly causing headache, vomiting, and, in rare instances, seizures or death.</s>
 <s id="27">But that's a pretty extreme situation.</s>
 <s id="28">On a normal, day-to-day basis, maintaining a well-hydrated system is easy to manage for those of us fortunate enough to have access to clean drinking water.</s>
 <s id="29">For a long time, conventional wisdom said that we should drink eight glasses a day.</s>
 <s id="30">That estimate has since been fine-tuned.</s>
 <s id="31">Now, the consensus is that the amount of water we need to imbibe depends largely on our weight and environment.</s>
 <s id="32">The recommended daily intake varies from between 2.5-3.7 liters of water for men, and about 2-2.7 liters for women, a range that is pushed up or down if we are healthy, active, old, or overheating.</s>
 <s id="33">While water is the healthiest hydrator, other beverages, even those with caffeine like coffee or tea, replenish fluids as well.</s>
 <s id="34">And water within food makes up about a fifth of our daily H20 intake.</s>
 <s id="35">Fruits and vegetables like strawberries, cucumbers, and even broccoli are over 90% water, and can supplement liquid intake while providing valuable nutrients and fiber.</s>
 <s id="36">Drinking well might also have various long-term benefits.</s>
 <s id="37">Studies have shown that optimal hydration can lower the chance of stroke, help manage diabetes, and potentially reduce the risk of certain types of cancer.</s>
 <s id="38">No matter what, getting the right amount of liquid makes a world of difference in how you'll feel, think, and function day to day.</s>
</text>
