<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Alright, I want to tell you how I got my superpowers through fatherhood.</s>
 <s id="2">I was working a job I hated, OK?</s>
 <s id="3">And I don't know if anyone here ever worked a job they hated.</s>
 <s id="4">Has anyone here ever worked a job they hated?</s>
 <s id="5">(Laughter) OK, good, because I'm not alone and I have something to confess; I don't want you guys to judge me.</s>
 <s id="6">This feels like a safe space, is it a safe space?</s>
 <s id="7">Audience: Yes.</s>
 <s id="8">Glen Henry: OK, I was working the job I hated, my manager and I were not getting along.</s>
 <s id="9">I was sitting in my car, looking in the rearview mirror, trying to figure out which friend I could call to call in a bomb threat, so I didn't have to go back in the building.</s>
 <s id="10">(Laughter) OK, this was having a lot of issues for me, I was having a lot of issues at my job and I'd come home every day from work and my wife would ask me the same question.</s>
 <s id="11">And when you hate your job, this is the worst question anyone could ask you.</s>
 <s id="12">She'd say, "Hey babe, how was your day?"</s>
 <s id="13">(Laughter) And I'd say, "Why you bringing up old stuff?"</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) I just left it, I don't want to think about that place again.</s>
 <s id="15">See, we were spending about 40 percent of my income on childcare.</s>
 <s id="16">We had one child.</s>
 <s id="17">And we were pregnant with our second child.</s>
 <s id="18">And we were trying to figure out how we were going to fix this whole thing of this money situation, and she said, "Hey, babe, I've got a great idea."</s>
 <s id="19">I said, "What's up?"</s>
 <s id="20">She said, "I think you'd be a great stay-at-home dad."</s>
 <s id="21">(Laughter) I was like, "Why would you say something like that?"</s>
 <s id="22">(Laughter) She said, "Because babies like you."</s>
 <s id="23">(Laughter) I was like, "No, they don't."</s>
 <s id="24">She was like, "No, they do like you.</s>
 <s id="25">And I think it would be great for our children to see what love looks like, coming from a father."</s>
 <s id="26">I was like, OK.</s>
 <s id="27">(Laughter) So, I had issues with this, because I haven't seen a lot of stay-at-home dads before and I thought men would judge me, so get this, I said this -- please don't be offended -- I said, "Uh, you know, that sounds boring.</s>
 <s id="28">And what do stay-at-home moms do all day, anyway?"</s>
 <s id="29">Audience: Ooh!</s>
 <s id="30">She smiled at me a smile only a woman full of knowledge can smile (Laughter) and said, "Well, this should be easy for you.</s>
 <s id="31">And it will save us some money, it seems like a no-brainer."</s>
 <s id="32">(Laughter) Fast-forward six months, I'd been a stay-at-home dad for about a week.</s>
 <s id="33">(Laughter) I was standing in my bathroom, looking into the mirror (Laughter) crying, tears -- (Laughter) running all down my face.</s>
 <s id="34">(Laughter) My one-and-a-half-year-old was banging on the bathroom door -- because I locked them out, you know -- (Laughter) crying, tears running down his face.</s>
 <s id="35">And my newborn was in the bassinet, crying, tears running down his face.</s>
 <s id="36">I looked at myself in the mirror, and I said ...</s>
 <s id="37">"Which friend can you call to call in a bomb threat?</s>
 <s id="38">We've got to get out of here."</s>
 <s id="39">(Laughter) See, I had traded my manager for my children.</s>
 <s id="40">I didn't know what I got myself into.</s>
 <s id="41">I thought I knew everything about being a stay-at-home parent, and in fact, I knew nothing at all.</s>
 <s id="42">Because even though my manager was -- well, at least my children were a lot cuter than my manager, they were just as demanding.</s>
 <s id="43">(Video) Child: Wipe my butt.</s>
 <s id="44">Papa, wipe my butt.</s>
 <s id="45">(Laughter) Wipe my butt.</s>
 <s id="46">(Laughter) GH: What had I gotten myself into?</s>
 <s id="47">I thought I knew everything about being a stay-at-home parent -- in fact, I knew nothing.</s>
 <s id="48">I thought that all I had to do was feed them, change their diapers, and they'd be fine.</s>
 <s id="49">Like, I really thought that's it.</s>
 <s id="50">"Sesame Street" on TV, keep them distracted, apple sauce in a bowl, milk in a bottle, they'd be fine.</s>
 <s id="51">But if you leave children alone, they'll get into just a little bit of mischief.</s>
 <s id="52">(Video) Child: Hi.</s>
 <s id="53">GH: Where is the powder?</s>
 <s id="54">Child: I don't know.</s>
 <s id="55">GH: Well, where did you put it, where did it -- Who did it?</s>
 <p id="p56">
  <s id="56.1">Child 1: No, you did it!</s>
  <s id="56.2">Child 2: No, you did it!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p57">
  <s id="57.1">Child 1: No, you did it!</s>
  <s id="57.2">Child 2: No, you did it!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="58">(Laughter) GH: You know what else I thought I knew about being a stay-at-home parent?</s>
 <s id="59">I thought that all I had to do was take them to the park once a week, because if I took them to the park once a week, they'd be fine.</s>
 <s id="60">In fact, I knew nothing at all.</s>
 <s id="61">OK.</s>
 <s id="62">If you take kids to park every day then that means they get dirty every day.</s>
 <s id="63">If they got dirty every day, they need baths every day, if they got baths every day -- I just don't think you understand, see, having two kids under two, you end up changing over 20 dirty diapers a day, OK.</s>
 <s id="64">And if you give them a bath, that's just more nakedness.</s>
 <s id="65">(Laughter) And a higher probability of getting peed on, and no one likes getting peed on, even if it's from a baby.</s>
 <s id="66">(Laughter) But I read this article by Father Lee which cites a survey done by two detergent companies, Omo and Persil.</s>
 <s id="67">And they did this study and it said, that at two hours a day, prisoners get more outside time than children.</s>
 <s id="68">That convicted me and so we went outside.</s>
 <s id="69">(Video) (Music) (Laughter) GH: See, I knew nothing about being a stay-at-home parent, and once I embraced the fact that I knew nothing, I began to learn from my new managers.</s>
 <s id="70">And I always was told that as a stay-at-home parent, you get no sleep.</s>
 <s id="71">Or as a parent in general, you get no sleep.</s>
 <s id="72">But that's not true, because if you sleep when they do, you actually can get some sleep.</s>
 <s id="73">(Laughter) You know what else I thought as a stay-at-home parent?</s>
 <s id="74">I though I knew that the best way to teach kids right from wrong was to discipline them, because that would make sure they understood right from wrong, the pain, the fear -- that would teach them.</s>
 <s id="75">But the truth is, the best way to teach my children right from wrong is to teach them.</s>
 <s id="76">Take out a whiteboard and draw pictures and make connections that they can understand.</s>
 <s id="77">That was the best way.</s>
 <s id="78">A lot of these images you're seeing are coming from my YouTube channel, "Beleaf in Fatherhood."</s>
 <s id="79">I document the misadventures of being a stay-at-home dad.</s>
 <s id="80">And it's not perfect, it's just showing that I'm trying.</s>
 <s id="81">And I'm not trying to be an example but just proof that it's possible for whoever else is doing this.</s>
 <s id="82">You know what I also knew about being a stay-at-home parent?</s>
 <s id="83">I knew that children needed love, but I just didn't know what love looked like.</s>
 <s id="84">(Video) (Music) GH: It turns out putting diapers on your head and play-fighting until the kids fall asleep is a great way to love your kids.</s>
 <s id="85">So, I was learning a lot, but it's not all fun and boogers, is it?</s>
 <s id="86">(Laughter) I asked a group of stay-at-home parents what's the hardest thing, the thing they underestimated most about being stay-at-home parents, and they said that the loneliness was one of those things.</s>
 <s id="87">Not having someone else to talk to, feeling inadequate, feeling selfish for wanting me-time.</s>
 <s id="88">And nursery rhymes suck.</s>
 <s id="89">(Laughter) Like, really, "Mary Had a Little Lamb" is cool the first couple of times, but after all these years on repeat, you wonder why Mary just ain't make herself a wool skirt and have lamb chops, you know what I'm saying?</s>
 <s id="90">(Laughter) The one thing I underestimated most was the emotional fatigue.</s>
 <s id="91">See, I was an artist, so I'd write songs for other artists.</s>
 <s id="92">Because that's how I made money from home.</s>
 <s id="93">But when you're with your kids all day, you become emotionally tired.</s>
 <s id="94">And that means all your creativity comes from your emotions, so you’re just tapped out, you're done.</s>
 <s id="95">So you become done with time.</s>
 <s id="96">Nap time, time-tables, time-out, time like to cook, with all types of time, you're just done.</s>
 <s id="97">You had no time for anything.</s>
 <s id="98">And some people are done with their spouse as a stay-at-home parent.</s>
 <s id="99">Because the spouse just doesn't get it.</s>
 <s id="100">I was talking to a friend of mine, he said, "Man, I come home from work, drawers are open, clothes hanging outside the drawers, the kids are still in their pajamas ...</s>
 <s id="101">And it can't be that hard to have dinner ready when I get home, right?"</s>
 <s id="102">(Laughter) Start to freak out, you know what I'm saying?</s>
 <s id="103">(Laughter) He was trying to confide in me -- (Laughter) I said, "You have no idea what you're talking about."</s>
 <s id="104">(Laughter) She wakes up every morning, tired from the night before, baby attached to her breast, dropping this kid off at school, and taking this one to the park.</s>
 <s id="105">Laundry piles up to the skies, he has a conversation on the phone for an hour with your mom about God knows what, takes the dog you wanted for a walk ...</s>
 <s id="106">(Laughter) And nobody died, bro.</s>
 <s id="107">She kept your kids alive all day, that's hard."</s>
 <s id="108">(Laughter) I have become an advocate for stay-at-home parents.</s>
 <s id="109">Why?</s>
 <s id="110">Because finally, I was standing in their shoes.</s>
 <s id="111">Because when you're standing in someone else's shoes, you see the world from a different perspective.</s>
 <s id="112">And when you start to take steps, it feels like baby steps, wobbling.</s>
 <s id="113">But then they turn into stomps.</s>
 <s id="114">And you start making footprints for the next generation to walk in.</s>
 <s id="115">See, we're walking on a certain path, as parents.</s>
 <s id="116">We're all in this together.</s>
 <s id="117">No one can deny that family is one of the biggest foundations in anyone's life.</s>
 <s id="118">And we're all walking on this path, and we're pulling these thickets out of the way, and these thorns, making it easier for the ones coming after us.</s>
 <s id="119">It turns out, parenting has a lot more to do with landscaping.</s>
 <s id="120">And learning.</s>
 <s id="121">More than teaching.</s>
 <s id="122">And the best thing to do is to show up for class.</s>
 <s id="123">Be present is what I learned as a stay-at-home dad.</s>
 <s id="124">And let your presence be a gift.</s>
 <s id="125">(Video) Shh.</s>
 <s id="126">(Door unlocking) Hi!</s>
 <s id="127">(Children giggling) (Laughter) GH: This was me, coming home from tour one day.</s>
 <s id="128">I thought that the father was supposed to pursue the child.</s>
 <s id="129">But it turns out the father makes himself present.</s>
 <s id="130">And the children run after him.</s>
 <s id="131">And that right there is a superpower.</s>
 <s id="132">And that right there, my friends, is everything.</s>
 <s id="133">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="134">(Applause)</s>
</text>
