<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I've been a political cartoonist on the global stage for the last 20 years.</s>
 <s id="2">Hey, we have seen a lot of things happen in those 20 years.</s>
 <s id="3">We saw three different Catholic popes, and we witnessed that unique moment: the election of a pope on St. Peter's Square -- you know, the little white smoke and the official announcement.</s>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">[It's a boy!]</s>
  <s id="4.2">(Laughter) (Applause) We saw four American presidents.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="5">Obama, of course.</s>
 <s id="6">Oh, Europeans liked him a lot.</s>
 <s id="7">He was a multilateralist.</s>
 <s id="8">He favored diplomacy.</s>
 <s id="9">He wanted to be friends with Iran.</s>
 <s id="10">(Laughter) And then ...</s>
 <s id="11">reality imitated caricature the day Donald Trump became the President of the United States of America.</s>
 <p id="p12">
  <s id="12.1">(Laughter) (Applause) You know, people come to us and they say, "It's too easy for you cartoonists.</s>
  <s id="12.2">I mean -- with people like Trump?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="13">Well, no, it's not easy to caricature a man who is himself a caricature.</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) No.</s>
 <s id="15">(Applause) Populists are no easy target for satire because you try to nail them down one day, and the next day, they outdo you.</s>
 <s id="16">For example, as soon as he was elected, I tried to imagine the tweet that Trump would send on Christmas Eve.</s>
 <s id="17">So I did this, OK?</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">[Merry Christmas to all!</s>
  <s id="18.2">Except all those pathetic losers.</s>
  <s id="18.3">So sad.]</s>
  <s id="18.4">(Laughter) And basically, the next day, Trump tweeted this: [Happy New Year to all, including to my many enemies and those who have fought me and lost so badly they just don't know what to do.</s>
  <s id="18.5">Love!]</s>
  <s id="18.6">(Laughter) It's the same!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="19">(Applause) This is the era of strongmen.</s>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">And soon, Donald Trump was able to meet his personal hero, Vladimir Putin, and this is how the first meeting went: [I'll help you find the hackers.</s>
  <s id="20.2">Give me your password.]</s>
  <s id="20.3">(Laughter) And I'm not inventing anything.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="21">He came out of that first meeting saying that the two of them had agreed on a joint task force on cybersecurity.</s>
 <s id="22">This is true, if you do remember.</s>
 <s id="23">Oh, who would have imagined the things we saw over these 20 years.</s>
 <s id="24">We saw Great Britain run towards a European Union exit.</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">[Hard Brexit?]</s>
  <s id="25.2">(Laughter) In the Middle East, we believed for a while in the democratic miracle of the Arab Spring.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">We saw dictators fall, we saw others hang on.</s>
 <s id="27">(Laughter) And then there is the timeless Kim dynasty of North Korea.</s>
 <s id="28">These guys seem to be coming straight out of Cartoon Network.</s>
 <s id="29">I was blessed to be able to draw two of them.</s>
 <s id="30">Kim Jong-il, the father, when he died a few years ago, that was a very dangerous moment.</s>
 <p id="p31">
  <s id="31.1">[That was close!]</s>
  <s id="31.2">(Laughter) That was -- (Applause) And then the son, Kim Jong-un, proved himself a worthy successor to the throne.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="32">He's now friends with the US president.</s>
 <s id="33">They meet each other all the time, and they talk like friends.</s>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">[What kind of hair gel?]</s>
  <s id="34.2">(Laughter) Should we be surprised to be living in a world ruled by egomaniacs?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="35">What if they were just a reflection of ourselves?</s>
 <s id="36">I mean, look at us, each of us.</s>
 <s id="37">(Laughter) Yeah, we love our smartphones; we love our selfies; we love ourselves.</s>
 <s id="38">And thanks to Facebook, we have a lot of friends all over the world.</s>
 <s id="39">Mark Zuckerberg is our friend.</s>
 <s id="40">(Laughter) You know, he and his peers in Silicon Valley are the kings and the emperors of our time.</s>
 <s id="41">Showing that the emperors have no clothes, that's the task of satire, right?</s>
 <s id="42">Speaking truth to power.</s>
 <s id="43">This has always been the historical role of political cartooning.</s>
 <s id="44">In the 1830s, postrevolutionary France under King Louis Philippe, journalists and caricaturists fought hard for the freedom of the press.</s>
 <s id="45">They were jailed, they were fined, but they prevailed.</s>
 <s id="46">And this caricature of the king by Daumier came to define the monarch.</s>
 <s id="47">It marked history.</s>
 <s id="48">It became the timeless symbol of satire triumphing over autocracy.</s>
 <s id="49">Today, 200 years after Daumier, are political cartoons at risk of disappearing?</s>
 <s id="50">Take this blank space on the front page of Turkish opposition newspaper "Cumhuriyet."</s>
 <s id="51">This is where Musa Kart's cartoon used to appear.</s>
 <s id="52">In 2018, Musa Kart was sentenced to three years in jail.</s>
 <s id="53">For doing what?</s>
 <s id="54">For doing political cartoons in Erdoğan's Turkey.</s>
 <s id="55">Cartoonists from Venezuela, Russia, Syria have been forced into exile.</s>
 <s id="56">Look at this image.</s>
 <s id="57">It seems so innocent, right?</s>
 <s id="58">Yet it is so provocative.</s>
 <s id="59">When he posted this image, Hani Abbas knew it would change his life.</s>
 <s id="60">It was in 2012, and the Syrians were taking to the streets.</s>
 <s id="61">Of course, the little red flower is the symbol of the Syrian revolution.</s>
 <s id="62">So pretty soon, the regime was after him, and he had to flee the country.</s>
 <s id="63">A good friend of his, cartoonist Akram Raslan, didn't make it out of Syria.</s>
 <s id="64">He died under torture.</s>
 <p id="p65">
  <s id="65.1">In the United States of America recently, some of the very top cartoonists, like Nick Anderson and Rob Rogers -- this is a cartoon by Rob -- [Memorial Day 2018. (on tombstone) Truth.</s>
  <s id="65.2">Honor.</s>
  <s id="65.3">Rule of Law.] they lost their positions because their publishers found their work too critical of Trump.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="66">And the same happened to Canadian cartoonist Michael de Adder.</s>
 <s id="67">Hey, maybe we should start worrying.</s>
 <s id="68">Political cartoons were born with democracy, and they are challenged when freedom is.</s>
 <s id="69">You know, over the years, with the Cartooning for Peace Foundation and other initiatives, Kofi Annan -- this is not well known -- he was the honorary chair of our foundation, the late Kofi Annan, Nobel Peace Laureate.</s>
 <s id="70">He was a great defender of cartoons.</s>
 <s id="71">Or, on the board of the Association of American Editorial Cartoonists, we have advocated on behalf of jailed, threatened, fired, exiled cartoonists.</s>
 <s id="72">But I never saw a case of someone losing his job over a cartoon he didn't do.</s>
 <s id="73">Well, that happened to me.</s>
 <s id="74">For the last 20 years, I have been with the "International Herald Tribune" and the "New York Times."</s>
 <s id="75">Then something happened.</s>
 <s id="76">In April 2019, a cartoon by a famous Portuguese cartoonist, which was first published in a newspaper "El Expresso" in Lisbon, was picked by an editor at the "New York Times" and reprinted in the international editions.</s>
 <s id="77">This thing blew up.</s>
 <s id="78">It was denounced as anti-Semitic, triggered widespread outrage, apologies and a lot of damage control by the Times.</s>
 <s id="79">A month after, my editor told me they were ending political cartoons altogether.</s>
 <s id="80">So we could, and we should, have a discussion about that cartoon.</s>
 <s id="81">Some people say it reminds them of the worst anti-Semitic propaganda.</s>
 <s id="82">Others, including in Israel, say no, it's just a harsh criticism of Trump, who is shown as blindly following the Prime Minister of Israel.</s>
 <s id="83">I have some issues with this cartoon, but that discussion did not happen at the "New York Times."</s>
 <s id="84">Under attack, they took the easiest path: in order to not have problems with political cartoons in the future, let's not have any at all.</s>
 <s id="85">Hey, this is new.</s>
 <s id="86">Did we just invent preventive self-censorship?</s>
 <s id="87">I think this is bigger than cartoons.</s>
 <s id="88">This is about opinion and journalism.</s>
 <s id="89">This, in the end, is about democracy.</s>
 <s id="90">We now live in a world where moralistic mobs gather on social media and rise like a storm.</s>
 <s id="91">The most outraged voices tend to define the conversation, and the angry crowd follows in.</s>
 <s id="92">These social media mobs, sometimes fueled by interest groups, fall upon newsrooms in an overwhelming blow.</s>
 <s id="93">They send publishers and editors scrambling for countermeasures.</s>
 <s id="94">This leaves no room for meaningful discussions.</s>
 <s id="95">Twitter is a place for fury, not for debate.</s>
 <s id="96">And you know what?</s>
 <s id="97">Someone described pretty well our human condition in this noisy age.</s>
 <s id="98">You know who?</s>
 <s id="99">Shakespeare, 400 years ago.</s>
 <p id="p100">
  <s id="100.1">["(Life is) a tale told by an idiot, full of sound and fury, signifying nothing."]</s>
  <s id="100.2">This speaks to me.</s>
  <s id="100.3">Shakespeare is still very relevant, no?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="101">But the world has changed a bit.</s>
 <p id="p102">
  <s id="102.1">[Too long!]</s>
  <s id="102.2">(Laughter) It's true.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="103">(Applause) You know, social media is both a blessing and a curse for cartoons.</s>
 <s id="104">This is the era of the image, so they get shared, they get viral, but that also makes them a prime target.</s>
 <s id="105">More than often, the real target behind the cartoon is the media that published it.</s>
 <p id="p106">
  <s id="106.1">[Covering Iraq?</s>
  <s id="106.2">No, Trump!]</s>
  <s id="106.3">That relationship between traditional media and social media is a funny one.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="107">On one hand, you have the time-consuming process of information, verification, curation.</s>
 <s id="108">On the other hand, it's an open buffet, frankly, for rumors, opinions, emotions, amplified by algorithms.</s>
 <s id="109">Even quality newspapers mimic the codes of social networks on their websites.</s>
 <s id="110">They highlight the 10 most read, the 10 most shared stories.</s>
 <s id="111">They should put forward the 10 most important stories.</s>
 <s id="112">(Applause) The media must not be intimidated by social media, and editors should stop being afraid of the angry mob.</s>
 <s id="113">(Applause) We're not going to put up warnings the way we do on cigarette packs, are we?</s>
 <s id="114">[Satire can hurt your feelings] (Laughter) Come on.</s>
 <s id="115">[Under your burkini you could be hiding a sex bomb] Political cartoons are meant to provoke, just like opinions.</s>
 <s id="116">But before all, they are meant to be thought-provoking.</s>
 <s id="117">You feel hurt?</s>
 <s id="118">Just let it go.</s>
 <s id="119">You don't like it?</s>
 <s id="120">Look the other way.</s>
 <s id="121">Freedom of expression is not incompatible with dialogue and listening to each other.</s>
 <s id="122">But it is incompatible with intolerance.</s>
 <s id="123">(Applause) Let us not become our own censors in the name of political correctness.</s>
 <s id="124">We need to stand up, we need to push back, because if we don't, we will wake up tomorrow in a sanitized world, where any form of satire and political cartooning becomes impossible.</s>
 <s id="125">Because, when political pressure meets political correctness, freedom of speech perishes.</s>
 <s id="126">(Applause) Do you remember January 2015?</s>
 <s id="127">With the massacre of journalists and cartoonists at "Charlie Hebdo" in Paris, we discovered the most extreme form of censorship: murder.</s>
 <s id="128">Remember how it felt.</s>
 <s id="129">[Without humor we are all dead] Whatever one thought of that satirical magazine, however one felt about those particular cartoons, we all sensed that something fundamental was at stake, that citizens of free societies -- actually, citizens of any society -- need humor as much as the air we breathe.</s>
 <s id="130">This is why the extremists, the dictators, the autocrats and, frankly, all the ideologues of the world cannot stand humor.</s>
 <s id="131">In the insane world we live in right now, we need political cartoons more than ever.</s>
 <s id="132">And we need humor.</s>
 <s id="133">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="134">(Applause)</s>
</text>
