<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Companies are losing control.</s>
 <s id="2">What happens on Wall Street no longer stays on Wall Street.</s>
 <p id="p3">
  <s id="3.1">What happens in Vegas ends up on YouTube.</s>
  <s id="3.2">(Laughter) Reputations are volatile.</s>
  <s id="3.3">Loyalties are fickle.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">Management teams seem increasingly disconnected from their staff.</s>
  <s id="4.2">(Laughter) A recent survey said that 27 percent of bosses believe their employees are inspired by their firm.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="5">However, in the same survey, only four percent of employees agreed.</s>
 <s id="6">Companies are losing control of their customers and their employees.</s>
 <s id="7">But are they really?</s>
 <s id="8">I'm a marketer, and as a marketer, I know that I've never really been in control.</s>
 <s id="9">Your brand is what other people say about you when you're not in the room, the saying goes.</s>
 <s id="10">Hyperconnectivity and transparency allow companies to be in that room now, 24/7.</s>
 <s id="11">They can listen and join the conversation.</s>
 <s id="12">In fact, they have more control over the loss of control than ever before.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">They can design for it.</s>
  <s id="13.2">But how?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="14">First of all, they can give employees and customers more control.</s>
 <s id="15">They can collaborate with them on the creation of ideas, knowledge, content, designs and product.</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">They can give them more control over pricing, which is what the band Radiohead did with its pay-as-you-like online release of its album "In Rainbows."</s>
  <s id="16.2">Buyers could determine the price, but the offer was exclusive, and only stood for a limited period of time.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="17">The album sold more copies than previous releases of the band.</s>
 <s id="18">The Danish chocolate company Anthon Berg opened a so-called "generous store" in Copenhagen.</s>
 <s id="19">It asked customers to purchase chocolate with the promise of good deeds towards loved ones.</s>
 <s id="20">It turned transactions into interactions, and generosity into a currency.</s>
 <s id="21">Companies can even give control to hackers.</s>
 <s id="22">When Microsoft Kinect came out, the motion-controlled add-on to its Xbox gaming console, it immediately drew the attention of hackers.</s>
 <s id="23">Microsoft first fought off the hacks, but then shifted course when it realized that actively supporting the community came with benefits.</s>
 <s id="24">The sense of co-ownership, the free publicity, the added value, all helped drive sales.</s>
 <s id="25">The ultimate empowerment of customers is to ask them not to buy.</s>
 <s id="26">Outdoor clothier Patagonia encouraged prospective buyers to check out eBay for its used products and to resole their shoes before purchasing new ones.</s>
 <s id="27">In an even more radical stance against consumerism, the company placed a "Don't Buy This Jacket" advertisement during the peak of shopping season.</s>
 <s id="28">It may have jeopardized short-term sales, but it builds lasting, long-term loyalty based on shared values.</s>
 <s id="29">Research has shown that giving employees more control over their work makes them happier and more productive.</s>
 <s id="30">The Brazilian company Semco Group famously lets employees set their own work schedules and even their salaries.</s>
 <s id="31">Hulu and Netflix, among other companies, have open vacation policies.</s>
 <s id="32">Companies can give people more control, but they can also give them less control.</s>
 <s id="33">Traditional business wisdom holds that trust is earned by predictable behavior, but when everything is consistent and standardized, how do you create meaningful experiences?</s>
 <s id="34">Giving people less control might be a wonderful way to counter the abundance of choice and make them happier.</s>
 <s id="35">Take the travel service Nextpedition.</s>
 <s id="36">Nextpedition turns the trip into a game, with surprising twists and turns along the way.</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">It does not tell the traveler where she's going until the very last minute, and information is provided just in time.</s>
  <s id="37.2">Similarly, Dutch airline KLM launched a surprise campaign, seemingly randomly handing out small gifts to travelers en route to their destination.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="38">U.K.-based Interflora monitored Twitter for users who were having a bad day, and then sent them a free bouquet of flowers.</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">Is there anything companies can do to make their employees feel less pressed for time?</s>
  <s id="39.2">Yes.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">Force them to help others.</s>
 <s id="41">A recent study suggests that having employees complete occasional altruistic tasks throughout the day increases their sense of overall productivity.</s>
 <s id="42">At Frog, the company I work for, we hold internal speed meet sessions that connect old and new employees, helping them get to know each other fast.</s>
 <s id="43">By applying a strict process, we give them less control, less choice, but we enable more and richer social interactions.</s>
 <s id="44">Companies are the makers of their fortunes, and like all of us, they are utterly exposed to serendipity.</s>
 <s id="45">That should make them more humble, more vulnerable and more human.</s>
 <s id="46">At the end of the day, as hyperconnectivity and transparency expose companies' behavior in broad daylight, staying true to their true selves is the only sustainable value proposition.</s>
 <s id="47">Or as the ballet dancer Alonzo King said, "What's interesting about you is you."</s>
 <s id="48">For the true selves of companies to come through, openness is paramount, but radical openness is not a solution, because when everything is open, nothing is open.</s>
 <s id="49">"A smile is a door that is half open and half closed," the author Jennifer Egan wrote.</s>
 <p id="p50">
  <s id="50.1">Companies can give their employees and customers more control or less.</s>
  <s id="50.2">They can worry about how much openness is good for them, and what needs to stay closed.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="51">Or they can simply smile, and remain open to all possibilities.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">Thank you.</s>
  <s id="52.2">(Applause) (Applause)</s>
 </p>
</text>
