<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">As the April sun rises on a pile of firewood, something royal stirs inside.</s>
 <s id="2">This wasp queen is one of thousands who mated in late autumn and hibernated through the winter.</s>
 <s id="3">Now she emerges into the spring air to begin her reign.</s>
 <s id="4">Most of her sisters weren’t so lucky.</s>
 <s id="5">While hibernating in compost piles and underground burrows, many sleeping queens were eaten by spiders.</s>
 <s id="6">Warm winters caused by climate change led other queens to emerge early, only to find there was no available food.</s>
 <s id="7">And some queens that survived the winter fell victim to the threats of spring, such as carnivorous plants, birds, and manmade pesticides.</s>
 <s id="8">Our queen is the lone survivor of her old hive, and now, she must become the foundress of a new one.</s>
 <s id="9">But first, breakfast.</s>
 <s id="10">The queen heads for a citrus grove full of honeybee hives.</s>
 <s id="11">The bees can be dangerous if provoked, but right now they’re paralyzed by the morning cold.</s>
 <s id="12">Their hairy bodies are dripping with sugar water from an earlier feeding, and the resourceful queen licks them for a morning snack.</s>
 <s id="13">Newly energized, our queen searches for a safe nesting area.</s>
 <s id="14">This tree hollow, safe from rain, wind, and predators, is ideal.</s>
 <s id="15">She chews the surrounding wood and plant fibers to make a paper-like pulp.</s>
 <s id="16">Then she builds around 50 brood cells that comprise the beginning of her nest.</s>
 <s id="17">Using sperm stored from last fall, the queen lays a fertilized egg into each cell, producing as many as 12 in 20 minutes.</s>
 <s id="18">Within a week, these will hatch into female larva.</s>
 <s id="19">But until then, the queen must hunt down smaller insects to feed her brood, all while expanding the hive, laying eggs, and defending against intruders.</s>
 <s id="20">Fortunately, our queen is well prepared.</s>
 <s id="21">Unlike bees, wasps can sting as many times as they need to.</s>
 <s id="22">With such a busy schedule, the queen barely has time to feed herself.</s>
 <s id="23">Luckily, she doesn’t have to.</s>
 <s id="24">When she feeds an insect to her grubs, they digest the bug into a sugary substance that sustains their mother.</s>
 <s id="25">By the end of July, these first larva have matured into adult workers, ready to take on foraging, building, and defense.</s>
 <s id="26">The queen can now lay eggs full-time, sustaining herself on her worker’s spoils and their unfertilized eggs.</s>
 <s id="27">Although each worker only lives for roughly 3 weeks, the queen’s continuous egg-laying swells their ranks.</s>
 <s id="28">In just one summer, the nest reaches the size of a basketball, supporting thousands of workers.</s>
 <s id="29">Such a large population needs to eat, and the nearby garden provides a veritable buffet.</s>
 <s id="30">As the swarm descends, alarmed humans try to swat them.</s>
 <s id="31">They even fight back with pesticides that purposefully poison wasps, and inadvertently impact a wide-range of local wildlife.</s>
 <s id="32">But the wasps are actually vital to this ecosystem.</s>
 <s id="33">Sitting at the top of the local invertebrate food chain, these insects keep spiders, mites, and centipedes, in check.</s>
 <s id="34">Wasps consume crop-eating insects, making them particularly helpful for farms and gardens.</s>
 <s id="35">They even pollinate fruits and vegetables, and help winemakers by biting into their grapes and jump-starting fermentation.</s>
 <s id="36">This feast continues until autumn, when the foundress changes course.</s>
 <s id="37">She begins grooming some eggs into a new generation of queens, while also laying unfertilized eggs that will mature into reproductive males called drones.</s>
 <s id="38">This new crop of queens and males requires more food.</s>
 <s id="39">But with summer over, the usual sources run dry, and the foraging wasps start taking more aggressive risks.</s>
 <s id="40">By September, the hive’s organization deteriorates.</s>
 <s id="41">Hungry workers no longer clean the nest and various scavengers move in.</s>
 <s id="42">Just when it seems the hive can no longer sustain itself, the fertile queens and their drones depart in a massive swarm.</s>
 <s id="43">As the days grow colder, the workers starve, and our queen reaches the end of her lifespan.</s>
 <s id="44">But above, a swarm of reproductive wasps has successfully mated.</s>
 <s id="45">The males die off shortly after, but the newly fertilized queens are ready to find shelter for their long sleep.</s>
 <s id="46">And this woodpile looks like the perfect place to spend the winter.</s>
</text>
