<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">It's the first sense you use when you're born.</s>
 <s id="2">One out of every fifty of your genes is dedicated to it.</s>
 <s id="3">It must be important, right?</s>
 <s id="4">Okay, take a deep breath through your nose.</s>
 <s id="5">It's your sense of smell, and it's breathtakingly powerful.</s>
 <s id="6">As an adult, you can distinguish about 10,000 different smells.</s>
 <s id="7">Here's how your nose does it.</s>
 <s id="8">Smell starts when you sniff molecules from the air into your nostrils.</s>
 <s id="9">95% of your nasal cavity is used just to filter that air before it hits your lungs.</s>
 <s id="10">But at the very back of your nose is a region called the olfactory epithelium, a little patch of skin that's key to everything you smell.</s>
 <s id="11">The olfactory epithelium has a layer of olfactory receptor cells, special neurons that sense smells, like the taste buds of your nose.</s>
 <s id="12">When odor molecules hit the back of your nose, they get stuck in a layer of mucus covering the olfactory epithelium.</s>
 <s id="13">As they dissolve, they bind to the olfactory receptor cells, which fire and send signals through the olfactory tract up to your brain.</s>
 <s id="14">As a side note, you can tell a lot about how good an animal's sense of smell is by the size of its olfactory epithelium.</s>
 <s id="15">A dog's olfactory epithelium is 20 times bigger than your puny human one.</s>
 <s id="16">But there's still a lot we don't know about this little patch of cells, too.</s>
 <s id="17">For example, our olfactory epithelium is pigmented, and scientists don't really know why.</s>
 <s id="18">But how do you actually tell the difference between smells?</s>
 <s id="19">It turns out that your brain has 40 million different olfactory receptor neurons, so odor A might trigger neurons 3, 427, and 988, and odor B might trigger neurons 8, 76, and 2,496,678.</s>
 <s id="20">All of these different combinations let you detect a staggeringly broad array of smells.</s>
 <s id="21">Olfactory neurons are always fresh and ready for action.</s>
 <s id="22">They're the only neuron in the body that gets replaced regularly, every four to eight weeks.</s>
 <s id="23">Once they are triggered, the signal travels through a bundle called the olfactory tract to destinations all over your brain, making stops in the amygdala, the thalamus, and the neocortex.</s>
 <s id="24">This is different from how sight and sound are processed.</s>
 <s id="25">Each of those signals goes first to a relay center in the middle of the cerebral hemisphere and then out to other regions of the brain.</s>
 <s id="26">But smell, because it evolved before most of your other senses, takes a direct route to these different regions of the brain, where it can trigger your fight-or-flight response, help you recall memories, or make your mouth water.</s>
 <s id="27">But even though we've all got the same physiological set-up, two nostrils and millions of olfactory neurons, not everybody smells the same things.</s>
 <s id="28">One of the most famous examples of this is the ability to smell so-called "asparagus pee."</s>
 <s id="29">For about a quarter of the population, urinating after eating asparagus means smelling a distinct odor.</s>
 <s id="30">The other 75% of us don't notice.</s>
 <s id="31">And this isn't the only case of smells differing from nose to nose.</s>
 <s id="32">For some people, the chemical androstenone smells like vanilla; to others, it smells like sweaty urine, which is unfortunate because androstenone is commonly found in tasty things like pork.</s>
 <s id="33">So with the sweaty urine smellers in mind, pork producers will castrate male pigs to stop them from making androstenone.</s>
 <s id="34">The inability to smell a scent is called anosmia, and there are about 100 known examples.</s>
 <s id="35">People with allicin anosmia can't smell garlic.</s>
 <s id="36">Those with eugenol anosmia can't smell cloves.</s>
 <s id="37">And some people can't smell anything at all.</s>
 <s id="38">This kind of full anosmia could have several causes.</s>
 <s id="39">Some people are born without a sense of smell.</s>
 <s id="40">Others lose it after an accident or during an illness.</s>
 <s id="41">If the olfactory epithelium gets swollen or infected, it can hamper your sense of smell, something you might have experienced when you were sick.</s>
 <s id="42">Not being able to smell anything can mess with your other senses, too.</s>
 <s id="43">Many people who can't smell at all also can't really taste the same way the rest of us do.</s>
 <s id="44">It turns out that how something tastes is closely related to how it smells.</s>
 <s id="45">As you chew your food, air is pushed up your nasal passage, carrying with it the smell of your food.</s>
 <s id="46">Those scents hit your olfactory epithelium and tell your brain a lot about what you're eating.</s>
 <s id="47">Without the ability to smell, you lose the ability to taste anything more complicated than the five tastes your taste buds can detect: sweet, salty, bitter, sour, and savory.</s>
 <s id="48">So, the next time you smell exhaust fumes, salty sea air, or roast chicken, you'll know exactly how you've done it and, perhaps, be a little more thankful that you can.</s>
</text>
