<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Salaam alaikum.</s>
 <s id="2">Welcome to Doha.</s>
 <s id="3">I am in charge of making this country's food secure.</s>
 <s id="4">That is my job for the next two years, to design an entire master plan, and then for the next 10 years to implement it -- of course, with so many other people.</s>
 <s id="5">But first, I need to talk to you about a story, which is my story, about the story of this country that you're all here in today.</s>
 <s id="6">And of course, most of you have had three meals today, and probably will continue to have after this event.</s>
 <s id="7">So going in, what was Qatar in the 1940s?</s>
 <s id="8">We were about 11,000 people living here.</s>
 <p id="p9">
  <s id="9.1">There was no water.</s>
  <s id="9.2">There was no energy, no oil, no cars, none of that.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="10">Most of the people who lived here either lived in coastal villages, fishing, or were nomads who roamed around with the environment trying to find water.</s>
 <s id="11">None of the glamour that you see today existed.</s>
 <s id="12">No cities like you see today in Doha or Dubai or Abu Dhabi or Kuwait or Riyadh.</s>
 <s id="13">It wasn't that they couldn't develop cities.</s>
 <s id="14">Resources weren't there to develop them.</s>
 <s id="15">And you can see that life expectancy was also short.</s>
 <s id="16">Most people died around the age of 50.</s>
 <s id="17">So let's move to chapter two: the oil era.</s>
 <s id="18">1939, that's when they discovered oil.</s>
 <s id="19">But unfortunately, it wasn't really fully exploited commercially until after the Second World War.</s>
 <s id="20">What did it do?</s>
 <s id="21">It changed the face of this country, as you can see today and witness.</s>
 <s id="22">It also made all those people who roamed around the desert -- looking for water, looking for food, trying to take care of their livestock -- urbanize.</s>
 <s id="23">You might find this strange, but in my family we have different accents.</s>
 <s id="24">My mother has an accent that is so different to my father, and we're all a population of about 300,000 people in the same country.</s>
 <s id="25">There are about five or six accents in this country as I speak.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">Someone says, "How so?</s>
  <s id="26.2">How could this happen?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">Because we lived scattered.</s>
 <s id="28">We couldn't live in a concentrated way simply because there was no resources.</s>
 <s id="29">And when the resources came, be it oil, we started building these fancy technologies and bringing people together because we needed the concentration.</s>
 <s id="30">People started to get to know each other.</s>
 <s id="31">And we realized that there are some differences in accents.</s>
 <s id="32">So that is the chapter two: the oil era.</s>
 <s id="33">Let's look at today.</s>
 <s id="34">This is probably the skyline that most of you know about Doha.</s>
 <s id="35">So what's the population today?</s>
 <s id="36">It's 1.7 million people.</s>
 <s id="37">That is in less than 60 years.</s>
 <s id="38">The average growth of our economy is about 15 percent for the past five years.</s>
 <s id="39">Lifespan has increased to 78.</s>
 <s id="40">Water consumption has increased to 430 liters.</s>
 <s id="41">And this is amongst the highest worldwide.</s>
 <s id="42">From having no water whatsoever to consuming water to the highest degree, higher than any other nation.</s>
 <s id="43">I don't know if this was a reaction to lack of water.</s>
 <s id="44">But what is interesting about the story that I've just said?</s>
 <s id="45">The interesting part is that we continue to grow 15 percent every year for the past five years without water.</s>
 <p id="p46">
  <s id="46.1">Now that is historic.</s>
  <s id="46.2">It's never happened before in history.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="47">Cities were totally wiped out because of the lack of water.</s>
 <s id="48">This is history being made in this region.</s>
 <s id="49">Not only cities that we're building, but cities with dreams and people who are wishing to be scientists, doctors.</s>
 <s id="50">Build a nice home, bring the architect, design my house.</s>
 <s id="51">These people are adamant that this is a livable space when it wasn't.</s>
 <s id="52">But of course, with the use of technology.</s>
 <s id="53">So Brazil has 1,782 millimeters per year of precipitation of rain.</s>
 <s id="54">Qatar has 74, and we have that growth rate.</s>
 <s id="55">The question is how.</s>
 <s id="56">How could we survive that?</s>
 <s id="57">We have no water whatsoever.</s>
 <s id="58">Simply because of this gigantic, mammoth machine called desalination.</s>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">Energy is the key factor here.</s>
  <s id="59.2">It changed everything.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="60">It is that thing that we pump out of the ground, we burn tons of, probably most of you used it coming to Doha.</s>
 <s id="61">So that is our lake, if you can see it.</s>
 <s id="62">That is our river.</s>
 <s id="63">That is how you all happen to use and enjoy water.</s>
 <s id="64">This is the best technology that this region could ever have: desalination.</s>
 <s id="65">So what are the risks?</s>
 <s id="66">Do you worry much?</s>
 <s id="67">I would say, perhaps if you look at the global facts, you will realize, of course I have to worry.</s>
 <s id="68">There is growing demand, growing population.</s>
 <s id="69">We've turned seven billion only a few months ago.</s>
 <s id="70">And so that number also demands food.</s>
 <s id="71">And there's predictions that we'll be nine billion by 2050.</s>
 <s id="72">So a country that has no water has to worry about what happens beyond its borders.</s>
 <s id="73">There's also changing diets.</s>
 <s id="74">By elevating to a higher socio-economic level, they also change their diet.</s>
 <s id="75">They start eating more meat and so on and so forth.</s>
 <s id="76">On the other hand, there is declining yields because of climate change and because of other factors.</s>
 <s id="77">And so someone has to really realize when the crisis is going to happen.</s>
 <s id="78">This is the situation in Qatar, for those who don't know.</s>
 <s id="79">We only have two days of water reserve.</s>
 <s id="80">We import 90 percent of our food, and we only cultivate less than one percent of our land.</s>
 <s id="81">The limited number of farmers that we have have been pushed out of their farming practices as a result of open market policy and bringing the big competitions, etc., etc.</s>
 <s id="82">So we also face risks.</s>
 <s id="83">These risks directly affect the sustainability of this nation and its continuity.</s>
 <s id="84">The question is, is there a solution?</s>
 <s id="85">Is there a sustainable solution?</s>
 <s id="86">Indeed there is.</s>
 <s id="87">This slide sums up thousands of pages of technical documents that we've been working on over the past two years.</s>
 <s id="88">Let's start with the water.</s>
 <s id="89">So we know very well -- I showed you earlier -- that we need this energy.</s>
 <s id="90">So if we're going to need energy, what sort of energy?</s>
 <p id="p91">
  <s id="91.1">A depletable energy?</s>
  <s id="91.2">Fossil fuel?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="92">Or should we use something else?</s>
 <s id="93">Do we have the comparative advantage to use another sort of energy?</s>
 <s id="94">I guess most of you by now realize that we do: 300 days of sun.</s>
 <s id="95">And so we will use that renewable energy to produce the water that we need.</s>
 <s id="96">And we will probably put 1,800 megawatts of solar systems to produce 3.5 million cubic meters of water.</s>
 <s id="97">And that is a lot of water.</s>
 <s id="98">That water will go then to the farmers, and the farmers will be able to water their plants, and they will be able then to supply society with food.</s>
 <s id="99">But in order to sustain the horizontal line -- because these are the projects, these are the systems that we will deliver -- we need to also develop the vertical line: system sustenance, high-level education, research and development, industries, technologies, to produce these technologies for application, and finally markets.</s>
 <s id="100">But what gels all of it, what enables it, is legislation, policies, regulations.</s>
 <s id="101">Without it we can't do anything.</s>
 <s id="102">So that's what we are planning to do.</s>
 <s id="103">Within two years we should hopefully be done with this plan and taking it to implementation.</s>
 <s id="104">Our objective is to be a millennium city, just like many millennium cities around: Istanbul, Rome, London, Paris, Damascus, Cairo.</s>
 <s id="105">We are only 60 years old, but we want to live forever as a city, to live in peace.</s>
 <s id="106">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="107">(Applause)</s>
</text>
