<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">As a child, I was raised by native Hawaiian elders -- three old women who took care of me while my parents worked.</s>
 <s id="2">The year is 1963.</s>
 <s id="3">We're at the ocean.</s>
 <s id="4">It's twilight.</s>
 <s id="5">We're watching the rising of the stars and the shifting of the tides.</s>
 <s id="6">It's a stretch of beach we know so well.</s>
 <s id="7">The smooth stones on the sand are familiar to us.</s>
 <s id="8">If you saw these women on the street in their faded clothes, you might dismiss them as poor and simple.</s>
 <s id="9">That would be a mistake.</s>
 <s id="10">These women are descendants of Polynesian navigators, trained in the old ways by their elders, and now they're passing it on to me.</s>
 <s id="11">They teach me the names of the winds and the rains, of astronomy according to a genealogy of stars.</s>
 <s id="12">There's a new moon on the horizon.</s>
 <s id="13">Hawaiians say it's a good night for fishing.</s>
 <s id="14">They begin to chant.</s>
 <s id="15">[Hawaiian chant] When they finish, they sit in a circle and ask me to come to join them.</s>
 <s id="16">They want to teach me about my destiny.</s>
 <s id="17">I thought every seven-year-old went through this.</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) "Baby girl, someday the world will be in trouble.</s>
 <s id="19">People will forget their wisdom.</s>
 <s id="20">It will take elders' voices from the far corners of the world to call the world into balance.</s>
 <s id="21">You will go far away.</s>
 <s id="22">It will sometimes be a lonely road.</s>
 <s id="23">We will not be there.</s>
 <s id="24">But you will look into the eyes of seeming strangers, and you will recognize your ohana, your family.</s>
 <s id="25">And it will take all of you.</s>
 <s id="26">It will take all of you."</s>
 <s id="27">These words, I hold onto all my life.</s>
 <s id="28">Because the idea of doing it alone terrifies me.</s>
 <s id="29">The year is 2007.</s>
 <s id="30">I'm on a remote island in Micronesia.</s>
 <s id="31">Satawal is one half-mile long by one mile wide.</s>
 <s id="32">It's the home of my mentor.</s>
 <s id="33">His name is Pius Mau Piailug.</s>
 <s id="34">Mau is a palu, a navigator priest.</s>
 <s id="35">He's also considered the greatest wave finder in the world.</s>
 <s id="36">There are fewer than a handful of palu left on this island.</s>
 <s id="37">Their tradition is so extraordinary that these mariners sailed three million square miles across the Pacific without the use of instruments.</s>
 <s id="38">They could synthesize patterns in nature using the rising and setting of stars, the sequence and direction of waves, the flight patterns of certain birds.</s>
 <s id="39">Even the slightest hint of color on the underbelly of a cloud would inform them and help them navigate with the keenest accuracy.</s>
 <s id="40">When Western scientists would join Mau on the canoe and watch him go into the hull, it appeared that an old man was going to rest.</s>
 <s id="41">In fact, the hull of the canoe is the womb of the vessel.</s>
 <s id="42">It is the most accurate place to feel the rhythm and sequence and direction of waves.</s>
 <s id="43">Mau was, in fact, gathering explicit data using his entire body.</s>
 <s id="44">It's what he had been trained to do since he was five years old.</s>
 <s id="45">Now science may dismiss this methodology, but Polynesian navigators use it today because it provides them an accurate determination of the angle and direction of their vessel.</s>
 <s id="46">The palu also had an uncanny ability to forecast weather conditions days in advance.</s>
 <s id="47">Sometimes I'd be with Mau on a cloud-covered night and we'd sit at the easternmost coast of the island, and he would look out, and then he would say, "Okay, we go."</s>
 <s id="48">He saw that first glint of light -- he knew what the weather was going to be three days from now.</s>
 <s id="49">Their achievements, intellectually and scientifically, are extraordinary, and they are so relevant for these times that we are in when we are riding out storms.</s>
 <s id="50">We are in such a critical moment of our collective history.</s>
 <s id="51">They have been compared to astronauts -- these elder navigators who sail vast open oceans in double-hulled canoes thousands of miles from a small island.</s>
 <s id="52">Their canoes, our rockets; their sea, our space.</s>
 <s id="53">The wisdom of these elders is not a mere collection of stories about old people in some remote spot.</s>
 <s id="54">This is part of our collective narrative.</s>
 <s id="55">It's humanity's DNA.</s>
 <s id="56">We cannot afford to lose it.</s>
 <s id="57">The year is 2010.</s>
 <s id="58">Just as the women in Hawaii that raised me predicted, the world is in trouble.</s>
 <s id="59">We live in a society bloated with data, yet starved for wisdom.</s>
 <s id="60">We're connected 24/7, yet anxiety, fear, depression and loneliness is at an all-time high.</s>
 <s id="61">We must course-correct.</s>
 <s id="62">An African shaman said, "Your society worships the jester while the king stands in plain clothes."</s>
 <s id="63">The link between the past and the future is fragile.</s>
 <s id="64">This I know intimately, because even as I travel throughout the world to listen to these stories and record them, I struggle.</s>
 <s id="65">I am haunted by the fact that I no longer remember the names of the winds and the rains.</s>
 <s id="66">Mau passed away five months ago, but his legacy and lessons live on.</s>
 <s id="67">And I am reminded that throughout the world there are cultures with vast sums of knowledge in them, as potent as the Micronesian navigators, that are going dismissed, that this is a testament to brilliant, brilliant technology and science and wisdom that is vanishing rapidly.</s>
 <s id="68">Because when an elder dies a library is burned, and throughout the world, libraries are ablaze.</s>
 <s id="69">I am grateful for the fact that I had a mentor like Mau who taught me how to navigate.</s>
 <s id="70">And I realize through a lesson that he shared that we continue to find our way.</s>
 <s id="71">And this is what he said: "The island is the canoe; the canoe, the island."</s>
 <s id="72">And what he meant was, if you are voyaging and far from home, your very survival depends on everyone aboard.</s>
 <s id="73">You cannot make the voyage alone, you were never meant to.</s>
 <s id="74">This whole notion of every man for himself is completely unsustainable.</s>
 <s id="75">It always was.</s>
 <s id="76">So in closing I would offer you this: The planet is our canoe, and we are the voyagers.</s>
 <s id="77">True navigation begins in the human heart.</s>
 <s id="78">It's the most important map of all.</s>
 <s id="79">Together, may we journey well.</s>
 <s id="80">(Applause)</s>
</text>
