<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I am holding something remarkably old.</s>
 <s id="2">It is older than any human artifact, older than life on Earth, older than the continents and the oceans between them.</s>
 <s id="3">This was formed over four billion years ago in the earliest days of the solar system while the planets were still forming.</s>
 <s id="4">This rusty lump of nickel and iron may not appear special, but when it is cut open ...</s>
 <s id="5">you can see that it is different from earthly metals.</s>
 <s id="6">This pattern reveals metallic crystals that can only form out in space where molten metal can cool extremely slowly, a few degrees every million years.</s>
 <s id="7">This was once part of a much larger object, one of millions left over after the planets formed.</s>
 <s id="8">We call these objects asteroids.</s>
 <s id="9">Asteroids are our oldest and most numerous cosmic neighbors.</s>
 <s id="10">This graphic shows near-Earth asteroids orbiting around the Sun, shown in yellow, and swinging close to the Earth's orbit, shown in blue.</s>
 <s id="11">The sizes of the Earth, Sun and asteroids have been greatly exaggerated so you can see them clearly.</s>
 <s id="12">Teams of scientists across the globe are searching for these objects, discovering new ones every day, steadily mapping near-Earth space.</s>
 <s id="13">Much of this work is funded by NASA.</s>
 <s id="14">I think of the search for these asteroids as a giant public works project, but instead of building a highway, we're charting outer space, building an archive that will last for generations.</s>
 <s id="15">These are the 1,556 near-Earth asteroids discovered just last year.</s>
 <s id="16">And these are all of the known near-Earth asteroids, which at last count was 13,733.</s>
 <s id="17">Each one has been imaged, cataloged and had its path around the Sun determined.</s>
 <s id="18">Although it varies from asteroid to asteroid, the paths of most asteroids can be predicted for dozens of years.</s>
 <s id="19">And the paths of some asteroids can be predicted with incredible precision.</s>
 <s id="20">For example, scientists at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory predicted where the asteroid Toutatis was going to be four years in advance to within 30 kilometers.</s>
 <s id="21">In those four years, Toutatis traveled 8.5 billion kilometers.</s>
 <s id="22">That's a fractional precision of 0.000000004.</s>
 <s id="23">(Laughter) Now, the reason I have this beautiful asteroid fragment is because, like all neighbors, asteroids sometimes drop by unexpectedly.</s>
 <s id="24">(Laughter) Three years ago today, a small asteroid exploded over the city of Chelyabinsk, Russia.</s>
 <s id="25">That object was about 19 meters across, or about as big as a convenience store.</s>
 <s id="26">Objects of this size hit the Earth every 50 years or so.</s>
 <s id="27">66 million years ago, a much larger object hit the Earth, causing a massive extinction.</s>
 <s id="28">75 percent of plant and animal species were lost, including, sadly, the dinosaurs.</s>
 <s id="29">That object was about 10 kilometers across, and 10 kilometers is roughly the cruising altitude of a 747 jet.</s>
 <s id="30">So the next time you're in an airplane, snag a window seat, look out and imagine a rock so enormous that resting on the ground, it just grazes your wingtip.</s>
 <s id="31">It's so wide that it takes your plane one full minute to fly past it.</s>
 <s id="32">That's the size of the asteroid that hit the Earth.</s>
 <s id="33">It has only been within my lifetime that asteroids have been considered a credible threat to our planet.</s>
 <s id="34">And since then, there's been a focused effort underway to discover and catalog these objects.</s>
 <s id="35">I am lucky enough to be part of this effort.</s>
 <s id="36">I'm part of a team of scientists that use NASA's NEOWISE telescope.</s>
 <s id="37">Now, NEOWISE was not designed to find asteroids.</s>
 <s id="38">It was designed to orbit the earth and look far beyond our solar system to seek out the coldest stars and the most luminous galaxies.</s>
 <s id="39">And it did that very well for its designed lifetime of seven months.</s>
 <s id="40">But today, six years later, it's still going.</s>
 <s id="41">We've repurposed it to discover and study asteroids.</s>
 <s id="42">And although it's a wonderful little space robot, these days it's kind of like a used car.</s>
 <s id="43">The cryogen that used to refrigerate its sensors is long gone, so we joke that its air-conditioning is broken.</s>
 <s id="44">It's got 920 million miles on the odometer, but it still runs great and reliably takes a photograph of the sky every 11 seconds.</s>
 <s id="45">It's taken 23 photos since I began speaking to you.</s>
 <s id="46">One of the reasons NEOWISE is so valuable is that it sees the sky in the thermal infrared.</s>
 <s id="47">That means that instead of seeing the sunlight that asteroids reflect, NEOWISE sees the heat that they emit.</s>
 <s id="48">This is a vital capability since some asteroids are as dark as coal and can be difficult or impossible to spot with other telescopes.</s>
 <s id="49">But all asteroids, light or dark, shine brightly for NEOWISE.</s>
 <s id="50">Astronomers are using every technique at their disposal to discover and study asteroids.</s>
 <s id="51">In 2010, a historic milestone was reached.</s>
 <s id="52">The community, together, discovered over 90 percent of asteroids bigger than one kilometer across -- objects capable of massive destruction to Earth.</s>
 <s id="53">But the job's not done yet.</s>
 <s id="54">An object 140 meters or bigger could decimate a medium-sized country.</s>
 <s id="55">So far, we've only found 25 percent of those.</s>
 <s id="56">We must keep searching the sky for near-Earth asteroids.</s>
 <s id="57">We are the only species able to understand calculus or build telescopes.</s>
 <s id="58">We know how to find these objects.</s>
 <s id="59">This is our responsibility.</s>
 <s id="60">If we found a hazardous asteroid with significant early warning, we could nudge it out of the way.</s>
 <s id="61">Unlike earthquakes, hurricanes or volcanic eruptions, an asteroid impact can be precisely predicted and prevented.</s>
 <s id="62">What we need to do now is map near-Earth space.</s>
 <s id="63">We must keep searching the sky.</s>
 <s id="64">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="65">(Applause)</s>
</text>
