<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Let's talk about manias.</s>
 <s id="2">Let's start with Beatlemania.</s>
 <s id="3">(Recording of crowd roaring) Hysterical teenagers, crying, screaming, pandemonium.</s>
 <s id="4">(Recording of crowd roaring) Sports mania: deafening crowds, all for one idea -- get the ball in the net.</s>
 <s id="5">(Recording) Goal!</s>
 <s id="6">Okay, religious mania: there's rapture, there's weeping, there's visions.</s>
 <s id="7">Manias can be good.</s>
 <s id="8">Manias can be alarming.</s>
 <s id="9">Or manias can be deadly.</s>
 <s id="10">(Recording of crowd cheering) The world has a new mania.</s>
 <s id="11">A mania for learning English.</s>
 <s id="12">Listen as Chinese students practice their English, by screaming it: Teacher: ... change my life!</s>
 <s id="13">Students: I want to change my life!</s>
 <s id="14">T: I don't want to let my parents down!</s>
 <s id="15">S: I don't want to let my parents down!</s>
 <s id="16">T: I don't ever want to let my country down!</s>
 <s id="17">S: I don't ever want to let my country down!</s>
 <p id="p18">
  <s id="18.1">T: Most importantly...</s>
  <s id="18.2">S: Most importantly...</s>
 </p>
 <s id="19">T: I don't want to let myself down!</s>
 <s id="20">S: I don't want to let myself down!</s>
 <s id="21">How many people are trying to learn English worldwide?</s>
 <s id="22">Two billion of them.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">Students: A t-shirt.</s>
  <s id="23.2">A dress.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="24">Jay Walker: In Latin America, in India, in Southeast Asia, and most of all, in China.</s>
 <s id="25">If you're a Chinese student, you start learning English in the third grade, by law.</s>
 <s id="26">That's why this year, China will become the world's largest English-speaking country.</s>
 <s id="27">(Laughter) Why English?</s>
 <s id="28">In a single word: opportunity.</s>
 <s id="29">Opportunity for a better life, a job, to be able to pay for school, or put better food on the table.</s>
 <s id="30">Imagine a student taking a giant test for three full days.</s>
 <s id="31">Her score on this one test literally determines her future.</s>
 <s id="32">She studies 12 hours a day for three years to prepare.</s>
 <s id="33">Twenty-five percent of her grade is based on English.</s>
 <s id="34">It's called the gaokao, and 80 million high school Chinese students have already taken this grueling test.</s>
 <s id="35">The intensity to learn English is almost unimaginable, unless you witness it.</s>
 <p id="p36">
  <s id="36.1">Teacher: Perfect!</s>
  <s id="36.2">Students: Perfect!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">T: Perfect!</s>
  <s id="37.2">S: Perfect!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="38">T: I want to speak perfect English!</s>
 <s id="39">S: I want to speak perfect English!</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">T: I want to speak ...</s>
  <s id="40.2">S: I want to speak ...</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">T: ... perfect English!</s>
  <s id="41.2">S: ... perfect English!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">T (yelling more loudly): I want to change my life!</s>
 <s id="43">S (yelling more loudly): I want to change my life!</s>
 <s id="44">JW: So is English mania good or bad?</s>
 <s id="45">Is English a tsunami, washing away other languages?</s>
 <s id="46">Not likely.</s>
 <s id="47">English is the world's second language.</s>
 <s id="48">Your native language is your life.</s>
 <s id="49">But with English you can become part of a wider conversation -- a global conversation about global problems, like climate change or poverty, or hunger or disease.</s>
 <s id="50">The world has other universal languages.</s>
 <s id="51">Mathematics is the language of science.</s>
 <s id="52">Music is the language of emotions.</s>
 <s id="53">And now English is becoming the language of problem-solving.</s>
 <s id="54">Not because America is pushing it, but because the world is pulling it.</s>
 <s id="55">So English mania is a turning point.</s>
 <s id="56">Like the harnessing of electricity in our cities, or the fall of the Berlin Wall, English represents hope for a better future -- a future where the world has a common language to solve its common problems.</s>
 <s id="57">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="58">(Applause)</s>
</text>
