<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I love infographics.</s>
 <s id="2">As an information designer, I've worked with all sorts of data over the past 25 years.</s>
 <s id="3">I have a few insights to share, but first: a little history.</s>
 <s id="4">Communication is the encoding, transmission and decoding of information.</s>
 <s id="5">Breakthroughs in communication mark turning points in human culture.</s>
 <s id="6">Oracy, literacy and numeracy were great developments in communication.</s>
 <s id="7">They allow us to encode ideas into words and quantities into numbers.</s>
 <s id="8">Without communication, we'd still be stuck in the Stone Ages.</s>
 <s id="9">Although humans have been around for a quarter million years, it was only 8,000 years ago that proto-writings began to surface.</s>
 <s id="10">Nearly 3,000 years later, the first proper writing systems took shape.</s>
 <s id="11">Maps have been around for millennia and diagrams for hundreds of years, but representing quantities through graphics is a relatively new development.</s>
 <s id="12">It wasn't until 1786 that William Playfair invented the first bar chart, giving birth to visual display of quantitative information.</s>
 <s id="13">Fifteen years later, he introduced the first pie and area charts.</s>
 <s id="14">His inventions are still the most commonly used chart forms today.</s>
 <s id="15">Florence Nightingale invented the coxcomb in 1857 for a presentation to Queen Victoria on troop mortality.</s>
 <s id="16">Highlighted in blue, she showed how most troops' deaths could have been prevented.</s>
 <s id="17">Shortly after, Charles Minard charted Napoleon's march on Moscow, illustrating how an army of 422,000 dwindled to just 10,000 as battles, geography and freezing temperatures took their toll.</s>
 <s id="18">He combined a Sankey diagram with cartography and a line chart for temperature.</s>
 <s id="19">I get excited when I get lots of data to play with, especially when it yields an interesting chart form.</s>
 <s id="20">Here, Nightingale's coxcomb was the inspiration to organize data on thousands of federal energy subsidies, scrutinizing the lack of investment in renewables over fossil fuels.</s>
 <s id="21">This Sankey diagram illustrates the flow of energy through the US economy, emphasizing how nearly half of the energy used is lost as waste heat.</s>
 <s id="22">I love it when data can be sculpted into beautiful shapes.</s>
 <s id="23">Here, the personal and professional connections of the women of Silicon Valley can be woven into arcs, same as the collaboration of inventors birthing patents across the globe can be mapped.</s>
 <s id="24">I've even made charts for me.</s>
 <s id="25">I'm a numbers person, so I rarely win at Scrabble.</s>
 <s id="26">I made this diagram to remember all the two- and three-letter words in the official Scrabble dictionary.</s>
 <s id="27">(Laughter) Knowing these 1,168 words certainly is a game changer.</s>
 <s id="28">(Laughter) Sometimes I produce code to quickly generate graphics from thousands of data points.</s>
 <s id="29">Coding also enables me to produce interactive graphics.</s>
 <s id="30">Now we can navigate information on our own terms.</s>
 <s id="31">Exotic chart forms certainly look cool, but something as simple as a little dot may be all you need to solve a particular thinking task.</s>
 <s id="32">In 2006, the "New York Times" redesigned their "Markets" section, cutting it down from eight pages of stock listings to just one and a half pages of essential market data.</s>
 <s id="33">We listed performance metrics for the most common stocks, but I wanted to help investors see how the stocks are doing.</s>
 <s id="34">So I added a simple little dot to show the current price relative to its one-year range.</s>
 <s id="35">At a glance, value investors can pick out stocks trading near their lows by looking for dots to the left.</s>
 <s id="36">Momentum investors can find stocks on an upward trajectory via dots to the right.</s>
 <s id="37">Shortly after, the "Wall Street Journal" copied the design.</s>
 <s id="38">Simplicity is often the goal for most graphics, but sometimes we need to embrace complexity and show large data sets in their full glory.</s>
 <s id="39">Alec Gallup, the former chairman of the Gallup Organization, once handed me a very thick book.</s>
 <s id="40">It was his family's legacy: hundreds of pages covering six decades of presidential approval data.</s>
 <s id="41">I told him the entire book could be graphed on a single page.</s>
 <s id="42">"Impossible," he said.</s>
 <s id="43">And here it is: 25,000 data points on a single page.</s>
 <s id="44">At a glance, one sees that most presidents start with a high approval rating, but few keep it.</s>
 <s id="45">Events like wars initially boost approval; scandals trigger declines.</s>
 <s id="46">These major events were annotated in the graphic but not in the book.</s>
 <s id="47">The point is, graphics can transmit data with incredible efficiency.</s>
 <s id="48">Graphicacy -- the ability to read and write graphics -- is still in its infancy.</s>
 <s id="49">New chart forms will emerge and specialized dialects will evolve.</s>
 <s id="50">Graphics that help us think faster or see a book's worth of information on a single page are the key to unlocking new discoveries.</s>
 <s id="51">Our visual cortex was built to decode complex information and is a master at pattern recognition.</s>
 <s id="52">Graphicacy enables us to harness our built-in GPU to process mountains of data and find the veins of gold hiding within.</s>
 <s id="53">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="54">(Applause and cheers)</s>
</text>
