<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="2">Two years ago, I stood on the TED stage in Arusha, Tanzania.</s>
 <s id="3">I spoke very briefly about one of my proudest creations.</s>
 <s id="4">It was a simple machine that changed my life.</s>
 <s id="5">Before that time, I had never been away from my home in Malawi.</s>
 <s id="6">I had never used a computer.</s>
 <s id="7">I had never seen an Internet.</s>
 <s id="8">On the stage that day, I was so nervous.</s>
 <s id="9">My English lost, I wanted to vomit.</s>
 <s id="10">(Laughter) I had never been surrounded by so many azungu, white people.</s>
 <s id="11">(Laughter) There was a story I wouldn't tell you then.</s>
 <s id="12">But well, I'm feeling good right now.</s>
 <s id="13">I would like to share that story today.</s>
 <s id="14">We have seven children in my family.</s>
 <s id="15">All sisters, excepting me.</s>
 <s id="16">This is me with my dad when I was a little boy.</s>
 <s id="17">Before I discovered the wonders of science, I was just a simple farmer in a country of poor farmers.</s>
 <s id="18">Like everyone else, we grew maize.</s>
 <s id="19">One year our fortune turned very bad.</s>
 <s id="20">In 2001 we experienced an awful famine.</s>
 <s id="21">Within five months all Malawians began to starve to death.</s>
 <s id="22">My family ate one meal per day, at night.</s>
 <s id="23">Only three swallows of nsima for each one of us.</s>
 <s id="24">The food passes through our bodies.</s>
 <s id="25">We drop down to nothing.</s>
 <s id="26">In Malawi, the secondary school, you have to pay school fees.</s>
 <s id="27">Because of the hunger, I was forced to drop out of school.</s>
 <s id="28">I looked at my father and looked at those dry fields.</s>
 <s id="29">It was the future I couldn't accept.</s>
 <s id="30">I felt very happy to be at the secondary school, so I was determined to do anything possible to receive education.</s>
 <s id="31">So I went to a library.</s>
 <s id="32">I read books, science books, especially physics.</s>
 <s id="33">I couldn't read English that well.</s>
 <s id="34">I used diagrams and pictures to learn the words around them.</s>
 <s id="35">Another book put that knowledge in my hands.</s>
 <s id="36">It said a windmill could pump water and generate electricity.</s>
 <s id="37">Pump water meant irrigation, a defense against hunger, which we were experiencing by that time.</s>
 <s id="38">So I decided I would build one windmill for myself.</s>
 <s id="39">But I didn't have materials to use, so I went to a scrap yard where I found my materials.</s>
 <s id="40">Many people, including my mother, said I was crazy.</s>
 <s id="41">(Laughter) I found a tractor fan, shock absorber, PVC pipes.</s>
 <s id="42">Using a bicycle frame and an old bicycle dynamo, I built my machine.</s>
 <s id="43">It was one light at first.</s>
 <s id="44">And then four lights, with switches, and even a circuit breaker, modeled after an electric bell.</s>
 <s id="45">Another machine pumps water for irrigation.</s>
 <s id="46">Queues of people start lining up at my house (Laughter) to charge their mobile phone.</s>
 <s id="47">(Applause) I could not get rid of them.</s>
 <s id="48">(Laughter) And the reporters came too, which lead to bloggers and which lead to a call from something called TED.</s>
 <s id="49">I had never seen an airplane before.</s>
 <s id="50">I had never slept in a hotel.</s>
 <p id="p51">
  <s id="51.1">So, on stage that day in Arusha, my English lost, I said something like, "I tried.</s>
  <s id="51.2">And I made it."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="52">So I would like to say something to all the people out there like me to the Africans, and the poor who are struggling with your dreams.</s>
 <s id="53">God bless.</s>
 <s id="54">Maybe one day you will watch this on the Internet.</s>
 <s id="55">I say to you, trust yourself and believe.</s>
 <s id="56">Whatever happens, don't give up.</s>
 <s id="57">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="58">(Applause)</s>
</text>
