<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Newspapers are dying for a few reasons.</s>
 <s id="2">Readers don't want to pay for yesterday's news, and advertisers follow them.</s>
 <s id="3">Your iPhone, your laptop, is much more handy than New York Times on Sunday.</s>
 <s id="4">And we should save trees in the end.</s>
 <s id="5">So it's enough to bury any industry.</s>
 <s id="6">So, should we rather ask, "Can anything save newspapers?"</s>
 <s id="7">There are several scenarios for the future newspaper.</s>
 <s id="8">Some people say it should be free; it should be tabloid, or even smaller: A4; it should be local, run by communities, or niche, for some smaller groups like business -- but then it's not free; it's very expensive.</s>
 <s id="9">It should be opinion-driven; less news, more views.</s>
 <s id="10">And we'd rather read it during breakfast, because later we listen to radio in a car, check your mail at work and in the evening you watch TV.</s>
 <s id="11">Sounds nice, but this can only buy time.</s>
 <s id="12">Because in the long run, I think there is no reason, no practical reason for newspapers to survive.</s>
 <s id="13">So what can we do?</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) Let me tell you my story.</s>
 <s id="15">20 years ago, Bonnier, Swedish publisher, started to set newspapers in the former Soviet Bloc.</s>
 <s id="16">After a few years, they had several newspapers in central and eastern Europe.</s>
 <s id="17">They were run by an inexperienced staff, with no visual culture, no budgets for visuals -- in many places there were not even art directors.</s>
 <s id="18">I decided to be -- to work for them as an art director.</s>
 <s id="19">Before, I was an architect, and my grandmother asked me once, "What are you doing for a living?"</s>
 <s id="20">I said, "I'm designing newspapers."</s>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">"What?</s>
  <s id="21.2">There's nothing to design there.</s>
  <s id="21.3">It's just boring letters" (Laughter) And she was right.</s>
  <s id="21.4">I was very frustrated, until one day.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="22">I came to London, and I've seen performance by Cirque du Soleil.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">And I had a revelation.</s>
  <s id="23.2">I thought, "These guys took some creepy, run-down entertainment, and put it to the highest possible level of performance art."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="24">I thought "Oh my God, maybe I can do the same with these boring newspapers."</s>
 <p id="p25">
  <s id="25.1">And I did.</s>
  <s id="25.2">We started to redesign them, one by one.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="26">The front page became our signature.</s>
 <s id="27">It was my personal intimate channel to talk to the readers.</s>
 <s id="28">I'm not going to tell you stories about teamwork or cooperation.</s>
 <s id="29">My approach was very egotistic.</s>
 <s id="30">I wanted my artistic statement, my interpretation of reality.</s>
 <s id="31">I wanted to make posters, not newspapers.</s>
 <s id="32">Not even magazines: posters.</s>
 <p id="p33">
  <s id="33.1">We were experimenting with type, with illustration, with photos.</s>
  <s id="33.2">And we had fun.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="34">Soon it started to bring results.</s>
 <s id="35">In Poland, our pages were named "Covers of the Year" three times in a row.</s>
 <s id="36">Other examples you can see here are from Latvia, Lithuania, Estonia and central European countries.</s>
 <s id="37">But it's not only about the front page.</s>
 <s id="38">The secret is that we were treating the whole newspaper as one piece, as one composition -- like music.</s>
 <s id="39">And music has a rhythm, has ups and downs.</s>
 <s id="40">And design is responsible for this experience.</s>
 <s id="41">Flipping through pages is readers experience, and I'm responsible for this experience.</s>
 <s id="42">We treated two pages, both spreads, as a one page, because that's how readers perceive it.</s>
 <s id="43">You can see some Russian pages here which got many awards on biggest infographic competition in Spain.</s>
 <s id="44">But the real award came from Society for Newspaper Design.</s>
 <s id="45">Just a year after redesigning this newspaper in Poland, they name it the World's Best-Designed Newspaper.</s>
 <s id="46">And two years later, the same award came to Estonia.</s>
 <s id="47">Isn't amazing?</s>
 <s id="48">What really makes it amazing: that the circulation of these newspapers were growing too.</s>
 <s id="49">Just some examples: in Russia, plus 11 after one year, plus 29 after three years of the redesign.</s>
 <s id="50">Same in Poland: plus 13, up to 35 percent raise of circulation after three years.</s>
 <s id="51">You can see on a graph, after years of stagnation, the paper started to grow, just after redesign.</s>
 <s id="52">But the real hit was in Bulgaria.</s>
 <s id="53">And that is really amazing.</s>
 <s id="54">Did design do this?</s>
 <s id="55">Design was just a part of the process.</s>
 <s id="56">And the process we made was not about changing the look, it was about improving the product completely.</s>
 <s id="57">I took an architectural rule about function and form and translated it into newspaper content and design.</s>
 <s id="58">And I put strategy at the top of it.</s>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">So first you ask a big question: why we do it?</s>
  <s id="59.2">What is the goal?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="60">Then we adjust the content accordingly.</s>
 <s id="61">And then, usually after two months, we start designing.</s>
 <s id="62">My bosses, in the beginning, were very surprised.</s>
 <s id="63">Why am I asking all of these business questions, instead of just showing them pages?</s>
 <s id="64">But soon they realized that this is the new role of designer: to be in this process from the very beginning to the very end.</s>
 <s id="65">So what is the lesson behind it?</s>
 <s id="66">The first lesson is about that design can change not just your product.</s>
 <s id="67">It can change your workflow -- actually, it can change everything in your company; it can turn your company upside down.</s>
 <s id="68">It can even change you.</s>
 <p id="p69">
  <s id="69.1">And who's responsible?</s>
  <s id="69.2">Designers.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="70">Give power to designers.</s>
 <s id="71">(Applause) But the second is even more important.</s>
 <s id="72">You can live in a small poor country, like me.</s>
 <s id="73">You can work for a small company, in a boring branch.</s>
 <s id="74">You can have no budgets, no people -- but still can put your work to the highest possible level.</s>
 <s id="75">And everybody can do it.</s>
 <s id="76">You just need inspiration, vision and determination.</s>
 <s id="77">And you need to remember that to be good is not enough.</s>
 <s id="78">Thank you.</s>
</text>
