<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I was raised by lesbians in the mountains, and I sort of came like a forest gnome to New York City a while back.</s>
 <s id="2">(Laughter) Really messed with my head, but I'll get into that later.</s>
 <s id="3">I'll start with when I was eight years old.</s>
 <s id="4">I took a wood box, and I buried a dollar bill, a pen and a fork inside this box in Colorado.</s>
 <s id="5">And I thought some strange humanoids or aliens in 500 years would find this box and learn about the way our species exchanged ideas, maybe how we ate our spaghetti.</s>
 <s id="6">I really didn't know.</s>
 <s id="7">Anyway, this is kind of funny, because here I am, 30 years later, and I'm still making boxes.</s>
 <s id="8">Now, at some point I was in Hawaii -- I like to hike and surf and do all that weird stuff, and I was making a collage for my ma.</s>
 <s id="9">And I took a dictionary and I ripped it up, and I made it into a sort of Agnes Martin grid, and I poured resin all over it and a bee got stuck.</s>
 <s id="10">Now, she's afraid of bees and she's allergic to them, so I poured more resin on the canvas, thinking I could hide it or something.</s>
 <s id="11">Instead, the opposite happened: It sort of created a magnification, like a magnifying glass, on the dictionary text.</s>
 <p id="p12">
  <s id="12.1">So what did I do?</s>
  <s id="12.2">I built more boxes.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="13">This time, I started putting electronics, frogs, strange bottles I'd find in the street -- anything I could find -- because I was always finding things my whole life, and trying to make relationships and tell stories between these objects.</s>
 <s id="14">So I started drawing around the objects, and I realized: Holy moly, I can draw in space!</s>
 <s id="15">I can make free-floating lines, like the way you would draw around a dead body at a crime scene.</s>
 <s id="16">So I took the objects out, and I created my own taxonomy of invented specimens.</s>
 <s id="17">First, botanical -- which you can kind of get a sense of.</s>
 <s id="18">Then I made some weird insects and creatures.</s>
 <s id="19">It was really fun; I was just drawing on the layers of resin.</s>
 <s id="20">And it was cool, because I was actually starting to have shows and stuff, I was making some money, I could take my girlfriend for dinner, and like, go to Sizzler.</s>
 <s id="21">It was some good shit, man.</s>
 <s id="22">(Laughter) At some point, I got up to the human form, life-size resin sculptures with drawings of humans inside the layers.</s>
 <s id="23">This was great, except for one thing: I was going to die.</s>
 <s id="24">I didn't know what to do, because the resin was going to kill me.</s>
 <s id="25">And I went to bed every night thinking about it.</s>
 <s id="26">So I tried using glass.</s>
 <s id="27">I started drawing on the layers of glass, almost like if you drew on a window, then you put another window, and another window, and you had all these windows together that made a three-dimensional composition.</s>
 <s id="28">And this really worked, because I could stop using the resin.</s>
 <s id="29">So I did this for years, which culminated in a very large work, which I call "The Triptych."</s>
 <s id="30">"The Triptych" was largely inspired by Hieronymus Bosch's "[The] Garden of Earthly Delights," which is a painting in the [Museo del] Prado in Spain.</s>
 <s id="31">Do you guys know this painting?</s>
 <s id="32">Good, it's a cool painting.</s>
 <s id="33">It's kind of ahead of its time, they say.</s>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">So, "The Triptych."</s>
  <s id="34.2">I'll walk you through this piece.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="35">It weighs 24,000 pounds.</s>
 <s id="36">It's 18 feet long.</s>
 <s id="37">It's double-sided, so it's 36 feet of composition.</s>
 <s id="38">It's kind of weird.</s>
 <s id="39">Well, that's the blood fountain.</s>
 <s id="40">(Laughter) To the left, you have Jesus and the locusts.</s>
 <s id="41">There's a cave where all these animal-headed creatures travel between two worlds.</s>
 <s id="42">They go from the representational world, to this analog-mesh underworld, where they're hiding.</s>
 <s id="43">This is where the animal-headed creatures are by the lighthouse, and they're all about to commit mass suicide into the ocean.</s>
 <s id="44">The ocean is made up of thousands of elements.</s>
 <s id="45">This is a bird god tied up to a battleship.</s>
 <s id="46">(Laughter) Billy Graham is in the ocean; the Horizon from the oil spill; Waldo; Osama Bin Laden's shelter -- there's all kinds of weird stuff that you can find if you look really hard, in the ocean.</s>
 <s id="47">Anyway, this is a lady creature.</s>
 <s id="48">She's coming out of the ocean, and she's spitting oil into one hand and she has clouds coming out of her other hand.</s>
 <s id="49">Her hands are like scales, and she has the mythological reference of the Earth and cosmos in balance.</s>
 <s id="50">So that's one side of "The Triptych."</s>
 <s id="51">It's a little narrative thing.</s>
 <s id="52">That's her hand that she's spitting into.</s>
 <s id="53">And then, when you go to the other side, she has like a trunk, like a bird's beak, and she's spitting clouds out of her trunk.</s>
 <s id="54">Then she has an 18-foot-long serpent's tail that connects "The Triptych."</s>
 <s id="55">Anyway, her tail catches on fire from the back of the volcano.</s>
 <s id="56">(Laughter) I don't know why that happened.</s>
 <s id="57">(Laughter) That happens, you know.</s>
 <s id="58">Her tail terminates in a cycloptic eyeball, made out of 1986 terrorist cards.</s>
 <s id="59">Have you guys seen those?</s>
 <s id="60">They were made in the 1980's, they're like baseball cards of terrorists.</s>
 <s id="61">Way ahead of their time.</s>
 <s id="62">(Laughter) That will bring you to my latest project.</s>
 <s id="63">I'm in the middle of two projects: One's called "Psychogeographies."</s>
 <s id="64">It's about a six-year project to make 100 of these humans.</s>
 <s id="65">Each one is an archive of our culture, through our ripped-up media and matter, whether it's encyclopedias or dictionaries or magazines.</s>
 <s id="66">But each one acts as a sort of an archive in the shape of a human, and they travel in groups of 20, 4, or 12 at a time.</s>
 <s id="67">They're like cells -- they come together, they divide.</s>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">And you kind of walk through them.</s>
  <s id="68.2">It's taking me years.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="69">Each one is basically a 3,000-pound microscope slide with a human stuck inside.</s>
 <s id="70">This one has a little cave in his chest.</s>
 <s id="71">That's his head; there's the chest, you can kind of see the beginning.</s>
 <s id="72">I'm going to go down the body for you: There's a waterfall coming out of his chest, covering his penis -- or not-penis, or whatever it is, a kind of androgynous thing.</s>
 <s id="73">I'll take you quickly through these works, because I can't explain them for too long.</s>
 <s id="74">There are the layers, you can kind of see it.</s>
 <s id="75">That's a body getting split in half.</s>
 <s id="76">This one has two heads, and it's communicating between the two heads.</s>
 <s id="77">You can see the pills coming out, going into one head from this weird statue.</s>
 <s id="78">There's a little forest scene inside the chest cavity.</s>
 <s id="79">Can you see that?</s>
 <s id="80">Anyway, this talk's all about these boxes, like the boxes we're in.</s>
 <s id="81">This box we're in, the solar system is a box.</s>
 <s id="82">This brings you to my latest box.</s>
 <p id="p83">
  <s id="83.1">It's a brick box.</s>
  <s id="83.2">It's called Pioneer Works.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="84">(Cheers) Inside of this box is a physicist, a neuroscientist, a painter, a musician, a writer, a radio station, a museum, a school, a publishing arm to disseminate all the content we make there into the world; a garden.</s>
 <s id="85">We shake this box up, and all these people kind of start hitting each other like particles.</s>
 <s id="86">And I think that's the way you change the world.</s>
 <s id="87">You redefine your insides and the box that you're living in.</s>
 <s id="88">And you come together to realize that we're all in this together, that this delusion of difference -- this idea of countries, of borders, of religion -- doesn't work.</s>
 <s id="89">We're all really made up of the same stuff, in the same box.</s>
 <s id="90">And if we don't start exchanging that stuff sweetly and nicely, we're all going to die real soon.</s>
 <s id="91">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="92">(Applause)</s>
</text>
