<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Allison Hunt: My three minutes hasn't started yet, has it?</s>
 <s id="2">Chris Anderson: No, you can't start the three minutes.</s>
 <s id="3">Reset the three minutes, that's just not fair.</s>
 <s id="4">AH: Oh my God, it's harsh up here.</s>
 <s id="5">I mean I'm nervous enough as it is.</s>
 <s id="6">But I am not as nervous as I was five weeks ago.</s>
 <s id="7">Five weeks ago I had total hip replacement surgery.</s>
 <s id="8">Do you know that surgery?</s>
 <s id="9">Electric saw, power drill, totally disgusting unless you're David Bolinsky, in which case it's all truth and beauty.</s>
 <s id="10">Sure David, if it's not your hip, it's truth and beauty.</s>
 <s id="11">Anyway, I did have a really big epiphany around the situation, so Chris invited me to tell you about it.</s>
 <s id="12">But first you need to know two things about me.</s>
 <s id="13">Just two things.</s>
 <s id="14">I'm Canadian, and I'm the youngest of seven kids.</s>
 <s id="15">Now, in Canada, we have that great healthcare system.</s>
 <s id="16">That means we get our new hips for free.</s>
 <p id="p17">
  <s id="17.1">And being the youngest of seven, I have never been at the front of the line for anything.</s>
  <s id="17.2">OK?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="18">So my hip had been hurting me for years.</s>
 <s id="19">I finally went to the doctor, which was free.</s>
 <s id="20">And she referred me to an orthopedic surgeon, also free.</s>
 <s id="21">Finally got to see him after 10 months of waiting -- almost a year.</s>
 <s id="22">That is what free gets you.</s>
 <p id="p23">
  <s id="23.1">I met the surgeon, and he took some free X-rays, and I got a good look at them.</s>
  <s id="23.2">And you know, even I could tell my hip was bad, and I actually work in marketing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="24">So he said, "Allison, we've got to get you on the table.</s>
 <s id="25">I'm going to replace your hip -- it's about an 18-month wait."</s>
 <s id="26">18 more months.</s>
 <s id="27">I'd already waited 10 months, and I had to wait 18 more months.</s>
 <s id="28">You know, it's such a long wait that I actually started to even think about it in terms of TEDs.</s>
 <s id="29">I wouldn't have my new hip for this TED.</s>
 <s id="30">I wouldn't have my new hip for TEDGlobal in Africa.</s>
 <s id="31">I would not have my new hip for TED2008.</s>
 <p id="p32">
  <s id="32.1">I would still be on my bad hip.</s>
  <s id="32.2">That was so disappointing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="33">So, I left his office and I was walking through the hospital, and that's when I had my epiphany.</s>
 <s id="34">This youngest of seven had to get herself to the front of the line.</s>
 <s id="35">Oh yeah.</s>
 <s id="36">Can I tell you how un-Canadian that is?</s>
 <s id="37">We do not think that way.</s>
 <p id="p38">
  <s id="38.1">We don't talk about it.</s>
  <s id="38.2">It's not even a consideration.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="39">In fact, when we're traveling abroad, it's how we identify fellow Canadians.</s>
 <p id="p40">
  <s id="40.1">"After you."</s>
  <s id="40.2">"Oh, no, no.</s>
  <s id="40.3">After you."</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">Hey, are you from Canada?</s>
  <s id="41.2">"Oh, me too!</s>
  <s id="41.3">Hi!"</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">"Great!</s>
  <s id="42.2">Excellent!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="43">So no, suddenly I wasn't averse to butting any geezer off the list.</s>
 <s id="44">Some 70-year-old who wanted his new hip so he could be back golfing, or gardening.</s>
 <p id="p45">
  <s id="45.1">No, no.</s>
  <s id="45.2">Front of the line.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="46">So by now I was walking the lobby, and of course, that hurt, because of my hip, and I kind of needed a sign.</s>
 <s id="47">And I saw a sign.</s>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">In the window of the hospital's tiny gift shop there was a sign that said, "Volunteers Needed."</s>
  <s id="48.2">Hmm.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="49">Well, they signed me up immediately.</s>
 <p id="p50">
  <s id="50.1">No reference checks.</s>
  <s id="50.2">None of the usual background stuff, no.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="51">They were desperate for volunteers because the average age of the volunteer at the hospital gift shop was 75.</s>
 <p id="p52">
  <s id="52.1">Yeah.</s>
  <s id="52.2">They needed some young blood.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="53">So, next thing you know, I had my bright blue volunteer vest, I had my photo ID, and I was fully trained by my 89-year-old boss.</s>
 <s id="54">I worked alone.</s>
 <s id="55">Every Friday morning I was at the gift shop.</s>
 <s id="56">While ringing in hospital staff's Tic Tacs, I'd casually ask, "What do you do?"</s>
 <s id="57">Then I'd tell them, "Well, I'm getting my hip replaced -- in 18 months.</s>
 <p id="p58">
  <s id="58.1">It's gonna be so great when the pain stops.</s>
  <s id="58.2">Ow!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="59">All the staff got to know the plucky, young volunteer.</s>
 <s id="60">My next surgeon's appointment was, coincidentally, right after a shift at the gift shop.</s>
 <s id="61">So, naturally, I had my vest and my identification.</s>
 <s id="62">I draped them casually over the chair in the doctor's office.</s>
 <s id="63">And you know, when he walked in, I could just tell that he saw them.</s>
 <s id="64">Moments later, I had a surgery date just weeks away, and a big fat prescription for Percocet.</s>
 <s id="65">Now, word on the street was that it was actually my volunteering that got me to the front of the line.</s>
 <s id="66">And, you know, I'm not even ashamed of that.</s>
 <s id="67">Two reasons.</s>
 <s id="68">First of all, I am going to take such good care of this new hip.</s>
 <s id="69">But also I intend to stick with the volunteering, which actually leads me to the biggest epiphany of them all.</s>
 <s id="70">Even when a Canadian cheats the system, they do it in a way that benefits society.</s>
</text>
