<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">As someone who has spent his entire career trying to be invisible standing in front of an audience is a cross between an out-of-body experience and a deer caught in the headlights, so please forgive me for violating one of the TED commandments by relying on words on paper, and I only hope I'm not struck by lightning bolts before I'm done.</s>
 <s id="2">I'd like to begin by talking about some of the ideas that motivated me to become a documentary photographer.</s>
 <s id="3">I was a student in the '60s, a time of social upheaval and questioning, and on a personal level, an awakening sense of idealism.</s>
 <s id="4">The war in Vietnam was raging; the Civil Rights Movement was under way; and pictures had a powerful influence on me.</s>
 <s id="5">Our political and military leaders were telling us one thing, and photographers were telling us another.</s>
 <s id="6">I believed the photographers, and so did millions of other Americans.</s>
 <s id="7">Their images fueled resistance to the war and to racism.</s>
 <s id="8">They not only recorded history; they helped change the course of history.</s>
 <s id="9">Their pictures became part of our collective consciousness and, as consciousness evolved into a shared sense of conscience, change became not only possible, but inevitable.</s>
 <s id="10">I saw that the free flow of information represented by journalism, specifically visual journalism, can bring into focus both the benefits and the cost of political policies.</s>
 <s id="11">It can give credit to sound decision-making, adding momentum to success.</s>
 <s id="12">In the face of poor political judgment or political inaction, it becomes a kind of intervention, assessing the damage and asking us to reassess our behavior.</s>
 <s id="13">It puts a human face on issues which from afar can appear abstract or ideological or monumental in their global impact.</s>
 <s id="14">What happens at ground level, far from the halls of power, happens to ordinary citizens one by one.</s>
 <s id="15">And I understood that documentary photography has the ability to interpret events from their point of view.</s>
 <s id="16">It gives a voice to those who otherwise would not have a voice.</s>
 <s id="17">And as a reaction, it stimulates public opinion and gives impetus to public debate, thereby preventing the interested parties from totally controlling the agenda, much as they would like to.</s>
 <s id="18">Coming of age in those days made real the concept that the free flow of information is absolutely vital for a free and dynamic society to function properly.</s>
 <s id="19">The press is certainly a business, and in order to survive it must be a successful business, but the right balance must be found between marketing considerations and journalistic responsibility.</s>
 <s id="20">Society's problems can't be solved until they're identified.</s>
 <s id="21">On a higher plane, the press is a service industry, and the service it provides is awareness.</s>
 <s id="22">Every story does not have to sell something.</s>
 <s id="23">There's also a time to give.</s>
 <s id="24">That was a tradition I wanted to follow.</s>
 <s id="25">Seeing the war created such incredibly high stakes for everyone involved and that visual journalism could actually become a factor in conflict resolution -- I wanted to be a photographer in order to be a war photographer.</s>
 <s id="26">But I was driven by an inherent sense that a picture that revealed the true face of war would almost by definition be an anti-war photograph.</s>
 <s id="27">I'd like to take you on a visual journey through some of the events and issues I've been involved in over the past 25 years.</s>
 <s id="28">In 1981, I went to Northern Ireland.</s>
 <s id="29">10 IRA prisoners were in the process of starving themselves to death in protest against conditions in jail.</s>
 <s id="30">The reaction on the streets was violent confrontation.</s>
 <s id="31">I saw that the front lines of contemporary wars are not on isolated battlefields, but right where people live.</s>
 <s id="32">During the early '80s, I spent a lot of time in Central America, which was engulfed by civil wars that straddled the ideological divide of the Cold War.</s>
 <s id="33">In Guatemala, the central government -- controlled by a oligarchy of European decent -- was waging a scorched Earth campaign against an indigenous rebellion, and I saw an image that reflected the history of Latin America: conquest through a combination of the Bible and the sword.</s>
 <s id="34">An anti-Sandinista guerrilla was mortally wounded as Commander Zero attacked a town in Southern Nicaragua.</s>
 <s id="35">A destroyed tank belonging to Somoza's national guard was left as a monument in a park in Managua, and was transformed by the energy and spirit of a child.</s>
 <s id="36">At the same time, a civil war was taking place in El Salvador, and again, the civilian population was caught up in the conflict.</s>
 <s id="37">I've been covering the Palestinian-Israeli conflict since 1981.</s>
 <s id="38">This is a moment from the beginning of the second intifada, in 2000, when it was still stones and Molotovs against an army.</s>
 <s id="39">In 2001, the uprising escalated into an armed conflict, and one of the major incidents was the destruction of the Palestinian refugee camp in the West Bank town of Jenin.</s>
 <s id="40">Without the political will to find common ground, the continual friction of tactic and counter-tactic only creates suspicion and hatred and vengeance, and perpetuates the cycle of violence.</s>
 <s id="41">In the '90s, after the breakup of the Soviet Union, Yugoslavia fractured along ethnic fault lines, and civil war broke out between Bosnia, Croatia and Serbia.</s>
 <s id="42">This is a scene of house-to-house fighting in Mostar, neighbor against neighbor.</s>
 <s id="43">A bedroom, the place where people share intimacy, where life itself is conceived, became a battlefield.</s>
 <s id="44">A mosque in northern Bosnia was destroyed by Serbian artillery and was used as a makeshift morgue.</s>
 <s id="45">Dead Serbian soldiers were collected after a battle and used as barter for the return of prisoners or Bosnian soldiers killed in action.</s>
 <s id="46">This was once a park.</s>
 <s id="47">The Bosnian soldier who guided me told me that all of his friends were there now.</s>
 <s id="48">At the same time in South Africa, after Nelson Mandela had been released from prison, the black population commenced the final phase of liberation from apartheid.</s>
 <s id="49">One of the things I had to learn as a journalist was what to do with my anger.</s>
 <s id="50">I had to use it, channel its energy, turn it into something that would clarify my vision, instead of clouding it.</s>
 <s id="51">In Transkei, I witnessed a rite of passage into manhood, of the Xhosa tribe.</s>
 <s id="52">Teenage boys lived in isolation, their bodies covered with white clay.</s>
 <s id="53">After several weeks, they washed off the white and took on the full responsibilities of men.</s>
 <s id="54">It was a very old ritual that seemed symbolic of the political struggle that was changing the face of South Africa.</s>
 <s id="55">Children in Soweto playing on a trampoline.</s>
 <s id="56">Elsewhere in Africa there was famine.</s>
 <s id="57">In Somalia, the central government collapsed and clan warfare broke out.</s>
 <s id="58">Farmers were driven off their land, and crops and livestock were destroyed or stolen.</s>
 <s id="59">Starvation was being used as a weapon of mass destruction -- primitive but extremely effective.</s>
 <s id="60">Hundreds of thousands of people were exterminated, slowly and painfully.</s>
 <s id="61">The international community responded with massive humanitarian relief, and hundreds of thousands of more lives were saved.</s>
 <s id="62">American troops were sent to protect the relief shipments, but they were eventually drawn into the conflict, and after the tragic battle in Mogadishu, they were withdrawn.</s>
 <s id="63">In southern Sudan, another civil war saw similar use of starvation as a means of genocide.</s>
 <s id="64">Again, international NGOs, united under the umbrella of the U.N., staged a massive relief operation and thousands of lives were saved.</s>
 <s id="65">I'm a witness, and I want my testimony to be honest and uncensored.</s>
 <s id="66">I also want it to be powerful and eloquent, and to do as much justice as possible to the experience of the people I'm photographing.</s>
 <s id="67">This man was in an NGO feeding center, being helped as much as he could be helped.</s>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">He literally had nothing.</s>
  <s id="68.2">He was a virtual skeleton, yet he could still summon the courage and the will to move.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="69">He had not given up, and if he didn't give up, how could anyone in the outside world ever dream of losing hope?</s>
 <s id="70">In 1994, after three months of covering the South African election, I saw the inauguration of Nelson Mandela, and it was the most uplifting thing I've ever seen.</s>
 <s id="71">It exemplified the best that humanity has to offer.</s>
 <s id="72">The next day I left for Rwanda, and it was like taking the express elevator to hell.</s>
 <s id="73">This man had just been liberated from a Hutu death camp.</s>
 <s id="74">He allowed me to photograph him for quite a long time, and he even turned his face toward the light, as if he wanted me to see him better.</s>
 <s id="75">I think he knew what the scars on his face would say to the rest of the world.</s>
 <s id="76">This time, maybe confused or discouraged by the military disaster in Somalia, the international community remained silent, and somewhere around 800,000 people were slaughtered by their own countrymen -- sometimes their own neighbors -- using farm implements as weapons.</s>
 <s id="77">Perhaps because a lesson had been learned by the weak response to the war in Bosnia and the failure in Rwanda, when Serbia attacked Kosovo, international action was taken much more decisively.</s>
 <s id="78">NATO forces went in, and the Serbian army withdrew.</s>
 <s id="79">Ethnic Albanians had been murdered, their farms destroyed and a huge number of people forcibly deported.</s>
 <s id="80">They were received in refugee camps set up by NGOs in Albania and Macedonia.</s>
 <s id="81">The imprint of a man who had been burned inside his own home.</s>
 <s id="82">The image reminded me of a cave painting, and echoed how primitive we still are in so many ways.</s>
 <s id="83">Between 1995 and '96, I covered the first two wars in Chechnya from inside Grozny.</s>
 <s id="84">This is a Chechen rebel on the front line against the Russian army.</s>
 <s id="85">The Russians bombarded Grozny constantly for weeks, killing mainly the civilians who were still trapped inside.</s>
 <s id="86">I found a boy from the local orphanage wandering around the front line.</s>
 <s id="87">My work has evolved from being concerned mainly with war to a focus on critical social issues as well.</s>
 <s id="88">After the fall of Ceausescu, I went to Romania and discovered a kind of gulag of children, where thousands of orphans were being kept in medieval conditions.</s>
 <s id="89">Ceausescu had imposed a quota on the number of children to be produced by each family, thereby making women's bodies an instrument of state economic policy.</s>
 <s id="90">Children who couldn't be supported by their families were raised in government orphanages.</s>
 <s id="91">Children with birth defects were labeled incurables, and confined for life to inhuman conditions.</s>
 <s id="92">As reports began to surface, again international aid went in.</s>
 <s id="93">Going deeper into the legacy of the Eastern European regimes, I worked for several months on a story about the effects of industrial pollution, where there had been no regard for the environment or the health of either workers or the general population.</s>
 <s id="94">An aluminum factory in Czechoslovakia was filled with carcinogenic smoke and dust, and four out of five workers came down with cancer.</s>
 <s id="95">After the fall of Suharto in Indonesia, I began to explore conditions of poverty in a country that was on its way towards modernization.</s>
 <s id="96">I spent a good deal of time with a man who lived with his family on a railway embankment and had lost an arm and a leg in a train accident.</s>
 <s id="97">When the story was published, unsolicited donations poured in.</s>
 <s id="98">A trust fund was established, and the family now lives in a house in the countryside and all their basic necessities are taken care of.</s>
 <s id="99">It was a story that wasn't trying to sell anything.</s>
 <s id="100">Journalism had provided a channel for people's natural sense of generosity, and the readers responded.</s>
 <s id="101">I met a band of homeless children who'd come to Jakarta from the countryside, and ended up living in a train station.</s>
 <s id="102">By the age of 12 or 14, they'd become beggars and drug addicts.</s>
 <s id="103">The rural poor had become the urban poor, and in the process, they'd become invisible.</s>
 <s id="104">These heroin addicts in detox in Pakistan reminded me of figures in a play by Beckett: isolated, waiting in the dark, but drawn to the light.</s>
 <s id="105">Agent Orange was a defoliant used during the Vietnam War to deny cover to the Vietcong and the North Vietnamese army.</s>
 <s id="106">The active ingredient was dioxin, an extremely toxic chemical that was sprayed in vast quantities, and whose effects passed through the genes to the next generation.</s>
 <s id="107">In 2000, I began documenting global health issues, concentrating first on AIDS in Africa.</s>
 <s id="108">I tried to tell the story through the work of caregivers.</s>
 <s id="109">I thought it was important to emphasize that people were being helped, whether by international NGOs or by local grassroots organizations.</s>
 <s id="110">So many children have been orphaned by the epidemic that grandmothers have taken the place of parents, and a lot of children had been born with HIV.</s>
 <s id="111">A hospital in Zambia.</s>
 <s id="112">I began documenting the close connection between HIV/AIDS and tuberculosis.</s>
 <s id="113">This is an MSF hospital in Cambodia.</s>
 <s id="114">My pictures can play a supporting role to the work of NGOs by shedding light on the critical social problems they're trying to deal with.</s>
 <s id="115">I went to Congo with MSF, and contributed to a book and an exhibition that focused attention on a forgotten war in which millions of people have died, and exposure to disease without treatment is used as a weapon.</s>
 <s id="116">A malnourished child being measured as part of the supplemental feeding program.</s>
 <s id="117">In the fall of 2004 I went to Darfur.</s>
 <s id="118">This time I was on assignment for a magazine, but again worked closely with MSF.</s>
 <s id="119">The international community still hasn't found a way to create the pressure necessary to stop this genocide.</s>
 <s id="120">An MSF hospital in a camp for displaced people.</s>
 <s id="121">I've been working on a long project on crime and punishment in America.</s>
 <s id="122">This is a scene from New Orleans.</s>
 <s id="123">A prisoner on a chain gang in Alabama was punished by being handcuffed to a post in the midday sun.</s>
 <s id="124">This experience raised a lot of questions, among them questions about race and equality and for whom in our country opportunities and options are available.</s>
 <s id="125">In the yard of a chain gang in Alabama.</s>
 <s id="126">I didn't see either of the planes hit, and when I glanced out my window, I saw the first tower burning, and I thought it might have been an accident.</s>
 <s id="127">A few minutes later when I looked again and saw the second tower burning, I knew we were at war.</s>
 <s id="128">In the midst of the wreckage at Ground Zero, I had a realization.</s>
 <s id="129">I'd been photographing in the Islamic world since 1981 -- not only in the Middle East, but also in Africa, Asia and Europe.</s>
 <s id="130">At the time I was photographing in these different places, I thought I was covering separate stories, but on 9/11 history crystallized, and I understood I'd actually been covering a single story for more than 20 years, and the attack on New York was its latest manifestation.</s>
 <s id="131">The central commercial district of Kabul, Afghanistan at the end of the civil war, shortly before the city fell to the Taliban.</s>
 <s id="132">Land mine victims being helped at the Red Cross rehab center being run by Alberto Cairo.</s>
 <s id="133">A boy who lost a leg to a leftover mine.</s>
 <s id="134">I'd witnessed immense suffering in the Islamic world from political oppression, civil war, foreign invasions, poverty, famine.</s>
 <p id="p135">
  <s id="135.1">I understood that in its suffering, the Islamic world had been crying out.</s>
  <s id="135.2">Why weren't we listening?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="136">A Taliban fighter shot during a battle as the Northern Alliance entered the city of Kunduz.</s>
 <s id="137">When war with Iraq was imminent, I realized the American troops would be very well covered, so I decided to cover the invasion from inside Baghdad.</s>
 <s id="138">A marketplace was hit by a mortar shell that killed several members of a single family.</s>
 <s id="139">A day after American forces entered Baghdad, a company of Marines began rounding up bank robbers and were cheered on by the crowds -- a hopeful moment that was short lived.</s>
 <s id="140">For the first time in years, Shi'ites were allowed to make the pilgrimage to Karbala to observe Ashura, and I was amazed by the sheer number of people and how fervently they practiced their religion.</s>
 <s id="141">A group of men march through the streets cutting themselves with knives.</s>
 <s id="142">It was obvious that the Shi'ites were a force to be reckoned with, and we would do well to understand them and learn how to deal with them.</s>
 <s id="143">Last year I spent several months documenting our wounded troops, from the battlefield in Iraq all the way home.</s>
 <s id="144">This is a helicopter medic giving CPR to a soldier who had been shot in the head.</s>
 <s id="145">Military medicine has become so efficient that the percentage of troops who survive after being wounded is much higher in this war than in any other war in our history.</s>
 <s id="146">The signature weapon of the war is the IED, and the signature wound is severe leg damage.</s>
 <s id="147">After enduring extreme pain and trauma, the wounded face a grueling physical and psychological struggle in rehab.</s>
 <s id="148">The spirit they displayed was absolutely remarkable.</s>
 <s id="149">I tried to imagine myself in their place, and I was totally humbled by their courage and determination in the face of such catastrophic loss.</s>
 <s id="150">Good people had been put in a very bad situation for questionable results.</s>
 <s id="151">One day in rehab someone, started talking about surfing and all these guys who'd never surfed before said, "Hey, let's go."</s>
 <s id="152">And they went surfing.</s>
 <s id="153">Photographers go to the extreme edges of human experience to show people what's going on.</s>
 <s id="154">Sometimes they put their lives on the line, because they believe your opinions and your influence matter.</s>
 <s id="155">They aim their pictures at your best instincts, generosity, a sense of right and wrong, the ability and the willingness to identify with others, the refusal to accept the unacceptable.</s>
 <s id="156">My TED wish: there's a vital story that needs to be told, and I wish for TED to help me gain access to it and then to help me come up with innovative and exciting ways to use news photography in the digital era.</s>
 <s id="157">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="158">(Applause)</s>
</text>
