<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Hi.</s>
 <s id="2">I want to talk about understanding, and the nature of understanding, and what the essence of understanding is, because understanding is something we aim for, everyone.</s>
 <s id="3">We want to understand things.</s>
 <s id="4">My claim is that understanding has to do with the ability to change your perspective.</s>
 <s id="5">If you don't have that, you don't have understanding.</s>
 <s id="6">So that is my claim.</s>
 <s id="7">And I want to focus on mathematics.</s>
 <s id="8">Many of us think of mathematics as addition, subtraction, multiplication, division, fractions, percent, geometry, algebra -- all that stuff.</s>
 <s id="9">But actually, I want to talk about the essence of mathematics as well.</s>
 <s id="10">And my claim is that mathematics has to do with patterns.</s>
 <s id="11">Behind me, you see a beautiful pattern, and this pattern actually emerges just from drawing circles in a very particular way.</s>
 <s id="12">So my day-to-day definition of mathematics that I use every day is the following: First of all, it's about finding patterns.</s>
 <s id="13">And by "pattern," I mean a connection, a structure, some regularity, some rules that govern what we see.</s>
 <s id="14">Second of all, I think it is about representing these patterns with a language.</s>
 <s id="15">We make up language if we don't have it, and in mathematics, this is essential.</s>
 <s id="16">It's also about making assumptions and playing around with these assumptions and just seeing what happens.</s>
 <s id="17">We're going to do that very soon.</s>
 <s id="18">And finally, it's about doing cool stuff.</s>
 <s id="19">Mathematics enables us to do so many things.</s>
 <s id="20">So let's have a look at these patterns.</s>
 <s id="21">If you want to tie a tie knot, there are patterns.</s>
 <s id="22">Tie knots have names.</s>
 <s id="23">And you can also do the mathematics of tie knots.</s>
 <s id="24">This is a left-out, right-in, center-out and tie.</s>
 <s id="25">This is a left-in, right-out, left-in, center-out and tie.</s>
 <s id="26">This is a language we made up for the patterns of tie knots, and a half-Windsor is all that.</s>
 <s id="27">This is a mathematics book about tying shoelaces at the university level, because there are patterns in shoelaces.</s>
 <s id="28">You can do it in so many different ways.</s>
 <s id="29">We can analyze it.</s>
 <s id="30">We can make up languages for it.</s>
 <s id="31">And representations are all over mathematics.</s>
 <s id="32">This is Leibniz's notation from 1675.</s>
 <s id="33">He invented a language for patterns in nature.</s>
 <s id="34">When we throw something up in the air, it falls down.</s>
 <s id="35">Why?</s>
 <s id="36">We're not sure, but we can represent this with mathematics in a pattern.</s>
 <s id="37">This is also a pattern.</s>
 <s id="38">This is also an invented language.</s>
 <s id="39">Can you guess for what?</s>
 <s id="40">It is actually a notation system for dancing, for tap dancing.</s>
 <s id="41">That enables him as a choreographer to do cool stuff, to do new things, because he has represented it.</s>
 <s id="42">I want you to think about how amazing representing something actually is.</s>
 <s id="43">Here it says the word "mathematics."</s>
 <s id="44">But actually, they're just dots, right?</s>
 <s id="45">So how in the world can these dots represent the word?</s>
 <s id="46">Well, they do.</s>
 <s id="47">They represent the word "mathematics," and these symbols also represent that word and this we can listen to.</s>
 <s id="48">It sounds like this.</s>
 <s id="49">(Beeps) Somehow these sounds represent the word and the concept.</s>
 <s id="50">How does this happen?</s>
 <s id="51">There's something amazing going on about representing stuff.</s>
 <s id="52">So I want to talk about that magic that happens when we actually represent something.</s>
 <s id="53">Here you see just lines with different widths.</s>
 <s id="54">They stand for numbers for a particular book.</s>
 <s id="55">And I can actually recommend this book, it's a very nice book.</s>
 <s id="56">(Laughter) Just trust me.</s>
 <s id="57">OK, so let's just do an experiment, just to play around with some straight lines.</s>
 <s id="58">This is a straight line.</s>
 <s id="59">Let's make another one.</s>
 <s id="60">So every time we move, we move one down and one across, and we draw a new straight line, right?</s>
 <s id="61">We do this over and over and over, and we look for patterns.</s>
 <s id="62">So this pattern emerges, and it's a rather nice pattern.</s>
 <s id="63">It looks like a curve, right?</s>
 <s id="64">Just from drawing simple, straight lines.</s>
 <p id="p65">
  <s id="65.1">Now I can change my perspective a little bit.</s>
  <s id="65.2">I can rotate it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="66">Have a look at the curve.</s>
 <s id="67">What does it look like?</s>
 <s id="68">Is it a part of a circle?</s>
 <s id="69">It's actually not a part of a circle.</s>
 <s id="70">So I have to continue my investigation and look for the true pattern.</s>
 <s id="71">Perhaps if I copy it and make some art?</s>
 <s id="72">Well, no.</s>
 <s id="73">Perhaps I should extend the lines like this, and look for the pattern there.</s>
 <s id="74">Let's make more lines.</s>
 <s id="75">We do this.</s>
 <s id="76">And then let's zoom out and change our perspective again.</s>
 <s id="77">Then we can actually see that what started out as just straight lines is actually a curve called a parabola.</s>
 <s id="78">This is represented by a simple equation, and it's a beautiful pattern.</s>
 <s id="79">So this is the stuff that we do.</s>
 <s id="80">We find patterns, and we represent them.</s>
 <s id="81">And I think this is a nice day-to-day definition.</s>
 <s id="82">But today I want to go a little bit deeper, and think about what the nature of this is.</s>
 <s id="83">What makes it possible?</s>
 <s id="84">There's one thing that's a little bit deeper, and that has to do with the ability to change your perspective.</s>
 <s id="85">And I claim that when you change your perspective, and if you take another point of view, you learn something new about what you are watching or looking at or hearing.</s>
 <s id="86">And I think this is a really important thing that we do all the time.</s>
 <s id="87">So let's just look at this simple equation, x + x = 2 • x.</s>
 <s id="88">This is a very nice pattern, and it's true, because 5 + 5 = 2 • 5, etc.</s>
 <s id="89">We've seen this over and over, and we represent it like this.</s>
 <s id="90">But think about it: this is an equation.</s>
 <s id="91">It says that something is equal to something else, and that's two different perspectives.</s>
 <s id="92">One perspective is, it's a sum.</s>
 <s id="93">It's something you plus together.</s>
 <s id="94">On the other hand, it's a multiplication, and those are two different perspectives.</s>
 <s id="95">And I would go as far as to say that every equation is like this, every mathematical equation where you use that equality sign is actually a metaphor.</s>
 <s id="96">It's an analogy between two things.</s>
 <s id="97">You're just viewing something and taking two different points of view, and you're expressing that in a language.</s>
 <s id="98">Have a look at this equation.</s>
 <s id="99">This is one of the most beautiful equations.</s>
 <s id="100">It simply says that, well, two things, they're both -1.</s>
 <s id="101">This thing on the left-hand side is -1, and the other one is.</s>
 <s id="102">And that, I think, is one of the essential parts of mathematics -- you take different points of view.</s>
 <s id="103">So let's just play around.</s>
 <s id="104">Let's take a number.</s>
 <p id="p105">
  <s id="105.1">We know four-thirds.</s>
  <s id="105.2">We know what four-thirds is.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="106">It's 1.333, but we have to have those three dots, otherwise it's not exactly four-thirds.</s>
 <s id="107">But this is only in base 10.</s>
 <s id="108">You know, the number system, we use 10 digits.</s>
 <s id="109">If we change that around and only use two digits, that's called the binary system.</s>
 <s id="110">It's written like this.</s>
 <s id="111">So we're now talking about the number.</s>
 <s id="112">The number is four-thirds.</s>
 <s id="113">We can write it like this, and we can change the base, change the number of digits, and we can write it differently.</s>
 <s id="114">So these are all representations of the same number.</s>
 <s id="115">We can even write it simply, like 1.3 or 1.6.</s>
 <s id="116">It all depends on how many digits you have.</s>
 <s id="117">Or perhaps we just simplify and write it like this.</s>
 <s id="118">I like this one, because this says four divided by three.</s>
 <s id="119">And this number expresses a relation between two numbers.</s>
 <s id="120">You have four on the one hand and three on the other.</s>
 <s id="121">And you can visualize this in many ways.</s>
 <s id="122">What I'm doing now is viewing that number from different perspectives.</s>
 <s id="123">I'm playing around.</s>
 <s id="124">I'm playing around with how we view something, and I'm doing it very deliberately.</s>
 <s id="125">We can take a grid.</s>
 <s id="126">If it's four across and three up, this line equals five, always.</s>
 <p id="p127">
  <s id="127.1">It has to be like this.</s>
  <s id="127.2">This is a beautiful pattern.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="128">Four and three and five.</s>
 <s id="129">And this rectangle, which is 4 x 3, you've seen a lot of times.</s>
 <s id="130">This is your average computer screen.</s>
 <s id="131">800 x 600 or 1,600 x 1,200 is a television or a computer screen.</s>
 <s id="132">So these are all nice representations, but I want to go a little bit further and just play more with this number.</s>
 <p id="p133">
  <s id="133.1">Here you see two circles.</s>
  <s id="133.2">I'm going to rotate them like this.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="134">Observe the upper-left one.</s>
 <s id="135">It goes a little bit faster, right?</s>
 <s id="136">You can see this.</s>
 <s id="137">It actually goes exactly four-thirds as fast.</s>
 <s id="138">That means that when it goes around four times, the other one goes around three times.</s>
 <s id="139">Now let's make two lines, and draw this dot where the lines meet.</s>
 <s id="140">We get this dot dancing around.</s>
 <s id="141">(Laughter) And this dot comes from that number.</s>
 <p id="p142">
  <s id="142.1">Right?</s>
  <s id="142.2">Now we should trace it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="143">Let's trace it and see what happens.</s>
 <s id="144">This is what mathematics is all about.</s>
 <s id="145">It's about seeing what happens.</s>
 <s id="146">And this emerges from four-thirds.</s>
 <s id="147">I like to say that this is the image of four-thirds.</s>
 <s id="148">It's much nicer -- (Cheers) Thank you!</s>
 <s id="149">(Applause) This is not new.</s>
 <s id="150">This has been known for a long time, but -- (Laughter) But this is four-thirds.</s>
 <s id="151">Let's do another experiment.</s>
 <s id="152">Let's now take a sound, this sound: (Beep) This is a perfect A, 440Hz.</s>
 <s id="153">Let's multiply it by two.</s>
 <p id="p154">
  <s id="154.1">We get this sound.</s>
  <s id="154.2">(Beep) When we play them together, it sounds like this.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="155">This is an octave, right?</s>
 <p id="p156">
  <s id="156.1">We can do this game.</s>
  <s id="156.2">We can play a sound, play the same A.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="157">We can multiply it by three-halves.</s>
 <s id="158">(Beep) This is what we call a perfect fifth.</s>
 <s id="159">(Beep) They sound really nice together.</s>
 <p id="p160">
  <s id="160.1">Let's multiply this sound by four-thirds.</s>
  <s id="160.2">(Beep) What happens?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p161">
  <s id="161.1">You get this sound.</s>
  <s id="161.2">(Beep) This is the perfect fourth.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="162">If the first one is an A, this is a D.</s>
 <p id="p163">
  <s id="163.1">They sound like this together.</s>
  <s id="163.2">(Beeps) This is the sound of four-thirds.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="164">What I'm doing now, I'm changing my perspective.</s>
 <s id="165">I'm just viewing a number from another perspective.</s>
 <s id="166">I can even do this with rhythms, right?</s>
 <s id="167">I can take a rhythm and play three beats at one time (Drumbeats) in a period of time, and I can play another sound four times in that same space.</s>
 <s id="168">(Clanking sounds) Sounds kind of boring, but listen to them together.</s>
 <p id="p169">
  <s id="169.1">(Drumbeats and clanking sounds) (Laughter) Hey!</s>
  <s id="169.2">So.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="170">(Laughter) I can even make a little hi-hat.</s>
 <s id="171">(Drumbeats and cymbals) Can you hear this?</s>
 <s id="172">So, this is the sound of four-thirds.</s>
 <s id="173">Again, this is as a rhythm.</s>
 <s id="174">(Drumbeats and cowbell) And I can keep doing this and play games with this number.</s>
 <p id="p175">
  <s id="175.1">Four-thirds is a really great number.</s>
  <s id="175.2">I love four-thirds!</s>
 </p>
 <s id="176">(Laughter) Truly -- it's an undervalued number.</s>
 <s id="177">So if you take a sphere and look at the volume of the sphere, it's actually four-thirds of some particular cylinder.</s>
 <p id="p178">
  <s id="178.1">So four-thirds is in the sphere.</s>
  <s id="178.2">It's the volume of the sphere.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="179">OK, so why am I doing all this?</s>
 <s id="180">Well, I want to talk about what it means to understand something and what we mean by understanding something.</s>
 <s id="181">That's my aim here.</s>
 <s id="182">And my claim is that you understand something if you have the ability to view it from different perspectives.</s>
 <p id="p183">
  <s id="183.1">Let's look at this letter.</s>
  <s id="183.2">It's a beautiful R, right?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="184">How do you know that?</s>
 <s id="185">Well, as a matter of fact, you've seen a bunch of R's, and you've generalized and abstracted all of these and found a pattern.</s>
 <s id="186">So you know that this is an R.</s>
 <s id="187">So what I'm aiming for here is saying something about how understanding and changing your perspective are linked.</s>
 <s id="188">And I'm a teacher and a lecturer, and I can actually use this to teach something, because when I give someone else another story, a metaphor, an analogy, if I tell a story from a different point of view, I enable understanding.</s>
 <s id="189">I make understanding possible, because you have to generalize over everything you see and hear, and if I give you another perspective, that will become easier for you.</s>
 <s id="190">Let's do a simple example again.</s>
 <p id="p191">
  <s id="191.1">This is four and three.</s>
  <s id="191.2">This is four triangles.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="192">So this is also four-thirds, in a way.</s>
 <s id="193">Let's just join them together.</s>
 <s id="194">Now we're going to play a game; we're going to fold it up into a three-dimensional structure.</s>
 <s id="195">I love this.</s>
 <s id="196">This is a square pyramid.</s>
 <s id="197">And let's just take two of them and put them together.</s>
 <s id="198">So this is what is called an octahedron.</s>
 <s id="199">It's one of the five platonic solids.</s>
 <s id="200">Now we can quite literally change our perspective, because we can rotate it around all of the axes and view it from different perspectives.</s>
 <s id="201">And I can change the axis, and then I can view it from another point of view, but it's the same thing, but it looks a little different.</s>
 <s id="202">I can do it even one more time.</s>
 <s id="203">Every time I do this, something else appears, so I'm actually learning more about the object when I change my perspective.</s>
 <s id="204">I can use this as a tool for creating understanding.</s>
 <s id="205">I can take two of these and put them together like this and see what happens.</s>
 <s id="206">And it looks a little bit like the octahedron.</s>
 <s id="207">Have a look at it if I spin it around like this.</s>
 <s id="208">What happens?</s>
 <s id="209">Well, if you take two of these, join them together and spin it around, there's your octahedron again, a beautiful structure.</s>
 <s id="210">If you lay it out flat on the floor, this is the octahedron.</s>
 <s id="211">This is the graph structure of an octahedron.</s>
 <s id="212">And I can continue doing this.</s>
 <s id="213">You can draw three great circles around the octahedron, and you rotate around, so actually three great circles is related to the octahedron.</s>
 <s id="214">And if I take a bicycle pump and just pump it up, you can see that this is also a little bit like the octahedron.</s>
 <s id="215">Do you see what I'm doing here?</s>
 <s id="216">I am changing the perspective every time.</s>
 <s id="217">So let's now take a step back -- and that's actually a metaphor, stepping back -- and have a look at what we're doing.</s>
 <s id="218">I'm playing around with metaphors.</s>
 <s id="219">I'm playing around with perspectives and analogies.</s>
 <s id="220">I'm telling one story in different ways.</s>
 <s id="221">I'm telling stories.</s>
 <s id="222">I'm making a narrative; I'm making several narratives.</s>
 <s id="223">And I think all of these things make understanding possible.</s>
 <s id="224">I think this actually is the essence of understanding something.</s>
 <s id="225">I truly believe this.</s>
 <s id="226">So this thing about changing your perspective -- it's absolutely fundamental for humans.</s>
 <s id="227">Let's play around with the Earth.</s>
 <s id="228">Let's zoom into the ocean, have a look at the ocean.</s>
 <s id="229">We can do this with anything.</s>
 <s id="230">We can take the ocean and view it up close.</s>
 <s id="231">We can look at the waves.</s>
 <s id="232">We can go to the beach.</s>
 <s id="233">We can view the ocean from another perspective.</s>
 <s id="234">Every time we do this, we learn a little bit more about the ocean.</s>
 <s id="235">If we go to the shore, we can kind of smell it, right?</s>
 <s id="236">We can hear the sound of the waves.</s>
 <s id="237">We can feel salt on our tongues.</s>
 <s id="238">So all of these are different perspectives.</s>
 <s id="239">And this is the best one.</s>
 <s id="240">We can go into the water.</s>
 <s id="241">We can see the water from the inside.</s>
 <s id="242">And you know what?</s>
 <s id="243">This is absolutely essential in mathematics and computer science.</s>
 <s id="244">If you're able to view a structure from the inside, then you really learn something about it.</s>
 <s id="245">That's somehow the essence of something.</s>
 <s id="246">So when we do this, and we've taken this journey into the ocean, we use our imagination.</s>
 <s id="247">And I think this is one level deeper, and it's actually a requirement for changing your perspective.</s>
 <s id="248">We can do a little game.</s>
 <s id="249">You can imagine that you're sitting there.</s>
 <s id="250">You can imagine that you're up here, and that you're sitting here.</s>
 <s id="251">You can view yourselves from the outside.</s>
 <s id="252">That's really a strange thing.</s>
 <s id="253">You're changing your perspective.</s>
 <s id="254">You're using your imagination, and you're viewing yourself from the outside.</s>
 <s id="255">That requires imagination.</s>
 <s id="256">Mathematics and computer science are the most imaginative art forms ever.</s>
 <s id="257">And this thing about changing perspectives should sound a little bit familiar to you, because we do it every day.</s>
 <s id="258">And then it's called empathy.</s>
 <s id="259">When I view the world from your perspective, I have empathy with you.</s>
 <s id="260">If I really, truly understand what the world looks like from your perspective, I am empathetic.</s>
 <s id="261">That requires imagination.</s>
 <s id="262">And that is how we obtain understanding.</s>
 <s id="263">And this is all over mathematics and this is all over computer science, and there's a really deep connection between empathy and these sciences.</s>
 <s id="264">So my conclusion is the following: understanding something really deeply has to do with the ability to change your perspective.</s>
 <s id="265">So my advice to you is: try to change your perspective.</s>
 <s id="266">You can study mathematics.</s>
 <s id="267">It's a wonderful way to train your brain.</s>
 <s id="268">Changing your perspective makes your mind more flexible.</s>
 <s id="269">It makes you open to new things, and it makes you able to understand things.</s>
 <s id="270">And to use yet another metaphor: have a mind like water.</s>
 <s id="271">That's nice.</s>
 <s id="272">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="273">(Applause)</s>
</text>
