<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Deep in our solar system, a new era of space exploration is unfolding.</s>
 <s id="2">Beneath the thick ice of Europa, in the vapor plumes on Enceladus, and within the methane lakes of Titan, astrobiologists are on the hunt for extraterrestrial life.</s>
 <s id="3">We’ve honed in on these three moons because each is an ‘ocean world,’ an environment that contains a liquid ocean– and liquid can support the formation of life.</s>
 <s id="4">Living organisms have to be able to grow, reproduce, and feed themselves, among other things.</s>
 <s id="5">All of those functions require the formation of complex molecules from more basic components.</s>
 <s id="6">Liquids such as water allow chemical compounds to remain in suspension instead of sinking under the force of gravity.</s>
 <s id="7">This enables them to interact frequently in a 3-dimensional space and, in the right conditions, go through chemical reactions that lead to the formation of living matter.</s>
 <s id="8">That alone isn’t enough; the small but complex biomolecules that we’re familiar with are sensitive to temperature— too hot or cold, and they won’t mix.</s>
 <s id="9">Liquid water has an additional advantage in that it’s relatively temperature-stable, meaning it can insulate molecules against large shifts in heat.</s>
 <s id="10">On Earth, these and other conditions in aquatic environments may have supported the emergence of life billions of years ago.</s>
 <s id="11">Tantalizingly, the same could be true in other parts of our solar system, like these three icy moons.</s>
 <s id="12">Europa, which is a moon of Jupiter, is probably the most intriguing ocean world.</s>
 <s id="13">Beneath a surface layer of ice thicker than Mount Everest, there exists a liquid ocean as much as 100 kilometers deep.</s>
 <s id="14">Astrobiologists think this hidden ocean could harbor life.</s>
 <s id="15">Thanks to the Galileo probe, we can deduce that its potential salt content is similar to that of some lakes on Earth.</s>
 <s id="16">But most of its characteristics will be a mystery until we can explore it further.</s>
 <s id="17">Like Jupiter, Saturn also has moons that might have the right conditions for life.</s>
 <s id="18">For instance– Enceladus is a tiny ball of ice that’s small enough to nestle within the surface area of the Gulf of Mexico.</s>
 <s id="19">Similarly to Europa, it likely contains an ocean deep under the ice.</s>
 <s id="20">But Enceladus also has geysers that frequently vent water vapor and tiny ice grains into space.</s>
 <s id="21">Astrobiologists are curious about whether these geysers are connected to the ocean below.</s>
 <s id="22">They hope to send a probe to test whether the geysers’ plumes of vapor contain life-enabling material from that hidden sea.</s>
 <s id="23">Although it’s the best known substance for nurturing life, water isn’t necessarily the only medium that can support living things.</s>
 <s id="24">Take Titan, Saturn’s largest moon, which has a thick nitrogen atmosphere containing methane and many other organic molecules.</s>
 <s id="25">Its clouds condense and rain onto Titan’s surface, sustaining lakes and seas full of liquid methane.</s>
 <s id="26">This compound’s particular chemistry means it’s not as supportive a medium as water.</s>
 <s id="27">But, paired with the high quantities of organic material that also rain down from the sky, these bodies of liquid methane could possibly support unfamiliar life forms.</s>
 <s id="28">So what might indicate that life exists on these or other worlds?</s>
 <s id="29">If it is out there, astrobiologists speculate that it would be microscopic, comparable to the bacteria we have on earth.</s>
 <s id="30">This would make it difficult to directly observe from a great distance, so astrobiologists seek clues called biosignatures.</s>
 <s id="31">Those may be cells, fossils, or mineral traces left behind by living things.</s>
 <s id="32">And finding any biosignatures will be challenging for many reasons.</s>
 <s id="33">One of the biggest concerns is to make sure we sterilize our probes extremely thoroughly.</s>
 <s id="34">Otherwise we could accidentally contaminate ocean worlds with Earth’s own bacteria, which could destroy alien life.</s>
 <s id="35">Titan, Enceladus, and Europa are just three of possibly many ocean worlds that we could explore.</s>
 <s id="36">We already know of several other candidates in our solar system, including Jupiter’s moons Callisto and Ganymede, Neptune’s Triton, and even Pluto.</s>
 <s id="37">If there’s this much potential for life to exist in our own tiny solar system, what unimagined secrets might the rest of the universe contain?</s>
</text>
