<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">So, I don't like to boast, but I am very good at finding things to be annoyed about.</s>
 <s id="2">It is a real specialty of mine.</s>
 <s id="3">I can hear 100 compliments and a single insult, and what do I remember?</s>
 <s id="4">The insult.</s>
 <s id="5">And according to the research, I'm not alone.</s>
 <s id="6">Unfortunately, the human brain is wired to focus on the negative.</s>
 <s id="7">Now, this might have been helpful when we were cave people, trying to avoid predators, but now it's a terrible way to go through life.</s>
 <s id="8">It is a real major component of anxiety and depression.</s>
 <s id="9">So how can we fight the brain's negative bias?</s>
 <s id="10">According to a lot of research, one of the best weapons is gratitude.</s>
 <s id="11">So knowing this, I started a new tradition in our house a couple of years ago.</s>
 <s id="12">Before a meal with my wife and kids, I would say a prayer of thanksgiving.</s>
 <s id="13">Prayer is not quite the right word.</s>
 <s id="14">I'm agnostic, so instead of thanking God, I would thank some of the people who helped make my food a reality.</s>
 <s id="15">I'd say, "I'd like to thank the farmer who grew these tomatoes, and the trucker who drove these tomatoes to the store, and the cashier who rang these tomatoes up."</s>
 <s id="16">And I thought it was going pretty well, this tradition.</s>
 <s id="17">Then one day, my 10-year-old son said, "You know, Dad, those people aren't in our apartment.</s>
 <s id="18">They can't hear you.</s>
 <s id="19">If you really cared, you would go and thank them in person."</s>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">And I thought, "Hmm.</s>
  <s id="20.2">That's an interesting idea."</s>
 </p>
 <s id="21">(Laughter) Now I'm a writer, and for my books I like to go on adventures.</s>
 <s id="22">Go on quests.</s>
 <s id="23">So I decided I'm going to take my son up on his challenge.</s>
 <s id="24">It seemed simple enough.</s>
 <s id="25">And to make it even simpler, I decided to focus on just one item.</s>
 <s id="26">An item I can't live without: my morning cup of coffee.</s>
 <s id="27">Well, it turned out to be not so simple at all.</s>
 <s id="28">(Laughter) This quest took me months.</s>
 <s id="29">It took me around the world.</s>
 <s id="30">Because I discovered that my coffee would not be possible without hundreds of people I take for granted.</s>
 <s id="31">So I would thank the trucker who drove the coffee beans to the coffee shop.</s>
 <s id="32">But he couldn't have done his job without the road.</s>
 <s id="33">So I would thank the people who paved the road.</s>
 <s id="34">(Laughter) And then I would thank the people who made the asphalt for the pavement.</s>
 <s id="35">And I came to realize that my coffee, like so much else in the world, requires the combined work of a shocking number of people from all walks of life.</s>
 <s id="36">Architects, biologists, designers, miners, goat herds, you name it.</s>
 <s id="37">I decided to call my project "Thanks a Thousand."</s>
 <s id="38">Because I ended up thanking over a thousand people.</s>
 <s id="39">And it was overwhelming, but it was also wonderful.</s>
 <s id="40">Because it allowed me to focus on the hundreds of things that go right every day, as opposed to the three or four that go wrong.</s>
 <s id="41">And it reminded me of the astounding interconnectedness or our world.</s>
 <s id="42">I learned dozens of lessons during this project, but let me just focus on five today.</s>
 <s id="43">The first is: look up.</s>
 <s id="44">I started my trail of gratitude by thanking the barista at my local coffee shop, Joe Coffee in New York.</s>
 <s id="45">Her name is Chung, and Chung is one of the most upbeat people you will ever meet.</s>
 <s id="46">Big smiler, enthusiastic hugger.</s>
 <s id="47">But even for Chung, being a barista is hard.</s>
 <s id="48">And that's because you are encountering people in a very dangerous state.</s>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) You know what it is -- precaffeination.</s>
 <s id="50">(Laughter) So, Chung has had people yell at her until she cried, including a nine-year-old girl, who didn't like the whipped cream design that Chung did on her hot chocolate.</s>
 <s id="51">So I thanked Chung, and she thanked me for thanking her.</s>
 <s id="52">I cut it off there.</s>
 <s id="53">I didn't want to go into an infinite thanking loop.</s>
 <s id="54">(Laughter) But Chung said that the hardest part is when people don't even treat her like a human being.</s>
 <s id="55">They treat her like a vending machine.</s>
 <s id="56">So, they'll hand her their credit card without even looking up from their phone.</s>
 <s id="57">And while she's saying this, I'm realizing I've done that.</s>
 <s id="58">I've been that a-hole.</s>
 <s id="59">And at that moment, I pledged: when dealing with people, I'm going to take those two seconds and look at them, make eye contact.</s>
 <s id="60">Because it reminds you, you're dealing with a human being who has family and aspirations and embarrassing high school memories.</s>
 <s id="61">And that little moment of connection is so important to both people's humanity and happiness.</s>
 <p id="p62">
  <s id="62.1">Alright, second lesson was: smell the roses.</s>
  <s id="62.2">And the dirt.</s>
  <s id="62.3">And the fertilizer.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="63">After Chung, I thanked this man.</s>
 <s id="64">This is Ed Kaufmann.</s>
 <s id="65">And Ed is the one who chooses which coffee they serve at my local coffee shop.</s>
 <s id="66">He goes around the world, to South America, to Africa, finding the best coffee beans.</s>
 <s id="67">So I thanked Ed.</s>
 <s id="68">And in return, Ed showed me how to taste coffee like a pro.</s>
 <s id="69">And it is quite a ritual.</s>
 <s id="70">You take your spoon and you dip it in the coffee and then you take a big, loud slurp.</s>
 <s id="71">Almost cartoonishly loud.</s>
 <s id="72">This is because you want to spray the coffee all over your mouth.</s>
 <s id="73">You have taste buds in the side of your cheeks, in the roof of your mouth, you've got to get them all.</s>
 <s id="74">So Ed would do this and he would -- his face would light up and he would say, "This coffee tastes of Honeycrisp apple and notes of soil and maple syrup."</s>
 <s id="75">And I would take a sip and I'd say, "I'm picking up coffee.</s>
 <s id="76">(Laughter) It tastes to me like coffee."</s>
 <s id="77">(Laughter) But inspired by Ed, I decided to really let the coffee sit on my tongue for five seconds -- we're all busy, but I could spare five seconds, and really think about the texture and the acidity and the sweetness.</s>
 <s id="78">And I started to do it with other foods.</s>
 <s id="79">And this idea of savoring is so important to gratitude.</s>
 <s id="80">Psychologists talk about how gratitude is about taking a moment and holding on to it as long as possible.</s>
 <s id="81">And slowing down time.</s>
 <s id="82">So that life doesn't go by in one big blur, as it often does.</s>
 <s id="83">Number three is: find the hidden masterpieces all around you.</s>
 <s id="84">Now, one of my favorite conversations during this year was with the guy who invented my coffee cup lid.</s>
 <s id="85">And until this point, I had given approximately zero thought to coffee cup lids.</s>
 <s id="86">But I loved talking to this inventor, Doug Fleming, because he was so passionate.</s>
 <s id="87">And the blood and sweat and tears he put into this lid, and that I had never even considered.</s>
 <s id="88">He says a bad lid can ruin your coffee.</s>
 <s id="89">That it can block the aroma, which is so important to the experience.</s>
 <s id="90">So he -- he's very innovative.</s>
 <s id="91">He's like the Elon Musk of coffee lids.</s>
 <s id="92">(Laughter) So he designed this lid that's got an upside-down hexagon so you can get your nose right in there and get maximum aroma.</s>
 <s id="93">And so I was delighted talking to him, and it made me realize there are hundreds of masterpieces all around us that we totally take for granted.</s>
 <s id="94">Like the on-off switch on my desk lamp has a little indentation for my thumb that perfectly fits my thumb.</s>
 <s id="95">And when something is done well, the process behind it is largely invisible.</s>
 <s id="96">But paying attention to it can tap into that sense of wonder and enrich our lives.</s>
 <s id="97">Number four is: fake it till you feel it.</s>
 <s id="98">By the end of the project, I was just in a thanking frenzy.</s>
 <s id="99">So I was -- I would get up and spend a couple hours, I'd write emails, send notes, make phone calls, visit people to thank them for their role in my coffee.</s>
 <s id="100">And some of them, quite honestly -- not that into it.</s>
 <s id="101">They would be like, "What is this?</s>
 <s id="102">Is this a pyramid scheme, what do you want, what are you selling?"</s>
 <s id="103">But most people were surprisingly moved.</s>
 <s id="104">I remember, I called the woman who does the pest control for the warehouse where my coffee is served -- I'm sorry -- where my coffee is stored.</s>
 <s id="105">And I said, "This may sound strange, but I want to thank you for keeping the bugs out of my coffee."</s>
 <s id="106">And she said, "Well, that does sound strange, but you just made my day."</s>
 <s id="107">And it was like an anti-crank phone call.</s>
 <s id="108">And it didn't just affect her, it affected me.</s>
 <s id="109">Because I would wake up every morning in my default mood, which is grumpiness, but I would force myself to write a thank-you note and then another and then another.</s>
 <s id="110">And what I found was that if you act as if you're grateful, you eventually become grateful for real.</s>
 <s id="111">The power of our actions to change our mind is astounding.</s>
 <s id="112">So, often we think that thought changes behavior, but behavior very often changes our thought.</s>
 <s id="113">And finally, the last lesson I want to tell you about is: practice six degrees of gratitude.</s>
 <s id="114">And every place, every stop on this gratitude trail would give birth to 100 other people that I could thank.</s>
 <s id="115">So I went down to Colombia to thank the farmers who grow my coffee beans.</s>
 <s id="116">And it was in a small mountain town, and I was driven there along these curvy, cliffside roads.</s>
 <s id="117">And every time we went around a hairpin turn the driver would do the sign of the cross.</s>
 <s id="118">And I was like, "Thank you for that.</s>
 <s id="119">(Laughter) But can you do that while keeping your hands on the wheel?</s>
 <s id="120">Because I am terrified."</s>
 <s id="121">But we made it.</s>
 <s id="122">And I met the farmers, the Guarnizo brothers.</s>
 <s id="123">It's a small farm, they make great coffee, they're paid above fair-trade prices for it.</s>
 <s id="124">And they showed me how the coffee is grown.</s>
 <s id="125">The bean is actually inside this fruit called the coffee cherry.</s>
 <s id="126">And I thanked them.</s>
 <s id="127">And they said, "Well, we couldn't do our job without 100 other people."</s>
 <s id="128">The machine that depulps the fruit is made in Brazil, and the pickup truck they drive around the farm, that is made from parts from all over the world.</s>
 <s id="129">In fact, the US exports steel to Colombia.</s>
 <s id="130">So I went to Indiana, and I thanked the steel makers.</s>
 <s id="131">And it just drove home that it doesn't take a village to make a cup of coffee.</s>
 <s id="132">It takes the world to make a cup of coffee.</s>
 <s id="133">And this global economy, this globalization, it does have downsides.</s>
 <s id="134">But I believe the long-term upsides are far greater, that progress is real.</s>
 <s id="135">We have made improvements in the last 50 years, poverty worldwide has gone down.</s>
 <s id="136">And that we should resist the temptation to retreat into our silos.</s>
 <s id="137">And we should resist this upsurge in isolationism and jingoism.</s>
 <s id="138">Which brings me to my final point.</s>
 <s id="139">Which is my hope that we use gratitude as a spark to action.</s>
 <s id="140">Some people worry that gratitude has a downside.</s>
 <s id="141">That we'll be so grateful, that we'll be complacent.</s>
 <s id="142">We'll be so, "Oh, everything's wonderful, I'm so grateful."</s>
 <s id="143">Well, it turns out, the opposite is true.</s>
 <s id="144">The research shows that the more grateful you are, the more likely you are to help others.</s>
 <s id="145">When you're in a bad state, you're often more focused on your own needs.</s>
 <s id="146">But gratitude makes you want to pay it forward.</s>
 <s id="147">And I experienced this personally.</s>
 <s id="148">I mean, I'm not Mother Teresa, I'm still a selfish bastard a huge amount of the time.</s>
 <s id="149">But I'm better than I was before this project.</s>
 <s id="150">And that's because it made me aware of the exploitation on the supply chain.</s>
 <s id="151">It reminded me that what I take for granted is not available to millions of people around the world.</s>
 <s id="152">Like water.</s>
 <s id="153">Coffee is 98.8 percent water.</s>
 <s id="154">So I figured I should go and thank the people at the New York reservoir, hundreds of them, who provide me water, and this miracle that I can turn a lever and get safe water.</s>
 <s id="155">And that millions of people around the world don't have this luxury and have to walk hours to get safe water.</s>
 <s id="156">It inspired me to see what I could do to help people get more access, and I did research and found a wonderful group called Dispensers for Safe Water.</s>
 <s id="157">And I got involved.</s>
 <s id="158">And I'm not expecting the Nobel Prize committee to knock down my door, but it's a baby step, it's a little something.</s>
 <s id="159">And it's all because of gratitude.</s>
 <s id="160">And it's why I encourage people, friends, family, to follow gratitude trails of their own.</s>
 <s id="161">Because it's a life-transforming experience.</s>
 <s id="162">And it doesn't have to be coffee.</s>
 <s id="163">It could be anything.</s>
 <s id="164">It could be a pair of socks, it could be a light bulb.</s>
 <s id="165">And you don't have to go around the world, you can just do a little gesture, like make eye contact or send a note to the designer of a logo you love.</s>
 <s id="166">It's more about a mindset.</s>
 <s id="167">Being aware of the thousands of people involved in every little thing we do.</s>
 <s id="168">Remembering that there's someone in a factory who made the fabric for the chairs you're sitting in right now.</s>
 <s id="169">That someone went into a mine and got the copper for this microphone so that I could say my final thank you, which is to thank you.</s>
 <s id="170">Thank you a thousand for listening to my story.</s>
 <s id="171">(Applause) (Cheering)</s>
</text>
