<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">The royal couple of Haiti rode into their coronation to thunderous applause.</s>
 <s id="2">After receiving his ornate crown and scepter, Henry Christophe ascended his throne, towering 20 meters in the air.</s>
 <s id="3">But little did the cheering onlookers know that the first king of Haiti would also be its last.</s>
 <s id="4">Enslaved at birth on the island of Grenada, Christophe spent his childhood being moved between multiple Caribbean islands.</s>
 <s id="5">Just 12 years old in 1779, he accompanied his master to aid the American revolutionaries in the Battle of Savannah.</s>
 <s id="6">This prolonged siege would be Christophe’s first encounter with violent revolution.</s>
 <s id="7">There are few surviving written records about Christophe’s life immediately after the war.</s>
 <s id="8">Over the next decade, we know he worked as a mason and a waiter at a hotel in the French colony of Saint-Domingue, as Haiti was then known.</s>
 <s id="9">In 1791, when the colony’s slaves rose up in rebellion, Christophe got another opportunity to fight for freedom.</s>
 <s id="10">Led by Toussaint Louverture, the rebels fought against plantation owners, as well as British and Spanish forces seeking control of the island.</s>
 <s id="11">Christophe quickly rose through the ranks, proving himself the equal of more experienced generals.</s>
 <s id="12">By 1793, Louverture had successfully liberated all of Saint-Domingue’s enslaved people, and by 1801 he’d established the island as a semi-autonomous colony.</s>
 <s id="13">But during this time, Napoleon Bonaparte had assumed power in France, and made it his mission to restore slavery and French authority throughout the empire.</s>
 <s id="14">French attempts to reinstate slavery met fierce resistance, with General Christophe even burning the capital city to prevent military occupation.</s>
 <s id="15">Finally, the rebellion and an outbreak of yellow fever forced French soldiers to withdraw— but the fight was not without casualties.</s>
 <s id="16">Louverture was captured, and left to die in a French prison; a fate that Christophe’s nine-year-old son would share only a few years later.</s>
 <s id="17">Following the revolution, Christophe and generals Jean-Jacques Dessalines and Alexandre Pétion rose to prominent positions in the new government.</s>
 <s id="18">In 1804, Dessalines was proclaimed the emperor of independent Haiti.</s>
 <s id="19">But his desire to hold exclusive power alienated his supporters.</s>
 <s id="20">Eventually, Dessalines’ rule incited a political conspiracy that ended in his assassination in 1806.</s>
 <s id="21">The subsequent power struggle led to a Civil War, which split the country in two.</s>
 <s id="22">By 1807, Christophe was governing as president of the north in Cap-Haïtien, and Pétion was ruling the south from Port-au-Prince.</s>
 <s id="23">Pétion tried to stay true to the revolution’s democratic roots by modeling his republic after the United States.</s>
 <s id="24">He even supported anti-colonial revolutionaries in other nations.</s>
 <s id="25">These policies endeared him to his people, but they slowed trade and economic growth.</s>
 <s id="26">Christophe, conversely, had more aggressive plans for an independent Haiti.</s>
 <s id="27">He redistributed land to the people, while retaining state control of agriculture.</s>
 <s id="28">He also established trade with many foreign nations, including Great Britain and the United States, and pledged non-interference with their foreign policies.</s>
 <s id="29">He even built a massive Citadel in case the French tried to invade again.</s>
 <s id="30">To accomplish all of this, Christophe instituted mandatory labor, and to strengthen his authority, he crowned himself king in 1811.</s>
 <s id="31">During his reign, he lived in an elegant palace called Sans Souci along with his wife and their three remaining children.</s>
 <s id="32">Christophe’s kingdom oversaw rapid development of trade, industry, culture, and education.</s>
 <s id="33">He imported renowned European artists to Haiti’s cultural scene, as well as European teachers, in order to establish public education.</s>
 <s id="34">But while the king was initially popular among his subjects, his labor mandates were an uncomfortable reminder of the slavery Haitians fought to destroy.</s>
 <s id="35">Over time, his increasingly authoritarian policies lost support, and his opponents to the south gained strength.</s>
 <s id="36">In October 1820, his reign finally reached its tragic conclusion.</s>
 <s id="37">Months after a debilitating stroke left him unable to govern, key members of his military defected to southern forces.</s>
 <s id="38">Betrayed and despondent, the king committed suicide.</s>
 <s id="39">Today, the traces of Christophe’s complicated history can still be found in the crumbling remains of his palaces, and in Haiti’s legacy as the first nation to permanently abolish slavery.</s>
</text>
