<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">[This talk contains graphic images] So I'm sitting across from Pedro, the coyote, the human smuggler, in his cement block apartment, in a dusty Reynosa neighborhood somewhere on the US-Mexico border.</s>
 <s id="2">It's 3am.</s>
 <s id="3">The day before, he had asked me to come back to his apartment.</s>
 <s id="4">We would talk man to man.</s>
 <s id="5">He wanted me to be there at night and alone.</s>
 <s id="6">I didn't know if he was setting me up, but I knew I wanted to tell his story.</s>
 <s id="7">He asked me, "What will you do if one of these pollitos, or migrants, slips into the water and can't swim?</s>
 <s id="8">Will you simply take your pictures and watch him drown?</s>
 <s id="9">Or will you jump in and help me?"</s>
 <s id="10">At that moment, Pedro wasn't a cartoonish TV version of a human smuggler.</s>
 <s id="11">He was just a young man, about my age, asking me some really tough questions.</s>
 <s id="12">This was life and death.</s>
 <s id="13">The next night, I photographed Pedro as he swam the Rio Grande, crossing with a group of young migrants into the United States.</s>
 <s id="14">Real lives hung in the balance every time he crossed people.</s>
 <s id="15">For the last 20 years, I've documented one of the largest transnational migrations in world history, which has resulted in millions of undocumented people living in the United States.</s>
 <s id="16">The vast majority of these people leave Central America and Mexico to escape grinding poverty and extreme levels of social violence.</s>
 <s id="17">I photograph intimate moments of everyday people's lives, of people living in the shadows.</s>
 <s id="18">Time and again, I've witnessed resilient individuals in extremely challenging situations constructing practical ways to improve their lives.</s>
 <s id="19">With these photographs, I place you squarely in the middle of these moments and ask you to think about them as if you knew them.</s>
 <s id="20">This body of work is a historical document, a time capsule that can teach us not only about migration, but about society and ourselves.</s>
 <s id="21">I started the project in the year 2000.</s>
 <s id="22">The migrant trail has taught me how we treat our most vulnerable residents in the United States.</s>
 <s id="23">It has taught me about violence and pain and hope and resilience and struggle and sacrifice.</s>
 <s id="24">It has taught me firsthand that rhetoric and political policy directly impact real people.</s>
 <s id="25">And most of all, the migrant trail has taught me that everyone who embarks on it is changed forever.</s>
 <s id="26">I began this project in the year 2000 by documenting a group of day laborers on Chicago’s Northwest side.</s>
 <s id="27">Each day, the men would wake up at 5am, go to a McDonald's, where they would stand outside and wait to jump into strangers' work vans, in the hopes of finding a job for the day.</s>
 <s id="28">They earned five dollars an hour, had no job security, no health insurance and were almost all undocumented.</s>
 <s id="29">The men were all pretty tough.</s>
 <s id="30">They had to be.</s>
 <s id="31">The police constantly harassed them for loitering, as they made their way each day.</s>
 <s id="32">Slowly, they welcomed me into their community.</s>
 <s id="33">And this was one of the first times that I consciously used my camera as a weapon.</s>
 <s id="34">One day, as the men were organizing to make a day-labor worker center, a young man named Tomás came up to me and asked me will I stay afterwards and photograph him.</s>
 <s id="35">So I agreed.</s>
 <s id="36">As he walked into the middle of the empty dirt lot, a light summer rain started to fall.</s>
 <p id="p37">
  <s id="37.1">Much to my surprise, he started to take off his clothes.</s>
  <s id="37.2">(Laughs) I didn't exactly know what to do.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="38">He pointed to the sky and said, "Our bodies are all we have."</s>
 <s id="39">He was proud, defiant and vulnerable, all at once.</s>
 <s id="40">And this remains one of my favorite photographs of the past 20 years.</s>
 <s id="41">His words have stuck with me ever since.</s>
 <s id="42">I met Lupe Guzmán around the same time, while she was organizing and fighting the day-labor agencies which were exploiting her and her coworkers.</s>
 <s id="43">She organized small-scale protests, sit-ins and much more.</s>
 <s id="44">She paid a high price for her activism, because the day-labor agencies like Ron's blackballed her and refused to give her work.</s>
 <s id="45">So in order to survive, she started selling elotes, or corn on the cob, on the street, as a street vendor.</s>
 <s id="46">And today, you can still find her selling all types of corn and different candies and stuff.</s>
 <s id="47">Lupe brought me into the inner world of her family and showed me the true impact of migration.</s>
 <s id="48">She introduced me to everyone in her extended family, Gabi, Juan, Conchi, Chava, everyone.</s>
 <s id="49">Her sister Remedios had married Anselmo, whose eight of nine siblings had migrated from Mexico to Chicago in the nineties.</s>
 <s id="50">So many people in her family opened their world to me and shared their stories.</s>
 <s id="51">Families are the heart and lifeblood of the migrant trail.</s>
 <s id="52">When these families migrate, they change and transform societies.</s>
 <s id="53">It's rare to be able to access so intimately the intimate and day-to-day lives of people who, by necessity, are closed to outsiders.</s>
 <s id="54">At the time, Lupe's family lived in the insular world of the Back of the Yards, a tight-knit Chicago neighborhood, which for more than 100 years had been a portal of entry for recent immigrants -- first, from Europe, like my family, and more recently, from Latin America.</s>
 <s id="55">Their world was largely hidden from view.</s>
 <s id="56">And they call the larger, white world outside the neighborhood "Gringolandia."</s>
 <s id="57">You know, like lots of generations moving to the Back of the Yards, the family did the thankless hidden jobs that most people didn't want to do: cleaning office buildings, preparing airline meals in cold factories, meat packing, demolitions.</s>
 <s id="58">It was hard manual labor for low exploitation wages.</s>
 <s id="59">But on weekends, they celebrated together, with backyard barbecues and birthday celebrations, like most working families the world over.</s>
 <s id="60">I became an honorary family member.</s>
 <s id="61">My nickname was "Johnny Canales," after the Tejano TV star.</s>
 <s id="62">I had access to the dominant culture, so I was part family photographer, part social worker and part strange outsider payaso clown, who was there to amuse them.</s>
 <s id="63">One of the most memorable moments of this time was photographing the birth of Lupe's granddaughter, Elizabeth.</s>
 <s id="64">Her two older siblings had crossed across the Sonoran Desert, being carried and pushed in strollers into the United States.</s>
 <s id="65">So at that time, her family allowed me to photograph her birth.</s>
 <s id="66">And it was one of the really coolest things as the nurses placed baby Elizabeth on Gabi's chest.</s>
 <s id="67">She was the family's first American citizen.</s>
 <s id="68">That girl is 17 today.</s>
 <s id="69">And I still remain in close contact with Lupe and much of her family.</s>
 <s id="70">My work is firmly rooted in my own family's history of exile and subsequent rebirth in the United States.</s>
 <s id="71">My father was born in Nazi Germany in 1934.</s>
 <s id="72">Like most assimilated German Jews, my grandparents simply hoped that the troubles of the Third Reich would blow over.</s>
 <s id="73">But in spring of 1939, a small but important event happened to my family.</s>
 <s id="74">My dad needed an appendectomy.</s>
 <s id="75">And because he was Jewish, not one hospital would operate on him.</s>
 <s id="76">The operation was carried out on his kitchen table, on the family's kitchen table.</s>
 <s id="77">Only after understanding the discrimination they faced did my grandparents make the gut-wrenching decision to send their two children on the Kindertransport bound for England.</s>
 <s id="78">My family's survival has informed my deep commitment to telling this migration story in a deep and nuanced way.</s>
 <s id="79">The past and the present are always interconnected.</s>
 <s id="80">The long-standing legacy of the US government's involvement in Latin America is controversial and well-documented.</s>
 <s id="81">The 1954 CIA-backed coup of Árbenz in Guatemala, the Iran-Contra scandal, the School of the Americas, the murder of Archbishop Romero on the steps of a San Salvador church are all examples of this complex history, a history which has led to instability and impunity in Central America.</s>
 <s id="82">Luckily, the history is not unremittingly dark.</s>
 <s id="83">The United States and Mexico took in thousands and millions, actually, of refugees escaping the civil wars of the 70s and 80s.</s>
 <s id="84">But by the time I was documenting the migrant trail in Guatemala in the late 2000s, most Americans had no connection to the increasing levels of violence, impunity and migration in Central America.</s>
 <s id="85">To most US citizens, it might as well have been the Moon.</s>
 <s id="86">Over the years, I slowly pieced together the complicated puzzle that stretched from Central America through Mexico to my backyard in Chicago.</s>
 <s id="87">I hit almost all the border towns -- Brownsville, Reynosa, McAllen, Yuma, Calexico -- recording the increasing militarization of the border.</s>
 <s id="88">Each time I returned, there was more infrastructure, more sensors, more fences, more Border Patrol agents and more high-tech facilities with which to incarcerate the men, women and children who our government detained.</s>
 <s id="89">Post-9/11, it became a huge industry.</s>
 <s id="90">I photographed the massive and historic immigration marches in Chicago, children at detention facilities and the slow percolating rise of anti-immigrant hate groups, including sheriff Joe Arpaio in Arizona.</s>
 <s id="91">I documented the children in detention facilities, deportation flights and a lot of different things.</s>
 <s id="92">I witnessed the rise of the Mexican drug war and the deepening levels of social violence in Central America.</s>
 <s id="93">I came to understand how interconnected all these disparate elements were and how interconnected we all are.</s>
 <s id="94">As photographers, we never really know which particular moment will stay with us or which particular person will be with us.</s>
 <s id="95">The people we photograph become a part of our collective history.</s>
 <s id="96">Jerica Estrada was a young eight-year-old girl whose memory has stayed with me.</s>
 <s id="97">Her father had gone to LA in order to work to support his family.</s>
 <s id="98">And like any dutiful father, he returned home to Guatemala, bearing gifts.</s>
 <s id="99">That weekend, he had presented his eldest son with a motorcycle -- a true luxury.</s>
 <s id="100">As the son was driving the father back home from a family party, a gang member rode up and shot the dad through the back.</s>
 <s id="101">It was a case of mistaken identity, an all too common occurrence in this country.</s>
 <s id="102">But the damage was done.</s>
 <s id="103">The bullet passed through the father and into the son.</s>
 <s id="104">This was not a random act of violence, but one instance of social violence in a region of the world where this has become the norm.</s>
 <s id="105">Impunity thrives when all the state and governmental institutions fail to protect the individual.</s>
 <s id="106">Too often, the result forces people to leave their homes and flee and take great risks in search of safety.</s>
 <s id="107">Jerica's father died en route to the hospital.</s>
 <s id="108">His body had saved his son's life.</s>
 <s id="109">As we arrived to the public hospital, to the gates of the public hospital, I noticed a young girl in a pink striped shirt, screaming.</s>
 <s id="110">Nobody comforted the little girl as she clasped her tiny hands.</s>
 <s id="111">She was the man's youngest daughter, her name was Jerica Estrada.</s>
 <s id="112">She cried and raged, and nobody could do anything, for her father was gone.</s>
 <s id="113">These days, when people ask me why young mothers with four-month-old babies will travel thousands of miles, knowing they will likely be imprisoned in the United States, I remember Jerica, and I think of her and of her pain and of her father who saved his son's life with his own body, and I understand the truly human need to migrate in search of a better life.</s>
 <s id="114">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="115">(Applause)</s>
</text>
