<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Picture this: your friend and you are watching a sitcom and a sassy sidekick walks into a room, carrying a four-tiered wedding cake.</s>
 <s id="2">He trips, falls, and face-plants into the cake.</s>
 <p id="p3">
  <s id="3.1">Your friend doubles over with laughter and says, "It's so ridiculous!</s>
  <s id="3.2">So ironic!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="4">Well, quick, what do you do?</s>
 <s id="5">Do you laugh along with the laugh track and let this grievous misinterpretation of irony go?</s>
 <s id="6">Or, do you throw caution to the wind and explain the true meaning of irony?</s>
 <s id="7">If you're me, you choose the latter.</s>
 <s id="8">Unfortunately, irony has been completely misunderstood.</s>
 <s id="9">We tend to throw out that term whenever we see something funny or coincidental.</s>
 <s id="10">And while many examples of true irony can be funny, that is not the driving factor of being ironic.</s>
 <s id="11">A situation is only ironic if what happens is the exact opposite of what was expected.</s>
 <s id="12">If you expect A, but get B, then you have irony.</s>
 <s id="13">Let's take the slap-stick cake situation as an example.</s>
 <s id="14">When someone walks in precariously balancing something that shouldn't be carried alone, trips, falls, and makes a mess, it is funny, but it's not ironic.</s>
 <s id="15">In fact, you probably expect someone who is single-handedly carrying a huge cake to trip.</s>
 <s id="16">When he does, reality aligns with expectations, and so that is not irony.</s>
 <s id="17">But what if the sassy sidekick walked in wearing a gold medal that he'd won at the cake walking event at the Atlanta Olympics in 1996?</s>
 <s id="18">What if that sidekick was a professional cake carrier?</s>
 <s id="19">Then, maybe there would have been a reasonable expectation that he would have been more skilled when carrying a ridiculously large cake.</s>
 <s id="20">Then, when that reasonable expectation was not met by the tripping sidekick, irony would have been exemplified.</s>
 <s id="21">Another example.</s>
 <s id="22">A senior citizen texting and blogging.</s>
 <s id="23">The common and reasonable expectation of more mature men and women is that they don't like or know technology, that they have a hard time turning on a computer, or that they have the old brick cell phones from the 1980s.</s>
 <s id="24">One should not expect them to be connected, high-tech, or savvy enough to text or to be blogging, which must seem like some sort of newfangled thing that "back in my day," they never had.</s>
 <s id="25">So when Granny pulls out her smart phone to post pictures of her dentures or her grandkids, irony ensues.</s>
 <s id="26">Reasonable expectations of the situation are not met.</s>
 <s id="27">That is irony.</s>
 <s id="28">So while the cake dropper might not be ironic, there are all kinds of situations in life that are.</s>
 <s id="29">Go out, and find those true examples of irony.</s>
</text>
