<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">A portly Miller, barely sober enough to sit on his horse, rambles on about the flighty wife of a crotchety old carpenter and the scholar she takes as her lover.</s>
 <s id="2">To get some time alone together, the scholar and the wife play various tricks that involve feigning madness, staging a biblical flood, and exposing themselves in public.</s>
 <s id="3">But the parish clerk is also lusting after the wife, and comes by every night to sing outside her house.</s>
 <s id="4">This becomes so tiresome that she tries to scare him away by hanging her rear end out the window for him to kiss.</s>
 <s id="5">When this appears not to work, her scholar decides to try farting in the same position, but this time, the clerk is waiting with a red-hot poker.</s>
 <s id="6">This might all sound like a bawdy joke, but it’s part of one of the most esteemed works of English literature ever created: The Canterbury Tales, which seamlessly blends the lofty and the lowly.</s>
 <s id="7">The work consists of 24 stories, each told by one of Chaucer’s spirited characters.</s>
 <s id="8">Narrators include familiar Medieval figures such as a Knight, a Clerk, and a Nun, and the less recognizable Reeve, and Mancible, and others.</s>
 <s id="9">The Tales are written in Middle English, which often looks entirely different from the language spoken today.</s>
 <s id="10">It was used between the 12th and 15th centuries, and evolved from Old English due to increased contact with European romantic languages after the Norman Conquest of 1066.</s>
 <s id="11">Most of the Middle English alphabet is still familiar today, with the inclusion of a few archaic symbols, such as yogh, which denotes the y, j, or gh sound.</s>
 <s id="12">The loquacious cast of the Tales first meet at the Tabard Inn in Southwark.</s>
 <s id="13">They have a journey in common: a pilgrimage to Canterbury to visit the shrine of St. Thomas Beckett, a martyred archbishop who was murdered in his own Cathedral.</s>
 <s id="14">Eager and nosy for some personal details, the host of the Inn proposes a competition: whoever tells the best tale will be treated to dinner.</s>
 <s id="15">If not for their pilgrimage, many of these figures would never have had the chance to interact.</s>
 <s id="16">This is because Medieval society followed a feudal system that divided the clergy and nobility from the working classes, made up of peasants and serfs.</s>
 <s id="17">By Chaucer’s time, a professional class of merchants and intellectuals had also emerged.</s>
 <s id="18">Chaucer spent most of his life as a government official during the Hundred Years' War, traveling throughout Italy and France, as well as his native England.</s>
 <s id="19">This may have influenced the panoramic vision of his work, and in the Tales, no level of society is above mockery.</s>
 <s id="20">Chaucer uses the quirks of the characters’ language – the ribald humor of the Cook, the solemn prose of the Parson, and the lofty notions of the Squire – to satirize their worldviews.</s>
 <s id="21">The varied dialects, genres, and literary tropes also make the work a vivid record of the different ways Medieval audiences entertained themselves.</s>
 <s id="22">For instance, the Knight’s tale of courtly love, chivalry, and destiny riffs on romance, while the tales of working-class narrators are generally comedies filled with scatological language, sexual deviance, and slapstick.</s>
 <s id="23">This variation includes something for everyone, and that’s one reason why readers continue to delight in the work in both Middle English and translation.</s>
 <s id="24">While the narrative runs to over 17,000 lines, it's apparently unfinished, as the prologue ambitiously introduces 29 pilgrims and promises four stories apiece, and the innkeeper never crowns a victor.</s>
 <s id="25">It’s possible that Chaucer was so caught up in his sumptuous creations that he delayed picking a winner - or perhaps he was so fond of each character that he just couldn’t choose.</s>
 <s id="26">Whatever the reason, this means that every reader is free to judge; the question of who wins is up to you.</s>
</text>
