<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Now, if President Obama invited me to be the next Czar of Mathematics, then I would have a suggestion for him that I think would vastly improve the mathematics education in this country.</s>
 <s id="2">And it would be easy to implement and inexpensive.</s>
 <s id="3">The mathematics curriculum that we have is based on a foundation of arithmetic and algebra.</s>
 <s id="4">And everything we learn after that is building up towards one subject.</s>
 <s id="5">And at top of that pyramid, it's calculus.</s>
 <s id="6">And I'm here to say that I think that that is the wrong summit of the pyramid ...</s>
 <s id="7">that the correct summit -- that all of our students, every high school graduate should know -- should be statistics: probability and statistics.</s>
 <p id="p8">
  <s id="8.1">(Applause) I mean, don't get me wrong.</s>
  <s id="8.2">Calculus is an important subject.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="9">It's one of the great products of the human mind.</s>
 <s id="10">The laws of nature are written in the language of calculus.</s>
 <s id="11">And every student who studies math, science, engineering, economics, they should definitely learn calculus by the end of their freshman year of college.</s>
 <s id="12">But I'm here to say, as a professor of mathematics, that very few people actually use calculus in a conscious, meaningful way, in their day-to-day lives.</s>
 <p id="p13">
  <s id="13.1">On the other hand, statistics -- that's a subject that you could, and should, use on daily basis.</s>
  <s id="13.2">Right?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">It's risk.</s>
  <s id="14.2">It's reward.</s>
  <s id="14.3">It's randomness.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="15">It's understanding data.</s>
 <p id="p16">
  <s id="16.1">I think if our students, if our high school students -- if all of the American citizens -- knew about probability and statistics, we wouldn't be in the economic mess that we're in today.</s>
  <s id="16.2">(Laughter) (Applause) Not only -- thank you -- not only that ...</s>
 </p>
 <s id="17">but if it's taught properly, it can be a lot of fun.</s>
 <s id="18">I mean, probability and statistics, it's the mathematics of games and gambling.</s>
 <p id="p19">
  <s id="19.1">It's analyzing trends.</s>
  <s id="19.2">It's predicting the future.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="20">Look, the world has changed from analog to digital.</s>
 <s id="21">And it's time for our mathematics curriculum to change from analog to digital, from the more classical, continuous mathematics, to the more modern, discrete mathematics -- the mathematics of uncertainty, of randomness, of data -- that being probability and statistics.</s>
 <p id="p22">
  <s id="22.1">In summary, instead of our students learning about the techniques of calculus, I think it would be far more significant if all of them knew what two standard deviations from the mean means.</s>
  <s id="22.2">And I mean it.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="23">Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="24">(Applause)</s>
</text>
