<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">He was a powerful king whose break with the church of Rome would forever change the course of English history.</s>
 <s id="2">But was he a charismatic reformer or a bullying tyrant?</s>
 <s id="3">Find out on History versus Henry VIII.</s>
 <p id="p4">
  <s id="4.1">Judge: Order, order.</s>
  <s id="4.2">Now, who do we have here?</s>
  <s id="4.3">Looks like quite the dashing fellow.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p5">
  <s id="5.1">Defense: Indeed, your honour.</s>
  <s id="5.2">This is Henry VIII, the acclaimed king who reformed England's religion and government and set it on course to becoming a modern nation.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">Prosecutor: I beg to differ.</s>
  <s id="6.2">This is a cruel, impulsive, and extravagant king who had as little regard for his people as he did for his six wives.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="7">Judge: Six wives?</s>
 <s id="8">Defense: Your honor, Henry's first marriage was arranged for him when he was only a child.</s>
 <s id="9">He only married Catherine of Aragon to strengthen England’s alliance with Spain.</s>
 <s id="10">Prosecutor: An alliance he was willing to toss aside with no regard for the nation.</s>
 <s id="11">Defense: Henry had every regard for the nation.</s>
 <s id="12">It was imperative to secure the Tudor dynasty by producing a male heir – something Catherine failed to do in over twenty years of marriage.</s>
 <s id="13">Prosecutor: It takes two to make an heir, your honor.</s>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">Defense: Ahem.</s>
  <s id="14.2">Regardless, England needed a new queen to ensure stability, but the Pope refused to annul the union and let the king remarry.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p15">
  <s id="15.1">Judge: Sounds like quite a pickle.</s>
  <s id="15.2">Can’t argue with the Pope.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="16">Prosecutor: And yet that’s exactly what the king decided to do.</s>
 <s id="17">He uprooted the country’s religious foundations and broke the Church of England away from Rome, leading to centuries of strife.</s>
 <s id="18">Defense: All Henry did was give the Church honest domestic leadership.</s>
 <s id="19">He freed his subjects from the corrupt Roman Catholic establishment.</s>
 <s id="20">And by rejecting the more radical changes of the Protestant reformation, he allowed his people to preserve most of their religious traditions.</s>
 <p id="p21">
  <s id="21.1">Prosecutor: Objection!</s>
  <s id="21.2">The Church had been a beloved and popular institution that brought comfort and charity to the masses.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="22">Thanks to Henry, church property was seized; hospitals closed, and precious monastic libraries lost forever, all to enrich the Crown.</s>
 <s id="23">Defense: Some of the funds were used to build new cathedrals and open secular schools.</s>
 <s id="24">And it was necessary for England to bring its affairs under its own control rather than Rome’s.</s>
 <s id="25">Prosecutor: You mean under Henry’s control.</s>
 <p id="p26">
  <s id="26.1">Defense: Not true.</s>
  <s id="26.2">All of the king’s major reforms went through Parliament.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="27">No other country of the time allowed its people such a say in government.</s>
 <s id="28">Prosecutor: He used Parliament as a rubber stamp for his own personal will.</s>
 <s id="29">Meanwhile he ruled like a tyrant, executing those he suspected of disloyalty.</s>
 <s id="30">Among his victims were the great statesman and philosopher Thomas More – once his close friend and advisor – and Anne Boleyn, the new queen Henry had torn the country apart to marry.</s>
 <s id="31">Judge: He executed his own wife?</s>
 <s id="32">Defense: That…wasn’t King Henry’s initiative.</s>
 <s id="33">She was accused of treason in a power struggle with the King’s minister, Thomas Cromwell.</s>
 <s id="34">Prosecutor: The trial was a sham and she wouldn’t have been convicted without Henry’s approval.</s>
 <s id="35">Besides, he wasn’t too upset by the outcome - he married Jane Seymour just 11 days later!</s>
 <s id="36">Defense: A marriage that, I note, succeeded in producing a male heir and guaranteeing a stable succession… though the new queen tragically died in childbirth.</s>
 <s id="37">Prosecutor: This tragedy didn’t deter him from an ill conceived fourth marriage to Anne of Cleves, which Henry then annulled on a whim and used as an excuse to execute Cromwell.</s>
 <s id="38">As if that weren’t enough, he then married Catherine Howard – a cousin of Anne Boleyn – before having her executed too.</s>
 <s id="39">Defense: She was engaged in adultery to which she confessed!</s>
 <s id="40">Regardless, Henry’s final marriage to Catherine Parr was actually very successful.</s>
 <p id="p41">
  <s id="41.1">Prosecutor: His sixth!</s>
  <s id="41.2">It only goes to show he was an intemperate king who allowed faction and intrigue to rule his court, concerned only with his own pleasure and grandiosity.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="42">Defense: That grandiosity was part of the king’s role as a model for his people.</s>
 <s id="43">He was a learned scholar and musician who generously patronized the arts, as well as being an imposing warrior and sportsman.</s>
 <s id="44">And the lavish tournaments he hosted enhanced England’s reputation on the world stage.</s>
 <s id="45">Prosecutor: And yet both his foreign and domestic policies were a disaster.</s>
 <s id="46">His campaigns in France and his brutal invasion of Scotland drained the treasury, and his attempt to pay for it by debasing the coinage led to constant inflation.</s>
 <s id="47">The lords and landowners responded by removing access to common pastures and turning the peasant population into beggars.</s>
 <s id="48">Defense: Beggars who would soon become yeomen farmers.</s>
 <s id="49">The enclosures made farming more efficient, and created a labor surplus that laid the foundation for the Industrial Revolution.</s>
 <s id="50">England would never have become the great power that it did without them …and without Henry.</s>
 <s id="51">Judge: Well, I think no matter what, we can all agree he looks great in that portrait.</s>
 <s id="52">A devout believer who broke with the Church.</s>
 <s id="53">A man of learning who executed scholars.</s>
 <s id="54">A king who brought stability to the throne, but used it to promote his own glory, Henry VIII embodied all the contradictions of monarchy on the verge of the modern era.</s>
 <s id="55">But separating the ruler from the myth is all part of putting history on trial.</s>
</text>
