<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">How many times have you used the word "awesome" today?</s>
 <p id="p2">
  <s id="2.1">Once?</s>
  <s id="2.2">Twice?</s>
  <s id="2.3">Seventeen times?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="3">Do you remember what you were describing when you used the word?</s>
 <s id="4">No, I didn't think so, because it's come down to this, people: You're using the word incorrectly, and tonight I hope to show you how to put the "awe" back in "awesome."</s>
 <s id="5">Recently, I was dining at an outdoor cafe, and the server came up to our table, and asked us if we had dined there before, and I said, "Yes, yes, we have."</s>
 <s id="6">And she said, "Awesome."</s>
 <s id="7">And I thought, "Really?</s>
 <s id="8">Awesome or just merely good that we decided to visit your restaurant again?"</s>
 <s id="9">The other day, one of my coworkers asked me if I could save that file as a PDF, and I said, "Well, of course," and he said, "Awesome."</s>
 <s id="10">Seriously, can saving anything as a PDF be awesome?</s>
 <s id="11">Sadly, the frequent overuse of the word "awesome" has now replaced words like "great" and "thank you."</s>
 <s id="12">So Webster's dictionary defines the word "awesome" as fear mingled with admiration or reverence, a feeling produced by something majestic.</s>
 <s id="13">Now, with that in mind, was your Quiznos sandwich awesome?</s>
 <p id="p14">
  <s id="14.1">How about that parking space?</s>
  <s id="14.2">Was that awesome?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p15">
  <s id="15.1">Or that game the other day?</s>
  <s id="15.2">Was that awesome?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="16">The answer is no, no and no.</s>
 <s id="17">A sandwich can be delicious, that parking space can be nearby, and that game can be a blowout, but not everything can be awesome.</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) So when you use the word "awesome" to describe the most mundane of things, you're taking away the very power of the word.</s>
 <s id="19">This author says, "Snowy days or finding money in your pants is awesome."</s>
 <p id="p20">
  <s id="20.1">(Laughter) Um, no, it is not, and we need to raise the bar for this poor schmuck.</s>
  <s id="20.2">(Laughter) So in other words, if you have everything, you value nothing.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="21">It's a lot like drinking from a firehose like this jackass right here.</s>
 <s id="22">There's no dynamic, there's no highs or lows, if everything is awesome.</s>
 <s id="23">Ladies and gentlemen, here are 10 things that are truly awesome.</s>
 <s id="24">Imagine, if you will, having to schlep everything on your back.</s>
 <s id="25">Wouldn't this be easier for me if I could roll this home?</s>
 <s id="26">Yes, so I think I'll invent the wheel.</s>
 <s id="27">The wheel, ladies and gentlemen.</s>
 <p id="p28">
  <s id="28.1">Is the wheel awesome?</s>
  <s id="28.2">Say it with me.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="29">Yes, the wheel is awesome!</s>
 <s id="30">The Great Pyramids were the tallest man-made structure in the world for 4,000 years.</s>
 <s id="31">Pharaoh had his slaves move millions of blocks just to this site to erect a big freaking headstone.</s>
 <s id="32">Were the Great Pyramids awesome?</s>
 <s id="33">Yes, the pyramids were awesome.</s>
 <p id="p34">
  <s id="34.1">The Grand Canyon.</s>
  <s id="34.2">Come on.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="35">It's almost 80 million years old.</s>
 <s id="36">Is the Grand Canyon awesome?</s>
 <s id="37">Yes, the Grand Canyon is.</s>
 <s id="38">Louis Daguerre invented photography in 1829, and earlier today, when you whipped out your smartphone and you took a shot of your awesome sandwich, and you know who you are — (Laughter) — wasn't that easier than exposing the image to copper plates coated with iodized silver?</s>
 <p id="p39">
  <s id="39.1">I mean, come on.</s>
  <s id="39.2">Is photography awesome?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="40">Yes, photography is awesome.</s>
 <s id="41">D-Day, June 6, 1944, the Allied invasion of Normandy, the largest amphibious invasion in world history.</s>
 <p id="p42">
  <s id="42.1">Was D-Day awesome?</s>
  <s id="42.2">Yes, it was awesome.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p43">
  <s id="43.1">Did you eat food today?</s>
  <s id="43.2">Did you eat?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="44">Then you can thank the honeybee, that's the one, because if crops aren't pollinated, we can't grow food, and then we're all going to die.</s>
 <s id="45">It's just like that.</s>
 <s id="46">But it's not like a flower can just get up and have sex with another flower, although that would be awesome.</s>
 <p id="p47">
  <s id="47.1">(Laughter) Bees are awesome.</s>
  <s id="47.2">Are you kidding me?</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p48">
  <s id="48.1">Landing on the moon!</s>
  <s id="48.2">Come on!</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p49">
  <s id="49.1">Apollo 11.</s>
  <s id="49.2">Are you kidding me?</s>
 </p>
 <s id="50">Sixty-six years after the Wright Brothers took off from Kitty Hawk, North Carolina, Neil Armstrong was 240,000 miles away.</s>
 <s id="51">That's like from here to the moon.</s>
 <s id="52">(Laughter) That's one small step for a man, one giant leap for awesome!</s>
 <s id="53">You're damn right, it was.</s>
 <s id="54">Woodstock, 1969: Rolling Stone Magazine said this changed the history of rock and roll.</s>
 <s id="55">Tickets were only 24 dollars back then.</s>
 <s id="56">You can't even buy a freaking t-shirt for that now.</s>
 <s id="57">Jimi Hendrix's version of "The Star-Spangled Banner" was the most iconic.</s>
 <p id="p58">
  <s id="58.1">Was Woodstock awesome?</s>
  <s id="58.2">Yes, it was awesome.</s>
 </p>
 <p id="p59">
  <s id="59.1">Sharks!</s>
  <s id="59.2">They're at the top of the food chain.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="60">Sharks have multiple rows of teeth that grow in their jaw and they move forward like a conveyor belt.</s>
 <s id="61">Some sharks can lose 30,000 teeth in their lifetime.</s>
 <s id="62">Does awesome inspire fear?</s>
 <s id="63">Oh, hell yeah, sharks are awesome!</s>
 <s id="64">The Internet was born in 1982 and it instantly took over global communication, and later tonight, when all these PowerPoints are uplifted to the Internet so that a guy in Siberia can get drunk and watch this crap, the Internet is awesome.</s>
 <s id="65">And finally, finally some of you can't wait to come up and tell me how awesome my PowerPoint was.</s>
 <s id="66">I will save you the time.</s>
 <p id="p67">
  <s id="67.1">It was not awesome, but it was true, and I hope it was entertaining, and out of all the audiences I've ever had, y'all are the most recent.</s>
  <s id="67.2">Thank you and good night.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="68">(Applause)</s>
</text>
