<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">You spend weeks studying for an important test.</s>
 <s id="2">On the big day, you wait nervously as your teacher hands it out.</s>
 <p id="p3">
  <s id="3.1">You’re working your way through, when you’re asked to define ‘ataraxia.’</s>
  <s id="3.2">You know you’ve seen it before, but your mind goes blank.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="4">What just happened?</s>
 <s id="5">The answer lies in the complex relationship between stress and memory.</s>
 <s id="6">There are many types and degrees of stress and different kinds of memory, but we’re going to focus on how short-term stress impacts your memory for facts.</s>
 <s id="7">To start, it helps to understand how this kind of memory works.</s>
 <s id="8">Facts you read, hear, or study become memories through a process with three main steps.</s>
 <s id="9">First comes acquisition: the moment you encounter a new piece of information.</s>
 <s id="10">Each sensory experience activates a unique set of brain areas.</s>
 <s id="11">In order to become lasting memories, these sensory experiences have to be consolidated by the hippocampus, influenced by the amygdala, which emphasizes experiences associated with strong emotions.</s>
 <s id="12">The hippocampus then encodes memories, probably by strengthening the synaptic connections stimulated during the original sensory experience.</s>
 <s id="13">Once a memory has been encoded, it can be remembered, or retrieved, later.</s>
 <s id="14">Memories are stored all over the brain, and it’s likely the prefrontal cortex that signals for their retrieval.</s>
 <s id="15">So how does stress affect each of these stages?</s>
 <s id="16">In the first two stages, moderate stress can actually help experiences enter your memory.</s>
 <s id="17">Your brain responds to stressful stimuli by releasing hormones known as corticosteroids, which activate a process of threat-detection and threat-response in the amygdala.</s>
 <s id="18">The amygdala prompts your hippocampus to consolidate the stress-inducing experience into a memory.</s>
 <s id="19">Meanwhile, the flood of corticosteroids from stress stimulates your hippocampus, also prompting memory consolidation.</s>
 <s id="20">But even though some stress can be helpful, extreme and chronic stress can have the opposite effect.</s>
 <s id="21">Researchers have tested this by injecting rats directly with stress hormones.</s>
 <s id="22">As they gradually increased the dose of corticosteroids, the rats’ performance on memory tests increased at first, but dropped off at higher doses.</s>
 <s id="23">In humans, we see a similar positive effect with moderate stress.</s>
 <s id="24">But that only appears when the stress is related to the memory task— so while time pressure might help you memorize a list, having a friend scare you will not.</s>
 <s id="25">And the weeks, months, or even years of sustained corticosteroids that result from chronic stress can damage the hippocampus and decrease your ability to form new memories.</s>
 <s id="26">It would be nice if some stress also helped us remember facts, but unfortunately, the opposite is true.</s>
 <s id="27">The act of remembering relies on the prefrontal cortex, which governs thought, attention, and reasoning.</s>
 <s id="28">When corticosteroids stimulate the amygdala, the amygdala inhibits, or lessens the activity of, the prefrontal cortex.</s>
 <s id="29">The reason for this inhibition is so the fight/flight/freeze response can overrule slower, more reasoned thought in a dangerous situation.</s>
 <s id="30">But that can also have the unfortunate effect of making your mind go blank during a test.</s>
 <s id="31">And then the act of trying to remember can itself be a stressor, leading to a vicious cycle of more corticosteroid release and an even smaller chance of remembering.</s>
 <s id="32">So what can you do to turn stress to your advantage and stay calm and collected when it matters the most?</s>
 <s id="33">First, if you know a stressful situation like a test is coming, try preparing in conditions similar to the stressful environment.</s>
 <s id="34">Novelty can be a stressor.</s>
 <s id="35">Completing practice questions under time pressure, or seated at a desk rather than on a couch, can make your stress response to these circumstances less sensitive during the test itself.</s>
 <s id="36">Exercise is another useful tool.</s>
 <s id="37">Increasing your heart and breathing rate is linked to chemical changes in your brain that help reduce anxiety and increase your sense of well-being.</s>
 <s id="38">Regular exercise is also widely thought to improve sleeping patterns, which comes in handy the night before a test.</s>
 <s id="39">And on the actual test day, try taking deep breaths to counteract your body’s flight/fight/freeze response.</s>
 <s id="40">Deep breathing exercises have shown measurable reduction in test anxiety in groups ranging from third graders to nursing students.</s>
 <s id="41">So the next time you find your mind going blank at a critical moment, take a few deep breaths until you remember ataraxia: a state of calmness, free from anxiety.</s>
</text>
