<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I consider it my life's mission to convey the urgency of climate change through my work.</s>
 <s id="2">I've traveled north to the Arctic to the capture the unfolding story of polar melt, and south to the Equator to document the subsequent rising seas.</s>
 <s id="3">Most recently, I visited the icy coast of Greenland and the low-lying islands of the Maldives, connecting two seemingly disparate but equally endangered parts of our planet.</s>
 <s id="4">My drawings explore moments of transition, turbulence and tranquility in the landscape, allowing viewers to emotionally connect with a place you might never have the chance to visit.</s>
 <s id="5">I choose to convey the beauty as opposed to the devastation.</s>
 <s id="6">If you can experience the sublimity of these landscapes, perhaps you'll be inspired to protect and preserve them.</s>
 <s id="7">Behavioral psychology tells us that we take action and make decisions based on our emotions above all else.</s>
 <s id="8">And studies have shown that art impacts our emotions more effectively than a scary news report.</s>
 <s id="9">Experts predict ice-free Arctic summers as early as 2020.</s>
 <s id="10">And sea levels are likely to rise between two and ten feet by century's end.</s>
 <s id="11">I have dedicated my career to illuminating these projections with an accessible medium, one that moves us in a way that statistics may not.</s>
 <s id="12">My process begins with traveling to the places at the forefront of climate change.</s>
 <s id="13">On-site, I take thousands of photographs.</s>
 <s id="14">Back in the studio, I work from both my memory of the experience and the photographs to create very large-scale compositions, sometimes over 10 feet wide.</s>
 <s id="15">I draw with soft pastel, which is dry like charcoal, but colors.</s>
 <s id="16">I consider my work drawings but others call them painting.</s>
 <s id="17">I cringe, though, when I'm referred to as a "finger painter."</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) But I don't use any tools and I have always used my fingers and palms to manipulate the pigment on the paper.</s>
 <s id="19">Drawing is a form of meditation for me.</s>
 <s id="20">It quiets my mind.</s>
 <s id="21">I don't perceive what I'm drawing as ice or water.</s>
 <s id="22">Instead, the image is stripped down to its most basic form of color and shape.</s>
 <s id="23">Once the piece is complete, I can finally experience the composition as a whole, as an iceberg floating through glassy water, or a wave cresting with foam.</s>
 <s id="24">On average, a piece this size takes me about, as you can see, 10 seconds.</s>
 <s id="25">(Laughter) (Applause) Really, more like 200 hours, 250 hours for something that size.</s>
 <s id="26">But I've been drawing ever since I could hold a crayon, really.</s>
 <s id="27">My mom was an artist, and growing up, we always had art supplies all over the house.</s>
 <s id="28">My mother's love of photography propelled her to the most remote regions of the earth, and my family and I were fortunate enough to join and support her on these adventures.</s>
 <s id="29">We rode camels in Northern Africa and mushed on dog sleds near the North Pole.</s>
 <s id="30">In August of 2012, I led my first expedition, taking a group of artists and scholars up the northwest coast of Greenland.</s>
 <s id="31">My mother was originally supposed to lead this trip.</s>
 <s id="32">She and I were in the early stages of planning, as we had intended to go together, when she fell victim to a brain tumor.</s>
 <s id="33">The cancer quickly took over her body and mind, and she passed away six months later.</s>
 <s id="34">During the months of her illness, though, her dedication to the expedition never wavered, and I made a promise to carry out her final journey.</s>
 <s id="35">My mother's passion for the Arctic echoed through my experience in Greenland, and I felt the power and the fragility of the landscape.</s>
 <s id="36">The sheer size of the icebergs is humbling.</s>
 <s id="37">The ice fields are alive with movement and sound in a way that I never expected.</s>
 <s id="38">I expanded the scale of my compositions to give you that same sense of awe that I experienced.</s>
 <s id="39">Yet, while the grandeur of the ice is evident, so, too, is its vulnerability.</s>
 <s id="40">From our boat, I could see the ice sweating under the unseasonably warm sun.</s>
 <s id="41">We had a chance to visit many of the Inuit communities in Greenland that now face huge challenges.</s>
 <s id="42">The locals spoke to me of vast areas of sea ice that are no longer freezing over as they once did.</s>
 <s id="43">And without ice, their hunting and harvesting grounds are severely diminished, threatening their way of life and survival.</s>
 <s id="44">The melting glaciers in Greenland are one of the largest contributing factors to rising sea levels, which have already begun to drown some of our world's lowest-lying islands.</s>
 <s id="45">One year after my trip to Greenland, I visited the Maldives, the lowest and flattest country in the entire world.</s>
 <s id="46">While I was there, I collected images and inspiration for a new body of work: drawings of waves lapping on the coast of a nation that could be entirely underwater within this century.</s>
 <s id="47">Devastating events happen every day on scales both global and personal.</s>
 <s id="48">When I was in Greenland, I scattered my mother's ashes amidst the melting ice.</s>
 <s id="49">Now she remains a part of the landscape she loved so much, even as it, too, passes and takes on new form.</s>
 <s id="50">Among the many gifts my mother gave me was the ability to focus on the positive, rather than the negative.</s>
 <s id="51">My drawings celebrate the beauty of what we all stand to lose.</s>
 <s id="52">I hope they can serve as records of sublime landscapes in flux, documenting the transition and inspiring our global community to take action for the future.</s>
 <s id="53">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="54">(Applause)</s>
</text>
