<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">This image of the Vitruvian Man, taken from Leonardo's sketches, has become one of the most recognizable symbols of the Renaissance.</s>
 <s id="2">But why?</s>
 <s id="3">It's a simple pen and ink drawing, right?</s>
 <s id="4">Wrong!</s>
 <s id="5">Let's start to answer this question with a math problem.</s>
 <s id="6">I know how to calculate the area of a circle.</s>
 <s id="7">I take the value for pi and multiply it by the radius squared.</s>
 <s id="8">I also know how to take the area of a square.</s>
 <s id="9">I multiply the base by itself.</s>
 <s id="10">But how can I take the area of a circle and create a square with an equal area?</s>
 <s id="11">This is a problem often called "squaring a circle" that was first proposed in the ancient world.</s>
 <s id="12">And like many ideas of the ancient world, it was given new life during the Renaissance.</s>
 <s id="13">As it turns out, this problem is impossible to solve because of the nature of pi, but that's another story.</s>
 <s id="14">Leonardo's sketch, which is influenced by the writings of the Roman architect, Vitruvius, places a man firmly at the center of a circle and a square.</s>
 <s id="15">Vitruvius claimed the navel is the center of the human body and that if one takes a compass and places the fixed point on the navel, a circle can be drawn perfectly around the body.</s>
 <s id="16">Additionally, Vitruvius recognized that arm span and height have a nearly perfect correspondence in the human body, thus placing the body perfectly inside a square as well.</s>
 <s id="17">Leonardo used the ideas of Vitruvius to solve the problem of squaring a circle metaphorically using mankind as the area for both shapes.</s>
 <s id="18">Leonardo wasn't just thinking about Vitruvius, though.</s>
 <s id="19">There was an intellectual movement in Italy at the time called Neoplatonism.</s>
 <s id="20">This movement took an old concept from the 4th century developed by Plato and Aristotle, called "The Great Chain of Being."</s>
 <s id="21">This belief holds that the universe has a hierarchy resembling a chain, and that chain starts at the top with God, then travels down through the angels, planets, stars, and all lifeforms before ending with demons and devils.</s>
 <s id="22">Early in this philosophic movement, it was thought that mankind's place in this chain was exactly in the center.</s>
 <s id="23">Because humans have a mortal body accompanied by an immortal soul, we divide the universe nicely in half.</s>
 <s id="24">Around the time Leonardo sketched the Vitruvian Man, however, a Neoplatonist named Pico Della Mirandola had a different idea.</s>
 <s id="25">He pried mankind off the chain and claimed that humans have a unique ability to take any position they want.</s>
 <s id="26">Pico claimed that God desired a being capable of comprehending the beautiful and complicated universe he had created.</s>
 <s id="27">This led to the creation of mankind, which he placed at the center of the universe with the ability to take whatever form he pleases.</s>
 <s id="28">Mankind, according to Pico, could crawl down the chain and behave like an animal or crawl up the chain and behave like a god, it's our choice.</s>
 <s id="29">Looking back at the sketch, we can see that by changing the position of the man, he can fill the irreconcilable areas of a circle and a square.</s>
 <s id="30">If geometry is the language the universe is written in, then this sketch seems to say we can exist within all its elements.</s>
 <s id="31">Mankind can fill whatever shape he pleases geometrically and philosophically as well.</s>
 <s id="32">In this one sketch, Leonardo was able to combine the mathematics, religion, philosophy, architecture, and artistic skill of his age.</s>
 <s id="33">No wonder it has become such an icon for the entire time period.</s>
</text>
