<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">If you want a glimpse of Marie Curie's manuscripts, you'll have to sign a waiver and put on protective gear to shield yourself from radiation contamination.</s>
 <s id="2">Madame Curie's remains, too, were interred in a lead-lined coffin, keeping the radiation that was the heart of her research, and likely the cause of her death, well contained.</s>
 <s id="3">Growing up in Warsaw in Russian-occupied Poland, the young Marie, originally named Maria Sklodowska, was a brilliant student, but she faced some challenging barriers.</s>
 <s id="4">As a woman, she was barred from pursuing higher education, so in an act of defiance, Marie enrolled in the Floating University, a secret institution that provided clandestine education to Polish youth.</s>
 <s id="5">By saving money and working as a governess and tutor, she eventually was able to move to Paris to study at the reputed Sorbonne.</s>
 <s id="6">There, Marie earned both a physics and mathematics degree surviving largely on bread and tea, and sometimes fainting from near starvation.</s>
 <s id="7">In Paris, Marie met the physicist Pierre Curie, who shared his lab and his heart with her.</s>
 <s id="8">But she longed to be back in Poland.</s>
 <s id="9">Upon her return to Warsaw, though, she found that securing an academic position as a woman remained a challenge.</s>
 <s id="10">All was not lost.</s>
 <s id="11">Back in Paris, the lovelorn Pierre was waiting, and the pair quickly married and became a formidable scientific team.</s>
 <s id="12">Another physicist's work sparked Marie Curie's interest.</s>
 <s id="13">In 1896, Henri Becquerel discovered that uranium spontaneously emitted a mysterious X-ray-like radiation that could interact with photographic film.</s>
 <s id="14">Curie soon found that the element thorium emitted similar radiation.</s>
 <s id="15">Most importantly, the strength of the radiation depended solely on the element's quantity, and was not affected by physical or chemical changes.</s>
 <s id="16">This led her to conclude that radiation was coming from something fundamental within the atoms of each element.</s>
 <s id="17">The idea was radical and helped to disprove the long-standing model of atoms as indivisible objects.</s>
 <s id="18">Next, by focusing on a super radioactive ore called pitchblende, the Curies realized that uranium alone couldn't be creating all the radiation.</s>
 <s id="19">So, were there other radioactive elements that might be responsible?</s>
 <s id="20">In 1898, they reported two new elements, polonium, named for Marie's native Poland, and radium, the Latin word for ray.</s>
 <s id="21">They also coined the term radioactivity along the way.</s>
 <s id="22">By 1902, the Curies had extracted a tenth of a gram of pure radium chloride salt from several tons of pitchblende, an incredible feat at the time.</s>
 <s id="23">Later that year, Pierre Curie and Henri Becquerel were nominated for the Nobel Prize in physics, but Marie was overlooked.</s>
 <s id="24">Pierre took a stand in support of his wife's well-earned recognition.</s>
 <s id="25">And so both of the Curies and Becquerel shared the 1903 Nobel Prize, making Marie Curie the first female Nobel Laureate.</s>
 <s id="26">Well funded and well respected, the Curies were on a roll.</s>
 <s id="27">But tragedy struck in 1906 when Pierre was crushed by a horse-drawn cart as he crossed a busy intersection.</s>
 <s id="28">Marie, devastated, immersed herself in her research and took over Pierre's teaching position at the Sorbonne, becoming the school's first female professor.</s>
 <s id="29">Her solo work was fruitful.</s>
 <s id="30">In 1911, she won yet another Nobel, this time in chemistry for her earlier discovery of radium and polonium, and her extraction and analysis of pure radium and its compounds.</s>
 <s id="31">This made her the first, and to this date, only person to win Nobel Prizes in two different sciences.</s>
 <s id="32">Professor Curie put her discoveries to work, changing the landscape of medical research and treatments.</s>
 <s id="33">She opened mobile radiology units during World War I, and investigated radiation's effects on tumors.</s>
 <s id="34">However, these benefits to humanity may have come at a high personal cost.</s>
 <s id="35">Curie died in 1934 of a bone marrow disease, which many today think was caused by her radiation exposure.</s>
 <s id="36">Marie Curie's revolutionary research laid the groundwork for our understanding of physics and chemistry, blazing trails in oncology, technology, medicine, and nuclear physics, to name a few.</s>
 <s id="37">For good or ill, her discoveries in radiation launched a new era, unearthing some of science's greatest secrets.</s>
</text>
