<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I've got a confession.</s>
 <s id="2">I love looking through people's garbage.</s>
 <s id="3">Now, it's not some creepy thing.</s>
 <s id="4">I'm usually just looking for old electronics, stuff I can take to my workshop and hack.</s>
 <s id="5">I do have a fetish for CD-ROM drives.</s>
 <s id="6">Each one's got three different motors, so now you can build things that move.</s>
 <s id="7">There's switches so you can turn things on and off.</s>
 <s id="8">There's even a freaking laser, so you can make a cool robot into an awesome robot.</s>
 <s id="9">Now, I've built a lot of stuff out of garbage, and some of these things have even been kind of useful.</s>
 <s id="10">But here's the thing, for me, garbage is just a chance to play, to be creative and build things to amuse myself.</s>
 <s id="11">This is what I love doing, so I just made it part of my day job.</s>
 <s id="12">I lead a university-based biological research lab, where we value curiosity and exploration above all else.</s>
 <s id="13">We aren't focused on any particular problem, and we're not trying to solve any particular disease.</s>
 <s id="14">This is just a place where people can come and ask fascinating questions and find answers.</s>
 <s id="15">And I realized a long time ago that if I challenge people to build the equipment they need out of the garbage I find, it's a great way to foster creativity.</s>
 <s id="16">And what happened was that artists and scientists from around the world started coming to my lab.</s>
 <s id="17">And it's not just because we value unconventional ideas, it's because we test and validate them with scientific rigor.</s>
 <s id="18">So one day I was hacking something, I was taking it apart, and I had this sudden idea: Could I treat biology like hardware?</s>
 <s id="19">Could I dismantle a biological system, mix and match the parts and then put it back together in some new and creative way?</s>
 <s id="20">My lab started working on this, and I want to show you the result.</s>
 <s id="21">Can any of you guys tell me what fruit this is?</s>
 <s id="22">Audience: Apple!</s>
 <s id="23">Andrew Pelling: That's right -- it's an apple.</s>
 <s id="24">Now, I actually want you to notice as well that this is a lot redder than most apples.</s>
 <s id="25">And that's because we grew human cells into it.</s>
 <s id="26">We took a totally innocent Macintosh apple, removed all the apple cells and DNA and then implanted human cells.</s>
 <s id="27">And what we're left with after removing all the apple cells is this cellulose scaffold.</s>
 <s id="28">This is the stuff that gives plants their shape and texture.</s>
 <s id="29">And these little holes that you can see, this is where all the apple cells used to be.</s>
 <s id="30">So then we come along, we implant some mammalian cells that you can see in blue.</s>
 <s id="31">What happens is, these guys start multiplying and they fill up this entire scaffold.</s>
 <s id="32">As weird as this is, it's actually really reminiscent of how our own tissues are organized.</s>
 <s id="33">And we found in our pre-clinical work that you can implant these scaffolds into the body, and the body will send in cells and a blood supply and actually keep these things alive.</s>
 <s id="34">This is the point when people started asking me, "Andrew, can you make body parts out of apples?"</s>
 <s id="35">And I'm like, "You've come to the right place."</s>
 <s id="36">(Laughter) I actually brought this up with my wife.</s>
 <s id="37">She's a musical instrument maker, and she does a lot of wood carving for a living.</s>
 <s id="38">So I asked her, "Could you, like, literally carve some ears out of an apple for us?"</s>
 <s id="39">And she did.</s>
 <s id="40">So I took her ears to the lab.</s>
 <s id="41">We then started preparing them.</s>
 <s id="42">Yeah, I know.</s>
 <s id="43">(Laughter) It's a good lab, man.</s>
 <s id="44">(Laughter) And then we grew cells on them.</s>
 <s id="45">And this is the result.</s>
 <s id="46">Listen, my lab is not in the ear-manufacturing business.</s>
 <s id="47">People have actually been working on this for decades.</s>
 <s id="48">Here's the issue: commercial scaffolds can be really expensive and problematic, because they're sourced from proprietary products, animals or cadavers.</s>
 <s id="49">We used an apple and it cost pennies.</s>
 <s id="50">What's also really cool here is it's not that hard to make these things.</s>
 <s id="51">The equipment you need can be built from garbage, and the key processing step only requires soap and water.</s>
 <s id="52">So what we did was put all the instructions online as open source.</s>
 <s id="53">And then we founded a mission-driven company, and we're developing kits to make it easier for anyone with a sink and a soldering iron to make these things at home.</s>
 <s id="54">What I'm really curious about is if one day, it will be possible to repair, rebuild and augment our own bodies with stuff we make in the kitchen.</s>
 <s id="55">Speaking of kitchens, here's some asparagus.</s>
 <s id="56">They're tasty, and they make your pee smell funny.</s>
 <s id="57">(Laughter) Now, I was in my kitchen, and I was noticing that when you look down the stalks of these asparagus, what you can see are all these tiny little vessels.</s>
 <s id="58">And when we image them in the lab, you can see how the cellulose forms these structures.</s>
 <s id="59">This image reminds me of two things: our blood vessels and the structure and organization of our nerves and spinal cord.</s>
 <s id="60">So here's the question: Can we grow axons and neurons down these channels?</s>
 <s id="61">Because if we can, then maybe we can use asparagus to form new connections between the ends of damaged and severed nerves.</s>
 <s id="62">Or maybe even a spinal cord.</s>
 <s id="63">Don't get me wrong -- this is exceptionally challenging and really hard work to do, and we are not the only ones working on this.</s>
 <s id="64">But we are the only ones using asparagus.</s>
 <s id="65">(Laughter) Right now, we've got really promising pilot data.</s>
 <s id="66">And we're working with tissue engineers and neurosurgeons to find out what's actually possible.</s>
 <s id="67">So listen, all of the work I've shown you, the stuff that I've built that's all around me on this stage and the other projects my lab is involved in are all a direct result of me playing with your garbage.</s>
 <s id="68">Play -- play is a key part of my scientific practice.</s>
 <s id="69">It's how I train my mind to be unconventional and to be creative and to decide to make human apple ears.</s>
 <s id="70">So, the next time any of you are looking at some old, broken-down, malfunctioning, piece-of-crap technology, I want you to think of me.</s>
 <s id="71">Because I want it.</s>
 <s id="72">(Laughter) Seriously, please find any way to get in touch with me, and let's see what we can build.</s>
 <s id="73">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="74">(Applause)</s>
</text>
