<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">In 1881, doctor William Halsted rushed to help his sister Minnie, who was hemorrhaging after childbirth.</s>
 <s id="2">He quickly inserted a needle into his arm, withdrew his own blood, and transferred it to her.</s>
 <s id="3">After a few uncertain minutes, she began to recover.</s>
 <s id="4">Halsted didn’t know how lucky they’d gotten.</s>
 <s id="5">His transfusion only worked because he and his sister happened to have the same blood type— something that isn’t guaranteed, even among close relatives.</s>
 <s id="6">Blood types hadn’t been discovered by Halsted’s time, though people had been experimenting with transfusions for centuries— mostly unsuccessfully.</s>
 <s id="7">In 1667, a French physician named Jean-Baptiste Denis became the first to try the technique on a human.</s>
 <s id="8">Denis transfused sheep’s blood into Antoine Mauroy, a man likely suffering from psychosis, in the hopes that it would reduce his symptoms.</s>
 <s id="9">Afterward, Mauroy was in good spirits.</s>
 <s id="10">But after a second transfusion, he developed a fever, severe pain in his lower back, intense burning in his arm, and he urinated a thick, black liquid.</s>
 <s id="11">Though nobody knew it at the time, these were the signs of a dangerous immune response unfolding inside his body.</s>
 <s id="12">This immune response starts  with the production of proteins called antibodies, which distinguish the body’s own cells from intruders.</s>
 <s id="13">They do so by recognizing the foreign proteins, or antigens, embedded in an intruder’s cell membrane.</s>
 <s id="14">Antibodies latch onto the antigens, signaling other immune cells to attack and destroy the foreign cells.</s>
 <s id="15">The destroyed cells are flushed from the body in urine.</s>
 <s id="16">In extreme cases, the massive break down of cells causes clots in the bloodstream that disrupt the flow of blood to vital organs, overload the kidneys, and cause organ failure.</s>
 <s id="17">Fortunately, Denis’s patient survived the transfusion.</s>
 <s id="18">But, after other cross-species transfusions proved fatal, the procedure was outlawed across Europe, falling out of favor for several centuries.</s>
 <s id="19">It wasn’t until 1901 that Austrian physician Karl Landsteiner discovered blood types, the crucial step in the success of human to human blood transfusions.</s>
 <s id="20">He noticed that when different types were mixed together, they formed clots.</s>
 <s id="21">This happens when antibodies latch on to cells with foreign antigens, causing blood cells to clump together.</s>
 <s id="22">But if the donor cells are the same blood type as the recipient’s cells, the donor cells won’t be flagged for destruction, and won’t form clumps.</s>
 <s id="23">By 1907, doctors were mixing together small amounts of blood before transfusing it.</s>
 <s id="24">If there were no clumps, the types were a match.</s>
 <s id="25">This enabled them to save thousands of lives, laying the foundation for modern transfusions.</s>
 <s id="26">Up to this point, all transfusions had occurred in real time, directly between two individuals.</s>
 <s id="27">That’s because blood begins to clot almost immediately after coming into contact with air— a defense mechanism to prevent excessive blood loss after injury.</s>
 <s id="28">In 1914, researchers discovered that the chemical sodium citrate stopped blood coagulating by removing the calcium necessary for clot formation.</s>
 <s id="29">Citrated blood could be stored for later use— the first step in making large scale blood transfusions possible.</s>
 <s id="30">In 1916, a pair of American scientists found an even more effective anticoagulant called heparin, which works by deactivating enzymes that enable clotting.</s>
 <s id="31">We still use heparin today.</s>
 <s id="32">At the same time, American and British researchers developed portable machines that could transport donor blood onto the battlefields of World War I.</s>
 <s id="33">Combined with the newly-discovered heparin, medics safely stored and preserved liters of blood, wheeling it directly onto the battlefield to transfuse wounded soldiers.</s>
 <s id="34">After the war, this crude portable box would become the inspiration for the modern-day blood bank, a fixture of hospitals around the world.</s>
</text>
