<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">What do Harry Potter, Katniss Everdeen, and Frodo all have in common with the heroes of ancient myths?</s>
 <s id="2">(Roar) What if I told you they are all variants of the same hero?</s>
 <s id="3">Do you believe that?</s>
 <s id="4">Joseph Campbell did.</s>
 <s id="5">He studied myths from all over the world and published a book called "The Hero with a Thousand Faces," retelling dozens of stories and explaining how each represents the mono-myth, or Hero's Journey.</s>
 <s id="6">So, what is the "hero's journey"?</s>
 <s id="7">Think of it as a cycle.</s>
 <s id="8">The journey begins and ends in a hero's ordinary world, but the quest passes through an unfamiliar, special world.</s>
 <s id="9">Along the way, there are some key events.</s>
 <s id="10">Think about your favorite book or movie.</s>
 <s id="11">Does it follow this pattern?</s>
 <s id="12">Status quo, that's where we start.</s>
 <s id="13">1:00: Call to Adventure.</s>
 <s id="14">The hero receives a mysterious message.</s>
 <s id="15">An invitation, a challenge?</s>
 <s id="16">2:00: Assistance The hero needs some help, probably from someone older, wiser.</s>
 <s id="17">3:00: Departure The hero crosses the threshold from his normal, safe home, and enters the special world and adventure.</s>
 <s id="18">We're not in Kansas anymore.</s>
 <s id="19">4:00: Trials Being a hero is hard work: our hero solves a riddle, slays a monster, escapes from a trap.</s>
 <s id="20">5:00: Approach It's time to face the biggest ordeal, the hero's worst fear.</s>
 <s id="21">(Roar) 6:00: Crisis This is the hero's darkest hour.</s>
 <s id="22">He faces death and possibly even dies, only to be reborn.</s>
 <s id="23">7:00: Treasure (Roar) As a result, the hero claims some treasure, special recognition, or power.</s>
 <s id="24">8:00: Result This can vary between stories.</s>
 <s id="25">Do the monsters bow down before the hero, or do they chase him as he flees from the special world?</s>
 <s id="26">9:00: Return After all that adventure, the hero returns to his ordinary world.</s>
 <s id="27">10:00: New Life This quest has changed the hero; he has outgrown his old life.</s>
 <s id="28">11:00: Resolution All the tangled plot lines get straightened out.</s>
 <s id="29">12:00: Status Quo, but upgraded to a new level.</s>
 <s id="30">Nothing is quite the same once you are a hero.</s>
 <s id="31">Many popular books and movies follow this ancient formula pretty closely.</s>
 <s id="32">But let's see how well "The Hunger Games" fits the hero's journey template.</s>
 <s id="33">When does Katniss Everdeen hear her call to adventure that gets the story moving?</s>
 <s id="34">When her sister's name is called from the lottery.</s>
 <s id="35">How about assistance?</s>
 <s id="36">Is anyone going to help her on her adventure?</s>
 <s id="37">Haymitch.</s>
 <s id="38">What about departure?</s>
 <s id="39">Does she leave her ordinary world?</s>
 <s id="40">She gets on a train to the capital.</s>
 <s id="41">OK, so you get the idea.</s>
 <s id="42">What do you have in common with Harry Potter, Katniss Everdeen, and Frodo?</s>
 <s id="43">Well, you're human, just like them.</s>
 <s id="44">The Hero's Journey myth exists in all human cultures and keeps getting updated, because we humans reflect on our world through symbolic stories of our own lives.</s>
 <s id="45">You leave your comfort zone, have an experience that transforms you, and then you recover and do it again.</s>
 <s id="46">You don't literally slay dragons or fight Voldemort, but you face problems just as scary.</s>
 <s id="47">Joseph Campbell said, "In the cave you fear to enter lies the treasure you seek."</s>
 <s id="48">What is the symbolic cave you fear to enter?</s>
 <s id="49">Auditions for the school play?</s>
 <s id="50">Baseball tryouts?</s>
 <s id="51">Love?</s>
 <s id="52">Watch for this formula in books, movies, and TV shows you come across.</s>
 <s id="53">You will certainly see it again.</s>
 <s id="54">But also be sensitive to it in your own life.</s>
 <s id="55">Listen for your call to adventure.</s>
 <s id="56">Accept the challenge.</s>
 <s id="57">Conquer your fear and claim the treasure you seek.</s>
 <s id="58">And then, do it all over again.</s>
</text>
