<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">(Whistling) (Whistling ends) (Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="2">(Applause) Thank you very much.</s>
 <s id="3">That was whistling.</s>
 <s id="4">I'm trying to do this in English.</s>
 <s id="5">What is a chubby, curly-haired guy from Holland -- why is he whistling?</s>
 <s id="6">Well actually, I've been whistling since the age of four, about four.</s>
 <s id="7">My dad was always whistling around the house, and I just thought that's part of communication in my family.</s>
 <s id="8">So I whistled along with him.</s>
 <s id="9">And actually, until I was 34, I always annoyed and irritated people with whistling, because, to be honest, my whistling is a kind of deviant behavior.</s>
 <s id="10">I whistled alone, I whistled in the classroom, I whistled on bike, I whistled everywhere.</s>
 <s id="11">And I also whistled at a Christmas Eve party with my family-in-law.</s>
 <s id="12">And they had some, in my opinion, terrible Christmas music.</s>
 <s id="13">And when I hear music that I don't like, I try to make it better.</s>
 <s id="14">(Laughter) So when "Rudolph the Red-Nosed Reindeer" -- you know it?</s>
 <s id="15">(Whistling) But it can also sound like this.</s>
 <s id="16">(Whistling) But during a Christmas party -- at dinner, actually -- it's very annoying.</s>
 <s id="17">So my sister-in-law asked me a few times, "Please stop whistling."</s>
 <s id="18">And I just couldn't.</s>
 <s id="19">And at one point -- and I had some wine, I have to admit that -- at one point I said, "If there was a contest, I would join."</s>
 <s id="20">And two weeks later, I received a text message: "You're going to America."</s>
 <s id="21">(Laughter) So, OK, I'm going to America.</s>
 <s id="22">I would love to, but why?</s>
 <s id="23">So I immediately called her up, of course.</s>
 <s id="24">She googled, and she found this World Whistling Championship in America, of course.</s>
 <s id="25">(Laughter) She didn't expect me to go there.</s>
 <s id="26">And I would have lost my face.</s>
 <s id="27">I don't know if that's correct English.</s>
 <s id="28">But the Dutch people here will understand what I mean.</s>
 <s id="29">(Laughter) I lost my face.</s>
 <s id="30">(Applause) And she thought, "He will never go there."</s>
 <s id="31">But actually, I did.</s>
 <s id="32">So I went to Louisburg, North Carolina, southeast of the United States, and I entered the world of whistling.</s>
 <s id="33">And I also entered the World Championship, and I won there, in 2004.</s>
 <s id="34">(Applause) That was great fun, of course.</s>
 <s id="35">And to defend my title -- like judokas do and sportsmen -- I thought, well let's go back in 2005 -- and I won again.</s>
 <s id="36">(Laughter) Then I couldn't participate for a few years.</s>
 <s id="37">And in 2008, I entered again in Japan, Tokyo, and I won again.</s>
 <s id="38">So what happened now is I'm standing here in Rotterdam, in the beautiful city, on a big stage, and I'm talking about whistling.</s>
 <s id="39">And actually, I earn my money whistling, at the moment.</s>
 <s id="40">So I quit my day job as a nurse.</s>
 <s id="41">(Applause) And I try to live my dream -- well, actually, it was never my dream, but it sounds so good.</s>
 <s id="42">(Laughter) OK, I'm not the only one whistling here.</s>
 <s id="43">You say, "Huh, what do you mean?"</s>
 <s id="44">Well actually, you are going to whistle along.</s>
 <s id="45">And then always the same thing happens: people are watching each other and think, "Oh, my God.</s>
 <p id="p46">
  <s id="46.1">Why?</s>
  <s id="46.2">Can I go away?"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="47">No, you can't.</s>
 <s id="48">(Laughter) Actually, it's very simple.</s>
 <s id="49">The track that I will whistle is called "Fête de la Belle."</s>
 <s id="50">It's about 80 minutes long.</s>
 <p id="p51">
  <s id="51.1">(Laughter) No, no, no.</s>
  <s id="51.2">It's four minutes long.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="52">And I want to first rehearse with you your whistling.</s>
 <s id="53">Yes, so I whistle the tone.</s>
 <s id="54">(Whistling) (Laughter) Sorry, I forgot one thing -- you whistle the same tone as me.</s>
 <s id="55">(Laughter) I heard a wide variety of tones.</s>
 <s id="56">(Geert Chatrou and audience whistling) (Whistling ends) This is very promising.</s>
 <s id="57">(Laughter) This is very promising.</s>
 <s id="58">I'll ask the technicians to start the music.</s>
 <s id="59">And if it's started, I just point where you whistle along, and we will see what happens.</s>
 <s id="60">(Laughter) Oh, I'm so sorry, technicians.</s>
 <s id="61">(Laughter) I'm so used to that.</s>
 <s id="62">(Laughter) I start it myself.</s>
 <s id="63">(Laughter) OK, here it is.</s>
 <s id="64">(Laughter) (Music) (Whistling) (Whistling ends) (Music) OK.</s>
 <s id="65">(Whistling) It's easy, isn't it?</s>
 <s id="66">(Whistling) Now comes the solo, I propose I do that myself, OK?</s>
 <s id="67">(Music) (Whistling) (Applause) Max Westerman: Geert Chatrou, the World Champion of Whistling.</s>
 <p id="p68">
  <s id="68.1">Geert Chatrou: Thank you.</s>
  <s id="68.2">Thank you.</s>
 </p>
</text>
