<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">Today, I want to talk to you about dreams.</s>
 <s id="2">I have been a lucid dreamer my whole life, and it's cooler than in the movies.</s>
 <s id="3">(Laughter) Beyond flying, breathing fire, and making hot men spontaneously appear ...</s>
 <s id="4">(Laughter) I can do things like read and write music.</s>
 <s id="5">Fun fact is that I wrote my personal statement to college in a dream.</s>
 <p id="p6">
  <s id="6.1">And I did accepted.</s>
  <s id="6.2">So, yeah.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="7">I am a very visual thinker.</s>
 <s id="8">I think in pictures, not words.</s>
 <s id="9">To me, words are more like instincts and language.</s>
 <s id="10">There are many people like me; Nikola Tesla, for example, who could visualize, design, test, and troubleshoot everything -- all of his inventions -- in his mind, accurately.</s>
 <s id="11">Language is kind of exclusive to our species, anyway.</s>
 <s id="12">I am a bit more primitive, like a beta version of Google Translate.</s>
 <s id="13">(Laughter) My brain has the ability to hyper-focus on things that interest me.</s>
 <s id="14">For example, once I had an affair with calculus that lasted longer than some celebrity marriages.</s>
 <s id="15">(Laughter) There are some other unusual things about me.</s>
 <s id="16">You may have noticed that I don't have much inflection in my voice.</s>
 <s id="17">That's why people often confuse me with a GPS.</s>
 <s id="18">(Laughter) This can make basic communication a challenge, unless you need directions.</s>
 <s id="19">(Laughter) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="20">(Applause) A few years ago, when I started doing presentations, I went to get head shots done for the first time.</s>
 <s id="21">The photographer told me to look flirty.</s>
 <s id="22">(Laughter) And I had no idea what she was talking about.</s>
 <s id="23">(Laughter) She said, "Do that thing, you know, with your eyes, when you're flirting with guys."</s>
 <p id="p24">
  <s id="24.1">"What thing?"</s>
  <s id="24.2">I asked.</s>
 </p>
 <s id="25">"You know, squint."</s>
 <s id="26">And so I tried, really.</s>
 <s id="27">It looked something like this.</s>
 <s id="28">(Laughter) I looked like I was searching for Waldo.</s>
 <s id="29">(Laughter) There's a reason for this, as there is a reason that Waldo is hiding.</s>
 <s id="30">(Laughter) I have Asperger's, a high-functioning form of autism that impairs the basic social skills one is expected to display.</s>
 <s id="31">It's made life difficult in many ways, and growing up, I struggled to fit in socially.</s>
 <s id="32">My friends would tell jokes, but I didn't understand them.</s>
 <s id="33">My personal heroes were George Carlin and Stephen Colbert -- and they taught me humor.</s>
 <s id="34">My personality switched from being shy and awkward to being defiant and cursing out a storm.</s>
 <s id="35">Needless to say, I did not have many friends.</s>
 <s id="36">I was also hypersensitive to texture.</s>
 <s id="37">The feel of water on my skin was like pins and needles, and so for years, I refused to shower.</s>
 <s id="38">I can assure you that my hygiene routine is up to standards now, though.</s>
 <s id="39">(Laughter) I had to do a lot to get here, and my parents -- things kind of got out of control when I was sexually assaulted by a peer, and on top of everything, it made a difficult situation worse.</s>
 <s id="40">And I had to travel 2,000 miles across the country to get treatment, but within days of them prescribing a new medication, my life turned into an episode of the Walking Dead.</s>
 <s id="41">I became paranoid, and began to hallucinate that rotting corpses were coming towards me.</s>
 <s id="42">My family finally rescued me, but by that time, I had lost 19 pounds in those three weeks, as well as developing severe anemia, and was on the verge of suicide.</s>
 <s id="43">I transferred to a new treatment center that understood my aversions, my trauma, and my social anxiety, and they knew how to treat it, and I got the help I finally needed.</s>
 <s id="44">And after 18 months of hard work, I went on to do incredible things.</s>
 <s id="45">One of the things with Asperger's is that oftentimes, these people have a very complex inner life, and I know for myself, I have a very colorful personality, rich ideas, and just a lot going on in my mind.</s>
 <s id="46">But there's a gap between where that stands, and how I communicate it with the rest of the world.</s>
 <s id="47">And this can make basic communication a challenge.</s>
 <s id="48">Not many places would hire me, due to my lack of social skills, which is why I applied to Waffle House.</s>
 <s id="49">(Laughter) Waffle House is an exceptional 24-hour diner -- (Laughter) (Applause) thank you -- where you can order your hash browns the many ways that someone would dispose of a human corpse ...</s>
 <s id="50">(Laughter) Sliced, diced, peppered, chunked, topped, capped, and covered.</s>
 <s id="51">(Laughter) As social norms would have it, you should only go to Waffle House at an ungodly hour in the night.</s>
 <s id="52">(Laughter) So one time, at 2 am, I was chatting with a waitress, and I asked her, "What's the most ridiculous thing that's happened to you on the job?"</s>
 <s id="53">And she told me that one time, a man walked in completely naked.</s>
 <p id="p54">
  <s id="54.1">(Laughter) I said, "Great!</s>
  <s id="54.2">Sign me up for the graveyard shift!"</s>
 </p>
 <s id="55">(Laughter) Needless to say, Waffle House did not hire me.</s>
 <s id="56">So in terms of having Asperger's, it can be viewed as a disadvantage, and sometimes it is a real pain in the butt, but it's also the opposite.</s>
 <s id="57">It's a gift, and it allows me to think innovatively.</s>
 <s id="58">At 19, I won a research competition for my research on coral reefs, and I ended up speaking at the UN Convention of Biological Diversity, presenting this research.</s>
 <s id="59">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="60">(Applause) And at 22, I'm getting ready to graduate college, and I am a co-founder of a biotech company called AutismSees.</s>
 <s id="61">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="62">(Applause) But consider what I had to do to get here: 25 therapists, 11 misdiagnoses, and years of pain and trauma.</s>
 <s id="63">I spent a lot of time thinking if there's a better way, and I think there is: autism-assistive technology.</s>
 <s id="64">This technology could play an integral role in helping people with autistic spectrum disorder, or ASD.</s>
 <s id="65">The app Podium, released by my company, AutismSees, has the ability to independently assess and help develop communication skills.</s>
 <s id="66">In addition to this, it tracks eye contact through camera and simulates a public-speaking and job-interview experience.</s>
 <s id="67">And so maybe one day, Waffle House will hire me, after practicing on it some more.</s>
 <s id="68">(Laughter) And one of the great things is that I've used Podium to help me prepare for today, and it's been a great help.</s>
 <s id="69">But it's more than that.</s>
 <s id="70">There's more that can be done.</s>
 <s id="71">For people with ASD -- it has been speculated that many innovative scientists, researchers, artists, and engineers have it; like, for example, Emily Dickinson, Jane Austen, Isaac Newton, and Bill Gates are some examples.</s>
 <s id="72">But the problem that's encountered is that these brilliant ideas often can't be shared if there are communication roadblocks.</s>
 <s id="73">And so, many people with autism are being overlooked every day, and they're being taken advantage of.</s>
 <s id="74">So my dream for people with autism is to change that, to remove the roadblocks that prevent them from succeeding.</s>
 <s id="75">One of the reasons I love lucid dreaming is because it allows me to be free, without judgment of social and physical consequences.</s>
 <s id="76">When I'm flying over scenes that I create in my mind, I am at peace.</s>
 <s id="77">I am free from judgment, and so I can do whatever I want, you know?</s>
 <s id="78">I'm making out with Brad Pitt, and Angelina is totally cool with it.</s>
 <s id="79">(Laughter) But the goal of autism-assistive technology is bigger than that, and more important.</s>
 <s id="80">My goal is to shift people's perspective of autism and people with higher-functioning Asperger's because there is a lot they can do.</s>
 <s id="81">I mean, look at Temple Grandin, for example.</s>
 <s id="82">And by doing so, we allow people to share their talents with this world and move this world forward.</s>
 <s id="83">In addition, we give them the courage to pursue their dreams in the real world, in real time.</s>
 <s id="84">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="85">(Applause) Thank you.</s>
 <s id="86">(Applause)</s>
</text>
