<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<text>
 <s id="1">I've been a journalist for more than 23 years, at the "Arkansas Democrat-Gazette," the "Pittsburgh Tribune Review" and most recently, "The Denver Post."</s>
 <s id="2">(Applause) When I started at "The Denver Post" in 2003, it was among the country's 10 largest newspapers, with an impressive subscriber base and nearly 300 journalists.</s>
 <s id="3">At the time, I was in my 30s.</s>
 <s id="4">Any ambitious journalist that age aspires to work for one of the big national papers, like "The New York Times" or "The Wall Street Journal."</s>
 <s id="5">But I was simply blown away by my first few weeks at "The Denver Post," and I thought, "This is going to be my paper.</s>
 <s id="6">I can make a career right here."</s>
 <s id="7">Well, seven years passed, we were sold to a hedge fund, Alden Global Capital.</s>
 <s id="8">Within a few years -- (Laughs) (Laughter) Some of you know this story.</s>
 <s id="9">(Laughter) Within a few years, buyouts ordered by past and present owners would reduce the newsroom by nearly half.</s>
 <s id="10">And I understood.</s>
 <s id="11">The rule of thumb used to be that 80 percent of a newspaper's revenue came from pricy print ads and classifieds.</s>
 <s id="12">With emerging giants like Google and Facebook and Craigslist, those advertizing dollars were evaporating.</s>
 <s id="13">The entire industry was undergoing a massive shift from print to digital.</s>
 <s id="14">Alden's orders were to be digital first.</s>
 <s id="15">Take advantage of blogs, video and social media.</s>
 <s id="16">They said that one day, the money we made online would make up for the money we lost in print.</s>
 <s id="17">But that day never came.</s>
 <s id="18">In 2013, we won a Pulitzer Prize for covering the Aurora theater shooting.</s>
 <s id="19">Alden ordered that more journalists be cut.</s>
 <s id="20">Again, and again, and again, and again.</s>
 <s id="21">We were forced to say goodbye to talented, hardworking journalists we considered not just friends but family.</s>
 <s id="22">Those of us left behind were stretched impossibly thin, covering multiple beats and writing rushed articles.</s>
 <s id="23">Inside a windowless meeting room in March of 2018, we learned that 30 more would have to go.</s>
 <s id="24">This paper that once had 300 journalists would now have 70.</s>
 <s id="25">And it didn't make sense.</s>
 <s id="26">Here, we'd won multiple Pulitzer Prizes.</s>
 <s id="27">We shifted our focus from print to digital, we hit ambitious targets and email from the brass talked up the Post's profit margins, which industry experts pegged at nearly 20 percent.</s>
 <s id="28">So if our company was so successful and so profitable, why was our newsroom getting so much smaller and smaller?</s>
 <s id="29">I knew that what was happening in Colorado was happening around the country.</s>
 <s id="30">Since 2004, nearly 1,800 newsrooms have closed.</s>
 <s id="31">You've heard of food deserts.</s>
 <s id="32">These are news deserts.</s>
 <s id="33">They are communities, often entire counties, with little to zero news coverage whatsoever.</s>
 <s id="34">Making matters worse, many papers have become ghost ships, pretending to sail with a newsroom but really just wrapping ads around filler copy.</s>
 <s id="35">More and more newsrooms are being sold off to companies like Alden.</s>
 <s id="36">And in that meeting, their intentions couldn't have been clearer.</s>
 <s id="37">Harvest what you can, throw away what's left.</s>
 <s id="38">So, working in secret with a team of eight writers, we prepared a special Sunday Perspective section on the importance of local news.</s>
 <s id="39">(Laughter) The Denver rebellion launched like a missile, and went off like a hydrogen bomb.</s>
 <s id="40">[In An Extraordinary Act Of Defiance, Denver Post Urges Its Owner To Sell The Paper] ['Denver Post' Editorial Board Publicly Calls Out Paper's Owner] [On The Denver Post, vultures and superheroes] (Applause and cheers) Clearly, we weren't alone in our outrage.</s>
 <s id="41">But as expected, I was forced to resign.</s>
 <s id="42">(Laughter) And a year later, nothing's changed.</s>
 <s id="43">"The Denver Post" is but a few lone journalists doing their admirable best in this husk of a once-great paper.</s>
 <s id="44">Now, at least some of you are thinking to yourself, "So what?"</s>
 <s id="45">Right?</s>
 <s id="46">So what?</s>
 <s id="47">Let this dying industry die.</s>
 <s id="48">And I kind of get that.</s>
 <s id="49">For one thing, the local news has been in decline for so long that many of you may not even remember what it's like to have a great local paper.</s>
 <s id="50">Maybe you've seen "Spotlight" or "The Paper," movies that romanticize what journalism used to be.</s>
 <s id="51">Well, I'm not here to be romantic or nostalgic.</s>
 <s id="52">I'm here to warn you that when local news dies, so does our democracy.</s>
 <s id="53">And that should concern you -- (Applause and cheers) And that should concern you, regardless of whether you subscribe.</s>
 <s id="54">Here's why.</s>
 <s id="55">A democracy is a government of the people.</s>
 <s id="56">People are the ultimate source of power and authority.</s>
 <s id="57">A great local newsroom acts like a mirror.</s>
 <s id="58">Its journalists see the community and reflect it back.</s>
 <s id="59">That information is empowering.</s>
 <s id="60">Seeing, knowing, understanding -- this is how good decisions are made.</s>
 <s id="61">When you have a great local paper, you have journalists sitting in on every city council meeting.</s>
 <s id="62">Listening in to state house and senate hearings.</s>
 <s id="63">Those important but, let's face it, sometimes devastatingly boring committee hearings.</s>
 <s id="64">(Laughter) Journalists discover the flaws and ill-conceived measures and those bills fail, because the public was well-informed.</s>
 <s id="65">Readers go to the polls and they know the pros and cons behind every ballot measure, because journalists did the heavy lifting for them.</s>
 <s id="66">Even better, researchers have found that reading a local paper can mobilize 13 percent of nonvoters to vote.</s>
 <s id="67">Thirteen percent.</s>
 <s id="68">(Applause) That's the number that can change the outcome of many elections.</s>
 <s id="69">When you don't have a great local paper, voters are left stranded at the polls, confused, trying to make their best guess based on a paragraph of legalese.</s>
 <s id="70">Flawed measures pass.</s>
 <s id="71">Well-conceived but highly technical measures fail.</s>
 <s id="72">Voters become more partisan.</s>
 <s id="73">Recently in Colorado, our governor's race had more candidates than anyone can remember.</s>
 <s id="74">In years past, journalists would have thoroughly vetted, scrutinized, fact-checked, profiled, debated every contender in the local paper.</s>
 <s id="75">"The Denver Post" did its best.</s>
 <s id="76">But in the place of past levels of rigorous reporting and research, the public is increasingly left to interpret dog-and-pony-show stump speeches and clever campaign ads for themselves.</s>
 <s id="77">With advertizing costing what it does, electability comes down to money.</s>
 <s id="78">So by the end of the primaries, the only candidates left standing were the wealthiest and best-funded.</s>
 <s id="79">Many experienced and praise-worthy candidates never got oxygen, because when local news declines, even big-ticket races become pay-to-play.</s>
 <s id="80">Is it any surprise that our new governor was the candidate worth more than 300 million dollars?</s>
 <s id="81">Or that billionaire businessmen like Donald Trump and Howard Schultz can seize the political stage?</s>
 <s id="82">I don't think this is what the Founding Fathers had in mind when they talked about free and fair elections.</s>
 <s id="83">(Applause and cheers) Now this is exactly why we can't just rely on the big national papers, like "The Journal" and "The Times" and "The Post."</s>
 <s id="84">Those are tremendous papers, and we need them now, my God, more than ever before.</s>
 <s id="85">But there is no world in which they could cover every election in every county in the country.</s>
 <s id="86">No.</s>
 <s id="87">The newsroom best equipped to cover your local election ought to be your local newsroom.</s>
 <s id="88">If you're lucky and still have one.</s>
 <s id="89">When election day is over, a great local paper is still there, waiting like a watchdog.</s>
 <s id="90">When they're being watched, politicians have less power, police do right by the public, even massive corporations are on their best behavior.</s>
 <s id="91">This mechanism that for generations has helped inform and guide us no longer functions the way it used to.</s>
 <s id="92">You know intimately what the poisoned national discourse feels like, what a mockery of reasoned debate it has become.</s>
 <s id="93">This is what happens when local newsrooms shutter and communities across the country go unwatched and unseen.</s>
 <s id="94">Until we recognize that the decline of local news has serious consequences for our society, this situation will not improve.</s>
 <s id="95">A properly staffed local newsroom isn't profitable, and in this age of Google and Facebook, it's not going to be.</s>
 <s id="96">If newspapers are vital to our democracy, then we should fund them like they're vital to our democracy.</s>
 <s id="97">(Applause and cheers) We cannot stand by and let our watchdogs be put down.</s>
 <s id="98">We can't let more communities vanish into darkness.</s>
 <s id="99">It is time to debate a public funding option before the fourth estate disappears, and with it, our grand democratic experiment.</s>
 <s id="100">We need much more than a rebellion.</s>
 <s id="101">It is time for a revolution.</s>
 <s id="102">Thank you.</s>
 <s id="103">(Applause and cheers)</s>
</text>
